- In the Lion King,
like I was thinking about it,
there's no democracy in any of the movie.
- [Teacher] No, there isn't.
- Yeah, and how the Lion King's,
like everything seems really British,
you know, like very England,
monarchy-type stuff.
But in the Lion King, what bothered me
is when it said like,
the two hyenas,
like Cheech from Cheech
and Chong was one of them,
and then Whoopi Goldberg
was the other one.
I was just like, how could they do that,
and like not realize that they were
feeding into this racial
stereotype by being
the voices of the hyenas?
Like don't they think about that stuff?
- [Girl] Yeah, I was
thinking the same thing.
- [Teacher] Did you think about it before,
when you first read Cinderella?
- I think when I watched the Lion King,
like I thought about it.
I mean, even when I was little,
I think it registered in my mind,
like, "That's a black woman's voice.
"Why would her voice be in this animal,
"and not any of the other voices?"
- [Teacher] Right.
I don't know Disney
intentionally did this.
They were building up into
an already existing culture
of racial stereotypes,
so I think the mentality of that
was why fix what's not been broken,
and when they should have fixed it.
- [Girl in striped sweater]
But at the same time,
Mufasa was that really, what's his name?
James Earl Jones, who's
like Morgan Freeman.
- [Teacher] Right, Mufasa was an evil--
- Like if I had to pick a God, it would be
James Earl Jones or Morgan Freeman.
- [Teacher] Mufasa was the
good, Simba's father, right?
- [Girl in striped sweater] Yeah.
With like the really deep voice.
- [Teacher] You made a good point, though,
about no democracy in Disney movies.
There isn't, because there's
no democracy in marketing.
There's no democracy in the media.
What are the six big media conglomerates?
Disney.
- [Boy] Disney, GE ...
- What else?
- [Boy] GE.
- GE.
- [Girl] Newscorp.
- Yeah, Newscorp.
- [Girl] Then Viacom.
- Viacom.
- [Boy] Time Warner.
- And Time Warner.
- [Girl in striped sweater]
But why can't Cinderella
be a first lady?
Why does she have to be a queen?
Like why can't she have
some other magical power?
- Why can't we instill some like, actual
life in there?
- But that's still not, this
is still not the classic,
but then I wouldn't be surprised if Disney
will come up with another story.
- [Girl] I hope they do.
- Well, they came up with Tiana, right?
Which added the gender stereo- the roles,
the racial roles, or
the racial stereotypes.
Tiana is absolutely beautiful.
The image.
However, there are, again,
the pre-existing culture and norms
that Disney is too
scared to move away from,
because that has provided
them or given them
this 80 billion dollar industry.
I did promise you a reading on,
we do have time,
I promised you a reading on China,
as to what happens in China.
Before I do that,
I just want your input on
the Disneyfication of children's culture,
with the article that you read.
I know you wanted to talk about it,
you were really excited.
If you have your article in front of you,
you can use that.
You can look at it.
I also jotted down plenty of notes,
but when you reflect on what we did today,
I want you to think, these books,
these books are
books are media, music is
media, videos are media, okay?
Food for thought for next time
when we have our discussion:
Does media construct
an image or a message?
There's no right or wrong
answer, but think about it.
Does the media construct an image
or a message?
Okay? As you read your read articles.
So, Hannah, to you, go ahead.
- [Hannah] The whole like Aladdin where,
how they changed the verse, the lyrics,
that was like awful.
- [Girl] That was crazy!
- Like, I think I have a
different opinion from everybody,
like, truth hurts, to me.
I think it's just like, I
don't care that it says that.
Like, I didn't notice that,
no one notices that while they're singing.
Like, while they're singing that,
no one like realizes,
oh, "Cut off your ear."
- [Girl] Kids don't. Like
if your (inaudible) was in--
- And that actually happened back then,
that actually happened.
- [Girl in maroon] The ear
one didn't bother me as much,
because that's kind of true.
But the whole, it's
barbaric, the (inaudible)
like that was awful. It shouldn't be--
- [Girl with blue scarf]
Because if you think about
where it is, if you look into the history,
it is barbaric, and they used to do it.
And in some places, they still do it.
It's the whole Hammurabi,
"An eye for an eye."
You know, it's that culture.
- [Hannah] Yeah, it's true,
it's true, so why not teach
what actually happened?
- But I don't really have a
problem with it, I mean like--
- But if that's the only
way that you're looking
at the Middle East, then that's wrong.
Because they have a
history with beautiful art,
they invented math, and like they gave us
all this wonderful stuff,
that you can't just look at the problems
that they have now,
or the violence that was in their culture,
because there's violence everywhere.
- I mean, that's just stereotyping.
- They cut people's ears off
in the Middle Ages in England
just as much as they did,
or at least as the same.
- They did worse things,
probably, in the Middle Ages,
than they did in cutting
off people's ears.
- It's just unfair that they
portayed the Middle East
like strictly as a barbaric, violent place
in that song.
It just makes it wrong.
- [Girl in blue and white] I
think it was like in general,
and it was because Arabia was so bad
in an oasis like that.
- [Girl in striped sweater]
Yeah, they weren't specific,
it was just "Arabia," but like it took,
there was like Indian things about Aladdin
that it wasn't supposed to be India,
it was supposed to be like
Israel, or totally different--
- There were a lot of like
Middle Eastern elements
rolled into one,
so it would make one thing,
like if you went to the Middle East,
if you went to like Pakistan,
it wouldn't be what they say it is,
or if you went to India
or you went to Israel,
like they just took bits and pieces
and combined it into one.
Which looks like a different--
- [Teacher] Why did they do that?
What would you think--
- They didn't look into it,
they didn't bother to do the research.
- [Girl with blue scarf]
Yeah, they probably didn't--
- [Girl in striped sweater]
Because their culture
is so different than American culture,
that they just thought that they could
just skip over it.
Like I thought it was gross that
they didn't even bother to translate
what they wanted to say on a manuscript.
Like if it was in English,
they would have had the actual letters
on the piece of paper,
but they just, you think that
you can just go like this on the board,
and that looks like Arabic writing?
That's not--
- Arabic writing is really complicated.
- And the whole thing
with all the accents,
how all the bad guys had accents,
and the good guys didn't.
The bad guys had like--
- Oh, the beards and noses?
- Bigger beards, and then the good guys,
they looked American.
- [Girl in grey jacket] I
think it made you assume
the worst,
like reading that just made me like,
"Wow," like, "Oh my gosh,"
it's not really giving
you the information--
- [Girl in striped sweater]
But yet, you didn't
notice it when you
watched it though, right?
- [Girl in grey jacket] Yeah,
I mean, you didn't at all.
- [Girl with blue scarf] I did, though.
- But then when we're older,
we go back in history--
- Maybe that's because I have that class
and we realized that it's
all war with religion,
and like I know those times.
- [Teacher] Go ahead.
Religion, what about it?
- She noticed that--
- I did notice those things,
like you can kind of tell like different
culturally-wise, like the different
Indian elements in Israel,
or the different like
Pakistani influences, but,
and they had like Hindu going on.
It's just really, really weird.
But I did notice that,
but like, I don't know,
maybe like Hannah said,
she didn't notice that,
but because she didn't grow up like
learning to write Arabic,
- [Hannah] No.
- And like reading about all that stuff.
I guess it's also like, how you grew up.
- Right.
- Someone who showed America,
like (inaudible) without photos.
- I have a question.
When you think about it,
when we talk about American culture,
we view it as pretty homogeneous,
of the American values.
Okay, there are these values,
and that's all there is.
But we know that that's not true.
Do you find that to be,
with these movies, by
blending all of those
different spaces, and all
those different cultures,
do you find that to be the
message is not carried out
the right way to children,
that the Middle East is
highly diverse, okay?
And not everybody looks the same,
or writes the same, or behaves the same,
but Disney has done something
that the media does. What
does the media assume?
That everybody who watches a movie--
- [Girl] Is going to react the same way.
- [Teacher] It's going to
react the same way, right?
So the media assumes that
homogeneity attitude. Yes?
- The problems in the past 20 years
in the Middle East,
like when little kids
grow up, and it's like,
if I look at a picture of Osama bin Laden,
I think, "Jafar," because he has a beard
and he looks like that.
Like we're taught that that is evil.
- [Girl with blue scarf]
Do you really? I don't.
- That the person with the
turban and beard is evil,
because the terrorists that
are doing these awful things
to people all over the world,
just happen to be Muslim,
totally extremist Muslims that
most of the people that
carry out their religion
don't practice.
Kind of like most Christians
during the Middle Ages
didn't go out and chop people's heads off
in the name of Jesus. It's the same thing.
- [Teacher] Right.
- You know?
But we look at those pictures
of those Middle Eastern men
and we think bad because of it,
which is like Jafar and Aladdin.
- [Hannah] That's when
acceptance comes in, like--
- [Girl in grey jacket] You
have to accept what's true
and what's not.
- Exactly.
- Talk about ignorance,
I mean, why do we have to accept that?
- [Hannah] Because it's not true.
- Because it's not true, there
are thousand and thousands
- You don't see me going
like, "Oh, I'm making bombs."
- I'm not like saying
acceptance like it's not true,
I'm not like saying acceptance
like, Osama bin Laden,
like accepting that's what
he looks like to like Jafar.
Like, that's who he was, so
that's what he looks like.
You know what I'm saying?
- Yeah, but I don't see that.
If I see,
if I look at Osama bin
Laden, I don't see Jafar.
- No I don't either.
- I don't identify it at all.
- I don't either, but
you know what I'm saying?
- Yeah, like little kids
like 10 years from now,
if they watch Aladdin and
they're going to grow up,
and what's going to be in
the news is September 11th
and Osama bin Laden.
- But what the point
is is that evil people
look like everybody else.
Like, Ursula could have just been a
really pretty mermaid,
and still done all the horrible things
that she did to Ariel.
- [Teacher] Right.
- Like it doesn't matter
what you look like,
they create these evil images of people,
like all old ladies
are either really smart
or they're evil.
They either have wisdom
or they're out to get you.
There's no in-between.
- [Teacher] Or the
zoo-keeper in (inaudible),
he had a German accent, he was evil,
and that was during a war, the movie.
- Or like the three crows, right?
That were talking in like the very like,
I don't know, African-American,
inner-city slang,
and they were, just all that
stuff that was just really--
- [Girl in grey jacket]
It kinds of makes it,
like just like the story was describing
what a bad person must look like,
we have that image like up here,
like tell them it looks like this,
so when we see them, we
automatically assume like,
"Oh man, it could be a terrorist,"
just like when we watch a movie,
like, "Oh, that's the bad guy."
So like it's the same as
if they're doing a cartoon,
and if we're in real life.
- Right, so that leads
to problems that we have
with profiling, for example.
Putting people on one side, or, yes?
- [Blonde girl] It doesn't
really relate to the article,
but I was watching a movie with my mom,
and I don't know what it was called,
but there's this like,
I guess class project,
or oral presentation
that someone had to do,
and this girl chose to
write about her religion,
which she was Muslim,
and she wrote about like 9/11
and she was like, "Just
because they did that
"doesn't mean we're all evil."
And like I don't know,
she had all this stuff,
and then the principal like
told the FBI or something,
and they came to her house
and deported her family
back to where she came from.
Just because of that. That's it.
- [Hannah] That's when like a school needs
to teach acceptance.
That's not the end. Or like
families and the school
needs to teach acceptance.
Everyone was calling her
like a suicide bomber,
and like, "Go kill yourself,"
or, "Are you gonna bomb all of us?"
- [Girl in striped sweater]
And we call ourselves a country
of freedom of religion.
- [Girl in black] I remember
when I was in sixth grade,
there was a girl, she was Muslim,
and people used to throw
markers at her and stuff,
and call her a terrorist.
It was around 9/11 and stuff like that,
and it used to like upset me
because I used to feel really bad.
Because she like didn't do anything,
she barely even knew how to talk.
They'd like throw
markers at her and stuff,
just because she was Muslim.
- Like, because like
no one has acceptance,
like no one learns that,
it's just like people make inferences,
like, "Oh, man, it's a bad person,
"so let's stay away, let's shy away,
"let's make fun of them,"
instead of like, when you're
going down the street,
and just like we were
talking about earlier,
how there's like, if
you see a big black man,
you're gonna put your phone away,
you're going to take your phone out
and try to call your mom,
put her on speed dial.
You don't have acceptance, either.
Like you may say we should get it,
but you don't have it.
It's just the way we grow up.
- [Blonde girl] We don't suspend judgment.
- [Teacher] You don't suspend judgment.
It's difficult to do so.
There is this conflict between acceptance
and our values. Because
the values that we have,
that think by this individualistic
view of what it is,
and in doing so, you
divide people into groups,
and construct images about those people,
and it's as simple as reading
a children's story, okay,
or as watching or turning
the TV on in the morning
and just watching the Disney Channel,
or Noggin, or Nick, Jr., or whatever.
There's messages that we
impart on our children,
there's messages that
we impart on ourselves.
Or picking up the newspaper.
I don't know if you guys have
noticed in the newspaper,
but there is a big, there's a dichotomy
between how different areas are described.
Immediate areas, our city
compared to our surrounding areas.
- (inaudible)
- Right, so media is biased.
They're systemically biased, okay?
There is no democracy, but here is
the fundamental thing as an American,
we pride ourselves in democracy,
we pride ourselves in leadership,
so what do you do?
What path do you follow?
How do you--