- Guys ready?
- [Students] Yes.
- Okay number one, start, give your idea.
Read the word, give your
idea of the definition.
- Okay what's your word?
"Soldier," okay and
okay you're gonna give your idea?
What's your idea of soldier?
- I think tax is like when
you buy something like,
the extra, yeah.
- One person at
a time, it goes in order,
so what's your idea?
- Like a government, so
- Okay you need help.
Have you ever seen a soldier before?
- Taxes for me are...
- Where?
- Money or something, I don't know.
- And what does
a soldier do, do you know?
Okay, he fights for freedom, very good.
So it's someone who fights for freedom,
that's your definition.
What's your definition?
(children discussing)
Very good, you guys keep
going, you're doing great.
Let me see how this
group is doing over here.
Where are you guys at?
Have you already given your definition?
- Yes.
- Okay did you already give yours?
Did you already give yours?
Did you give yours yet?
What do you think it is?
What's the word?
- Patriot.
- Very good, patriot, and did
you listen to their ideas?
- Yeah.
- Okay and you need thinking time? Okay.
And remember, you can
build on their ideas too.
Louder, a little bit louder.
- I think it means to...
I think it's
- You've heard
it in a song, that word?
- Yeah.
- Yeah?
So someone was a patriot in a song?
What did it mean, in the
song, if they were a patriot?
How did they feel?
- They feel sad?
- Sometimes sad, you can feel sad
if you're a patriot.
On 9/11, when the planes crashed through
the buildings, people were sad because
they were patriots, they
loved their country, right?
And they were sad to see that.
Can you be happy if you're a patriot too?
- Yeah.
- When would you
be happy if you were a patriot?
You're a patriot for the
United States, right?
Or even for the country your
family originally came from.
How do you feel about that
country if you're a patriot?
- Happy.
- Happy, and do you not like
them or do you love them,
that country?
- I love them.
- You love them, okay, so a
patriot is someone that what?
- You could be more excited or happy?
- Okay and how do you feel in your heart
about the country?
Do you dislike it or do you like it a lot?
- I like it a lot.
- Okay, alright.
And I didn't hear your ideas
but can you guys get together
and agree, or do you
want to look it up first?
Should we look it up, to make
sure we have the right idea?
Okay everyone let's get into our books and
let me make sure you have your papers too.
There are your papers too,
goodness Miss Bryant got ahead of herself.
Just in case you forget the
direction, the page is 493
to check, go all the way to
your glossary page 493 to check.
(students discussing)
Let me see what you guys have, let's see.
Okay and where does that
money go to, do you guys know?
- The government.
- Oh, did you
look it up to make sure
that it was perfect, your definition?
Okay let's look it up real
quick and make sure because
it looks pretty good but
let's just make sure.
That's my fault because
I got busy with table one
and didn't give you this
paper so on page 493
there you go, 493 it starts
but then you have to go
in ABC order, right?
And let's look it up and make sure
you have the right definition.
You guys are looking up tax, that's right.
- A "T."
- "T, T, T," tax,
good, like the way you're
using your resource, 'cause
that was one of the things
we said we're gonna do,
is use our resource.
(students discussing)
Okay, what did you get?
Do you know where to read it?
(child reading)
Good, I like the way that you
worked together and helped,
so, Les, what did you have?
- [Teacher and students]
Taxes for new money
- To where, where does that money go?
- [Students] The government.
- Okay so let's add that.
Who started this?
- Her.
- Me.
- Okay so you wanna add that?
You guys all agree?
- [Students] Yeah.
- You feel good?
'Cause it's not just
any money for anybody,
it's money to the?
- [Students] Government.
- Okay, so let's add that, go ahead.
Good, I like the way you used
your resource and checked it.
(students discussing)
- A patriot is a person who
loves and supports
- their country.
- And that's kinda
what you guys said anyway
right, you said they love,
is that what you guys said
'cause I wasn't here earlier,
did you say stuff like that?
Oh great. Are all of you patriots?
Do you love your country?
- Loves and supports their country.
(shuffling papers)
- Okay, now what happens?
It goes to person
- Number two.
- Number two, you
get to read it and they're
gonna repeat the question, right?
Okay there you go and
here's the directions
just in case you forget.
- What is it like? Describe it.
- Okay, let's repeat.
- [Teacher and students]
What is it like? Describe it.
- You guys, did you repeat? Let's repeat.
- [Teacher and students]
What is it like? Describe it.
- Okay so before we
write, you get to start,
so what is it like?
Can you describe a patriot?
- [Boy] Yes.
- Okay what is it like?
- [Boy] It's like
- Or who is he like, 'cause
they're a person, right?
- [Boy] Is like someone who will
respect their country.
- Who's that? Can you think of
a person? Oh I'm sorry honey.
Can you think of a person?
Who's an example?
Let's see, describe it, so
when you think a patriot,
okay they support their
country, what else?
- [Boy] Respect the government.
- Very good, those are good
words, so you could put
that there, but we're not
gonna write yet, right?
Because we're gonna
give everyone a chance.
What would you say?
What do you think of
when you think of patriot
and you would describe it if you had to
describe it to someone.
- Patriot is
soldier.
- That's a great example.
What about you?
- Someone respect
every city everywhere and respect
to everybody to not be...
- Very nice.
- Can it be also honoring?
- I like that vocabulary
word, honor, how do you guys
feel about honoring?
What do you say about respecting?
Okay, alright, you get to write first.
You write one then it'll
go around and each of you
can write one in a box,
okay, every one of you write
something in the box.
If you need help, ask your
table for help, right?
Okay, good.
How's it goin'?
(students discussing)
- If something costs $7.99,
it's plus, like, tax.
- Plus like, a dollar.
- Yeah, a dollar.
- Taxes come in
like, a dollar or two dollars.
- Just put
taxes like, extra money.
- Great, okay now you.
Alright so we said it
protects the country,
fights, what did you
say when you gave ideas?
- Fights for his,
risks his life for others.
- What do you guys think,
risks his life for others?
Should we include that?
- [Students] Yeah.
- Yeah? Okay, that's good.
Good, okay and then you're
gonna write one too, right?
(students discussing)
- [Teacher] What else
makes that "kuh" sound,
a "C" and what else?
- "K."
- You guys agree?
Okay let's put it down, a "K."
Risks.
I like the way you're helping
each other, that's great.
Alright.
Very nice.
Okay and you get to put an idea down too,
we wanna make sure everyone gets a chance.
So put your idea down, you
can put it in any of the boxes
because there's room, here, here, or here.
No that's fine because we're
all gonna keep going, yep,
so I want you to put your idea
that you said earlier here,
here, or here for describing the soldier.
Do you remember what you said?
What'd you say?
(boy speaking)
Very good, so put that down.
(students discussing)
- Tax is more
money for the government.
- You can just look in the book.
- Just put tax is
extra money for the government.
- We already have that.
- Oh I know, tax
is extra money for the government.
Tax is, I-S
for extra money for the government.
(students spelling aloud)
- Okay so has
everyone given an example?
Okay so whose turn was
it to write, your turn?
So you write first and make sure everyone
gets to write one in.
- Tax is extra
money for government.
Money, money, money.
M-O-N-E-
- Yes, did you guys give
your examples first?
- Yeah.
- Before you wrote? Okay good.
Do your parents pay taxes?
- [Students] Yes.
- They do. Everyone pays taxes,
that could be an example.
I have a question. Do
your parents pay taxes?
Everyone pays taxes, don't they?
Do we have to pay taxes
when we get gasoline?
- Yes.
- Yes, do we
have to pay taxes when
we buy a video game?
- Yeah.
- Everything.
- Yes,
everything except for food.
Food they don't tax,
isn't that nice of them?
(laughter)
Okay and what does the tax go to support?
- The government?
- The government
and the schools, right?
And the firemen, the policemen,
good, okay so now you have
some more.
Great conversation, great conversation.
(students discussing)
- Was Thomas
Jefferson a patriot?
- Martin Luther King.
- Martin Luther King was a patriot, good.
Who else was a patriot?
- Abraham LIncoln?
- Yes, okay let's take turns
though, who's turn is it now?
Who's a patriot?
Someone who loves their country.
(students discussing)
Are you a patriot?
Could you say "I am a patriot?"
- I'm a patriot.
- Very good,
there's an example.
Can you think of someone who's a patriot?
- A soldier.
- A soldier. Why's a soldier a patriot?
Why do you think they love
their country so much?
What are they willing to risk?
- Their heart?
- Their heart and their what?
They could, what could
happen if they got shot?
- They die.
- Yeah, they're risking their
lives, so they really love
their country, they're
really patriots aren't they?
Very good, so you ready to write?
Who's turn is it?
No that's okay, so whoever's
next, so if it's your turn
you go.
Oh okay, so it's your turn so
you get to write an example
of a patriot.
Try to write in a complete
sentence, I bet you can.
(students discussing)
- You just draw pictures.