- We are now getting into Earth,
Sun, and Moon interactions.
We have done one thing,
well, we have done several things,
all year, on that first slide,
which you copied onto your board.
What is it?
- The moon phases.
You do the moon phases every day.
So, you should be pretty familiar
with moon phases, what they are,
how they happen, all that good stuff.
We get to move on.
Okay.
Let’s start with something you do know.
What is a moon phase?
Tom.
- It’s what, well, it’s technically,
when you look up in the sky,
and, like, what light you
see in the moon.
- Good.
What light you see in the moon.
Where does the light come from?
The green she’s reflecting.
- The sun?
- The sun.
How does that work?
- The sun shines on the moon
and reflects back.
- Good, the sun shines on
the moon and reflects back.
So, that’s how we see the moon.
Do you agree with that?
I see most of you agree.
Good.
Okay.
Then, if we know that
it comes from the sun,
why don’t you tell me some of
the moon phases, so we can
build on what you just told me.
What are some of the moon phases?
This one should be easy.
- Waxing crescent.
- Waxing crescent, excellent.
Aisha?
- Waxing gibbous.
- Waxing gibbous, very good.
Grillen?
- Waning crescent.
- Waning crescent. Bailey?
- Full moon.
- Full moon. Tom?
- Waning gibbous.
- Waning gibbous. Ramos?
- 1st quarter.
- 1st quarter, excellent.
- New moon.
- New moon, excellent.
- Last quarter.
- Third quarter.
- Third quarter and last quarter, very good.
When we talked in the last class,
some of you said, “Second quarter!”
Then, the second quarter is half time,
so, that would be what moon phase?
[Inaudible]
What’s halfway in between first and third?
[laughter]
What moon phase is that?
[Inaudible]
- Full moon?
- Yay, full moon, yay!
[laughter]
Yeah, just start spouting everything out,
and then, eventually, you’ll be right.
That works for me.
Yeah, it’s a full moon.
Get it, half, full?
Or not, okay.
So, we have all these moon phases.
How can you tell which one’s which?
Why don’t you just look up and say,
“Yay, it’s a fingernail!”
How do you tell which one’s which?
- Because different
moon phases look different.
- How does it look different?
- Because--
- It’s okay.
- Because different parts of the moon
have light on it, in different amounts.
- Okay, different parts of the moon have
different amounts of light on it.
How would I be able to
tell a waxing something
from a waning something?
[Inaudible]
You’re almost, almost there.
Yeah?
[student laughs]
[Inaudible]
- I think you will because the moon
has different kinds of faces.
- Good, very good.
Different kinds of faces.
- One lights up on the left side
and the other lights up on the right side.
- Which one lights up on the right side?
- The waxing.
- How do you know that?
- Because, um...
Well, you always told us it’s
light on the right, it’s wax-iting.
- Yeah, it’s light on
the right, it’s wax-iting!
Or, what you guys like to do...
- Wax on, wane off.
- Or, wane off.
I don’t know, wax on.
Okay?
So, I don’t have a problem,
I don’t think that you have a problem
knowing the different phases of the moon.
I think you guys are pretty set on that.
How about what causes
the phases of the moon?
What makes that happen?
You’ve already told me
light reflecting off the
moon that comes from the sun,
but, why would you have
parts?
Why wouldn’t you just be able to see
the whole thing, all the time?
Sean.
- Because the earth blocks out
some of the light that’s
coming from the moon.
- Okay, good.
Brenda?
- Because the earth rotates with time,
and when the earth rotates,
the earth blocks the sun,
so you can see, maybe,
at the top of the moon.
- Okay, good.
Tom?
- There are other stars
shining in different directions,
not just the sun.
- Okay, very good.
Stars shining at different directions.
Anything else?
Nancy.
- Because the moon is moving,
and so [Inaudible]
- Okay, as the moon moves,
we see different phases.
So, I hear a lot of
that the earth blocks the moon,
the sun from reaching the moon.
Are you in agreeance?
- Yeah.
- A little bit.
- Yeah, yeah, somewhat?
Okay.
Here’s what we’re gonna do.
You have won the experiment.
You’ve done the flip camera.
But, what I want you to do,
on your table,
everybody has, like a big lollipop.
You either have the blue styrofoam ball,
you have the big, white styrofoam ball,
you have a little styrofoam ball.
I want you,
each person in your group to have
one of those styrofoam balls.
Okay?
And then, you are going to come this way--
- Down in your light paths?
- You are gonna come up front,
and gather around
my lovely light bulb.
Okay?
Come forth, children.
[Background Chatter]
And you might wanna squat
down, if you’re near the front.
Yay!
I know it’s bright.
Good?
- Can’t see.
- Oh, you can’t see,
okay, alright.
Oh, [Inaudible]
Okay, what I want you to do,
and you’re already doing it,
hold it out in front of you,
I want you to look at your moon.
What am I holding in my left hand?
- The sun.
- The light bulb, the sun.
You have the moon, yay.
Here, hold it out in front of you.
What moon phase do you have on your moon?
Aisha?
- New moon.
Why is it a new moon?
- Because you can’t see any light.
- You can’t see any light.
I can see lots of light.
It’s blinding me.
Oh, there we go.
But, there’s a light source.
Isn’t my moon illuminated?
Becky?
- It’s illuminated
on one side, but since
you’re behind it, you don’t
see any of the light coming--
- Well, then, how do I
know it’s illuminated?
- Because you can see other light?
- Oh!
So, I look across from me, and I see Sean.
Sean, you have a full moon.
[laughter]
Now, you’re supposed to disagree with me,
and tell me that no, you don’t.
- Oh, okay.
Um...
- What moon do you have?
- A new moon.
- No, you don’t, you have a full moon.
[laughter]
- He has a waxing moon.
- No, he doesn’t, he has a full moon.
[Inaudible]
You all are crazy.
Look.
[laughter]
It’s illuminated on the other side.
Okay.
Oh, yeah, you could do that.
But then, wouldn’t your head
be in line with the earth?
[Inaudible]
It doesn’t make any sense.
But, that is one way
that we can figure out
that the moon is illuminated.
Not that we have 15 different moons,
or 28, or however many people we have.
But, just because we’re
looking at a new moon,
doesn’t mean that the
moon’s not illuminated,
it’s just the other side.
So, I look across, and I can
see full moon across from me.
What else can you see,
from where you’re standing?
Tell me what you see
and where you see it.
Yes.
- Over there, with Zack and Sarah,
I see fullmoon.
- Okay, good.
- Over there, I see a waning gibbous.
- Really?
I see a waxing gibbous.
Uh, Becky.
- I see a full moon, over at Zack.
- Nice.
- I see a waxing gibbous with Charlese.
- I see a full moon.
- Well, I see a waxing gibbous.
- Why?
Why do you see a waxing
gibbous, and I see a full moon?
- Because we’re in different places.
- What’s that got to do with anything?
[laughter]
I thought y'all told me
that we saw moon phases
because the Earth's shadow blocks
the sunlight from reaching the moon.
How can we see moon phases then?
Tiffany?
Ooo...
Kaitlyn?
- Line of sight.
- Line of sight?
What does that mean?
- Um...
- Besides, your sight in a line.
[nervous laughter]
- It's, um, well...
Because sunlight's here,
it looks like a new moon,
but if the sunlight were,
like over there, it wouldn't.
- Huh?
Interesting.
Brooke.
- Well, I'm just suspecting
that Lauren turns
kind of the moon out of view
then, like I couldn't see a shadow
I could only see the new moon.
- Oh, because, oh, well, oh
Lauren's head is in the way.
[giggling]
- Look at if the
Earth was in the way that.
- If the Earth was in the way,
would that cause a moon phase?
- Yeah.
- Is the Earth in the way
of the moon all the time?
- No.
- What could we call...
Sorry.
[giggling]
What do we call it when
we have the Earth and the moon
and the sun lined up,
or if the moon is blocking
light from getting to the Earth,
or if the Earth is blocking
light from getting to the moon?
[Background Chatter]
Bailey?
- An eclipse.
Have we talked about an eclipse before?
[Inaudible]
A little bit.
Just a little bit.
So, is there anything in between me,
well, is there anything
between the moon and the sun?
In my...
- No.
vicinty, because if I ask you,
you're gonna be like,
"Yeah, Lauren's head is in the way."
[laughter]
"She's blocking all the light."
[nervous laughter]
There's nothing in between
me and the light source,
yet all around you're saying
you see different moon phases.
Correct?
- Mmm hmm.
I want you to think about that.
Why you can see different
phases on my styrofoam ball,
but there's nothing in between us.
- Because the moon and the earth
is at a different angle.
- Ooh.
'Cause the earth is at a different angle.
- Because of our position?
- Your positions.
Very interesting.
Here's what I'm willing to have you do.
You all have a light bulb,
some work, some don't
I know there was at least
one group in the last class
that blew a light bulb.
[giggling]
So, you might have to share,
but I'm gonna have you
go back to your seats.
Some of you have three people.
Some of you have four people.
Some of you have two.
Daniel, you have three now.
I want you to set yourselves up
in an arrangement around
your light bulb,
where you personally can see
four different moon phases,
or three different moon phases,
depending on how many
people are in your group.
So, you need to be able to see,
if there are four of you,
four different moon phases.
You stand there.
You hold it,
and if you get it,
raise your hand for me now.
[tapping]
Okay, that was your challenge.
You don't have to fill anything.
You don't have to do anything.
Off you go.
[Background Chatter]
- Try not to blow it.
- Alright, move Michael.
- Where do you think it's gonna be?
- Put it like this.
Okay.
- It doesn't have a switch.
It's just automatically on and off.
- Yay, we made it.
- Nice.
[Background Chatter]
- Are we getting there?
- Okay.
- Okay, since you have four people,
you're going to position yourselves
differently than they are.
They only have three.
So, you're gonna think,
think about a clock.
Where on the clock will
you put everybody,
so you can all see four
different moon phases,
from your angle.
- Well, one can go at twelve.
- Twelve, twelve, six, and nine and three.
- Like a cross.
- Do it.
- I don't think we can put
anybody over there.
- And then, tell me when you get it.
- We can't put anybody over there.
So, that'll be like twelve,
this'll be like...
- Well, we need a camera for it.
- Right there, we're not using a camera.
- Okay.
- Well, now...
- So Brenda can stand there,
Brooke can..
- Or, we can do, like, um,
like, this kinda way.
I'll be here.
she'll be there, and she'll be there,
and you'll be at the corner.
- Yeah.
- Okay.
[Background Chatter]
So, take your moon.
- It won't move until you
stand there and hold it.
- No, I see yours.
New moon.
[Background Chatter]
[Inaudible]
- No, it looks like a waxing.
- Excellent, ladies and gentlemen,
I have a group who has it.
Ooo, it looks like I have
another group who has it.
Ooo I have another group who has it.
Somebody tell me,
If you equate it to a clock,
where are you standing?
Tell me what numbers you're standing on,
Jamie.
- Uh, oh...
- Oh.
Forget about that?
[laughter]
For one moment, we had it.
- She's on number one.
She's sitting at four.
- On a clock.
- She's nine.
She's three, and six and twelve.
- Good.
So, one of the ways you can do it is,
twelve, three, six, nine.
You can do it that way.
Or, you could actually scoot yourselves
a little differently,
you could rearrange yourselves
and see something besides...
What are you moon phases that you have?
- Um, that's waxing gibbous
- Waxing gibbous
There's full moon, new moon,
and this looks like...
- I see full.
I see new,
and then if you're at nine and three,
I should only be able to
see [clicks tongue] half.
What would those things be?
- Mmm...
- Go ahead.
- First and third quarter.
- Good, first and third quarter.
I want you guys to see
if you can figure out
different arrangements to make it--
- Okay.
- Something besides those four.
And, you got it too.
- Okay, we could...
- Get a...
- And then someone could be...
Could be right there, and right there.
[Background Chatter]
- Yeah.
- I see a full moon, I see a full moon.
- I just see a full moon.
Because your the light source.
- I see a full moon, and a...
- I see a full moon.
- I just see a full moon.
- Do you see a half moon here?
- I see a full moon.
- Well...
[Background Chatter]
- Now, do you wanna switch out?
- Okay, I'll take it.
- Okay, it's blinding.
- Ooo, yay.
Oh, yeah.
I see a new moon,
and I like see a...
- Everybody got it at least once.
[Background Chatter]
- Yep.
Okay, do me a favor,
unplug your light bulb,
and come back to your group.
[Background Chatter]
- Okay.
Was there anything in between
you, well, actually,
your moon and your sun?
[coughing]
- No.
So, does your theory or your hypothesis
that the Earth blocks the light
from reaching the moon still work?
- No.
- Carolyn says no.
Tom.
- Technically it can work,
because when you have a,
I forgot what kinda
eclipse it's called,
but it's an eclipse of the moon
it goes, like, all red or something,
we had it this year,
and the Arth, Earth, arth...
The Earth is blocking it in a way worse.
- Okay, so is that going to
change the phase of the moon,
nightly?
Becky.
- No.
- She says no.
Do you agree?
So what changes the phase of the moon?
Ben?
- The way we see it from Earth.
Agree?
- Yes.
- Ah, interesting.
Now, when you did
the experiment before,
when you did it with a flip camera,
we're gonna re-watch
some of those videos.
I'm just gonna do the montage,
so it's not necessarily gonna be
your entire class,
but we're gonna go through,
and you need to critique each one.
You need to figure out
do they do something wrong?
Do they do something correct?
Do you need to do something with that?
Do you need to re-think
your flip camera video?
Because, we're gonna do it again
after we get finished with this.
Make sense?
Are you sure?
- Mmm hmm.
- Are you positive?
- Let's watch the first one.
[chair screeching]
Okay.
Let me play it for you again.
See the phases?
- Yeah.
[giggling]
- Alright, now.
I want you to tell me.
Besides being blinded.
What did they do correct?
What was right?
- They were in a orbit
not around the sun,
just a orbit.
- Excellent, they were not
orbiting around the sun,
a.k.a. the lightbulb.
What did they do incorrect?
- They didn't call out the phases.
- Okay, they didn't call out the phases.
- They didn't orbit, orbit the camera.
- They did.
The camera was in the middle.
So, it went around.
So, that's okay.
Think about that.
They went around.
There's even something wrong...