- So, here's the first set.
I thought I'd start a little bit easy.
So, go ahead and within your groups now,
I'll give you like a minute to tell me
all the methods that you can
of how to separate, how to
figure out which one it is.
Okay? Go ahead.
- [Male Student] You can uh...
- [Christina] You can you use
Beer's Law for this, right?
- [Male Student 2] You
aren't able to taste that.
- You aren't able to,
that's not big enough.
- Our...(mumbles)
- Okay, so...
- [Male Student 3] Doesn't dissociate.
- [Male Student 2] How's
the temperature? Boil it.
- Yeah, that's the only way.
- So, the one with the highest
concentration's going to have
the highest boiling point.
- [Male Student 2] Yeah.
- [Male Student 4] You could
freeze it and weigh it.
- [Natalie] Okay, freezing it.
- The point three would
have the most weight.
- Weight. Yeah.
But which one would freeze first?
- [Female Students] Point one.
- Point one would freeze
first because there's less.
Okay. What else?
- Point three weighs more.
- But we would need to
freeze it first, no?
- [Natalie] What? We
wouldn't need to freeze it.
- [Male Student 5] The
first one being, would
be with the tasting one.
- Or the volume one. I
don't know the tasting one.
- Okay, you say the tasting one,
you say the volume one.
Whichever one comes first.
(laughs)
- [Male Student 6] The one
who boils fastest would
be the one with the
point one, right? Okay.
- So, the one that boils the fastest.
- [Male Student 6] Point one.
- You could measure the vapor pressure
by also just leaving them and adding them
and then just coming back
after like five minutes or ten minutes.
- Alright. So, we can have equal volumes
of each solution, right?
And then, after like a certain time--
- [Teacher] Alright,
that's it. Everybody stop.
Stop, stop, stop. Okay.
So, who want to go first?
We'll start with with Miles,
I think you had your hand
up first, so go ahead.
What's one way that you
can identify these things?
- [Miles] Well, you could
boil all the solutions
until all the water vaporizes,
and the beaker with the most sugar in it
would be the 0.3 molar,
0.2 would be the middle,
and 0.1 would be the least.
- Okay.
- [Miles] If they were
all the same volume.
- [Class] Ahh...
- [Teacher] Yeah.
You guys heard that, now?
Good. Good listening skills on that.
If they were the same volume
at the beginning, alright?
Does everybody agree?
So, one method is boil away and weigh.
Did you say weigh?
How do you know which one has the most?
I would imagine you
could weigh it, right?
- [Miles] You could weight it.
- Start with equal volumes. Okay.
There's several other ways.
How about Joseph?
- If you take equal
volumes of each solution
and you taste them,
whichever one tastes more sugary
would have the highest concentration.
(mumbles)
- Okay. Anybody have comments on that?
Jimmy?
- I don't think we're able to
distinguish the taste that well.
Because our mouth isn't that sensitive.
- [Teacher] Okay. Miles?
- What if someone dropped
some lead nitrate in there?
(Students laugh)
- So, there's two concerns.
Obviously I think Miles
is the most important.
You know you guys can see
that I'm smart enough to
put the right substances.
(Male Student laughs)
I keep forgetting I'm getting old.
And I may go in the back,
and I reach for the lead
nitrate or something, right?
(mumbles)
And then the other part,
what do you guys think of the other part?
Could you taste the difference
between a 0.2, 0.3, and a 0.1?
And just say "Ah, that's
the sweetest one."
- [Student] It's kind of hard.
- {Miles] You'd need some salt.
- The problem I think is
this is something we would
actually need to try, right?
I don't think this is a theoretical thing
that we're trying to,
we're practicing theory here.
We would actually have to
do this in a lab, right?
I would imagine we would.
- Wouldn't it be different
for every person?
Because we could--
- [Teacher] It could be different
for every person, right?
Because I can't see as
well as you, for example maybe, right?
So, there could be variations
in tasting of those.
Ian?
- Given excess humans...
(laughs)
- [Teacher] Oh, wait.
You're on the next one?
- [Ian] No, on this one.
- Alright. I didn't get that either.
(laughs)
Okay, so let's look at
another method, alright?
We're not going to list that one
because we don't want
to be tasting things.
Okay so Paran, your group.
- What about at equal volumes
you could test the vapor pressure
and the 0.1 would have the most,
and 0.3 would have the least
because there's more sugar covering it?
- [Teacher] What do you guys think?
Okay, Juan?
- He didn't say how you could measure it.
The way you could measure it is that
with equal volumes you leave them out,
and the one that evaporates the fastest
is the one with the
highest vapor pressure.
(mumbles)
- Everybody agree?
- [Students] Yeah.
- Okay. So, that was my concern too, right?
How do you measure the vapor pressure?
You're not wrong.
But how do measure it?
And thank you, Juan, for bringing that up.
- [Male Student] Could you repeat that?
- Okay, so you would take equal
volumes and leave them out
to evaporate because they'd
always be evaporating?
The one with the highest vapor pressure
which is 0.1 molar,
would evaporate the most after
a certain amount of time.
(mumbles)
- So, I'm going to write
this as evaporation rate.
Who's got another method? Different view?
Alright, Jimmy?
- Okay, so you're gonna
put the same amount
in a sealed container
and put it into light.
Whichever one grows
algae first is the 0.3.
Then the second one is
0.2, the last one 0.1.
- What do you guys think?
- [Male Student] Could you repeat that?
- So, you're going to take equal amounts,
take it into the light,
make sure it's the same
conditions for each one,
and then whichever one grows
algae first is the 0.3.
Second is 0.2, last is 0.1.
- [Teacher] What do you guys think?
I know some of you guys
are thinking that's bio,
but you took it, most
of you at least right?
So, we could finish
this. What do you think?
- Wouldn't it take a long time
for the algae to start growing?
- [Male Student] It's going to work, right?
- [Teacher] Nobody sees--
- [Miles] Where's the algae--
- [Teacher] You're always asking me.
Come one, folks. You think about this.
I'm going to say the problems.
But I want you to tell me first, alright?
(mumbles)
- [Teacher] Alright, let's go with Ivan.
- I don't think the results
would be consistent.
Because what if some algae
cells just go in one solution
and start going there for no reason.
- So, because you didn't mention
how much algae you put in,
there could be an issue there.
What else, though?
No Juan, you go alright?
- I don't think you can assume that
you have all the necessary
stuff in the water
for the algae to grow in the first place.
- So, I think Juan is saying
growing conditions require
lots of other things.
Not just amount of sugar
and amount of water.
There could be other nutrients,
is that what you're saying?
- [Juan] Yeah.
- Nutrients and other things of that sort.
Could I just back up for a sec?
Algae produces sugar, right?
Assuming that you're talking
about algae that grows,
they use carbon dioxide.
So my hunch is, there's several, right?
One, I think as Ivan pointed out,
you've got to put in a certain amount.
Why don't you put in something that
eats the sugar like yeast,
and then we could all finish
and have a beer at the end?
(laughs)
You picked algae so, yeah.
Although is that a bad idea?
It could work, but we have to
be careful with conditions.
A lot of conditions need to be met.
Anything else?
- [Female Student] You boil them.
- [Teacher] Hold on. Let these guys go.
- If you have equal volumes
and you add heat to them,
0.1 should boil first.
- Okay, so you could use boiling point.
Elevation.
I wrote this down before
we even discussed it.
But everybody agrees that works, right?
So, what's another easy one that we,
boiling point elevation, right?
You need me to repeat that or you got it?
(mumbles)
What immediately follows with that idea?
- [Miles] Freezing point depression.
- Freezing point depression.
Okay, what else?
I have a question for you then.
Could we use Beer's Law for this?
No? Tell me why.
Ian, you have your hand up.
- At first glace I would say no because
I do not believe that stuff
actually has a coloring solution.
- [Teacher] What do you guys think?
- [Students] Yep.
- [Teacher] Don't you need color?
Unless what? Unless?
Come on, keep going with this stuff.
Not you Ian. You spoke.
I'd like to have as many
people participate as possible.
Alright Nick, go ahead.
- You could add food coloring possibly.
Yeah, you could add food coloring
and maybe the higher concentration
would appear darker, possibly?
- Nick, we're trying to figure out
the difference between these, right?
- [Nick] Yeah.
- What do you mean "add?"
You mean add a drop to each of these?
- [Nick] Yeah.
- But then what would you be measuring?
The food coloring.
You wouldn't be measuring the sugar.
You know what I mean?
- [Nick] Yeah, I know what you mean.
- You're still okay with that?
- Uh, I don't know.
- Wait, Nick.
If you add food coloring, how much?
One drop?
- [Nick] Yeah.
- Okay. One drop to each of these, right?
Now they all look the same.
(laughs)
Don't they?
- [Nick] Yeah.
- And if I stick this in
my spectral photometer,
they should all measure the same.
Did I succeed in figuring
out which one is which?
You understand that, right?
- [Nick] Yeah, yeah.
- [Teacher] Okay. Nat?
- Could you somehow measure
how fast the food coloring spreads?
- That's interesting.
Could you measure how fast
the food coloring spreads?
- You'd have to indicate that
high concentration would--
- [Teacher} Hang on.
But once again we have to be
careful of conditions, right?
- [Miles] All the temperatures
have to be the same.
- What do you guys think?
- [Miles] Sure.
- Why would that work?
- Because the sugar
molecules are getting wet
and it's not able to spread
through the molecules.
So, that would be in the 0.3.
- [Teacher} Anybody else
have thoughts on that one?
My hunch on this one is it probably works,
but this goes into the
category of that taste one
where I think we really
need to expand, right?
[Male Student] Science!
- Glad you like it. Alright.
How about, wait.
Gevorg hasn't spoken.
So I'm thinking, Gevorg,
it's your turn buddy.
What did you want to add?
You wanted to add a new technique?
Okay, go ahead.
- If we did a Benedict's Test,
I don't know if it would
just turn the same color
because I'm not sure how
the Benedict's reacts
with different concentrations.
But maybe if you put the same
amount of Benedict's
and if it gets darker or it
gets affected with the molarity
then you could use a color emitter
or a spectrometer to test.
- [Teacher] What do you guys think?
Benedict's is a reaction between
this Benedict's stuff with sugar,
to show the presence of sugar.
- [Miles] What comes out of the reaction?
- [Teacher] I'm not sure
but it's a color change.
- [Miles] Oh well, the more color change--
- [Teacher] But if the
color change is too intense,
it could just be like
it's all going to change that color or not,
see what I'm saying?
That's what your pointing out, right?
So again, that sounds
like an experimental one.
Could I share one more?
How about this.
You know when you take your AP test,
you just don't know what.
And we started with something
that I think is sort of easy.
Could you use density?
What do you guys think?
Someone who hasn't talked yet.
Could we use density?
(mumbles)
And how do we use density?
What do you guys think? No?
Alright, Ian. Since nobody's going for it.
- Do I have to say it?
- [Teacher] Go ahead and say it.
Tell me how. Tell us how.
- Take equal volume of each of the three
and weigh it.
- [Teacher] Exactly.
Which one's going to weigh the most?
The one that has the most sugar, okay?
If you take equal volumes,
this one will weigh the most.
This will be the most dense.
The more sugar you add,
the denser it gets.
You know this, right?
Does anybody have any more?
Alright, let's move on.
Set number two.
Now this says "solid"
and I'm trying to get you
to see a different range on these.
Go ahead and talk about it.
I'll give you a minute or so.
- [Student] Colors?
(mumbles)
- [Student] Conductivity?
- We could root the potassium chloride
out with conductivity.
- Well, they're solid.
You have to remember.
So, solid has a lot of problems with it.
- [Miles] That's just...solving it.
- [Student 2] It's hard
to conduct a current.
- [Miles] Well you could dissolve it--
- [Student 2] It's doable.
It's just a little difficult.
[Melissa] Potassium.
- Then um...
- [Female Student] Wait, calcium.
- What about pH sensing?
So CACL2.
- Well they're solids.
- Oh, if you put them into a solvent?
- Yeah.
Can we put them into solvents?
Can we make it into--
- So, lead can't dissolve in water, right?
- Lead?
- [Female Student] I mean lead chloride.
- [Ian] No, lead chloride
will not dissolve in water.
- [Female Student] But
then KCL and CACL2 would?
- They would.
- So, you can rule that
out. That's one way.
But then how do you figure out
between the other solution?
- Couldn't there be a bigger
concentration of chloride
and then you could form a precipitate?
- I wouldn't say form a precipitate,
I would say...
(mumbles)
Actually, I'm thinking you can hybridize
the fact the lead chloride
doesn't dissolve at all
with boiling point elevation,
freezing point depression
because you're going to
have more little bits in
the CACL2 than the KCL.
- As an end result,
calcium chloride, potassium
chloride get what?
PBCL2 does nothing.
So, after that if you boil it, right?
Calcium chloride,
potassium, the higher value.
- [Teacher] Alright you guys. That's it.
Let's gather up. Okay.
Some of you guys just got back,
so you guys know what we're doing, right?
- [Student] Yes.
- [Teacher] Okay.
Let's get it together.
Alright, everybody stop now.
Christina, you had your hand up first.
Take the easiest one.
What's the easiest way
to distinguish these?
- You could take equal
amounts of each of them and weigh them,
and then PBCL2 would be the heaviest,
and the KCL would be the lightest.
- [Teacher] Equal volumes?
- I mean equal amounts.
- [Teacher] What's an amount, though?
- Like grams.
(class moans)
- [Teacher] But if I take equal grams,
then I could have ten grams of this,
ten grams of this, ten grams of that.
- No, I didn't say that.
(laughs)
- [Teacher] Alright,
what did you say then?
- I meant like equal--
- [Teacher] Equal what?
- Volume.
- [Teacher] Volume, okay.
Now let's answer that one.
What do you guys think?
She's saying take,
let's say 10 milliliters, 10
milliliters, 10 milliliters.
And this one's going to weigh the most.
This one would weigh, which one's second?
- [Christina] Oh, sorry.
Second would be CACL2.
- Okay, so this one would be second.
What do you guys think?
Someone other than Ian?
(mumbles)
Okay Ian, go ahead.
- Does atomic weight, atomic
mass directly influence--
- [Teacher] Listen to this, Miles.
- Does atomic mass
directly influence density?
- [Teacher] That's the question.
Does the formula mass have anything to do
with the density of these solids?
They're all ionic compounds.
And the answer to that is no.
You cannot assume that because
this has the highest formula mass,
that this is the most dense. Okay?
Where, just to follow that up,
where could you use formula mass
in relationship to density
in a pattern that works?
- Ivan? Oh wait, let's give it to him.
Just, he's just walked in. Niresh?
- Is it in gases?
- [Teacher] Gases, right?
Does everybody agree?
Gases, you could do that.
If the formula mass is high on a gas,
then it's going to have more density.
Could you do that for liquids, now?
Could you do that for liquids?
Ivan?
- You could do it if
it's all the same subsets
for different concentrations.