- Okay guys, yesterday we talked about
three key vocabulary
words that we mentioned,
we studied, we found definitions for.
Those words were adaptation,
there's habitat and community.
Okay, adaptation is the first word.
Who can tell me something
about adaptation?
Karina.
- Adaptation is how animals
act, like the howler monkeys,
they howl so they can tell other monkeys
that they are in danger,
so they can survive
- Okay, so they can survive, right?
Adaptation helps them survive.
And then, habitat.
Who can tell me what habitat is?
Ernesto.
- Where you live.
- Okay it's the environment
where they live.
It's the surroundings, okay?
It's the trees, it's the
plants, it's the ground,
and it's the climate that they live in.
And, the last one is community.
Okay, so, if we're
thinking about animals,
what makes up a community
for these animals?
Who can tell me?
Sergio.
- The community
- What makes up a community?
It's not the environment
- The animals?
- It's all the animals.
Do we have just one animal in the community?
(collective no)
- We have many, we have many.
It could be very many.
Okay, we're going to on,
and I'd like you to listen to this sound.
Shhhh.
Just listen to this sound.
(owl hooting)
Okay, you may have, and you
can hear this sound at night.
Okay, what I'd like you yo do right now
is tell me one thing that you
know about this animal, okay.
If you know the name of this animal,
go ahead and write that down too.
First of all. let's just
write it in our "K".
Just put it under for "K".
What do you know about that animal?
Just write it down first,
then we'll talk about it.
I'd like you to discuss
what you know also.
Talk to a neighbor.
Okay, this is what you know,
so you are going to be looking at that.
What is something you
know about that animal?
Okay?
Tell your neighbor "What do
you know about this animal?"
Just tell a neighbor.
(background chatter)
- Tell a neighbor what you know.
- Tell your neighbor,
Eddie, what you know.
What do you know?
You can talk out loud, guys.
(background chatter)
Okay, small ears, okay.
All right, so write that down.
Okay, now after that go
to what you want to know.
Go to the "W".
What do you want to
know about this animal?
By the way, what animal is this?
- An owl.
- It's an owl.
It's a Great Horned Owl, okay.
Now, what I'd like you to do,
you want to put this information.
Yea, what do you want to know.
So, write one thing about
what you want to know.
What do you want to know?
Tell a neighbor, "What
do you want to know?"
Sergio.
(background chatter)
You don't have to whisper, you can say it.
How old an owl can live?
Okay, good. Good, okay.
Now, one thing I want you to think about.
Let's listen to this sound again, okay?
Listen to the sound again.
(owl hooting)
Any predictions, and you can just tell me,
without writing them down.
What do you think that--
Why does the owl make
the sound that it makes?
Yea
- Maybe to warn other owls.
- Warn other owls?
Anything else?
Yea, Ernesto.
- To communicate.
- And to communicate, that's right.
Okay, let's take a look
a page twenty-three.
Okay, we're going to look at
text structure on page 23.
This is the Great Horned Owl.
And, I'd like everyone to
put your finger on the title
for this animal, the Great Horned Owl.
Just put your finger so I know
you know what the title is.
Next, I'd like you to put
your finger on the caption.
Okay, and can I have one
person read the caption?
Let's have Karina read the caption.
- Owls have large eyes to
help them see in the dark.
- Okay, very good.
Then we have, underneath the
title of the Great Horned Owl,
We have what I call bullet points.
We talked a little bit about them.
And, put your fingers on
the bullet points there.
And, let's have Ernesto
read those bullet points.
- Bird found in North,
Central, and South America.
Live in the canopy and understory.
- Understory, very good.
And we live in what continent?
Eddie, what continent do we live in?
- North America.
So, we'll find these,
and actually I will usually
hear these at night.
And usually hear them kind
of in the winter time.
All right, let's have the first paragraph.
Eddie, why don't you continue?
- The Great Horned Owl has
no ears, but can hear anyway.
It can also see very good,
even on the darkest night.
- Okay, and the second paragraph, Makayla.
- An owl hunts for food at
night from high in the air.
When it hears a mouse move or squeak,
the owl swoops down upon it.
- Swoops, okay very good.
Okay, now we've read
about the Great Horned Owl.
I'd like you to tell your neighbor,
one thing that you learned
new about this owl,
that you are going to
put down under the "L".
What is one thing that
you learned about the owl?
(background chatter)
Okay, so write something down
that you've talked about with
your partner or your neighbor.
Now we're going to continue
working in partners here
and I'm going to give you
something to take a look at.
And I'm going to have you guys,
just close your books for a second.
After you're done
writing, close your books.
Okay, I'm going to give each
pair or each little group
one of these sticks.
I want you to look at the stick carfeully
and look how an animal might have
changed or interacted
with the stick, okay?
So take a close look at it, all right?
And, take a look at it,
and then I'd like you to put down
what you know about that stick, okay?
There are, yes you can
see that some insects have
interacted with the stick also.
But what is something,
look at the ends of the stick,
and let's put down something we know
about what an animal might
have done to this stick.
Okay, just write it down
or tell your neighbor.
Tell your neighbor.
(background chatter)
Yeah, he bit the stick on here.
But did he actually cut it?
Was he able to bite it?
- Yes
Yeah he was, he was.
Okay, all right, now who can tell me
what animal this might be?
Karina.
- A beaver.
- It is a beaver and you
will find these in this area.
What I would like you to put down next is
what you want to know about the beaver.
So, let's write that down.
Just skip this and go right
to "What do you want to know?"
Tell your neighbor.
Go ahead and tell your neighbor about it.
What do you want to know?
(background chatter)
Okay, tell your neighbor, guys, too
once you have written it down.
(background chatter)
- How old can a beaver live?
- Okay, how old can a beaver live?
That's good.
Yea, Keelie.
- What I want to know how about
are they electric.
- Okay.
(background chatter)
Okay, I want to know
how long they are in their house, maybe.
Yes.
- I want to know how big can they be.
- Okay good
- I have hair on here.
- It's possible.
Actually, yeah that is very possible,
you have hair of a beaver
I would actually, I'm
going to hang onto that.
And actually let's put
that in the garbage.
But, that's good.
- It's right here.
(laughter)
- Okay i'll take it.
Okay.
Yea, you're going to find that probably,
we're not going to look
at the sticks too much.
We need to find insects
still living in the stick,
but we're going to leave
that for right now.
I'd like you to take
a look at page twenty.
Take a look at page twenty.
I do recommend that if
you ever by chance go to
Deerbro, there's a forest
near the school here.
Your parents can take you.
You might actually see a beaver house.
Okay, let's find out some more information
about beaver on page twenty.
Put your fingers on the title.
You know what, I'll take that.
Here we go.
And you know what, let me recollect these,
because we have.
Let me collect those back.
Thank you.
There we go.
Okay, put your fingers on
the beaver, the title, okay?
Can I have one person
read the bullet again?
Bullet marks.
Sergio, go ahead.
- Mammal found in North
America, Europe, and Asia
Lives in rivers and streams
near the forest floor.
- okay, and can you name another mammal?
If you happen to know
what the mammal might be.
Can you name another mammal?
- Whale.
- A whale is a mammal,
and we are also mammals
Okay, the next paragraph I'd like to have
one person read that paragraph.
Karina.
- Beavers eat bark,
twigs, leaves and roots.
They have wide flat tails.
These tails help beavers
to clear a placement,
Beavers use their split
claws to comb their own fur.
They also use their claws to
spread oil onto their fur.
This oil helps keep
them warm in the water.
- Okay, before we go on,
as we're going to be
looking at a lot of things,
think about what it is you're learning.
What's something new that you're
learning about this beaver?
Now, before we go on,
everybody put your finger on the caption.
Okay, caption.
Makayla, what does the caption say?
- A beaver's fur keeps
it warm in the snow.
- All right, very good.
So, let's take one more thing.
We're going to take a look at
a diagram on page seventeen.
So, now let's go to page seventeen.
And this talks a little
bit more about a beaver.
And the title, let's put our
finger on the title of page 17.
What does the title say?
Keelie
- Graph Section Diagram
- Okay, we're looking
at page 17 right here.
Put your finger on the top of the diagram,
And that's the title.
What does it say Keelie?
- Beaver lodge.
- Okay what is, we know
a beaver is the animal,
What's a lodge Keelie?
- Their house, where they live.
- Yea, it's like their house.
Okay, next there's a caption
built into the diagram and it's green.
Let's have Sergio read the caption there.
- This beaver lodge was
built on a shallow part
of the wood floor.
If it wouldn't float, the
lodge will have to be rebuilt.
- Okay, very good.
Let's get some more information.
There's some other things in the diagram
to give us information, Makayla.
- Some lodges are two meters, 6.5' high.
- Okay, very good.
And, Keelie.
- The lodge is made from logs and sticks.
- Okay, and Eddie, the last one.
- Beavers come in and out under the water.
- Okay, so this is where they live.
This is how they live,
and why do you think
they build their house this way?
Anybody?
What do you think they do?
Why do they build it this way?
Karina.
- Because when they, when people come,
like hunters, if they want to catch them
It is going to be difficult for them.
- Okay, like predators?
Other predatory animals?
- Yeah.
So this is a way they adapt.
So, how do they adapt to
survive in their environment?
Makayla.
- To enter from the underground water.
- Okay, can you use adapt
or adaptation in a sentence?
Beavers...
- Beavers adapt to
- Beavers adapt how?
Yea, Karina.
- Beavers adapt by entering from a
little hole under the water.
- Okay, so they adapt in that way,
other predators can't
see when they're coming.
And as we saw on the sticks, the sticks,
they just pile these sticks up on here
and they move them around
until they make something
that looks like this, okay?
So, what kind of a habitat
do the beavers live in again?
Using the word habitat,
I'd like you to tell me.
What's the habitat of a beaver?
- They live in lodges.
Okay, what's around their lodge?
Yeah, Karina.
- Sticks and wood.
- Okay, sticks, but then
what is this blue stuff here?
- Water.
- It's water.
Yeah, so they actually go
underwater to get into their home.
And that makes it very safe.
So, I would like you to add one more thing
to what you learned on the
third column of this organizer.
Okay?
Okay, once you've got one third, okay.
And, Eddie, when you've got something,
why don't you tell your neighbor?
When you've got something,
tell your neighbor
what you learned
(background chatter)
- Like this?
- Okay.
Actually, right here, yea.
What you've learned.
(background chatter)
Okay, and if you were to go out somewhere,
and you were in the
woods, what would you see?
What do you think you
would see from this house?
This is all water, so all
you're going to see...
Are you going to see the hole that's here?
- No.
What do you think you're going to see?
- The sticks.
- Just like a stick.
Just a mound of sticks,
about two meters high.
Which is probably about that tall.