- Okay, I can see two
[inaudible]
in here...
- Can you read the article first, please?
- Yes.
- Loudly.
- The president of the republic should be
an Egyptian born to Egyptian parents and
enjoy salient political rights. His age
must not be less than 40 Gregorian years.
- Mm-hmm.
- I agree with the president, um...
- He should be Egyptian born to Egyptian
parents, because it will have, make him
have well-rounded perspectives, and it may
lead him to having interests to other
countries, and so...
- It would make him have interest, or will
not make him, prevent him?
- It would not prevent him to, um, from
getting to a different country's interest
than his country.
- Okay. Good job.
- I agree with Yessenia, because if both,
if he's from parents that are Egyptians,
he can have some connection with
Egyptians, and he won't have pressure from
other countries that want to change some
of the rules they have. And, um, have,
like, wars with different countries about
their economy and things they have
different.
- Mm-hmm.
- That's what I, that's what my opinion,
yeah, that's why I agree with her.
- Good.
- I disagree with the part of the, where
it says that they should be Egyptian
parents.
- Mm-hmm.
- But I agree with Jesus and his concerns
about the Egyptian parents. But my opinion
is that they should have at least one
parent Egyptian and the other another race.
- Mm-hmm.
- Because if one parent's Egyptian, like,
the child, or the, becoming president,
would have a something of concerns, and
would know some parts of Egypt and its
government, and if the other, and this
other race would help him guarantee for
the governments in the other places and
countries, states.
- Okay. Good job.
- Which, the legislative process.
- Good job.
- I agree with Yessenia and Jesus, because
if they're from Egypt and their parents
are Egyptian, then they can have some
cultural background, and they'll know more
from people, and they'll have connections
with the people.
- Good. Good. So now, what is the result
now? Do you think you're going to change
the part? I see, I've heard some different
opinions here. Are you going with the
change, or do you want to keep it as it
is?
- I think we should keep it as it is,
because, I mean, that's a good thing to
have Egyptian parents and a background,
like Hilda said, a background of culture.
- Mm-hmm.
- So I'll say yes, leave it. Just leave it
the same.
- Okay.
- Just that part.
- Okay. Very good. So you will just leave
that part as it is without change. Is
there any other parts for this article?
- Yeah, there's a second part. His age
must not be less than 40 Gregorian years.
- Mm-hmm.
- Um, I disagree, because, um, when you're
young, you'll know more about technology
and computers and everything.
- Mm-hmm.
- And that's how, um... the youth and
younger children in Egypt, that's how they
went and communicate.
- I agree with Yessenia a lot, because
when a president is younger but not old,
he can connect with the youth and other
younger people. Because when Egypt was in
the revolution, the president was 81 years
old.
- Mm-hmm. Mm-hmm.
- Eighty-four. And behind the revolution
was the young, and they were, like,
younger. So he didn't really understand
them really well, and they didn't
understand him well, because he was a
little older than them. So for me, I'll
say 35, um... yeah, that's a good age
for the president. They can connect with
teenagers and people of younger...
- I just...
- Very good. I like the connection that
you made, Jesus, between the age and the
people who were behind the revolution.
Good job.
- I disagree with Jessie and Jesus.
- Good. Yeah.
- Because I think that part of the
constitution is okay, because 40, um, 40
years is, makes them have plenty of
experience and
[inaudible]
to doing his, their work. And, like, it
makes them... like, for, like, what
Jesus said about technology, they can
learn about it, and they can show them and
all. So basically, they, they'll pretty
much know.
- Who do you mean by they?
- The becoming president.
- That the old, or the young?
- The old.
- The older one. He cannot understand or
work with technology that much?
- Yeah. Because Jesus said that they, um,
they won't know about technology much.
- Mm-hmm.
- But they, if they're 40, they would have
plenty of experience.
- Mm-hmm.
- And they can learn about the technology
and know how to communicate with the
younger adults and teens, you know?
- Okay. Good, good.
- I agree with Emi, but I agree with Jesus
and Yessenia, so...
- Mm-hm. That's okay.
- Um, because...
- Focus on what you want to do.
- Like, youth was, like, 70 or 80% of
Egypt.
- Oh, good.
- But if he's older, he's going to have
more responsibilities.
- Mm-hmm.
- And he can be more responsible.
- Mm-hm.
- So...
- I disagree with Hilda. Responsibility.
Because when they're younger, they're more
active and more responsible. Like, they
can remember most things where they keep
stuff. And when they're active, they can,
like, travel through Egypt and see what's
wrong with the country, and what's wrong
with the economy, and they can make
changes and talk to some people about
their opinions and things they want to
change the country. So I'll say the
younger, but not too young. Like, 35 and up.
- Thank you.
- My opinion is that 40 is okay, because
the young, the young people, like, at 35,
because 35's not that young, but lower
than that, can make a little bit of
difficulties, because they make, they
might make, like, a mistake. They might
not know a thing, and they just put
another thing.
- You mean they will not be mature enough?
- Yeah, mature.
- Sure. Good.
- Like, the 40s, the 40-year-old people,
like, they, they pretty much know
everything. They learn it, they were
educated. The government laws, and...
- Mm-hmm.
- ...this and that.
- But I think that part is, 40 years is
better.
- Good. So you would like to say, okay,
just to open or, or, or break it down to
35, it's okay to be less than 35, but not
so young like 30 or 20, or even teenager,
right? Well, I like that, the two parts
that you brought, Hilda, about 70%, that
the majority of the population of Egypt
are already youth. And your part that you
said that this will make, Jesus, that that
will make, help them to have good
connection with the young people there.
Good job.
So what did you decide on? I see that
you're going with certain direction.
- We should change it. The first part of
the statement of Art. 75.
- Mm-hmm.
- Which is the constitution. We should
keep that as it is. And the second part of
the 40 years, we should change it. Well,
we should leave it like that, as well.
- Very good. I like how you are
compromising with them, Emi, and you are
going with the change. So what part are
you going to change?
- Um...
- It will be transforming to what?
- Thirty-five.
- Mm-hmm.
- Thirty-five years.
- Not less than 35.
- Not less.
- Good job. Excellent. Very good. After
you take your notes, let's move to the
next article.
- Article 77. The term of the presidency
shall be Gregorian, six Gregorian years,
starting from the date of the announcement
of the results of the
[inaudible].
- Mm-hmm.
- The president of the republic may be
re-elected for other successful years.
- Mm-hmm.
- I disagree with the six years. Um...
- Yes. Mm-hmm. Yes. Keep going.
- Because I think it's a little longer,
and some advantages are that people could
get tired of the same president, um,
having them over again. And I think it
should be lower, for four years, like in
America. And some of the disadvantages are
that people could like him, and he might
be re-elected for another six more years.
Um, people could elect him because he did
some great things to the economy and
things to the country. And that's what I
think of for the first one. What do you
all think about it?
- You think the first one should be as it
is, or changed?
- Changed to four years.
- Yeah.
- Okay.
- What do you think?
- I agree. I agree with Jesus, because an
example of this is Hosni Mubarak. He, he,
um, was following, supposedly, the terms
of the constitution, which, which he made
an excuse and took many chances in, um,
having the presidency. So I, for, like, 30
years. So I, my opinion is to lower it
down to four years, and if they're
re-elected, which, they can use democracy
like here in America.
- Mm-hmm.
- If they're re-elected, they will have at
least 12 years. Basically.
- Okay.
- Do you disagree?
- Um, the statement, I agree, because it
will give them more stability and more
time to elect.
- Mm-hmm.
- I agree with Jesus and Emi.
- Why do you agree with them?
- Because six years is a lot of years, and
if they don't like him, they'll have to
wait a lot, a long time so that another
president can come into power.
- Okay. So you think bringing it down to
four years is better than having the
president for one term for six years?
- Yes.
- Okay.
- The second one is the president of the
republic may be elected for another
successful years. The thing I dislike
about this is that they don't really
explain how, um, the terms. For example,
the president of Egypt, um, used an excuse
to be re-elected, because, um, he said
that in the constitution, it said, it
didn't say specifically how much, how many
terms, um, they lead. So I'll, I'll change
that, that, um, leave specifically a
number of terms they need to be elected.
Um...
- Very good point, Luis. I didn't... um,
Jesus, I'm sorry. Very good point here.
You brought really a very important point.
And this is what will, this was, like, the
concern of many people over there. The
specification of, of what?
- Successful terms.
- Of the, how many terms, very good.
Successive terms. Very good.
- Does anybody have an opinion or
disagreement?
- Uh, I...
- I agree with...
- Okay. I agree with, um, you, because
that's what Hosni Mubarak was really, he
was making excuse to, like, stay, um, him
how, like, it is, to keep him as a
president and re-elect him over and over,
to, um... and he was telling them that
he was following the constitution, because
their theory said there was, like, no
number of
[inaudible].
- Yeah, so he...
- I agree also, because, like you said,
the example of Hosni Mubarak was the
serious, serious excuse. They, um, the
people were basically mad at them that,
um, certain term, because they didn't give
a number of the terms, so, um, that's why
Hosni Mubarak made that excuse and wanted
to take over.
- Very good. When, the point of staying
too many years in power or in office, that
brings to me something that's going on in
other two countries. You remember any of
the other countries in the Middle East,
and Africa, that has something going on
there? Because of this specific part?
- Libya and Yemen.
- What's going on in Libya now?
- They're protesting against, um, Gaddafi?
- Very good, yes. Good job. I like how you
remembered his name. Why? Why they are
protesting against him?
- Because he'd been in power for, like,
about 43 years.
- Good job. Mm-hmm. Okay, what else is
going on in another country? Or what
country is having something going on?
- Yemen.
- Very good. Okay. Well, this brings us to
go back again a little further, something
about different types of governments.
Remember, Egypt was a republic, okay? When
their, the president stayed there for so
many years, that will not be a republic
country. That will be what?
- A dictatorship.
- A dictatorship. Very good. That will be
a dictatorship. So the, the, the type of
government is, if government is not a, the
republic, or maybe democracy, as they say
or claim, but it will be... it will be?
- A dicta--
- A dictatorship. Very good. And the
people in power, the people in the office,
government office, will be what?
Dictators. Okay? It's because they do what
they want to do, and they don't listen to
other people. Okay, and what is another
name for dictatorship, or very close to
it?