- And one more.
- There's this one spider
and he's around all day
and then he comes and comes out.
- [Teacher] Oh, so it's waiting for him.
You know, i'ts like a trap.
- It covers itself in the flower
and like it sets in the flower.
It sits perfectly still in the flower
and then when something lands on it,
it attacks it and eats it.
- Wonderful, so they're
not really attracted
to flowers, they're
attracted to the insects
in order to ambush them.
Is that what you're telling me?
- [Student] Yes.
- Okay, all right.
So, and we talked about what is it
that attracts these?
Well, we see a lot of bugs,
we see humming birds,
and Jack mentioned this word, pollen.
Do you know what pollen is?
- [Student] Ah...
- [Teacher] Do you know what pollen is?
Are these things attracted to the pollen?
- [Students] Yes.
- [Student] Well, not really though.
- [Teacher] No, not really?
- [Student] Sometimes.
- [Teacher] Sometimes.
- [Student] I guess.
- [Teacher] Say that again please?
- [Student] It's an ingredient to make honey.
- Pollen is an ingredient to make honey?
- [Student] Oh, nectar? Yeah.
- So bees are attracted to flowers
because of their... blank.
- [Jimmy] Nectar.
Go ahead, Jimmy.
How would you fill this in?
The bees are attracted to flowers
because of their... blank.
Go ahead and write your answer in.
- [Jimmy] Oh, okay.
- I see some people writing pollen.
You have color.
They're definitely
attracted to their color.
We have nectar.
And we have, we actually
have all of them here.
So, which one is it?
Is it one of these or all of these?
- [Student] All of these.
- [Student] All of them.
- All of them, tell me more.
Tell me.
- [Student] I think it's pollen
and nectar because
the nectar's in the
pollen and the bees take
the pollen and then use
the pollen to make stuff,
or honey out of it.
So, it's kind of like
taking it to its'...
- So, we say that flowers attract insects,
so we can connect these two ideas here.
And we've talked about their color.
The insects were attracted
because of their color
and they're also attracted
because of their...
- [Student] Nectar.
- Nectar, okay, let's
put nectar right here.
And they're also attracted
because of their good smell?
- [Student] No.
- [Student] Yeah.
- [Teacher] No?
- [Student] The nectar smells good,
that's why butterflies go to them.
- [Teacher] Maybe look that up on Google.
Why do you think flowers
take all the trouble
to make them smell good?
- [Student] So bees will go to them.
- Why do people go to trouble to smell good?
- [Student] (inaudible)
- Why not?
- [Student] Because, it would be gross.
- Say that again.
- Attention?
- You want attention?
You want to be attractive
to other people too?
- [Student] Heck no.
- Maybe you're too young for that.
Yeah, when you get older, don't you want
to attract other people?
- [Student] Sure.
- Don't you want other
people to find you pleasant?
- [Student] Yes.
- You know, it's not a big thing,
but are these fragrances
signals to these insects?
They're attractive right?
And we'll talk about, I
agree, they are useful,
but that's not going to fit
into my process just yet.
But all of these things do
attract the insects, right?
But what is it that keeps the insects
coming back?
It's sort of like the color, the smell,
you know, the, maybe
the shape of the flower.
All of these things
are like advertisements
to the insects.
Why?
- [Student] For the nectar?
- For the nectar.
It's the nectar that's going
to keep them coming back.
All right, you see this bee here?
What's all this yellow stuff on the bee?
- [Students] Pollen?
- Pollen.
Does the pollen attract the bee?
- [Students] No.
- Does the bee want the pollen?
- [Student] Yes and
no because the pollen
helps all of the flowers to stay alive.
- [Teacher] The pollen is definitely
important to the flower, right?
- [Student] Mm-hm? The bees
just spread it around.
- [Teacher] The bees spread it around?
How many people are aware
that bees spread pollen?
I see just about all your hands go up.
So the insects are spreading,
let's put that up here,
they're going to spread
the stuff called pollen.
Right?
Of course, the insects
are really getting what?
- [Students] Nectar.
- Yeah, so let's put they are taking
or they obtain this nectar here, right?
And nectar is another word for what?
- [Students] Food.
- You all understand that
nectar is their food?
- [Student] For the bees.
- [Teacher] For the bees?
Just the bees?
- [Student] No, and hummingbirds.
- And insects?
- [Student] Us.
- And hummingbirds?
- [Student] Us, us, we have honey.
Nectar is technically honey.
- So, nectar is actually a food for us,
because we steal it from the bees, right?
- Yeah.
- And we hide it from the bears, yes?
- [Student] Isn't there this one
point where it has saliva, or something
in the bottom of it, and it's in the shape
of a picture, and all of
these flies and everything
are attracted from the
sweet smell and everything,
and they get into the water,
they can't move and
everything, they're paralyzed?
- Okay, it's a trap.
- [Student] Yeah.
- [Student] Like the venus fly trap.
- Just like the venus fly trap.
- [Student] Yeah, I don't know what it's called.
- Do venus fly traps have flowers?
- [Student] No, they have clear white.
- [Student] The mouth smells really sweet.
- [Student] That's because it catches flies.
- Okay, we're going to talk
about that in a minute.
A lot of people, when I was
reading your paragraphs,
a lot of people told
me that venus fly traps
were one of the many kinds of plants
that don't have flowers.
All right, but let's look
at this thing about pollen
for a minute.
Why is it that the
flowers want these insects
to keep stealing their nectar?
What's going on here?
They want them to spread
the pollen, but why?
- [Student] To make more food?
- [Teacher] To make what?
- [Teacher] You think
it's to make more food.
What do you think Olivia?
- [Olivia] To make like honey.
- [Teacher] The flowers
want the bees to make honey?
- [Olivia] No, they like
need it to make more food.
- [Student] Pollen is an
ingredient for nectar to make.
- I understand that,
but why does the flower
go to all this trouble?
Do flowers just like bees?
- [Student] No.
- They say hey, you're a nice guy.
We'll make you some...
- [Student] To keep them alive, I think?
- To keep... the flowers
are making the food
to keep the bees alive?
- [Students] No.
- [Student]  I don't know.
- [Teacher] That's okay, that's okay.
What do you think, Joe?
- [Joe] To fertilize other flowers?
- Fertilize?
What's fertilize?
You mean to like give them
like fertilizer on the ground?
Or are you talking about a
different kind of fertilizer?
- Different.
- You're calling it a
different kind of fertilizer.
Interesting.
How many people understand that flowers
are related to fertilization?
How many people have heard that before?
Hands up here, okay.
So, if you want to ask what pollen is,
you might want to ask what flowers do.
All right and to answer
that, I first of all,
let's make sure, this
dandelion, is this a flower
or is this a weed?
- [Students] Flower.
- [Students] A weed.
- Okay, thumbs up or thumbs down.
Who says it's a weed?
Okay?
I see most of you thumbs
up, a couple of you
have sideways or down.
Next, how about this one,
how many people think
it's a flower?
Okay.
How many people say it's
a weed and a flower?
Now I see some people who don't know.
Well, let me ask you this.
If you're to look at this, here's a pretty
good picture of it, what
makes you think it's a flower?
Are there characteristics about this plant
that make you think it's a flower?
- [Student] Yes.
- [Student] I don't think it's a flower...
- That's not my question.
Are there characteristics
about this that make you
think it's a flower?
- [Student] Yes.
- What would those be?
- The petals?
- The petals? Excellent.
Anything else?
- [Student] It's color?
- It's colorful?
Anything else?
- [Student] It has some nectar, maybe?
- You think it has nectar?
- [Student] Maybe a little bit.
- Have you ever seen insects hovering
around dandelions?
- Yes.
- Who have seen... who have seen?
Yeah, it's very common.
Well, you can actually see bees on top of,
on top of flowers.
Here's a close up of the dandelion.
What do you notice there?
- [Student] That looks a lot more ugly?
- It looks ugly?
- [Student] Yeah.
- Really?
- [Student] No it looks cool.
- [Student] It looks like water spouts
goin' like...
- It does look like water.
What do you see on the side here?
- [Student] Pollen.
- Does that look like pollen?
What does pollen look like?
- [Student] Just tiny balls of... stuff.
- Of stuff, yeah?
- There those tiny little,
like, they look like
little leftover pieces
just hanging off the side
of the stem and it's with the bees
and it sticks to the bees
when they land on the flower,
so it stays with them for a while.
A ball and then it sticks to the bee,
like if you want to see the
bee, it's got all the yellow stuff
on his leg?
- [Voiceover] Yeah, we had
the picture earlier, yeah.
- [Student] Yeah, I saw a bee on
a flower in the summer
and he had a bunch of that yellow stuff
on his body?
- [Teacher] Cool.
- [Student] Actually, that's the pollen.
- So the pollen, so it
is picking up pollen.
So, it sounds to me that,
I guess what I want
to convince you is that
dandelions are flowers.
- [Students] They are?
- Yeah, they're definitely flowers.
Let me show you a picture of a dandelion.
A little video, it's
about one minute long,
and let's go ahead and
turn the lights off.
And as you're watching it, just tell me
what you observe happening in the video.
Just go ahead and shout it out.
- [Students] The flower is
opening, it's blossoming.
- Okay, this is time
lapse, so this is happening
a lot faster than what it really normally,
but you saw the flower open?
- [Student] It's dormant, dying now.
- [Teacher] And now it's closing up
and it's dying.
- [Student] It's going dormant.
- [Teacher] It's dead.
How many people think it's dead?
- [Student] No, it's still growing.
- [Student] It's dormant.
- [Student] It's growing
into that white stuff.
- [Teacher] Say that again?
- [Marissa] It's turning
into that thing in the ball.
- [Teacher] That's like,
Marissa's making a prediction.
- [Student] It's gonna grow taller.
- [Student] No, it's going to break up.
- [Teacher] Do you see
the insects all over it?
Every now and then you can kind of
see an insect on it.
- [Student] Oh, yeah.
- [Student] Yeah, there's
one down at the root.
- [Teacher] At the very base of it.
- [Student] Yeah, something's happening.
- [Teacher] Something's happening.
- [Student] It got taller on the screen.
- [Teacher] Oh, the bottom
petals are starting to die.
- [Student] (inaudible)
- [Teacher] What's that?
- [Student] It's starting
to look like an onion.
- [Teacher] What's
that thing on the top?
- [Student] It's going to blow away.
- [Student] It's going
to grow into a dandelion.
- [Teacher] That was
the flower, wasn't it?
- [Student] That's
the thing you blow on.
- [Teacher] What's that?
- [Student] They're
seeds, they're seeds!
- [Student] Yeah, you
blow on them and it's really fun.
- [Student] It's reproducing.
- [Teacher] I'm hearing
Steven say they're seeds.
And Brandon, oh that thing disappeared.
That whole top blew away.
- [Student] That's the
stuff that you like to blow.
- [Teacher] How many
people think these are seeds?
- [Andrew] I know they are.
- [Teacher] Ah, Andrew's thinking.
So the flower turned into what?
- [Student] A seed.
- [Student] A reproducer.
- [Teacher] A big seed?
- [Student] No,
they're all little seeds.
- [Student] No, they're all individual seeds.
- [Teacher] Are they blowing?
- [Students] Yes.
- [Teacher] Make a wish.
Can I have the lights on please.
So you have...
- [Student] Like a month period.
- [Teacher] Yeah, that took a while.
And I think you've seen dandelions,
you may not have, you've probably seen
the dandelions in two stages.
Sometimes they're like gel flowers
and later they turn into
these little white, puffy,
seed pods, right?
- [Student] You puff on them and they
blow in the wind.
- [Teacher] Yeah, what does the wind do?
- [Student] It blows them away
and it starts reproducing.
- So each seed is like a little parachute?
- [Student] Yeah.
- And it's dispersed to new lands?
- [Student] Yes.
- All right, so if I were to say flowers,
if I were to make a
connection between flowers
and seeds, what would you say about that?
What will you say?
What is the connection
between flowers and seeds?
McKenzie?
- [McKenzie] They both reproduce.
- [Teacher] They're both
related to reproduction.
Okay, uh-huh?
- [Student] One makes another?
- Okay, so one flowers make seeds
or flowers produce seeds,
and there's that word
that McKenzie was using, reproduce
because seeds grow into...
- [Student] Flowers?
- Flowers which then...
- [Student] Grow into seeds?
- [Teacher] Which then...
- [Student] Grow into more plants?
- [Teacher] What does that sound like?
- [All Students] Life cycles!
- Wonderful, wonderful,
these are life cycles.
What I'm going to ask you to do right now,
is we're going to look at a seed
very, very closely.
I have some, you know what these are?
Lima beans?
- [Student] Oh, I love lima beans.
- You do, really?
- [Student] Yeah.
- Oh, I don't like lima beans.
- [Student] I've never tried them.
- [Student] I like
them in my favorite dish,
chicken pot pie.
- My dad loves lima beans, anyway.
I have some. They have been soaking overnight
in some water, and they're going to look
a little bit different
because they've been soaking
under water.
What I want you to do
is, when you get one,
I want you to open it up, like a book.
Dig your thumbnails into
the side of the seed
and open it up very
carefully, and I want you
to look inside.
That's what the magnifying
glasses are for.
I want you to be able to tell me what
do you find inside the seed?
Everyone clear?
Go ahead, one person
from each table come up
and get a couple of seeds?
- [Student] How many?
- Oh, you know what?
Get maybe three of them
in case one of them
doesn't work.
We have a spare.
Three not unbroken, nice plump seeds.
Take them to your seat.
I just want you to look at them.
- [Student] They're bigger.
- [Teacher] They are bigger, aren't they?
What else are they?
- [Student] They're sort of hard.
- [Student] They look
like mandarin oranges.
- [Teacher] (laughing) Why's that,
what makes you think they're like oranges?
- [Students] They're not hard anymore!
- They're no what?
- [Student] They're not hard anymore.
- They're not hard.
- [Student] We grew them last year.
- What's that?
- Oh, you grew these last year.
What do these turn into?
- [Voiceover] Farmer's (inaudible).
- [Teacher] They turn into plants?
- [Student] What are we
supposed to be looking for?
- [Teacher] Well, you tell me.
Don't break them open.
Here's how I want you...
Can I borrow this?
Okay, I want you to go
to the round part here,
and you notice it has like a seed coat?
- [Students] Yeah.
- Okay, you know kind of peel that back.
- [Student] Oh cool?
- And then open it up like a book.
Okay?
- [Student] I'm looking at the skin.
- [Student] Like this?
- [Teacher] Yeah, open it up like a book
and look inside and see what you find.
There's a little surprise there.
- [Students] What is this?
- [Student] It's a bug!
- [Teacher] It's located... yeah.
- [Student] Oh, gross.
- [Student] Mine's already broken so.
- [Teacher] Well, you
have a good one right here.
This is perfect.
- [Student] Oh I see it.
- [Teacher] Look at that.
That's a really good one.
- [Student] I don't see it.
- [Teacher] Yeah, go ahead break it.
Just like you did.
- [Student] I can't open it.
- And oh, yours is right here.
Yours kind of fell apart.
Do you have another seed?
Be there in a second.
- [Student] Okay.
- Oh, there it is right there.
Do you see that?
- [Student] I don't have one.
- Look at it very carefully
with the magnifiers.
What do you have?
Let me see what you got.
Yeah, right there.
There's actually part of it right here,
broke in half and that's attached,
and there's also a little bit here.
Perfect, look at this, Patrick.
That's what you want to look at.
- [Student] I can't open mine.
- [Teacher] See it, see it there?
What do you see?
- [Student] I don't see it.
- [Teacher] Oh, there is
a little bit of green there,
isn't there?
- [Student] Yeah.
- [Teacher] Who else is having trouble?
- [Student] Me.
- [Student] I already opened mine.
- [Teacher] Yes you did.
- [Student] Are they
supposed to smell bad?
- [Teacher] Yeah, they do
kind of smell, don't they?
- [Student] Yeah, they smell.
- Did you see that whole thing
right on the tip?
Look at that under the magnifying glass.
Okay, okay look at my photograph up here.
Here we go.
This is kind of what you're looking at.
You have these two like
little half circles,
little kidney shaped starchy figures,
but what is this thing right here?
- [Student] It's a seed. It's starting
to sprout.
- What is it?
- [Student] It's a start of a lima bean.
- I thought this whole thing right here.
- [Student] It's the
start of a lima bean plant.
- [Teacher] This is like
a plant sprouting out.
Is that what you're trying to say Steven?
What's that?
Is there anything about
this that makes you
look like a plant or
makes you think it might
be a plant?
- [Steven] Like that, like the
big parts might be like,
maybe like the soil or the stuff
that needs to get bigger?
Like when we add water to stuff
it starts to get bigger?
- [Teacher] Well, did you
notice there are two parts
to it?
- [Steven] Yeah.
- [Student] Yeah, it like goes down?
- [Teacher] There is,
what's this right here?
- [Student] It's the sprout.
- [Teacher] Okay, I
heard you say it looks
like a stem.
Anybody think it looks like anything else?
Uh-huh?
Go ahead, McKenzie?
Why are these pointing here?
Why are these pointed?
- [McKenzie] It's kind of new.
- [Teacher] That makes sense.
- [Student] Looking to break through.
- [Teacher] Break through the...
- [Student] The soil.
- And what breaks through the soil?
What part of the plant
breaks through the soil?
- [Student] The seed?
- [Student] The root?
- Does it look like a root?
- [Students] Yeah.
- How many people think it looks
a little bit like a root?
And this looks a little bit like a stem.
What does this look like to you?
- [Student] A flower.
- Let me see, it looks like this
and there's another one that
kind of looks like that.
What does that look like to you?
- [Student] Leaves.
- Leaves.
What do leaves, okay.
Do you ever see anybody draw pictures?
Whats that?
- [Student] It looks like a carrot.
- (laughing) It looks like a carrot,
doesn't it?
Okay, look at those leaf like structures
very carefully with your magnifier.
I want you to look for a detail.
You see a little characteristic.
- [Student] Oh I see it, I see it!
- What do you see?
- [Student] I see like the veins of a leaf.
- Wonderful.
- [Student] I don't. Oh yeah, I do.
- Wonderful, you have little veins there
on the leaf?
Yeah, you can see.