- To learn today.
We're going to begin a unit on indoor
ultimate frisbee, and
we've got the indoor, soft
styrofoam frisbee, all right?
One thing about the frisbee
I want you to understand,
number one, it's styrofoam.
That means you can easily break them.
All right, please don't bend
them like I'm doing here
any more than I just did.
Obviously, tugging on them, pulling them,
poking them is going to harm the frisbee.
You want it to be intact,
so just use the frisbee
as it's meant to be used,
and don't play with it
in any other way, okay?
So that way we keep the
frisbee in good shape.
Now, here is the question
we want to answer:
why do frisbees fly?
A lot of different reasons,
and a lot of these reasons
have to do with the concept of flight.
All right, like an
airplane, like a helicopter,
or a paper airplane, okay?
Now, frisbee flight's a little different
than some other types of flight.
Firstly we're going to look
at this: angular momentum,
big word, but the concept
of angular momentum
essentially means that frisbees fly,
one of the reasons why
frisbees fly and maintain
stability in flight is because they spin.
So, the fact that the frisbees spin
is called angular momentum.
All right, and again, that's what produces
stability in the air.
You find angular momentum
in a lot of things.
You guys ever use a top, a spinning top?
- [Class member] Yes, at home.
- That's an act of a football as a top.
If I just balance this
football, it'll fall, right?
It doesn't remain upright.
But, when I spin the football like a top,
it maintains its upright position.
That is angular momentum.
That is why it does not fall down.
The force of friction will eventually
slow down the football,
and that's why it will
topple over and fall,
but while it's spinning,
angular momentum is what keeps it up.
When a frisbee spins,
the reason why it doesn't
wobble in flight and fall from the air
is because it's supposed to
spin, as you can see there,
and that's what keeps it stable.
That's also what helps us
to throw it accurately.
Another concept is angular lift.
Angular lift, like an airplane.
There's different pressures
above and below the wing.
These concepts are really complicated
if you look into them in detail,
but the basic gist of this concept is that
there's a low pressure on top,
and a high pressure on the bottom,
and when I throw the airplane,
that pressure difference
is what gives it lift
and allows it to fly, okay?
Now, one thing I'm going to do
before I throw this airplane
is I'm going to use force.
Force production, I produce
force behind the plane
and that allows it to fly.
In the same way, I will produce
force behind the frisbee,
and that will allow it to fly.
The other end is force absorption,
which we'll talk about in just a minute.
So again, aerodynamic lift is when
the pressure differences
allow this airplane to lift,
and I'm going to produce
force for that to happen.
- [Class member] Can I go get it?
- No, we'll leave that there, all right?
Now, I need one person to demonstrate
how to throw the frisbee properly.
Julia, please.
(class members not chosen complain)
I'll have you stand here, now watch.
You're going to, listen,
I'm going to go over this
one time with you, and
then you're going to
use these checklists on the cones
to teach one another
how to do it properly.
Now, I know a lot of you, listen, please.
I know a lot of you would
like when you do the frisbee,
you can throw the frisbee,
but there's one...
The difference between really
just throwing the frisbee
and understanding how
to throw the frisbee.
Understanding the
mechanics behind it, okay?
So, the mechanics behind
throwing a frisbee
are just this:
the mechanics behind a frisbee are this:
number one, I need to know my target.
Two, when throwing a frisbee,
you step with the same foot.
Not the opposite foot, like
when you throw a baseball,
but rather, I step with the same foot.
I'm going to point my elbow at my target,
I'm going to curl my wrist and bring the
frisbee across my chest.
Girls, I need you to pay attention.
If you miss this instruction it's going to
be more complicated later.
So, I'm going to step towards my target,
frisbee curled up to my chest,
and then point my elbow at my target.
Now, when I extend my elbow,
I'm going to snap my wrist.
That's going to create
the spin that gives this
one, two, three...
- [Class] Angular momentum.
- Angular momentum.
And that's what's going
to give it stability.
So, I'm going to step, point the elbow,
snap the wrist, point to my target,
produce force, and on the other end,
what Julia's going to do, once I throw it,
is she's going to use force absorption.
She's going to catch it.
Fundamentals of catching.
Julia, what I'd like you to do is,
square yourself with the frisbee.
If the frisbee moves to your right,
I want you to move to your right, okay?
If it moves to your left, I
want you to move to your left.
Because you want to meet it,
and square your body to it.
And last, I want you to put
your hands in this position,
palms together and fingers out.
All right, they don't have to be touching,
but we're going to try
to pancake the frisbee.
All right, hopefully my throw goes well.
Here we go.
Step, elbow, oh, wrist snap, release.
One more thing I forgot to mention,
release it level with the ground.
If I release it at an angle
here, it's going to go
up or down this way, if I
release it at an angle here,
it's going to go up or down this way.
So, release it level, one
more thing to remember.
Ready?
Step, nice try.
Don't laugh, don't laugh.
All right, I want you
to try the same thing.
I want you to step with the same foot,
point your elbow in, and when you throw,
throw it, point your finger at me,
remember to release it level.
You're ready, go.
Yes!
It's all right, you can
grab it with one hand,
there's no problem with that.
That frisbee had good
spin on it, all right.
She released it, did she release it level?
- [Class member] No.
- No, that's why it bounced off the wall.
One more time, step, elbow, wrist snap,
point, release level.
Good catch.
- [Class member] Nice one, dude!
- Here you go, you got it.
Perfect.
Now, I could have moved
to the side a little bit
to catch that frisbee,
but I did a little reach,
and that's okay, too.
All right, so with your
groups of four, remember,
wait, wait, wait!
You're going to coach your
partner in throwing and catching,
use the checklist on the cones.
Ready, set, grab one frisbee, go.
(class shuffles around)
(background chatter)
- Can I stand here?
- You and you, here.
You're going to be here.
You guys are all working together,
you're going to hold this.
Wait, wait, wait!
There should be two on each cone,
one person holding the cone.
Stop, where's your partner?
You're going to coach her throwing.
You're going to go first, and I want you
to catch it, and then throw it to her,
and you're going to be catching,
and every couple tries,
we're going to switch.
Okay, pick up your cone and coach.
Pick up your cone...
(background chatter)
You're the instructor,
he's going to catch, right?
All right.
You're the instructor,
you should watch her.
(background chatter)
- One, two, three, frisbee!
- Make sure you're reading and helping!
(background chatter)
All right, practice a couple times,
and, three, stop!
Stop, stop, stop.
Now, with the catch,
with the force absorption, okay?
You're absorbing that throw, listen.
I know that the throws aren't
all going to be accurate,
that's all the more reason
why you have to move
to where you think the
frisbee's going to land,
and meet the oncoming frisbee, okay?
So, with your partner's
help, coach's help,
keep practicing, and we're going to switch
in just a minute.
Make sure you correct
any improper technique.