♪ [music] ♪
- [Instructor] Okay. What was this Animoto
video telling us? Can someone raise
their hand and... Yes, Brandy.
- [Brandy] Telling you not to plagiarize.
- [Instructor] Telling you not to
plagiarize. Very good. So, if that's what
you were thinking, you are thinking about
what we're going to talk about today,
which is plagiarism. Now, I'm going to go
on the internet right now and we're going
to look at the definition of plagiarism.
Well, actually, we're going to look at the
definition for plagiarize, which is "to
steal and pass-off as your own." So, you
can think of internet plagiarism as equal
to...
- [students] Cheating.
- [Instructor] Cheating, and that is
considered...
- [students] Academic misconduct.
- [Instructor] Academic misconduct, and
that's when you get in big trouble
sometimes. Now, we're going to watch a
TeacherTube video about plagiarism. So,
you will be using your worksheet, and
we're going to hear a story about this kid
named Billy, and you've got some bubbles
here. So, right here in the central box is
what you're going to write down-- you're
going to write in this box, and you can't
write anything yet because nothing's
happened so far, but you're going to write
about what Billy did. And in the little
circles right here you're going to write
the causes, why it probably happened, and
you're going to predict what happens to
Billy. So, we're going to start right now
so I want everybody to listen carefully.
Here we go.
- [Mr. Harris] Mrs. Calstad
- [Mrs. Calstad] Hey Mr. Harris.
- I have to show you this research report
by Billy. He did it on horses. It sounds
really good. The pictures are good, too.
- Oh, I love horses, let me see it. Wow,
Mr. Harris, this is really good.
- I told you it was.
- But you know what, it kind of sounds
familiar. I've seen a lot of students
looking at this website called
allhorses.info, and I think it's some of
this exact same information. I think we
should check it out.
- Let's pull it up.
- Sure.
- Here's the website, Mr. Harris, and it
says right here, "The horse has been one
of the most popular domesticated animals
for centuries." What does Billy's report
say?
- "The horse has been one of the most
popular domesticated animals for
centuries."
- So, it's the exact same sentence? That's
not good.
- That's not good. That's cheating.
- And look at that picture, too. It's the
exact same photo.
- That is the exact same photo.
- Did Billy give credit to his sources
anywhere on that page?
- No. I don't see it anywhere.
- No. Well, that's a pretty serious thing.
- I've heard of students in college being
expelled for that.
- Really?
- Yes.
- I think they call it plagiarism when you
copy someone else's work and don't give
them credit, and that's a shame, because
all Billy had to do was write down where
he got his facts, and give some credit to
that photo, too.
- How could he have written his report
differently?
- Well, if you look at his first sentence,
when it says "The horse has been one of
the most popular domesticated animals for
centuries, " he just could've changed the
words a little bit. Maybe he could have
explained what domesticated means. I don't
think that's a word that he would use a
lot.
- I see what you mean.
- What could he have done with this
picture though?
- Well, he could use this picture. If he
took the picture himself, he wouldn't have
to do anything, but if he did take it from
this website, which it looks like he did,
he'd just need to copy the web address
down at the top, and that would be it.
That way, he could give the photographer
credit for that person's work.
- So, what you're saying is, it's okay to
use facts from other sources, just put
them in your own words.
- Correct.
- And, be sure to include, in your report,
who wrote these facts.
- Exactly, and as far as the photos go,
you can use a photo as long as you include
the web address that's on your screen, and
I think in library and psychology class
you and I will work on that with students
so everyone will know how they can
properly give credit to their sources.
- We definitely will. That sounds good.
Now we just need to talk to Billy about
this.
- Sounds like a plan.
- Where is that Billy?
- [Instructor] Okay, you have your work
sheets. Let's start filling them out right
now. Make sure your name's on your paper,
and we won't take too long, we've got some
extra time [inaudible] as well. So, when you start
writing, if you have a question, raise your hand.
You're going to do the predicted cause and
the predicted effects.
Now, while you're filling these out, I'm
also going to ask a question. I want
to do a quick question. What do you think
happened to Billy? Can somebody raise
their hand and tell me? What do you think
might happen to Billy?
- [male student] He got in trouble with
the teacher.
- [Instructor] He probably got in trouble
with the teacher. Anybody else?
- [female student] Detention.
- [Instructor] And possibly detention,
yes.
- [male student] Suspension.
- [Instructor] Say it one more time.
- [male student] A suspension.
- [Instructor] Very good. Okay. Now, let's
do a quick think pair share. Okay, what is the
message of this video? So, talk to you
neighbor. Let's think in a pair. Talk to
your neighbor. The person sitting right
next to you. Cassie, you work with Brandy.
Brandy, you work with Santiago. Talk to your neighbor
real quick. Your question is, what is the message of this video?
[Background Chatter]
Okay, we're going to stop right now. Raise
your hand if you can share, if you can
share out right now. Yes.
- [male student] He could use
facts and research [inaudible].
- [Instructor] Very good. So, if he used
facts and research information in his own
words this wouldn't have happened. Yes.
- [female student] He has to give credit
to the original site, or the place he got
it.
- [Instructor] Very good. Thank you,
Cassie, that was great. Okay. So, now
we've done our video, and I just wanted to
say that, as a sixth grader, I made a big
mistake. Before they had the internet, I
used an encyclopedia set and I copied
stuff into my report, and I thought
"Here's the information, " I didn't realize
I was actually plagiarizing it because I
didn't put it in my own words. So, now
what we're going to do is, we're going to
move over to our renaissance responders.
So, right now, you're all logged in, and I
am going to go over to that right now, and
we have a survey. So, it's all
re-programmed, and we're ready to go, and
what we're going to do is, we're going to
flip our paper to the back side, and
you've got your questions right here.
We're doing an anonymous survey to find
out how you feel about plagiarism. So, I
don't want you to feel that it's going to
be something that I'm going to know your
response to, because it really is going to
be anonymous, and I want you to circle the
answer that is the most popular response
to the group. So, when you look up here,
you're going to see a graph, and you're
going to circle the answer that is the
most popular and you're going to star the
answer that is the second most popular.
Okay. What is the level of plagiarism at
our school? You have three choices,
"students do not plagiarize very often,"
that's letter A; B, "about half of the
students plagiarize;" C, "almost everyone
plagiarizes." Go ahead and
respond. Now, we're going to look at the
graph, and we're waiting for everybody to
respond right now, and I'm looking and I
can see some people have responded and
some people have not responded. On your
paper, you will be circling the most
popular response, and you're starring the
second most popular response. Can somebody
tell me what the most popular response is
right now?
- [together] A.
- [Instructor] A. Okay, and that was,
"students don't plagiarize very often."
That's good to know. So, go ahead and mark
on your paper right now. A has a circle
around it for number one, and our second
most popular response actually is C and E,
so both of those will get starred. I'm so
sorry, did I say E? I meant C. I think
that what happened is, somebody made a
response in a column that they shouldn't
have made a response in that column. So,
they answered the wrong question. So, you
did it the proper way. We're going to move
on to our question number two.