- Alright Anne Carol, what's your job?
How much sugar are you putting in?
- Two tablespoons.
There you go, fill it all the
way up to the top, Thomason.
That's okay.
Thomas, can you show her?
There you go.
That's okay.
You'll get it, we're
gonna make a mess today.
There you go, Caleb, way
to open the bag for her.
Go ahead, Anne Carol.
Why don't you pull it --
There you go.
- One half cup of milk.
- Good job, Anne Carol.
- One more.
- We need more. Need more.
- That's good, that's good.
- There you go.
Alright, good job, baby girl.
What did we put in it?
- Milk.
- You can do it.
- One whole cup.
- Hang on, it's leaking.
- Milk.  Milk spills.
- Okay, we'll get it.
You're good. Alright.
Help them put it in there.
- That was exactly one cup.
- Exactly one cup.
[Background Chatter]
- Next is the milk.
- That's okay.
There you go.
- Okay, now
I need this Anne Carol.
- Oh, okay.
- I need the other side.
- Careful, vanilla is
really expensive.
- I got it.
- Vanilla.
How much did you put in?
- A half.
- Half a teaspoon.
Alright, we're almost ready.
- That was cool.
- Whose turn is it?
- Uh, my turn.
[Background Chatter]
- It looks like chocolate milk.
- A half cup?
- Half cup.
Alright Anne Carol, how
ya doin' over there?
Good.
It does look like pudding.
- A liquid.
- It's a liquid.
Do you think that's
a solid Anne Carol?
- No!
- What is it?
- Smells like it.
- That's okay, it'll get all over.
That's okay.
Sure, no problem.
Yeah, get it up to the top.
There you go.
- Okay, now.
- Look good?
- Yeah!
- Alright.
- Can we seal it?
- Is that one of your directions?
Is that the next one?
Did we get everything in?
- Yes.
Did we get sugar?
- Yep.
- Did we get our milk?
- Our vanilla?
- Yes.
And our regular and our condensed milk?
- Alright.
Make sure it's sealed
really, really good.
- We need the other bag.
- Give me that bag, sweetie.
- Here you go.
- Yep, it's closed.
- That's good we have two bags.
- Oh, what you got in there, Thomas?
- It's ice and rocks.
- Is it sealed really, really good?
Alright hold on we're
gonna put this in first.
Hold on.
Alright, what's in here?
- Rock salt and ice.
Now, what is this?
- Liquid.
- You think it's gonna freeze it?
Turn it to ice cream.
Let's find out.
Alright, this one's
gotta be sealed first.
Go ahead, Thomas.
Seal it really, really good.
You don't want it to leak.
Alright.
Yeah, no cracks 'cause we
don't want it to leak.
Think it's good?
Alright, and then do this one.
Ready Anne Carol?
- Uh-huh.
- We still got one
more thing to do.
- Four bags.
Isn't that right, Ms. Moore?
- That's right, Caleb.
- Only two more.
- There's like one bag
and then three in there.
Let's see you make some ice cream.
- Shake it and eat it.
- Yeah.
- About 30 seconds of shaking.
- Yeah it looks cool.
- Why you think we put
rock salt in ice?
- It makes the flavor?
- Oh, it's so cold!
- It keeps ice from melting.
- It does keep the ice from melting.
Very good.
Is it cold Anne Carol?
- What happened to that?
- We have like this ice cream maker,
and we like put in it
and then we turn it on
and it makes good --
- My turn? Alright.
I'm gonna get this --
My hands are gonna cold.
I'm gonna try to get
the bag in the center.
Why you think?
[Background Chatter]
- I'm rubbing my hands
so they can get warm.
- Do you think it's a solid yet?
- Rub your hands.
Your turn.
It's gonna take a little while.
Yeah, you can warm your hands up.
Because, what's gonna happen
if our hands are warmer?
- It makes more warm.
- Yeah, it's gonna make
it easier isn't it?
Alright you keep making
that ice cream,
I'm gonna go check on
the other group, okay.
Help each other. Help each other.
- Pass it on to Thomas.
- Hey Thomas?
- It's on the side, we have
to get it in the middle.
And the other kind needs to get cold.
- Oh! Oh, it's so cold!
- Caleb.
- My turn, please. My turn.
- No you already did it.
- My turn. It's my turn now.
- It's starting to look like it?
- It's mixed together.
- Oh my goodness.
- Whoa that's cold.
[ice rustling]
- You think it's gonna turn into a solid?
Is that what's gonna happen?
- Solid and liquid.
- A solid and liquid?
- Yeah because it melts.
- Oh, if it melts it's gonna be a?
- Liquid.
- Do you think that is a gas, Anne Carol?
- No.
- What do you think it is?
- A solid.
It could turn into a liquid.
Do you think that an ice cube --
Hold on, Amy's got a good question.
What did you say?
- Maybe sometimes it could
turn into a gas state.
- How would you turn it into a gas?
- Boil it.
- You boil it. Very good.
- It could melt too and turn into a --
- It could turn into one as it melts.
- My house is a solid.
Your house is a solid, Anne Carol.
Good job.
- It's so cold.
- Shake it, shake it.
Give it a good shake.
[laughter]
Alright, I'll be right back, guys.
- Try not to squeeze
it, then it might pop.
- Ms. Moore?
- Yes ma'am?
- Will you do it, please?
- You want me to help you?
Okay.
Let's re-check it and see?
- Have to open a lot of bags.
- What is it still?
- Liquid.
- So we're get it right in the middle.
You wanna feel it?
- Whoa.
- It's still a liquid.
Is it getting colder?
- Yes.
It did mix together, didn't it?
We're gettin there.
It does look like
that now, doesn't it?
That's okay.
Alright, ready guys?
We're gonna get it more in there.
- There's like 50 pieces of ice in there.
- There is a lot of them.
Alright, here goes your turn, Kevin.
Getting colder. Getting colder.
- Hey look --
- What you need, sweetie?
- Aw, thank you, darling.
Keeping your hands warm there, Thomas?
Ready to go?
Do you think it's easier to
go to the store or make it?
- To the store.
- Make it.
- Is it more fun to make it?
- Yeah.
Yes ma'am?
[Background Chatter]
- That's okay.
You can make up your own flavor.
Alright, if it's not your turn,
what I want you to do,
is you're gonna start to filling
out these questions, okay?
Yep, you can start
filling those out.
Alright, you start
You can help each
other with these.
So what did you make?
- Ice cream.
- One thing was solid,
what was that, Kayla?
- Sugar.
- Ice!
Ice and sugar.
- Oh, we did use ice.
We did use ice.
- So three.
- What else is in here, though?
What else is in here?
- Rock salt.
- There you go.
- Guys we're almost done!
Look, look at it.
- Keep going. Yes?
It shows, what were
the solids you used?
Good, you have one of them on there.
- Salt.
- Yep.
- We used salt.
- It's gonna be vanilla ice cream.