- And I'm going to look
at what number that is
and I see that that is
20 inches, okay?
Now, your information that you get,
we're going to be writing
in our chart here.
So do you see at the
bottom of your page,
it has ramp with one book,
you're going to write
the distance that
your car moved.
Now don't write 20 inches,
'cause yours is
going to be different, okay?
You write how far your car
went for ramp number one.
Okay?
Hold on just a second Isabelle.
Now, I gave you guys numbers.
And the numbers are
so that we all get
a chance to do every
part of this experiment.
The number one person is
going to set up the ramp.
So they're going to
put the dictionary
and the ramp, get it all
set up for the group.
The number two person
is going to get
to hold the car, and let it go, okay?
And then the number three person,
is going to measure the distance
that it went, okay?
Close attention (mumbles).
Okay, so you're going
to all have a job to do.
Now this is with the one dictionary.
When we do the experiment next, we're
going to try it with two dictionaries
and see how it changes, okay?
But for right now, we're going
to try just one dictionary.
Are there any questions
before we get started?
Miguel.
- Like, the first one goes first,
and then on the second thing,
like you try to set
the number one does
the second job,
and the second person
does the number three
and the number three
does the number one job?
- Yes, so everyone is
going to get a chance to do
every single part of
the experiment, okay?
So we don't need to fight
over who gets to do the car,
and who can get that, okay?
Isabelle, question?
- But what if we do the same,
each of us what we do?
- Oh, if that's what you
get, if you get 20 inches
on yours, then you write
that down, okay?
Yes.
Angie.
- When you took...
- No, we're all going
to talk to each other
in nice, friendly voices,
that's right.
Okay, Max, last question, and then
we need to get started.
- Are we going to use the rulers?
- Yes, you're going to use the rulers.
And I know I didn't give
those to the groups,
but I'm going to pass
those out right now, okay?
Can I have you guys
please quietly walk
with your papers and your
pencil to your group?
[Background Chatter]
- Who's going to set up the ramp?
- Me.
[Background Chatter]
- Okay, you're number two.
- Start it in the corner?
[Background Chatter]
- It's a meter.
- Come on over here.
Okay, get your paper.
- No, but watch out!
- Don't do it!
- Awesome!
[Background Chatter]
- Okay boys and girls, once you get
to your group, you can
go ahead and get started.
- It looks farther.
- And this group, you may use
this ruler.
- Okay, measure it.
One right here, and then here.
- Are you okay?
[Background Chatter]
- No, from here.
- From there, there.
No, Ms. Sprano said from here.
Nine inches.
No, 11,11, 11 inches.
- It looks like eight.
Wait is, oh no it's eight.
Remember what Ms. Sprano said?
- No, she said from the front.
- Actually, I said from the back.
Good listening Miguel.
So how far did the car go?
- Eight inches.
- Eight inches, okay, excellent.
So write down your information.
You've got a pencil right here.
Okay so the next step,
Isabelle, Miguel and Angie.
Is you're going to try
it with two dictionaries.
Okay?
- But number three is
going to set it up?
- Look up at the chart to
see who's going to set it up.
- So, who's setting it up?
- Um, number two.
[Background Chatter]
- Okay, let's figure it out.
Okay, now go to your
group for a second.
Okay now, is this how far going to?
- Yea, 'till we go.
- Well wait a second,
are we measuring
from the top of the ramp, or are we
measuring from the bottom?
So, you're going to put the ruler
right up next to the edge of the ramp,
and then measure to the end of the car.
So how far did that car go?
- Five.
- No, it's to the end of the car.
So how far did the car go?
- Two.
- Two inches.
Now, do you guys think that
because you're on a thicker carpet,
that's going to change your results?
- It should go up like that.
- Do you think that the thicker carpet
is going to slow the car down and make it
not go so far?
- Yes.
- Yeah?
Would you guys like to move
to that part of the carpet?
- Yeah.
- Okay, you can move to that carpet,
and see what the difference is.
And you guys will have to share
that with the class, okay?
So try it again with just
one dictionary, okay?
- So then one.
[Background Chatter]
- Have to let the car go guys!
- We're going to try
it with two dictionaries.
- Okay, so look at the chart to see
who's going to set it up next.
- Oh my God, this
is going to be loud.
- We're good Ms. Sprano!
- She said from the very back!
- You set it up.
No, I mean, you let go.
- Who's turn is it?
You're doing the first one.
Who's number three?
We all have jobs to do.
Who's number one?
Okay, so your job is to
set up the ramp,
which you did a good job on.
Number two person, who's
the number two person?
So Giselle.
- I'm number three.
- No, she was two.
- It's fine, she's number three.
So Giselle, you're
going to let the car go,
and look, Esmeralda is going to measure.
Okay, so...
[Background Chatter]
Excellent.
Okay, now put that down.
Now which side do we
need to start with?
Very good.
And then we can spin
it around there.
So now you want to move it over
so that you can measure
at the end of the carpet.
Can you scoot it over some?
Very good, so how far
did the car go?
Seven inches, good.
Okay, so let's write
that down on our chart.
Finish yours.
Change this so it's seven inches.
Okay, now what's our next step,
what are we going to do next?
- I don't know.
- Are we going to try it
with two dictionaries?
Okay, so now, who's going to set that up?
Looks like the number two person,
so Giselle is going to
go ahead and set up
the dictionary, so put one
more dictionary on top.
Okay, good.
Well, number three is
going to let the car go.
So now it's Esmeralda's turn.
So you guys, what do you
think is going to happen?
Do you think it's
going to go farther,
or do you think
it's going to be closer?
When you let go of
the car right now,
what do you think
is going to happen?
You think it'll fall down?
Okay, well let's see what happens.
Woah, did you see how far that went?
Okay, don't pick it.
Now, wait a second, it's
Edgar's turn to measure.
So let's see, how far did it go Edgar?
So we measure to the, 14.
Wow, that went farther, didn't it?
So your next step is going to be
to do it with three dictionaries.
Please go sit down in your
group and raise your hand.
Let's go sit down at our group.
[Background Chatter]
- The car's there.
- 15 and a half!
- 15 and a half.
[Background Chatter]
15 and a half.
Who knows how to write 15 and a half?
[Background Chatter]
- So number two would get to
measure the distance on this one, okay?
[Background Chatter]
Okay, so let me see
how you're doing here.
Okay, well can we try it again?
Can we try it again?
So, you're on the second experiment.
So number three, who's
the number three person?
- He is.
- Jose's the number three person?
Okay, so Jose get's to let it go.
Should we move this out of the way,
or should we keep it here?
So, are you number three?
- No, I'm number one,
but number one
set it up.
But then see.
Oh.
- Okay so, it looks like it's
Jose's turn to let the car go.
So hand the car--
- No, he sets up ramp.
- Can you go sit down please,
and I'll be
right with you.
- Got it.
- Okay Jose, try it.
It's my car, put it right here
and let's see what happens.
Okay, let go.
Excellent, okay who's measuring?
- Me.
- Okay, so let's measure.
Now do we want it,
are we measuring with
inches or centimeters?
No, it's right, we're
doing it the right way.
Don't worry.
[Background Chatter]
15 inches.
Did it go farther,
or was it closer?
[Background Chatter]
Okay, so then I have a
question for you guys, listen.
If we put three dictionaries here,
do you think it's going to go farther,
or it's going to go closer?
- Farther.
- You think it's going to be farther?
What do you think Jose?
- Farther.
- What do you think?
- Well okay, we better check it out.
Did you write down your numbers?
So for the second one it was 15 inches.
Okay?
Now, we're on the last
part, that means the
number three person sets up the ramp.
Are you the number three person?
So set up the ramp, where's
your other dictionary?
Okay, so then we have to
use the dictionary, okay?
Can you let go?
Okay it's, oh wow that
might be pretty cool, huh?
Okay, so Devon it's your
turn to let the car go.
[Background Chatter]
And I like how you're
moving all the stuff out of the way.
Selena, you want to stay
there, or do you want to move?
Oh, okay.
So who's turn is it to measure?
Again?
- No, number one gets to.
- You know what, I think
we mixed it up.
Now, Selena lets go of the car.
And Devon measures this time, okay?
[Background Chatter]
Did you, okay, so maybe
it's Jose's turn.
Okay, go ahead.
(kids talking to each other)
Ooh, look how much it turned!
Okay, so measure how far it went.
[Background Chatter]
Okay, so measure how far it went,
let's see what happened.
- Do we move the...
[Background Chatter]
- 17.
Try it again, let's try it again.
[Background Chatter]
- Okay, let's see,
how are you guys doing?
You got all yours finished?
Okay, good.
Okay, well I haven't gone over that.
[Clapping]
[students clap]
Okay, boys and girls,
raise your hand if your
group had a chance
to do all three experiments.
All three.
Okay.