♪ Sing noel, sing noel, noel, noel ♪
- [Teacher] Please freeze for a moment.
Gentlemen, what did you think about your
performance? I wouldn't say "terrible,"
but were you accurately on pitch,
all of you?
- No.
- No. Like as soon as the ladies came in,
you were like, "Whoo," and then you
forgot what you were singing. Okay? So,
don't let them distract you. They're
trying. They're trying to have this
beautiful sound and pull you off. But hold
firm, men. Hold firm to your position.
All right? Let's try it again. Here we go.
♪ Sing noel, sing noel, noel, noel ♪
Lock it in.
Two parts.
♪ Sing noel, sing noel, noel, noel ♪
Together.
♪ Sing we all noel!♪
The support!
- Two parts.
♪ Sing we all noel! Sing we all noel! ♪
Back to the beginning.
♪ Sing noel, sing noel, noel, noel ♪
End song. All right. If you were going to
give yourself a grade, what would you give
it, Alison? As a class.
- [Alison] Like out of A's and B's and C's?
- Yep.
- I would give an A-minus.
- Okay, and why the minus? What do you
think we think need to improve?
- The pitch was kind of off at some parts.
- Okay. So there was maybe some pitch
issues. What about energy level? It was
okay, but this.... But one of the things
about African music is it is something
that is like felt in their soul. Okay. It
is traditionally, when you listen, I mean,
they are just letting it... You know, when
we see any of the performances, or listen
to any of the CDs we've listened to, it's
just very gut-felt. I feel like you're,
"♪ Sing noel, sing noel, noel, noel ♪" So,
"This is so pretty." Yes, we want, "♪ SING
NOEL, SING NOEL, NOEL, NOEL. ♪" Especially
on that, "♪ Sing we all noel. ♪" That's me.
We're singing! It's like you're telling
people, "We are singing!"
Not, "♪ Sing, I think, we all noel. ♪" Okay?
So let's make sure that we're right there
on that. One more time. See if you can get
a little more weight to your sound. I
don't mean make it flat. I just mean with
more confidence, more security, more
support, Okay? Here we go.
♪ Sing noel, sing noel, noel, noel ♪
Awesome!
Two part.
♪ Sing noel, sing noel, noel, noel ♪
Support this!
♪ Sing we all noel! Sing we all noel! ♪
♪ Sing noel, sing noel, noel, noel ♪
Good. And stop there. So you get the idea.
That was awesome! Did you hear the
difference?
- [Together] Yeah.
- Awesome. I love that you challenged
yourselves. You pushed yourselves there.
It's hot. Those notes are kind of high. I
know that. And you just pushed right
through it. So good job. Let's review the
instrument parts we just got to touch on
last time. So, I'm going to come here so
we can do our body percussion. Real quick.
We are going to start with our bass part.
Ladies and gentlemen, we are not going
to use these right now because traditional
African music is by rote, meaning you
learn it by hearing. You learn it by
doing. If you are a visual learner, these
are our music stands by the instruments,
so this will help you. And you know, I
want everyone to be successful, so you use
the tools that will help you be
successful. You be an independent learner
where you decide. If this is what you
need, grab a music stand. Okay? If you
don't, you don't need it. Okay? So there
are music stands in each of the instrument
sections when you pick. Okay? So, basses
first. Let's all kind of scoot over this
way. So bass section first. We have,
starting with your left hand, [clapping as they sing]
"♪ Sing, oh sing, oh sing noel ♪
- [Clapping together as they sing]
- And you have that crossover.
[Clapping as they sing]
"♪ Sing, oh sing, oh sing noel ♪
- Everybody feel comfortable with that?
Any questions? You look good. You look
like you have it. All right. Then we have
the xylophones. This one's a tricky one.
So we have, for that part... Let me just
double check on our words that we decided
for last time. So, we have, [clapping as they sing]
"♪ Sing noel, sing noel. Let's simply celebrate it. Sing
noel. Sing noel. Let's simply celebrate it. ♪"
- [Clapping as they sing]  Sing noel. Sing noel.
Let's simply celebrate it. Sing noel. Sing noel.
Let's simply celebrate it. ♪
- Okay? So the trickiest part is how many
G's. All right. So remember, we have low C
and high C, So you have, "C, C, C. C, C,
C." And there's four Gs over that
syncopated rhythm. G, G, G, G, F, E, D.
Okay? So it's kind of like, "One, two,
three, down the ladder you go."
Okay? So let's try that.
- C, C, C. C, C, C. G, G, G, G, F, E, D.
C, C, C. C, C, C. G, G, G, G, F, E, D.
- Got it? Got the idea? All right. Then we
go on to the glockenspiels. And for that
one, we can just clap that rhythm, because
I think on the instruments it will be
easier to see, to show, because they're so
obviously a little, so it's not really
like that. So here we go. It goes, "♪ Sing,
oh, yes, sing noel, noel. ♪"
- ♪ Sing, oh, yes, sing noel, noel. Sing,
oh, yes, sing noel, noel. ♪
- Okay? Got the idea for that rhythm? So I
will come over and help that section, and
some of you may remember that from last
time. Then we have our percussion section.
Okay? We have first the conga drum. A real
quick review on conga drum playing.
Everything in you is going to want to tip
it toward you. If we can kind of spin back
here so I can show you. When you play a
conga drum you scoot over this way a
little bit. And scoot over that way. There
we go. So, when you play conga drum, you
actually are going to hold it in between
your legs, and put your feet around the
base, and you're going to tip it out from
you. So that that way the sound can come
out, but you also have the correct play
style. Remember pat on the ends.
when you're playing. And those are in...
You can pat this on your lap as well.
♪ [Drumming] ♪
Right now, practice on your fingers.
Okay? So here's on this. Practice with a
good technique, right now. Ready. Go.
♪ [Drumming] ♪
- [Drumming Together]
♪ This is the part of the conga drum.♪
- All right. You've got the idea? And that
goes over and over, each measure. Then we
have the log drum. And the log drum... And
again, the parts are right here on the
stand if you need them. You're going to
have... One side, you're going to play,
"Sing." So basically...
♪ [music] ♪
And it doesn't matter with those. "Sing
noel, sing noel, sing noel." Okay? So you
can clap that real quick.
- [Clapping Together] Sing noel, sing noel,
sing noel, sing.
- Okay? See how it fits? Hello. Welcome.
- Thank you very much.
- All right. So. Next we are going to have
this part, which is traditional African
bell. And this one you have, "Rest, rest,
rest, [Rings Bell] noel." Sorry, hi to low. So it's,
"Rest, rest, rest, [Rings Bell] noel.
Rest, rest, rest, [Rings Bell] noel, rest."
Can you snap it? [Rings Bell] Noel. Rest,
rest, rest, [Rings Bell] noel. "Rest, rest, rest,
[Rings Bell] noel.
And you can try it. Rest, rest, rest. Hi and fast.
[Rings Bell] Noel. Rest. Get them up!
[Rings Bell] Noel. Rest, rest, rest,
[Rings Bell] noel. Yes.
Ladies and gentleman, I'm always
spot-checking to see if you have rhythmic
accuracy when we're doing this. It's
really important that I see that
participation. Because then when we go to
pick parts, I'm looking to see who has it.
Yes, there's choice, but also to check you
off on including this rhythm thing. Okay?
So let's try it again. Ready.
Go. Rest, rest, rest.
♪ [Rings Bell] ♪
Rest, rest, rest.
Rest, rest, rest, [Clapping together] noel.
Rest, rest, rest,
[Clapping together] noel. You got it. And then,
I love these shakers. [Shaking in rhythm]
You are the pulse. You are the
heartbeat and the foundation of this song.
So it would really be nice if you could
pulse with my pulse so we could all pulse
together. So again, really important. We
might add in some other, more African
instruments. They're kind of loud, so
we'll see if you can get the correct
sound. [Rhythmic shaking stops]
So what I'd like you to do now. Do
you have any question? All right. If you
really mastered the instrument that you
got to start on last time, I would
challenge you to maybe pick a different
one. Okay? If you were still working on
it, you're welcome to stay there. But
without any payoffs, so just kind of
selection, I would like you all to go and
pick an instrument part. Remember we
have glockenspiels, basses, xylophones,
and percussion. So open? Two glockenspiels
open, and a bunch of xylophones open.
Who was there first? Who was there first
between you and Ellen?
- [Female student] I was here.
- You were there? Okay. So if you want to
join the glockenspiels, you can do that.
You can go to xylophones. Oh, nobody's up
to the challenge.
♪ [music] ♪
All right. Once you get there, you can
start practicing.
♪ [music] ♪
All right. Hold up, everybody! All right.
Thank you. Since we're trying to add in
some singing over the top of it
eventually, if you have the green mallets,
would you, especially for you guys, switch
them out with the felt mallets instead?
So here's a set. Well, you
need those for that as well. So we have
one. There should be another one in there.
- [Male student] Oh, here, right here.
- Nope, those are green.
You don't want those.
- [Male student] Oh,
here's another one, right here.
- Here, here you go, here's a set That's awesome.
Thank you. Because that's just going to make it
a lot softer, and not quite as angry
sounding. All right. So, let's listen to
each part so you can know what you're
listening for. Remember, when you are
playing in an ensemble like this, if you
can't hear the other parts, what does that
tell you?
- [Together] You're playing too loud.
- Yes, you're playing too loud. And
remember, again, texture is everything. We
want to be able to pull out the different
parts, so maybe at the end we can
talk about different ways we can set up a
form to highlight that. But for right now,
let's make sure that we can keep it soft.
Okay? It's not a competition. All right?
No one's going to win. It's the whole
class that we're trying to do this
together. So if we hear bass part first.
And let's go ahead and add at least shaker
for right now, and then we'll build in
one or two sections. One, two,
ready, go.
♪ [music] ♪
Okay. Time out. So, you're listening for
the beat. She's watching me instead of the
basses, right? Because you're doing their
work a little bit, and you need to keep it
nice and steady. What happened, we ended
up with three different tempos. Did you
hear that? One, two, ready, go.
♪ [music] ♪
Okay. Pretty good. And then we started to
kind of get off where the beginning of the
patterns are. Okay. One thing that will
help is adding the singing to it. Okay?