- It'll disintegrate (unintelligible)
- [Teacher] Okay.
So, as a quick vote,
how many people thought,
on this one, oh, sorry, Kevin, go ahead.
- Also, I think it's gonna decrease,
because, the paper's gonna burn
and incinerate, but also, the match,
when you light the match,
it's gonna burn, too.
- Okay.
Some of you, maybe,
forgot about the match.
I haven't heard you
mention it, until just now,
so that, not only is
the paper gonna burn up,
but so will, at least part of, the match.
Okay, 'cause it's burning too, alright?
A quick vote.
How many people, on this one,
said the mass would go
down, would decrease?
And how many said it would increase?
And, how many said it'd stay the same?
So, the majority of you are
on the decrease side, on this.
Okay, here's my next question.
We've now heard what a bunch of people
had to say, about each
different situation.
One, if it would increase, or decrease,
or stay the same.
My question to you now is that,
after listening to all the people
throw ideas out there,
has anybody changed their
mind on any of these?
In other words,
like, maybe for the ice in the water one,
I was thinking it was going to increase,
but, after listening to every one,
now, I think it's gonna decrease.