- Counting on that.
I agree with AJ, but also I think that...
What I want to say is that
it kind of adds a lot more risk
when they get rid of the space shuttle
because kind of like what AJ was saying,
it's good to have a backup
just in case you want it.
And we still do need to go
up to space every now and again
if we want to maintain stuff up there.
So we know that,
so we're having other people work with it,
but the problem is,
is that actually adds more risk
because now we have to deal
with the fact that,
"What if they messed up?
"What if they blow up
"or do something wrong?"
And if they're not as stringent
on safety standards as we are
then there's gonna be a lot more problems
and if it's not able to do the same things
that's going to be completely bad, too.
- Okay, Eric said, "Go up to fix things."
What would be some things
that we would need to make sure
that we're going up to maintain in space?
Just to kind of follow up.
- [Girl] International Space Station.
- Okay, International Space Station.
- Some of the satellites we have in orbit.
- Okay, satellites that do what for us?
- Television and communication.
- Okay.
- Ms. McCall, what's that one with the sun
that is predicting the sun flares?
- [Teacher] You can just write Sun Probe.
- Sun probe.
- [Teacher] That's fine.
Excuse me while I turn this on.
- [Eric] And the Hubble.
- Hubble's gone a lot longer
than they expected it to,
so if it breaks, we'd want to repair it.
- Especially since we
don't have a new one.
- Alana.
- I know how Mer
was talking about the risks,
like with the Challenger
and that was really devastating,
but I remember the wife
whose husband died on Challenger.
She said that he knew the risks.
That's part of being an astronaut
and being in NASA
and willing to go up there
and you're risking your life.
It's not like they went in there
totally blind about that.
I think that's kind of the price
of gaining so much knowledge
about something so unknown right now.
We have to be able to
risk our lives to get it
and if they have people
willing to do that,
I say go for it.
- [Teacher] Okay, Blanca and then Megan.
- I get what she's saying
with they risked their lives,
but you're also risking...
the money and time that
everyone has put into it.
They spent all this time
and all this money on
these ginormous space things
and to put them up into space.
And like the Challenger
it just exploded
and they didn't even really get that far
just for one minor error.
And I don't think they
should cut all the way
like they were saying.
Have it just when you need it,
but it's still a lot of money
that our country doesn't
really have right now,
so maybe it's not the most important thing
and there's other things
that they need to fix
before they can go back
to putting more money into that.
- [Teacher] We'll go Megan, then Bieber.
- So, you know how we're paying Russia
to fly up to the
International Space Station?
I think what we should
do is have a shuttle
and have people pay us to ride up
to the space station.
Because then we have more funding for NASA
and then we have a shuttle.
Then people know they can get us
instead of giving all this money
to Russia to fly up there.
I feel like we should
still have our own shuttle
so that we can fly up, not for free,
but we can fly up with the United States
and then have open seats
for other countries
who need to come in.
They can pay us for it
and then we get the money.
- [Teacher] Okay, Bieber,
you need to sit close.
Eli, then we'll go Rachel.
- I don't know what color to show,
but Russia's not making a profit
off of us riding up there.
They're just trying to cover their costs.
It's not like we'll be doing good business
ferrying people to the
International Space Station.
It's not like a tourist
attraction or anything.
It's pretty bland up there.
Russia's just trying to pay
to get us up there.
That's the cost of flying somebody there.
They're not making profit out of it.
- [Teacher] Okay, good,
that's a downpoint. Rachel?
- [Rachel] I agree with
what Eli said and also,
people were talking earlier about...
jobs and how it creates a bunch of jobs.
And I think I read somewhere
that they created 25,000
jobs or something like that.
But if you think about it,
if there's 300 million people,
that's still less than
1% of the population.
So, while it seems like a big number,
it's still not creating as many jobs
and we could be creating
other jobs somewhere else.
Especially with the economy,
so we could be spending the money
that we would be spending on NASA
on something else to
help boost our economy
before we start focusing more on NASA
and spending billions of dollars.
- [Teacher] Amber, then Clark.
- I was going to say I kind of agree with that
because our economy is so bad right now.
Any kind of job that is offered
will be really good for us right now,
at this point in time.
So, I don't think cutting the funding
for it would be a really
smart idea because
that's also putting a lot
of people out of work.
- [Teacher] Clark.
- The statistics with the jobs created
are probably from when NASA
was being used a lot
and now that it's been cut down already
all those jobs have already been cut.
And I don't think in this economy,
people need jobs requiring
that much education...
not everybody has that kind of education
to have a job like that.
People just need regular jobs in general.
- So, you're saying their employment
would be kind of geared towards
upper level educated
as opposed to maybe...
- And like in science and stuff
and not everybody has that.
- That's a downpoint. Luis.
- Going back to the billions of dollars
that are wasted or could
be used for better things,
I found out that the funding for NASA
only accounts for 0.7%
of the US government spending.
I feel like if you just cut all of that,
that's not really going to make
a huge difference when the government's
spending 99.3% on other things.
- [Teacher] We'll go Hallie, then Troy.
- Going back to the risk
of sending people out into space,
I researched and...
I found out that
the risk of manned space flights
are actually increasing because
the budget cuts have already happened.
As we're pushing for more
people and more money,
we're actually hurting ourselves more
because the safety and
quality assurance programs
have been trimmed back.
The risk is just becoming more and more.
- That's an interesting point.
As we're slowly cutting back
on the budgets already,
we're automatically increasing that risk
because of those budget cuts.
Troy?
- I actually support...
them cutting the budget because...
for one, when they cut budget,
they're setting aside money to...
buy more space exploration
from private companies.
Those people are more likely
to employ more employees
than the government,
which also stimulates
the economy a lot more.
I mean, if everybody's employed
by the government,
like what could happen to Greece.
- Okay, Shannon hasn't spoken, Bieber.
- Kind of off of what Holly said
with the risk and everything going up,
I did a little research and with NASA,
there was only a 4.1% fatality rate.
Out of something like 439 astronauts,
there have only been 18 deaths.
I feel like there are other jobs
with a higher fatality rate
than being an astronaut.
- Okay, so even with the budget cuts,
we're not seeing this huge increase...
Jillian.
- A lot of people are
making the points that
it's only affecting the people
that are on the space shuttles,
but at the same time,
I don't think people realize
the amount of carbon dioxide...
put off by one shuttle launch.
It's 28 tons of carbon
dioxide and it's killing...
the plants and fish around the site area
and it has a lot of
negative effect on everyone,
not just the people in the space shuttle.
- So, you're taking the
environmental aspect.
Besides looking at costs,
besides looking at jobs,
there's this environmental piece
specifically with carbon dioxide.
What is the issue associated
with carbon dioxide, Jillian?
- The ozone layer depleted...
and global warming.
- Thank you, global warming.
Tyler?
- To go along with what Luis said,
they only get 0.7% of
the national spending,
but we also have gained
more knowledge from NASA
than any other government thing.
We can discover
maybe how Earth is going to end,
and we can discover things
that are more important
than other government,
government spending.
- So, you're kind of going at the idea
that the benefits are outweighing
the small amount of cost
when we compare government spending.
We'll go Eli, then Justin.
- Also, Luis said it doesn't account
for very much of the US budget
and if we cut that spending,
it's really not going to go
to anything more productive.
Maybe more guns or something.
It's not going to feed the world
and buy food for homeless people.
It's just going to go to
corporations and wars.
And then in regards to CO2 emissions...
does anyone know how much
CO2 emissions a moose puts out in a year?
Far more than a truck driver.
Cows and moose.
I think they can flirt over that.
I think that's just moose.
(laughter)
- So, you're making the comparison to say
the idea that even though
it's a human-made craft,
if we look at natural sources
of the CO2 emission...
- And the relative frequency
that a moose passes gas.
A space shuttle launch doesn't have
that big of an effect on the environment.
- Touche.
Anyone have a cup that hasn't spoken yet,
that wants to jump in real quick?
Justin.
- Going off of what Tyler said,
if we stop funding NASA,
then we pretty much cut off studying
anything outside of our solar system
because of the atmosphere of Earth
just doesn't allow us to see that far.
So, it would lessen the chances
of seeing the birth of a star
or the death of a star
or where earth might be
heading in the future.
- Interesting point.
Amber, then Eric.
- Besides everything about the jobs,
NASA has created a lot of things
that have helped us today,
different technologies.
Like in someone's presentation,
they were saying something about
they're creating lighter
systems for firefighters,
and then cosmetic companies
are even using their stuff.
So, there's a lot of technology
that's been created because of NASA,
so I think it's benefited us a lot more
than it hasn't helped us.
- And so, you're saying those products
that have been produced
because of the exploration
are useful to us in our everyday lives.
It's not just useful for
exploring many new things.
I forgot my order.
Was it Eric on that one?
- I have a couple different connections.
One of them's with the cost.
Like they're saying, it's
0.7% of the total budget,
but the thing is, not only
is it that low of a cost,
it's 14 billion, just to
give you an actual number.
It's 14 billion dollars for
the entire budget of NASA.
This year, just for this year alone.
To give you a comparison,
it's around $640 between $680
for the military budget.
That is 47 times more expensive.
Now you can say,
"Well, alright, that's the military."
The thing is that first of all,
it has a lot higher mortality rate.
Second of all, it's...
a lot less productive in general.
I mean, we're pretty much paying people
to kill other people on the planet.
I'm sorry, but that's
not very cool in general.
For one of those things,
we're trying to get a high fatality rate,
not for our side but the other side.
But the other thing is that
for jobs creations,
if you want to create more jobs
and you're going for a more positive feel,
you wouldn't decrease funding for NASA,
you would increase funding.
Because, think about it.
If you increased it 47
times to the military,
I'm pretty sure you'd get
a lot more than one million
even a lot, lot more than
just one million jobs from NASA,
if you increased this funding a lot,
because imagine whole new planets.
Just for environment alone is the fact
that we have seven billion
people on this planet,
and with seven billion people,
we can't hold that many people
very long on this planet.
But there are so many
other planets out there,
that we could easily fit everyone.
There's enough planets
in this entire galaxy
for each person to have their own planet.
That's how many planets there are.
- So, you're thinking planning for the future,
that it might be beneficial for us.
Holly.
- As I was researching,
I found out that there's
really no short-term benefits
and we're not guaranteed
long-term benefits.
Yes, we are learning about things outside
of our solar system and universe,
but the main goal of
studying outside the universe
is so eventually it could help us.
We're not guaranteed to find some new way
to cure cancer or to
protect the earth from...
magnetic storms.
There might be some way
we can save ourselves,
but we're not guaranteed that.
- So, you're saying the unknown part
of that research kind of plays into
the factor.
We can keep researching,
but we may never find the answer.
Monique, you got some info?
- Yeah, I think when Hepetiah
said how benefits outweigh
the budget and the risks,
we've talked about what was up there.
The benefits are so much longer than
what we have in the risk section.
We gain knowledge, we need to study,
the sun probe and Hubble
and International Space Station.
With jobs, it provides
a whole section of jobs,
having shuttles go up to space.
Not only that, but they've created
new inventions through that,
and I think the inventions
they have created
is really important at
home and in the hospital.
Going from there,
there's going to be more.
Not just stopping now.
- So again, tying in the
cost-benefit analysis,
that the benefits are much more
outweighing the costs.
A.J. and then we'll go Alana.
- I guess to counter what Troy said
and what a few people have said,
when they talk about that more jobs
can be created using the money.
It's not just about the economy.
When you think about it,
NASA wasn't meant to
help the economy at all,
and it wasn't meant for job creation,
even though it has
employed so many people.
Through the research that I did,
there was a story from somebody
that's going to be retiring just because
he knows he'd lose his job anyway.
He said that, "After 30
years, this is all I know."
We're losing the most brilliant
minds our country has,
because they just don't
know what else to do.
NASA's been open for decades
and that's their job.
Technicians and analysts,
they're not going to just
become accountants or something.
There's nothing after NASA.
That's probably the highest,
most prestigious thing.
What do you do after that?
It's not like they're just
going to fill minimum wage jobs,
which is what most people
are looking for right now, anyway,
if you're thinking about job creation.
- It's a good point, you have
all these highly educated,
specialized people as A.J. points out.
Where are they going to go?
Are they going to be able to
find jobs within our country?
Are they going to go
overseas and then maybe
be helpful and more productive
for other countries?
It's a good point.
Alana, then Troy.
- I know we're talking a lot about
the cost-benefit and job creation,
but I want to go back to the safety,
and I have a question for
everyone just to think about.
The main part in all the failed missions,
especially with the
shuttle and the Challenger,
it's basically been human error.
You know they talk about how
the higher guys wouldn't listen,
that it was too cold outside
and the ring would break and
everything,
but I've been thinking:
what if we were to use some
sort of higher technology
instead of relying on human
and the possible errors that we make.
Like robots, we use robots
to build half our cars,
and that probably cuts down a lot
on the human error rate.
So, do you think using more robotic
and higher technology than just humans,
would that help in any
way with the safety issue
and the errors that we make?
- [Teacher] That's an interesting point.
We'll have to put that
on the question board.
Troy, what you got?
- Kind of to counter what A.J. said,
these people are highly educated.
Minimum wage places are probably the ones
that are hiring the least.
Companies with a lot of money
are the ones that are hiring them now.
People that have...
highly specialized degrees,
they're really intelligent
and they could be working
at places like in finance.
Those people are being hired
a lot more than people that
have financial degrees.
If you can do quantitative physics,
those people are going to be hired
a lot more than someone
who's just a finance agent.
- So, your counterpoint is the idea that
because they're so highly educated,
they will find some sort of a niche.
- Yeah. There's a lot of people
that actually get
degrees in rocket science
and end up going into finance
because it pays better.
- Interesting. Jillian?
- Back to what Alana said,
if you're using robots to make it safer,
that's also just going to cost more money
to make those robots
and to find people that
can make those robots.
If you're using robots as the engineers,
then you're having people lose jobs.
- Interesting point.
So, kind of a counterpoint to...
shifting our focus from human
exploration to robotics,
there's some drawback association.
We'll go Rachel.
- Going back to what
Eric said a while ago,
he was talking about the military
and it has a higher budget,
but I feel like the military
helps a lot of people,
and it creates a lot of
jobs and educates people,
because the military pays
for a lot of people's
education, university and stuff.
I know a lot of people now,
since university is so expensive,
a lot of people are
going into the military
so they can get their education paid for.
So, I feel like it should
have a higher budget
because it's creating so many jobs
and especially for people
who aren't necessarily...
has a doctorate in physics or something.
People that are really smart,
like what Troy said,
they won't really have
that much of a problem finding jobs,
especially with a big corporation.
They don't have to necessarily
work for the government
or NASA or something.
So, I think that the budget
should stay where it is,
because that's pretty funny.
- [Teacher] We'll go Megan and Tyler.
- I don't know when it was mentioned,
but we were talking about
how we're trying to find
how the earth will be when all has failed,
and I feel like with all
the carbon dioxide emitted
and with our atmosphere right now,
we're trying to discover
what our world will be like
when all of that's gone.
I feel like that's really important
for the development of Earth,
is to know what it's going to be like
when there is no more.
What can we do so that we don't
turn into a Mars or Venus?
What can we do now to
stop it from happening?
- Good, so you're making connections
to maybe the video when
they talked about the future if there's
an issue with our magnetosphere.
Potentially could we wind up like Mars?
So, kind of getting a jumpstart
to say where we are
headed, future-wise.
So, almost like a selfish need
to figure out what's going on out there
and where we might go.
Anyone that hasn't spoken
yet want to comment?