- Like a long A?
- Not long A.
- Long O?
- No, I'll give you a hint. There's some
letters up on the front. What is
the sound?
- [together] "Er."
- It's "er."
- "Er. " Everybody say "er."
- [together] "Er."
- Okay. What we're going to do... If you
remember last week, we looked at some
pictures. And when you heard the "er"
sound, what sound did you make?
- "Er."
- No.
- [together] E-R.
- What did you make?
- Tweet, tweet.
- Tweet, tweet because a bird says tweet,
tweet and a bird has "er." So my first
picture is a train. Do you hear it?
- Yes, ma'am.
- No.
- Do you hear an "er"?
- Oh, no. No.
- So are you going to say tweet, tweet?
- [together] No.
- No. Shirt.
- [together] Tweet, tweet.
- Girl.
- Bird.
- [together] Tweet, tweet.
- Rope.
- No.
- Skirt.
- [together] Tweet, tweet.
- Purse.
- Shark.
- [together] Tweet, tweet.
- Do you hear "er" in shark?
- No.
- Do you hear the difference? What do you
hear? "Ar." That's different. Okay. Let's
look really quick, eyes up here. When I
have the word skirt, what two letters make
"er?"
- [together] I-R.
- Very good. This is a nurse. What two
letters make "er"?
- [together] U-R.
- Good.
- Tweet!
- This is a fern. What two letters say
"er?"
- [together] E-R.
- Very good. We're going to read some
words, okay? I want you to look at this
word first. Connor, look at the word.
Everybody, what word is that?
- [together] Sir.
- Look at it. Think about it first. What
word?
- [together] Fur.
- Four.
- Fur.
- What's this word?
- [together] Fur.
- Very good. Think about it first. What
word?
- [together] Spur.
- Think about it first. What word?
- [together] Hurt.
- Think about it. Don't say it. And what
word is it?
- [together] Spurt.
- Spurt. Very good. Think about it first.
What word?
- [together] Nerve.
- Think about it. What word?
- [together] Serve.
- Think about it.
- Nurse.
- What word?
- [together] Nurse.
- Think about it.
- Purse.
- What? You're thinking. I can't hear you
think. All right. Ready? What word?
- [together] Purse.
- Good. Think about it. What word?
- [together] Germ.
- Think about it. Don't say it yet.
What word?
- [together] Term.
- Term. Eyes up here. Okay. Good. Now
we're going to go to our work mats and
we're going to build some words, okay?
Okay. You can give the students a point,
because you all did a very good job.
Everybody was paying attention and
participating. All right, watch how Miss
Dodd is doing this because you're going to
do the same thing. Get your word mat out
in front of you and put your letters
out so you can see them.
We have to go kind of quick.
I'm going to put this on top of this
just for now, okay?
- Thanks.
- You're welcome. All right. Let's see.
Let's see how fast we can get those out.
Let's see. I'm going to say we can do it
in 40 seconds.
Let me help you out. Let's put all
these out so you can see them.
- You have a lot of words.
- Shh.
- Okay. We're not putting them down on the
mat. We're going to put them up here and
then we're going to pull
them down to the mat.
There we go.
- Economics.
- Shh.
- All right. Let's see if we made it. Are
we all done?
- Yes, ma'am.
- All right. Give the students another
point because you did it in enough time.
Okay. Miss Dodd has the words up here,
also, the word parts. So first, let's look
at the ending parts, okay? What do you
think this says?
- [together] "Er."
- "Er." Very good. Look at this next one.
What does this say?
- [together] "Urt."
- "Urt." Eyes up here. Eyes up here. Good.
- What does this say?
- [together] "Er."
- Good. What does this say?
- [together] "Urse."
- And what does this say?
- [together] "Erve."
- Okay. These are the same cards that you
have, so we're going to make some words, okay?
- Okay.
- First, we're going to start with "urt."
U-R-T. So let's pull that down to where it
says rhyme. U-R-T. Okay? And I want you to
make the word hurt. Hurt.
- Good job. All right. Let's spell hurt
together.
- [together] H-U-R-T. Hurt.
- Very good. All right. So Miss Dodd will
pull down my H and it looks like everybody
got that. Okay. Now I want you to take
your U-R. Pull down your U-R. Okay? And
this time, I'm going to give you a clue.
I want you to make the word that is
something that is on an animal. Covers an
animal. Keeps him warm. His what? We don't
want our H right now. Let's see
if you can figure it out.
You should have U-R right here, okay?
And now we're going to... So
what was the answer to my clue?
- [together] Fur.
- Fur. Spell it.
- [together] F-U-R. Fur.
- Keep your U-R and I want you to make the
word spur. Spur. We talked about this word
last week. A spur. Okay? Yes.
- Who put the things out?
- I did. Okay. Who remembers
what a spur is?
- Something that you kick?
- Very good. Here's a picture of a spur.
Remember there was a thing that the cowboy
has on his boots that he kicks the horse
and it makes the horse go fast? Okay. So I
should pull down my S-P and this word is?
- [together] Spur.
- Very good. All right. I want you to pull
down your U-R-S-E. U-R-S-E. And you
shouldn't have anything in front of the
U-R-S-E. You should just have it just like
Madison has it here. She doesn't have
anything for onset. She only has her
rhyme. Okay? All right. What
does that part say?
- [together] "Urse."
- "Urse." Okay. I want you to add a P and
see what word you get and if you have a D,
you might want to flip it over. It's also
a P. Okay? All right. What word is that?
- [together] Purse.
- Purse. Very good. Okay. I want you to
take your I-R and pull it down. And this
time, I want you to make your own word
with I-R. It might not be the same word
your neighbor makes. I want you to make
your own word with I-R. Look at all the
onset parts that you have and see what you
can add to "ir." Good job.
- All right. Let's look at what we came up
with. What did you come up with?
- Sir.
- Sir. Okay. So I'll pull down my S here.
This word is sir. That is correct and I
see a few people have sir. Let's see.
Let's look at this one. What did you make?
- Spir.
- But what two letters actually say "ur"
in spur?
- I-R?
- Not I-R. Remember?
- U-R.
- Yep. Let's put it up here so we remember
it. Spur is S-P-U-R.
- I've got another one.
- All right.
- Dirt.
- Okay.
- Oh, yeah.
- How do you spell dirt?
- Oh, yeah. Wait. Oh yeah.
- We might not have that ending, but do
you know how to spell dirt? D...
- I-R-T.
- Very good. All right. Let's move on to
another one. Oh, I see that you have
G-I-R. "Gir." What were you thinking when
you wrote that? Can you use that in a
sentence? No? Okay. This one is not a
word, okay? Now we're going to pull out
our E-R-V-E. E-R-V-E. Let's see how
quickly we can get it up.
You all are doing a good job.
You're all probably going to
get another point. E-R-V-E.
Okay? And I want you to
fill in the blank. The ladies in the
cafeteria blank us our food. The ladies in
the cafeteria blank us our food. What can
we put in front of the E-R-V-E that would
complete that sentence? It's got to make
sense. All right. What is this word?
- "Erve."
- Let's see. What if I were to put an S?
What word would I have?
- Serve?
- Serve. Does that make sense in my
sentence? Do the ladies in the cafeteria
serve us our food? Yeah. So what word did
we come up with?
- [together] Serve.
- Serve. Very good. Okay. So this is what
I want you to do. I want you to take all
your cards just like Miss Dodd's doing
here and I'm just going to put them
together pretty quick. I don't have to
really take my time here and then I'm
going to stick them on my page. We're
going to make a pile in the middle.
Good job. All right. Good. And remember,
it doesn't have to be perfect. Good job.
And let's take it all...
- Is this yours?
- Good job.
- No.
- All right. I'm going to go ahead and
hand you our story. We're going
to take what we've learned and take it to
text. We're going to read a story that
has lots of words that have the "er"
sound.
- This looks like [inaudible].
- I have one.
- Yeah. That one's his.
- Curls that swirl.
- All right.
- I can't put it...
- Whoa. It's got 12 pages.
- Okay. All right. Let me go ahead and
take those so we can go ahead and start
reading, okay? Okay. You can give the
students a point because you did a good
job last time. Okay. I'm going to give
everybody a highlighter because as we're
reading, I want you highlighting words
that have the "er" sound. Okay? So what's
my title?
- [together] Curls that swirl.
- Very good. Do you see some words that
have the "er" sound?
- Yes, ma'am.
- Let's highlight them. What's my first
word?
- Curls.
- U-R.
- Curls. What's my next word that has
"er"?
- [together] Swirl.
- Swirl. Very good. All right. Curls that
swirl. What are they talking about, about
curls? What kind of curls are they talking
about?
- Like curls in your hair.
- Curls in your hair. Very good. Okay. As
we're going, I'm going to be putting the
words up here, okay? So we have curls and
we have swirl and we will use these words
again tomorrow. Okay, so let's open up to
the first page.
- Miss Dodd? Miss Dodd?
- Highlight it again?
- No highlighting yet, okay?
- Cheryl? Oh, okay. Well, come up. No, no.
We're on this page here. Page three at the
bottom, okay?
- Okay.
- Okay. So let's see how quickly we can
get to page three. All right.
What we're going to do is I want you
following along. Miss Dodd's going to
model how we're going to read this page.
As I'm reading, you can highlight when I
say an "er" word. Does everybody
understand the directions?
- [together] Yes, ma'am.
- Okay, but you need to be listening
because after this, we're going to read it
all together, okay? Here we go. Once
there was a small girl who had hair that
curled and swirled and twirled.
Drop where you hand is.
- I messed up.
- That's okay. We'll go
back and look at it.
- This one?
- We'll talk about it. It swirled over
her shirt and way past her skirt.
Okay. Now. Stop. No, no. We're going to
just look at that one page because I see
some things that make me ask some
questions. What word did you ask me about?
- That wasn't me.
- Did you ask me about a word? What word?
- There.
- There. Okay. Let's look at the word
there. Okay. Now should we highlight
there?
- Yes, ma'am.
- Raise your hand if you say yes we
should. Raise your hand if you say no we
shouldn't. Okay. Well, let's look at it.
Does it have E-R like we're looking for?
- [together] Yes.
- It does, but does it say "er"?
- No.
- No. It has a different sound. Every E-R
isn't going to say "er." It's just going
to be special times, so in this case,
should we highlight it?
- [together] No.
- No, okay. And it's okay if you did,
okay? All right. Let's go ahead and read
it together now. Everybody follow along.
Let's put our finger under the first word
or your highlighter is fine.