- Can you think of... what-what images
are coming into your head about the
Holocaust that relate to this?
- Um, people dying in the gas chambers
- Okay, and... and how did that happen?
- He convinced other people that they were
awful, and then that's really the only way
you can get people to do something as
cruel as that.
- Okay, so you're saying Hitler couldn't
have carried out all that evil himself so
he had to convince other people that
basically the Jewish people were what?
- Nothing
- They were just less than... just a
lesser race of people
- You're on a good track, I'll check back
with you in a second.
[chatter]
- ... by stepping on another group of
people.
- So the other groups would actually help
them.
- Like we have to remember that the
injustice... the injustice is what causes
us to want to go and help and restore
justice and it's not just injustice
anyway.
- you have to want to help and not just
sit back and do nothing.
- Well outside people like in Atlanta and
Birmingham, like, in there, like, in
Birmingham were being persecuted while
people in Atlanta weren't really doing
anything.
- Well I mean, look what's happening
today, I mean, we have a volunteer army
and people are volunteering and going and
trying to stop the injustice in
Afghanistan and so that was practically
the same thing as what Martin Luther King
did for Alabama.
- So you're saying you see a connection in
the real world news? That sort of our
soldiers, the fact that they volunteer
would be an example for number five? Is
that what you are saying?
- Yeah
- Had y'all talked about number five yet?
- Uh, we were just going in order and
seeing which ones that we could...
- And yours is...
read me your quotation.
- Um, "Injustice anywhere is a threat to
justice everywhere."
- Okay good. Well you're just being to
come up with things. Okay go ahead I'm
just going to...
- Okay, so what's the first question?
- Explain the context in which, um, Martin
Luther King said this and how it applies
in that situation.
- Okay
- He doesn't want people to sit back and
not do anything about a problem, he wants
them to go and help and stop...
- It's almost as if their problem is his
problem-
- Is his problem.
- Good, I like that.
- But even though he wants them to help,
well he doesn't want them to do it in a
violent way.
- Always need to underguard MLK with
that, don't we?
- And that sort of ties into "It's wrong
to use immoral means to attain moral
ends."
- Do you find yourself, as you're
discussing any one of these, the others
layer on there?
- Yeah
- That's why it feels so important to have
gotten this whole document as a whole.
Think
you've gotten enough from them, Brianna,
for that one?
- Yeah, I think so.
- Well I guess Clyde's already said that,
there's already one for the current news--
- Yeah
- ... that we could put down.
- So the volunteer soldiers.
- Volunteer army.
- I'll check back with y'all, good job.
- ... are they more reluctant to, like,
um, listen to the lower class bunnies
cause they felt like they had a better
rule of it.
- Yeah I think that's it.
- Okay, so in Watership Down, the higher
class rabbits did not want to give up
their superior... how do you spell that
because I think I spelled that before...
privileges
- Privileges? You know what, to be honest
with you every time I am typing, I let
spell-check do it because that d and g
always messes me up
- I was spelling superiority.
- Superiority, I'm sorry. Okay, so what
group have you chosen Colleen? and what...
what... ?
- Uh, privileged groups seldom give up
their privileges voluntarily and groups
tend to be more immoral than individuals.
- And I hear that you're using a Watership
Down example, which-
- My idea.
- Your idea, good for you! And what is
the, um, what Warren are we talking about?
- The very first one, um.
- Sandleform.
- Sandleform, yeah.
- Yeah, go ahead and tell me about that.
- Yeah, it's like, um, the higher class
rabbits didn't want to give up their
privileges of superiority to listen to the
lower bunnies.
[cross talk]
- Does that make sense to you, India?
That's a good example, I really like it!
Okay, have you gotten anything else?
- Um, we did the one about the time in
history where this quotation applies?
- What was the time in history, Bish?
- Um...
- Number two.
- Where this quotation applies is the
Holocaust. Um, during Nazi rule, people
felt better about discriminating against
the Jews because many others were also
doing it.
- So what was the privileged group
that were reluctant to give up its
privileges?
- Um, actually I think this one was
grouped to be more of an individuals
rights.
- Right, so the whole group of what?
- The whole group of, um...
- Nazis.
- ... the Nazis and the pretty much
anyone that favored Hitler and the Nazis.
- But maybe they wouldn't have carried out
those atrocities alone but kind of got
into a mob mentality, is that kind of where
we are with this?
- Yes.
- Good, well y'all go ahead, I'm just
going to watch a minute
- So...
- I'll finish writing the Watership Down
one... the higher class rabbits did not
want to give up their superiority to...
how about... admit that some of the
lower
- Number four would be easier to connect
to a teenager's life... that one actually
fits for both of those.
- What does?
- Um, for telling a time in a teenager's
life, um, both of these, the two parts of
the quote would apply because it's like,
when you're getting, like, verbally
abused, it feels much worse coming from a
group than it does from an individual.
So if there's a whole group picking on
you, then that makes it worse and the
privileged groups seldom give up their
privileges voluntarily. So say, say someone
has a good cafeteria lunch table and
someone who's sitting over by the garbage
cans wants to move over there, so they ask,
"Hey you don't have to sit over at our
table, but can you move somewhere else so
we can sit there just for a day." They'll
probably say "No" because they won't think
of another place to go besides that table
that those other people left.
- And they don't want to go by the garbage
cans.
- Nobody wants to.
- I think that's a good connection. A good,
very present day connection. Good, I'll
be back. Yes of course
- Um, Allison, would you like to?
- I have no clue, would it be okay to
write about, like, how people in foreign
countries use, like, the sex trade as an
"it," an I-it relationship?
- Certainly.
- Mr. Gallant's class.
- We just had to make sure it was all
right with you before we started just writing
it down.
- That's okay, that's okay, that seems
very real to me. Okay
- ... fictional things, so if it's
fictional, it doesn't have to be people
- I didn't say that we could use, um,
what's that, Watership Down, I said we
could use that, did I not?
- All right, let's see...
- Okay, whatever.
- I said we can use Hazel and the Warren
for oppressed people that are not...
- But I think we should do Efrafa because
the bunnies, like, revolted and they got
free remember?
- Yeah.
- That's what I'm thinking.
- I'm hearing an argument where both of
you think Watership would be a good
connection but we're debating which what?
- Oppressed people cannot remain oppressed
forever.
- Which Warren would like... be better
- I think Efrafa.
- Which one did you say?
- Um, the first one that came to from...
what was it called...
- [together] Sandleford.
- Sandleford.
- Okay, tell me why you think that.
- Because they were, they had freedom, but
it was like they were just, they couldn't
do what they wanted all the time. They
could just do certain things in a certain
vicinity. They couldn't go out or go
anywhere, and they were just stuck against
their will for that long of a time until
they, um, like, revolted against their
Warren and left.
- What were you going to add, Michael?
- Oh, like it was like a routine everyday,
like, it was the same thing, they followed
like a routine, like they went out and
then ate and then slept
- But I think Efrafa is like that except
for it's a lot worse, like they didn't
even get to go out, like they got like
feeding times and they would have to feed,
like, right here and they'd have to go
right back into their Warren.
- I think they're both good examples, but
I think Machi's is more able to be
explained by that because they did, but in
his, you know, uh, uh, Hazel and Big-Wig
and all them broke away and then they went
to go search for...
- They eventually got what they wanted. In
Efrafa they didn't get what they wanted
until someone came in to...
- And not everybody in Efrafa got out.
- But not everyone in, um, Sandleford got
out, most of them didn't.
- But I mean the group that we're talking
about, the main...
- But the main characters got out and
achieved what they wanted, where they
wanted.
- Because no one else would listen.
- Let me tell you something, the main
reason we're doing this is so that these
quotations and these philosophies and that
kind of thing, will inform our later life.
It doesn't make me sad that you have two
examples because when it's a little bit
wrong, or when it's a lot wrong because
when you notice it when it's a little bit
wrong sometimes you can keep it from
getting a lot wrong, so it kind of pleases
me that you're seeing it at two different
levels, so I think use Efrafa and
Sandleford, and you'll have the best answer,
Okay?
Okay, what are we working on?
- We are trying to debate whether we
should pick Cuba or Egypt as current
events for-
- ... for privileged groups so we can
get...
- Well, let's hear your arguments.
- Cuba, Fidel Castro has been a tyrant for
60 years and he's still going strong.
- Metaphorically, he's about to die.
- He's still in power, okay? Egypt's been
resolved already.
- No.
- Well, they're arguing that it's not in
the news but it's going on right now.
- Well I think it would be best if we did
something that was going on in the news
that we've like talked about in class that's
really really really...
- And we all understand it.
- What don't you understand about Cuba
though?
- Like there's nothing that's really in
the news right now
- Cuba, they still have the same old thing
just like every other country that's
happened, just a little bit worse.
- Here's what I'm hearing. You have a
great example but your group is wanting to
go with the Egypt example, and it doesn't
dis, uh, disvalue yours because it's
important to be able to understand that it
can happen over a long time and sometimes
when he's talking about apathy, when it's
happened for a long time, people don't,
less and less and less, revolt, Okay?
- Could we possibly do Cuba in the history
one?
- Oh I think you could! Work on that,
that's a great idea.
How are we coming?
- Good, we're done.
- Good, done
- I think we are finished.
- I want to hear your, uh, everyday life
one.
- All right, our, for our teenager?
- Yes.
- All right, we're saying, like, if
there's a group of popular kids and
they're like calling names and putting
down a group of the not-so-popular kids
and they're just not treating them like
they're normal people too, they're just
treating them like lesser people.
- Less than human?
- They might, they might not pay attention
to them, also, they just...
- In the way you wouldn't necessarily
recognize a theme, but in a way, you would
never ignore a human or we would think
should never ignore a human being. Okay,
great. So I want you, as you're looking
back over yours, make sure that you've
given your reader or your listener enough
information. My shortest one was like
three sentences and there's nothing magic
about the number of sentences, just check
yours because you're a little ahead of
everyone else for thoroughness and see if
there's any details you
could add. Okay great.
How are we coming?
- Um, good.
- Pretty much done.
- Awesome, awesome. You've got three of
the four? Which ones did you do?
- Um, the tell us a time in history when
the quotation applies and the fiction
quotation and the teenagers of life.
- And your quotation was?
- Oh, we did, um, it is wrong to use
immoral means to attain moral ends, the
last temptation is the greatest treason to
do the right deed for the wrong reasons.
- Thank y'all for choosing that one,
that's a very hard one
- And we put
[Inaudible].
- And the third one, great. Now will some
body tell me what your fictional one was?
- Um, we did... why don't you explain
this one Isabelle?
- Okay, I did Peter Pan.
- Uh-huh.
- 'Cause when Peter Pan, he persuades, or, he
offers to take the children to the other
place and it sounds wonderful to them, but
he's doing it for the wrong reasons.
- What reasons do you think he's really
doing it?
- To have a mother for the children, the
lost children.
- And so he's not really thinking of their
well-being, he's thinking of his and the
lost boys' well-being.
- Right.
- What a great connection. I'm so proud of
y'all! That's awesome! And did you do
news?
- Uh, we did history.
- History, what's your historical one?
- Uh, we did, uh, when the
Europeans-