All right, Mr. Bailey.
- 5.03.
[Background Chatter]
All right let's talk for a
minute before you continue
with your little test.
First of all, let's talk about motion.
What do you know about motion?
- Motion is the way that you
get from one place to another.
It's changing position.
- Changing position, so
just now, Bailey was running,
was he changing position?
- Yes.
- Yes, all right so how do we
know that he was in motion?
Like, when he is running
toward me
how do I know he's in motion?
[Background Chatter]
- That stays there and
you can see him coming up.
- Nobody else was moving around.
- So that's our frame of reference.
He came over there so we
know he's coming toward us.
All right so you guys did a trial.
How many times did you run, Bailey?
- Three.
- All right so what are
we gonna do now?
- We're gonna have to
add them all up
and divide them by three.
- Why are we dividing by three?
- Because we did it three times.
- Okay, you did it three times.
You're finding your average.
What's another word for average?
- Mean.
- Mean, good.
All right so let's find
his mean or his average.
And then we'll record that
and double check to make sure
the whole group has the same
amount or the same number.
Okay, what did you get?
- 5.21.
- 5.21, is that what everybody has?
Nathan maybe you redo yours
and just check
since three people have that.
Let's name some things
that are in motion.
What do you know that's in motion?
- The earth.
- The earth is in motion, yup.
But I don't feel the earth
move so how do I know
it's in motion?
- 'Cause sun is the frame of reference.
- Okay, so if I was thinking of the sun
which is what they do,
and the earth we know we
could see the earth is moving
and the sun would be
your frame of reference.
What else do you know that moves?
- Animals.
- Insects.
- Cars.
- Insects, cars.
- Boats.
- People.
- People, books.
- Boats.
- Boats [laughing].
All right so how are
we gonna find our speed
because now we know how
many seconds it took him
but what's something
else that I need to know
besides how long it took him?
- The distance.
[Background Chatter]
The distance traveled
which is a hundred feet.
- So what difference did we do?
- Hundred feet.
- A hundred feet.
Okay, so what's the first
thing you have to do
is measure out your hundred feet?
- Yes.
- You did that and chalk-marked it?
Good, all right so let's--
- We're talking about
the average time taken.
- All right, so let's do that now.
- 19.
- So let's talk about
what that means, 19.19.
- Feet per second.
- What's that mean? Feet per second.
- 19 feet per second.
- So if I say "feet per second"
can you explain that to me?
What does that mean "19 feet per second"?
- Every second I would go 19.19 feet.
- Good okay, so if I'm driving in my car
and my car's going 70 miles per hour
and I'm on the interstate
do I say my car's going 75?
- No.
- No you'd say miles per
hour, bleh, 70 miles per hour.
- Can you tell me, Nathan, why?
What does that mean "70 miles per hour"?
- 70 miles per hour means you're
going 70 miles per each hour.
- For every hour, so that's good to know
for vacations, right?
Especially when you have
little kids who are saying,
"Are we there yet?"
[laughs]
You gotta figure out how
long it's gonna take you.
- Are we there yet?
- Right, okay.
All right you're going
to go into your next part
and I'll be right back
to check on you.
Who's the next person?
- Jordan
- It's gonna be Jordan.
All right, Miss Jordan.
- Hold the longest
tape and put it down
right here so it will stay up.
- He thinks he
needs one more piece of tape.
- Ready?
Ready.
Set, go.
[balloon deflates]
1.76.
- 1.89.
- Okay, so why don't you
write them both.
Do you have two spots?
- Only have one.
- You have two spots; write one there
and one there.
That's what you do there,
just like that.
- What did you get?
- 1.89.
- All right let's come talk
about what you're doing.
So let's get the three kinds of balloons
that you're testing.
Just gonna bring over here.
Dan, why don't you get the, um,
come slide that over here
so we can get that tape off
and get ready for the next one.
We might try that one here.
So we have...
- A big round one.
- A big round one, a green one, okay.
- A long one.
- Okay.
- And a birthday one.
- Did you all predict the
same one would be the fastest
or do you have different predictions?
- Different.
- Different predictions,
what do you think?
- The Happy Birthday one.
- You think the Happy Birthday one.
- Long.
- Can you tell me why
you think Happy Birthday
and then you'll tell
me why you think long.
- At first my prediction was
the long one because it was
not as much wind blowing against it.
But now there's wind blowing.
It blew it to the sides and
putting more force against it
which slowed it down and
made the long go faster.
- It'd be like this wind.
- Yes.
- You had this big.
That is a pretty good prediction.
[laughs]
Why do you guys think it's
gonna be the long one?
- I think it's the long one
because it's more smaller
and the air can come off faster
and it's more stretchier.
- Stretchier.
- Tight, it's more tight.
- All right, all right we had some
[Background Chatter]
- ...wasn't going all the way
so we changed it to 20.
- It would stop about maybe
three feet away from the end.
- It would stop, so what
did you decide to do?
- We changed it to 20.
- You moved it to 20.
Okay so...
What else could you have
done besides move it to 20?
- Blow up the balloon more.
- Maybe blow up the balloon more.
Maybe the little one wouldn't
have worked though, huh?
It's not that much in there.
- We tried the big red
one putting more air
but it still stopped.
- The little one--
- I think the wind kind of
changed how fast it would go
and how far.
- All right, so...
All right...
So let's come back this way.
- Watch out behind you, Megan.
- Dan you can go over to...
There's motion in the wind, huh?
- 176 and 108.
- All right, so here we go.
What are you gonna do first?
Let's do the round balloon first.
That was nobody's prediction, right?
- Nope.
- So let's do that one first.
What are we gonna do?
- 20...
- Add both up.
And then what are you gonna do?
- Divide by two.
- Why are we dividing by two?
- To get the average.
Why did you do it twice?
Why didn't you just--
- And there's two, the two trials.
- Why you did two trials?
Why wouldn't you just do one?
Why do you think that would've
been better to do two?
- Divided by
[Background Chatter]
- Then we wouldn't have to divide it,
we wouldn't have to
find the average at all.
But I guess we'd get
a better result.
What'd you get there?
- 2.35.
- 3.73.
- That's what I got, 2.35.
- You add these two together
and you divide them.
Remember this is the average.
Can you have four?
- I divided by two but I got 3.73.
- Let's try again.
On the calculator I always do
things twice to double check.
- 2.35.
Everybody's good?
Okay so let's go down to
the bottom of our sheet
and we are going to figure
out our average speed.
So what's our formula for that?
How do we figure out average speed?
- You do 20 because of the...
- Okay, so that's when we
took 20 because, you see,
we had 30 on our sheet
because originally
we were doing 30.
So let's cross out
30 since you guys said
you changed it to 20.
And I think it was Dan that
said, if we were to probably,
no Hannah said we could
probably could put more air
in that balloon.
But changing the feet,
that'll work.
Now how fast did the
first balloon go?
- 19.35 by 20.
- Look at your formula again.
- 8.52.
- Your distance is 20 so
you're gonna do your distance
divided by your average time.
Good?
- 8.51.
- Okay and I'll come back
to check on you you.
All right, let's see how
these guys are doing.
This one's a runner.
The line's over here right, Jordan?
- 16.
- We're at the end of Nathan's
so let's go ahead
and figure out Nathan together.
I'll come sit in your spot.
- They're in here.
- So to figure out Nathan,
let's talk about it together
while we're doing it.
We need some more calculators over here.
- Wait, what's this?
- 641.
- Everybody please do catch up.
Got your pencils?
- Wait, wait.
- 641, 575
- Tell me again what we're doing?
- ...average time.
- 6.08.
- Does everybody have six?
Read it back correctly.
- Six point O eight.
- Is that how you read
it correctly in math?
- Six decimal.
- Do we say decimal?
- Six--
- Six point zero eight.
- Do we say point?
- Six and--
- And--
- Eight hundredths.
- Six and eight hundredths.
Ohhhh.
- Gotta get it.
- So let's look just at our
average time for just a second.
Stop for a minute and let's look at
the top at our average time.
How do we know who is going the fastest
when we're look at just the
top part, just the time?
- Average time.
- The lowest.
- The lowest number, right,
'cause he's getting
in the fastest time.
So now when we go to the bottom
and we're figuring out the
speed, how do we do speed?
Whoever's the lowest number?
- The highest number.
- The highest number it's going to be.
Let's go ahead and do Nathan
and then we'll compare
then we'll let Demi do hers.
- 16 point...
- 16.44, right?
- Yep.
- So let's look so far at the bottom.
Bailey, Jordan and Nathan.
Who is the fastest?
- So far Bailey.
- So far Bailey, okay, so how can we,
instead of looking at this,
this looks like a whole
bunch of numbers to me.
What can I do visually just to
make it a little bit clearer?
- Make a bar graph.
- Okay, we can make a bar
graph with this.
Anything else we can do?
- Line graph.
- Maybe get
each person to make a line graph.
- Take your own three times
and make a line graph
with your own three times.
- Because that would be
you, right, over time?
That would be a great idea.
So we can do the straight line graphs.
That's a good idea with
the line graph, Bailey.
So when we make a line graph
we'll do that at the end
using this information and
then we'll do a bar graph
using this information.
Does that sound good?
All right, Demi's turn's up.
Let's go.
- Let's see how we are doing here.
Okay, we're at the very end.
So which one ended up being the fastest?
- The long one.
But I think that Devon had
a very good prediction.
I think his reasoning was good.
See that wind blowing?
In a race, when you're in
a race, and you're running,
or when you're in a foot ball team,
what side do you want to
be on if you have the ball
and you're trying to get
that ball to the other side?
You want the wind to be
with you, right?
Because if you're against the wind,
the wind is pushing on you,
so I think Devon had an excellent...
Good job, Devon, next time.
All right, we're at the bottom.
Why do you think that
balloon was the fastest?
- I put, "The shape of it,
the wind went right past it."
- All right, remember
there was unbalanced force.
So the force inside the
balloon, where was the force?
- The wind, the air.
- The air that Devon
blew inside that balloon,
the air inside pushed the balloon
and that's what made it
travel and it was
an unbalanced force
so when you let go--
- It probably was the
fastest because even though
the wind was blowing
it's on a round part
to where it would spin and
the wind would just roll
off of the balloon and it would
just make the balloon roll
but it would still go as
fast as it usually goes.
- That's a pretty good idea too.
It's kind of like when
you're driving a car
if you're on vacation
sometimes your parents,
you may see them driving
behind a 18 wheeler.
Why do you think they would do that?
- Because the wind blocks the--
- Because the wind is blocking.
- 18 wheel blocks it.
The 18 wheeler's blocking the wind
so you can get more miles per hour,
I mean you can get better
gas mileage doing that.
If you ever see your parents doing
that...
- Some people don't like to do
that though because of rocks.
- Rocks, yeah it could be dangerous
- Yeah it could be dangerous
becuase of rocks.
Good job.