- Get out your journal, I'll read it aloud
and I'll put the time on the timer.
Get our your journal.
We're looking at journal entry number 14.
And you're not allowed
to write I don't know,
take a guess if you're not sure,
but don't write I don't know.
So question 14 is very simple.
Why do you think an earthquake happens?
You can write it, you can draw a picture.
So I'm asking you why do you
think an earthquake happens.
You have three minutes
right now to write what
you think. Why do you think
an earthquake happens?
(whispering)
Why do you think an earthquake happens,
and why do you think...
(whispering)
Remember there's no right or wrong,
it's what you think is the answer.
Remember you can draw a
picture if that helps you.
Okay if you want to draw
(mumbles) alright you've
got like a minute left so
you can draw a picture.
Write down what you think.
(whispering)
I'm gonna give you about 30 more seconds.
Many of you are still writing and that's
fine,
but I thought before we talk about this
let's take a look at a little clip
because I realize maybe not everybody
has experience with an earthquake.
So this one's kinda cool.
It was shot obviously on somebody's iPhone
so it's not the best quality,
but many of you know that
Japan has lots of earthquakes
all the time, they're
very used to earthquakes.
So this person lives in Japan,
and so again they're used
to earthquakes, right?
So they weren't like
panicking so he actually
took his iPhone and filmed the ground.
So I want you to take a look.
We're only gonna look
at about a minute of it,
but I want you to notice how
the ground is moving, okay?
And we're gonna use that idea to talk
about why earthquakes happen.
So this is pretty cool.
So this was back in March 2011.
So notice.
(rumbling)
Now they're gonna go to another part.
Notice the ground in the
back, watch the back.
You'll see something happen.
(yelling)
Watch what's happening.
(rumbling)
Alright so that's real, it's not like
there was a machine
underneath there doing that.
So you guys, we can solve what's happening,
so let's take that and let's
talk about this through.
Why do you think an earthquake happens?
Why do you guys think
an earthquake happens?
And remember, when we talk
we're gonna let one person
go at a time and we're gonna make sure
we talk loudly so that we can hear.
Alright so let's just start on this side.
We're gonna work this way,
Tony, what did you write?
Why do you think an earthquake happens?
- Well, I think there's something wrong
with the mantle that's
coming out through the crust
and makes it vibrate the earth
and causing an earthquake?
- Okay, something to do with the mantle
causes the earth to vibrate?
Also I liked how you
used a complete sentence.
So remember, if you're not sure,
there's some sentence starters up there.
Jheyline, what did you write?
- I think earthquakes happen because two
plate boundaries overlap each other.
- Excellent, because plate
boundaries overlap each other.
Jose.
- [Jose] I think that earthquakes
happen when plates crash.
- When plates crash.
- [Jose] Together.
- Anybody else?
Adrian, and then Dajana.
- I think that earthquakes
happen because plates slide.
- Because plates slide, excellent.
Dajana?
- I think an earthquake happens
from too much stress?
(mumbles)
Also, I think the plate boundaries overlap.
- Ooh, I like what you said,
and that's exactly where I'm going next.
So in that video clip you
guys saw the ground move.
I'm gonna give you 10 seconds.
And that 10 seconds you're gonna share
with the person next to you
how did the ground move?
What direction was that ground moving?
So you have 10 seconds, share
with your partner next to you
or share with the people across from you.
Go, 10 seconds.
(students chattering)
Alright, finishing up in five,
four, three, two, one, zero.
Okay, so I heard lots of people
talking so I'm gonna pull
a name, this time, remember
you can say what you said
or what the person next to you said.
So what kind of movement did
you notice in that video clip?
Let's see... (mumbles).
Now Neferly, what kind
of movement did you see?
- [Neferly] They were
moving (mumbling) apart?
- Good, moving apart, what
else did you notice, Angel?
- [Angel] They were moving apart.
- Moving apart, what else
did you notice, Dajana?
- Well, it was crashing
everywhere, but I saw the...
(mumbling)
- Ooh, kind of like water
coming out of the sky?
Josh, what else did you notice?
(knocking)
Oh, so a little bit of up and down movement?
Alright so, up and down movement.
Anybody else notice any
other type of movement?
So you guys said up and
down, you said moving apart.
(background noise drowns out speaker)
Oh, did you see how that
piece literally slid?
- Yeah.
- Alright, so that's movement.
You guys know some words for this.
What are some words that we've learned
to describe movement,
and Dajana said a couple.
What words, Jina?
- [Jina] Shearing.
- Yes, so there was
some shearing happening.
What else was happening?
Rodolfo.
- [Rodolfo] Tension?
- Yes, some tension pulling apart.
And what else did you notice, Daniel?
- Compression?
- Yeah, compression, squeezing together.
Okay, so we're getting this
idea that, didn't Dajana,
you said it was stress, or you
said stress, Dajana right?
So something about stress
being kind of important.
So we're gonna take that idea.
Give us a moment, okay, thanks.
Alright, so sorry
about the interruption.
So stress, Dajana was saying stress.
So let me give you an example.
So let's imagine that this
rubber band is not a rubber band.
Let's imagine that it's a rock.
And let's imagine it's a rock, I know,
it's a rubber band, but
let's imagine it's a rock.
So I'm gonna take, I'm gonna go
like this, it's a rock, remember?
So I'm doing this to the
rock, and then I'm gonna
stand here for an entire
year, and then a year from now
I'm gonna put my hands further apart.
And then another year, I'm gonna
put my hands further apart.
What's happening to this
rock, or this rubber band?
What's happening to this rock over time?
What's happening, Lupita, to this rock?
- [Lupita] It's stretching.
- It's stretching, what else?
Add to that, Tucker.
- [Tucker] (mumbling)
and stretching it out,
stretch is added to it?
- Stress is added too, nice, Victor?
- [Victor] So maybe it's
getting a little compression.
- Okay, maybe a little compression too.
My hands are getting tired, Tony?
- Continental drift?
- Ooh, like okay, so if there were
other pieces like my hands were
Africa and South America,
they'd be moving apart.
Ernesto?
- [Ernesto] Thinner in the middle?
- Thinner in the middle. Sakura?
- [Sakura] Tension.
- So tension, now I'm gonna
stop because my hands
starting to hurt, but what would
happen if I kept doing that?
I'm gonna have you take 10 seconds
to talk to the person next to you.
What might happen if I kept doing that,
and I kept doing that,
and I kept doing that?
What might happen to this
rubber band, or this rock?
So 10 seconds, to the
person next to you, ten seconds.
(students chattering)
Alright, finishing up in five,
four, three, two, one, zero.
Okay, I heard lots of good discussion.
So if I kept doing this, I kept doing it,
I kept doing it, Moses, what might happen?
- [Moses] It might crack and break.
- It might crack and break.
Everyone, what else maybe might happen?
Victor?
- [Victor] It will scrape the mountain
and it will create an
earthquake and it'll break.
- Ooh, oh I like, 'cause you
remember this a lot right?
Little earthquake, excellent Tucker?
- It's just like when
you shove your fingers, go
all the way back it will break.
- Oh yeah, that would be painful.
Jheyline?
- It'd probably explode from so much
tension and stretch everything.
- Did everybody hear
that word she just said?
Which word did you say, it would?
- Explode.
- Explode, wow.
That's a big, powerful word, but that's
pretty equal to what happened, right?
Big amount of power.
- Or like when you were
doing that with the rock,
like when you were moving it,
like it would get more thinner
and get more, it would kinda get wider
when after all while it's still going
it's gonna like (mumbles).
- Good, so let's step back a little bit.
So who was it, someone had
said earthquake, right?
You had said earthquake.
So it's sounding like, what
if that happens first?
So before the earth actually moves,
before what we saw in the video,
what did you guys think was happening?
And Moses had used the word for it too.
What was happening to the rocks over time?
So over time what was
happening in that rock
that would eventually
lead to an earthquake?
What's happening over time?
Ernesto, what's happening over time?
- It's stretching?
- It's stretching, keep
going with that, Diego?
- [Diego] It was standing.
- It was standing, Tony?
- [Tony] It's spreading apart?
- Spreading apart, Jheyline?
- [Jheyline] Widening?
- Widening, Tiger?
- Breaking?
- Breaking, so wait before
the breaking though,
you guys were saying it was stretching,
it was pulling, so what
word can you describe
it building up in here,
building up, Stephanie?
- [Stephanie] Through stress?
- Ah, okay, so it sounds
like if we're gonna make an
earthquake we need to have stress first.
We have said stress that builds, right?
Stress builds, and then
what's gonna happen
when the stress builds, and it builds,
and it builds and it builds
and it can't take it anymore?
What's going to happen, Manuel?
- Collide?
- This is stress, keep going.
Not collide, what's another
word that's kind of, same idea?
So you said it when I was over here.
It's gonna keep stressing, and stressing,
and what's gonna happen to the rock?
- Rip?
- It'll what?
- Rip, what's another word you can say.
- It'll explode.
- Explode, Adrian?
- Break?
- Break, great, so there's
going to be a rupture.
Or a break.
And then is that it?
End of the story?
Nice day, that's it?
Where does all this energy go, right?
There's all this energy
building up, where does it go?
Yeah it ruptures, it
breaks, and then is it over?
- No.
- No, what, where, what happened?
Where did the energy go?
Where did that energy go?
Irma, where'd it go?
- [Irma] Plate tectonics?
- Yeah, it has to do with
plate tectonics, absolutely.
Where did that energy go?
Where did it go, Rodolfo?
- [Rodolfo] Plate boundaries?
- [Teacher] Yeah, plate boundaries.
So okay we got stress builds, ruptures,
it breaks, and then is that it?
- No.
- That's the earthquake?
What action?
Yeah, Anna.
- It becomes an earthquake?
- Yeah, it becomes an earthquake
and so what do we experience?
Jheyline?
- Shaking?
- Shaking, oh!
So it sounds like there's
a rupture or a break,
and then that's gonna lead to shaking
and that shaking is actually
what being released?
- An earthquake.
- It's an earthquake, yes and what is that
shaking actually being released?
So the shaking is released, what?
Victor?
- All the stress?
- Yes, it's releasing all the stress.
What's another word you could say?
Releasing all of its...?
- Power.
- Power is a good word, or, Diego?
- [Diego] Energy.
- Energy, right?
So it seems like all an earthquake is,
is stress building up,
building up, building up,
breaks, and then we feel that.
What do we experience the energy as?
So what do we experience,
think of the energy as?
What do we experience it, as an energy?
(knocking)
- That?
- That, what's that?
(knocking)
- Shaking.
- Shaking, right?
Alright awesome.
So now we're gonna, you
guys did that perfectly.
So we're gonna write
that down in our notes.
- [All Students] Woah.
- I know, that, earthquakes
release energy, right?
So that's what happens as a result.
So we are not in any way done with this,
because we are gonna talk
all about different (mumbles).
You guys have made a good
start on what's happening.
So we are gonna take two notes today.
They're pretty short.
I'm sorry, the first one's a little long.
The other one's super short.
But this is what you
guys were just telling me
except now we're gonna add
the word elastic strain,
which is what you guys were telling me.
You were telling me that
energy was building up,
you were telling me
stress was building up,
and that's gonna cause elastic strain.
Yes, Dajana?
- The pictures that
you showed us (mumbles).
- What?
- It only cut through the (mumbles).
- Kind of, yeah.
- Yes.
- So like maybe 'cause on the bottom
that came out of the ground (mumbles).
- Yeah.
- And then it just spilled it over,
then it came out of the ground.
- Yeah, so thank you for
those of you who got started.
Rodolfo, let me just
read this off for people.
So our first topic today
is earthquake energy.
And this is what we just talked about.
But now we're getting a
chance to write it down
and we're adding in a bigger word.
And that word is elastic strain.
So elastic strain is the energy stored
as rocks change shape.
Okay, so that's step
one in an earthquake.
Step two.
Energy is released when the
rock ruptures or breaks.
So elastic strain is the energy
stored as rocks change shape
and energy is released when
the rock ruptures or it breaks
and released energy
travels in seismic waves,
and we will learn all
about those next week.
But you can still write
down, you just think
released energy travels
and it's felt as shaking.