- [Boy in Camo] Anything else?
- [Girl in striped shirt] So,
what composter would you want?
- [Boy in camo] I think we would want maybe like
a three-tray or four-tray vermicomposter.
And I do now admit it
would be helpful to get one
that would be cheaper.
Maybe you guys have a different idea?
- [Boy in brown] Maybe, I was thinking
that maybe we can make one,
because I printed off some
directions how to make
a vermicomposter.
So again, that would
save us a lot of money
just to make it.
Like, this might cost $20
to get all these supplies.
And I know some people have
supplies at their houses
that they could bring in to use for this.
And this might cost $20,
when a store-bought one
off the internet may cost $100.
- [Girl in striped shirt] Yes, but the
store-bought one's are quality,
and a professional makes it.
So they know what they're doing.
- [Boy in dark blue] I doesn't really
matter, I mean it has the same purpose,
it does the same thing.
I just matters on the worms.
- [Boy in brown] The only thing that
we really have to buy is the worms.
- [Boy in camo] Dylan and Ben, I got to
admit, I do agree with Claire.
Buying one would be a good
quality and what do we know
about, I know it says. . .
what do we know, about...
- [Teacher] Now, where are
you guys in your conversation?
- [Girl in black] We're deciding
to do wood, metal, or plastic.
But he said that the wood would rot
and the metal could rust.
- [Boy in striped shirt] It could rust
because of the moistness of the compost.
- [Teacher] Okay.
- [Boy in white] It's not metal.
- [Boy in hoodie] We're not talking about metal.
- [Girl in black] So we might do plastic.
- [Teacher] On what?
- [Student] If we make it.
- [Teacher] Purchasing one?
- [Student] No, if we make our own.
(Background Chatter)
- [Boy in white] But this one is award-winning.
- [Student] Seventy dollars.
- [Teacher] All right, and
did you know what website
you found that so you
could share it as a class?
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] This is
buying a vermicomposter
that would cost $70.
And what did you say about yours?
- [Boy in hoodie] This is about like
$20, because we need two
of these eight to 10 gallon
plastic storage boxes.
And we need two of them,
and it says the cost
is about five dollars each.
And that would save us
a lot so we could get
Weebly pro, tools, and then maybe later on
we could by the reusable bags.
- [Teacher] So what are
your thoughts on helping
the whole community?
- [Boy in hoodie] I think we should build
this because it's better
and we would have more money left over.
- [Teacher] And how would you spend
the other money left over?
- [Boy in hoodie] I would spend it on
like, stuff that we need
for composting, like for tools.
- [Teacher] Okay, wait, we
have multiple conversations
going here in this group.
So let's wait.
- [Boy in hoodie] I would spend
it on the tools, Weebly Pro,
and if we have some money left over
we could probably get
more from the compost.
And then we could get that tea
thing that gets the tea out.
And that way you could get more money.
And then we could get something else.
- [Boy in tie-dye] What's Weebly Pro?
- [Boy in hoodie] It's like an extra,
you can search it up on Google.
- [Girl in black] Isn't it a website?
- [Boy in gray hoodie] It's 26 compost, and then
you can have a many slides
as you want, videos.
And then we can sell our
compost on the internet,
and that would help a lot.
- [Teacher] So, how is the Weebly
Pro better than the Weebly
that we already have?
Because you were the webmaster
on the class website,
on the composting website.
And you want to, what
do you want us to do?
- [Boy in gray hoodie] We can have,
buy the six-month plan,
and then the guys for next
year, they figure it out.
- [Teacher] And how would us buying the Weebly Pro
help the community?
- [Boy in gray hoodie] It would help us
to sell it and to inform about compost.
- [Teacher] Okay, any other comments or thought?
- [Boy in striped shirt] We could,
it could maybe inform the people more
because we could make a
video of how to compost
so they could make their own.
- [Teacher] Okay, inform who?
Be more specific.
- [Boy in striped shirt] The viewers of the website.
- [Teacher] All of our guests?
- [Boy in white] Yeah.
- [Brunette girl in glasses] There's a
greater chance it's not gonna fail.
- [Boy in camo] Guys, we're not
playing the what-if game.
- [Boy in plaid] I not saying,
but we have a chance that the cups
might break, because
they're cups and they have
an easier chance,
- [Brunette girl in glasses] It has a
bigger chance of not failing.
- [Boy in brown] We have to take risks.
We have to.
- [Boy in dark blue] Plus,
you would have the pride
of making your own.
(Background Chatter)
- [Boy in gray] If we make our own,
and we mess up,
then we're just wasting money.
- [Boy in dark blue] What
if, what if, what if, what it.
- [Boy in gray] I'm not doing the what-if!
- [Girl in green] ' Cause remember last time
when we built a-- (Background Chatter)
- [Girl in green shirt] If you make it,
there is a greater chance you will fail.
- [Boy in camo] Maybe instead
of cups, we use PVC pipes.
I mean, they're that cheap,
and I mean they would hold
longer than styrofoam cups.
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Shhh, too many people.
- [Boy in gray] That's better quality.
- [Boy in camo] I
do agree with you, Adam,
but I also do agree with Dylan and Ben
on two different subjects.
- [Boy in brown] Guys, why don't
we just make everything?
We can make the compost bin,
- [Boy in gray] But
if we make everything,
- [Boy in brown] reusable bags.
(Background Chatter)
- [Boy in gray] Why don't we buy
the vermicomposter,
and then we make the bags?
- [Blond girl in glasses] The reusable
bags are more like, for people to buy
if they want to have an easy reusable bag.
And then the tools, we
might really need later on
when we don't need the reusable bags.
We might need the tools, or we said,
we might need to go buy
this now, and it might be
too late already.
- [Teacher] What's the major difference
between the vermicomposter
and the reusable bags?
Jessica, what's the major
difference between the two?
- [Brunette girl in glasses] In vermicomposting,
it keeps reproducing, there's three products.
While the reusable bags,
when you sell them once,
and that's all you get from that bag.
- [Boy in plaid] And with the
vermicomposter, it keeps going.
It's very unlikely, almost impossible,
that all the worms are
going to die in one night.
- [Boy in dark blue] Plus,why would
you buy the bags if you can make them?
'Cause my mom has a friend
that makes her own bags
out of store bags, like
Walmart and Target bags.
And she melts them down
and puts them into a bag.
- [Boy in gray] Why don't we
buy the vermicomposter
so it's a better quality,
and we make the bags?
They're easier.
- [Boy in brown] It's very hard
to find a perfect vermicomposter
that's plastic and won't break.
Most of them are terracotta
and they'll shatter
if somebody knocks it over.
It's also wood, and wood
will start to absorb the smells
of the compost and then it
will start to smell bad.
- [Boy in gray] How do you know
we're going to do wood?
- [Boy in brown] Compost things on
the internet are using
either terracotta or wood.
Terracotta shatters really easily.
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Okay, so we need
to do more research on this.
- [Boy in gray] I found a four-tray
bin that's plastic for $89.99.
- [Boy in brown] But still, why
would we pay $100, when we can pay. . .
- [Boy in gray] For quality.
- [Boy in brown] ...a mere $20.
(Background Chatter debating necessity of quality)
- [Girl in striped shirt] I know,
but the materials we use
aren't made for composting.
- [Teacher] Listen to Carly for a second.
What Carly?
- [Blond girl in glasses] Because if
we do what Ben's mom's friend can do,
you could easily save
more money like you do
if you make the vermicomposter.
- [Teacher] Do you think you
could get your mom's friend
to come in and teach us
as a class on how to make
our own like she already does?
(Background Chatter)
- [Girl in green] I think we should buy
the vermicomposter first,
like buy it or make it, and
then buy the reusable bags.
So, just like Ben's mom's friend's bags.
- [Boy in brown] But we should make them
both, because then we will
still have some money left over to buy
other things like tools.
- [Student] Like a new aerator.
- [Boy in gray] If we make the reusable
bags we won't get to
put our symbol on it, which
I think is part of the bag.
- [Girl in black] We're thinking
about doing ovens.
- [Boy in white] 'Cause it's like one,
two, three, four, five, six.
- [Girl in pink] If we made it, we
wouldn't have a guarantee
that it would work,
because we could screw up
the way we make it.
Or we could just mess it up in general.
But if we bought one, it would be kind of
guaranteed to work.
- [Girl in striped shirt] But sometimes
we miss a part, or a tool that we need
to put it together.
- [Teacher] How do you
know that sometimes,
what experience do you have that sometimes
all the parts aren't always there?
- [Girl in striped shirt] Because
when we were making the other one
and forgot one of the
tools, so we couldn't do
one part of it.
And then it just all got all messed up.
- [Student] It just threw us off.
- [Teacher] So from your
experience you know that
sometimes when we order something,
we don't always get it.
- [Boy in white] This part is the
leading thing right there,
it comes built.
All we have to do it put
the plastic bars together,
and it will be kind of easy.
'Cause it just like, goes.
Yeah, and you can work
as a group to make it.
Because it's like those styrofoams
where you pull it together.
And you can just see where
it's put together, the sticks.
- [Teacher] Like the
couplers on the sides.
- [Boy in hoodie] So, we have
something to be proud of that we made.
- [Girl in black] Everybody said
that we wanted a see-through one
so we could actually see the dirt.
- [Teacher] And this
one's not see-through.
So, if we made our own,
could we get a clear tote?
(Background Chatter)
- [Boy in tie-dye] ...'cause the worms
don't like light.
So you can lift to look.
And the worms don't like
light, so when you look at it,
lift it up, look at it
and then put it back down.
- [Teacher] That's a good idea.
No one else has thought
about that, Christian.
And how do you know that
the worms don't like light?
- [Boy in tie-dye] Because we looked it up on the internet.
- [Boy in white] And then one time
I was in my house, and I saw a worm
out in the street, and it was kind of like
rattling, rattling in the sun.
So then my sister kicked
it in, back in the grass.
So then it was much happier
and I re-research that.
- [Boy in gray hoodie] Okay, but
do we have to do vermicompost?
- [Teacher] No, we don't
have to do it at all.
It's going to be our class.
We need to vote on what's
going to be the best
for the community.
- [Boy in tie-dye] What about reusable bags?
- [Boy in striped shirt] I think the
reusable bags are (Background Chatter).
- [Teacher] And why?
How is the reusable
bags different than what
we're already doing?
- [Boy in striped shirt] If we sell the,
if the people next year sell them
at the Holiday Boutique,
then if we sell compost, then it would be
the same customers.
And if we give the customer
something different
more people will come because, they'll
yeah, and they need bags.
- [Teacher] They could buy
bags to put their stuff in
that they buy?
- [Girl in striped shirt] And for backpacks and
stuff for when they go
grocery shopping they need
something to put them in
instead of just wasting
all those plastic bag.
They could use the reusable bag.
- [Boy in gray] I have an idea,
I think we should stick with
our old compost in our tumbler,
And then we should get the bags.
And we should have the
compost and the bags
of compost tea.
And then they could buy the bags,
and they could buy the compost,
and they could have the
compost tea in the bag
and they could carry it
so it's not that hard.
- [Teacher] So we could use our
bags as the packaging
for the compost?
- [Boy in striped shirt] Yeah, that's
what I was thinking.
- [Girl in black] It's gonna cost extra.
- [Boy in striped shirt] And then
make it just a bit more expensive
'cause then you get to
keep the reusable bag
and the compost.
- [Boy in white] You know, if you put
your money in the bank
they give you money?
This would basically give
you money, because you can
make the compost, yeah the interest, yeah.
So we can get the money
from this, and then we can
buy the bags for the high-level tea.
- [Boy in gray] But that has no
holes for the worms.
The sun is coming right into--
(Background Chatter)
But would it fit in our room?
- [Teacher] So, we need to
get more information on this.
- [Boy in gray] Remember we were talking about
the internet could be
wrong about its size?
- [Teacher] Yeah, but
normally they don't do
false advertisement,
- [Boy in white] This is like in a this--
(Background Chatter)--the bottom is like
this size of a desk.
- [Teacher] You could
compare this to this vase
or this container that they
would put the plant in.
- [Student] It's like a shower,
it's like the size of a shower.
- [Student] Yeah, you guys
need more information.
- [Teacher] We need more information
before you can make a decision on that?
- [Student] A lot of
information on this already.
- [Boy in white] But we won't
make tea if this one
would have really worked, cause it's made.
You know, the more it
costs the better it works.
- [Teacher] Do you agree with his comment?
- [Some students] No.
- [Other Student] Yeah, that's what Cara said.
(Several students disagree.)
- [Teacher] Can anyone give an example?
- [Boy in striped shirt] I don't agree
with that, because when I was real little
I bought some toy cars
and they didn't work
as well as I got--some that were cheaper.
And the cheaper ones worked
better than the expensive ones.
- [Teacher] Okay, you guys
continue discussing that.