- Write at the top of your paper
The color that you want for your sugar
and the color you want for your salt
- on both of them?
Sugar on one, salt on the other
- Yes, because you can
make from your sheet two.
(group discussions)
Now the purpose of these sheets
is so you can actually take your spoon
Malik, take your spoon
and dip out onto that paper.
This gives you a better visual
of how much sugar and how much salt
is in that particular food.
Now what's the most important
thing about the label?
- Serving Size
- Serving size. Good Aaron, serving size.
So that is showing most of these
is the container itself.
That's the reason we went to snack foods
so that you could see how much that is.
This also gives you a better idea of
how much you eat.
Some of you, like Aaron, may
eat two or three of these
especially if it was Gummies, right Aaron?
- Yes
- It's not Gummies but it's close
Okay, so any questions
before you get started?
Okay, decide who is
going to do calculations
decide who's going to measure first
I want you to rotate those
responsibilities around
and Devon, what is your question?
(group discussions)
Remember the personal column
is how much you would eat
(group discussions)
- [Voiceover] the serving size
- Doesn't matter, your group remember
has to cooperate, figure out who's
going to do what and just look at responsibilities
- [Voiceover] Just make sure everyone sees
how much sugar; how much salt it is
That's the important part.
On the back of your paper.
- [Voiceover] When it says
about 29 grams right here
- What's the serving size?
- Serving size is here... [inaudible]
there are four servings in here
- [Voiceover] They would eat half the bag
then it would be two servings
(group discussions)
-So next is the total calories, and it's got...
- 130 calories
- total carbs
(group discussions overlapping)
- ok so nine grams
- Now when you dip out your salt and sugar
try to replace it in the correct bucket
we don't want the salt in the sugar or
the sugar in the salt.
So pay attention to what you're doing.
(group discussions overlapping)
- Now remember, you have to calculate
what you would eat.
(group discussions overlapping)
- [Voiceover] Give me some sugar.
- [Voiceover] 11 grams divided by four.
(group discussions overlapping)
- Put two teaspoons on here
- [Voiceover] Is it sodium?
- Dip it out you see how much
See visually how much it is.
(group discussions overlapping)
- I don't have any salt.
- Yes Paul
(group discussions overlapping)
I want to encourage you
that after you done something that's
really sugary, do something
that you would think would be salty
as if it surprises you,
how much sugars in it
(group discussions overlapping)