- (Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Starter-stopper,
opposite side. Okay.
Everybody has their marbles.
How many trials are we doing?
- [Kids] Five.
- [Teacher] Five trials.
If the first one doesn't work,
raise your hand.
I will come help you
and we'll talk about why it doesn't work
and what we're gonna do to change it.
What you're gonna do to change it.
Okay?
Timers.
Get your people ready.
Remember you're gonna say, "Ready, set,"
as soon as that: "go."
All right. Go.
- [Kids] Ready.
Set.
Go.
- [Boy] Oh! You're supposed to get it.
- [Teacher] Right here.
This great piling direction.
Did y'all's work?
- [Group 1] Yeah.
- [Teacher] Good. Good.
Did you record the time?
- [Boy in blue] Look.
- [Teacher] Tell him. You guys
are ready to keep going.
Five trials. Good job.
And we'll discuss why
yours worked in a minute.
- [Boy in sweater] We gonna take-
- [Teacher] Okay hang on. Tell me what happened.
- [Girl with glasses] When it got here, it stopped.
- [Teacher] It stopped. Why did--
- [Girl with glasses] Friction.
- [Teacher] Okay, the--
- [Angel] Probably because
the speed wasn't great enough.
- Okay. So you think
you needed more speed?
- [Boy with Sweater] No. I think we need to take this off.
- [Teacher] Okay. Let's try taking that off.
Where do you think you can put
those to get more speed?
- [Kids] Up here.
- [Teacher] Ok.
Now, what is that gonna give the marbles?
- [Girl with glasses] More momentum?
- [Teacher] Yes.
- [Boy with sweater] Let's make it bigger.
Three centimeters.
- [Boy behind camera]
Is this our second one?
Are we gonna do a second try?
- [Teacher] You're going
back to your first one
because you want to make sure it works.
So reset it. Okay.
Try again.
[Kids exclaim in excitement]
- [Teacher] Did it work?
- [Kids] Yeah.
- [Teacher] Let's discuss
why did it work this time?
- [Angel] Look how we gave them these.
- [Teacher] By doing what?
- [Boy with sweater] By um. Making it higher.
- [Teacher] Elevation? Ooh.
And what's another word that--
- [Girl with glasses] Altitude.
- [Teacher] Yeah. That's good. Okay.
So it worked. How long did it take?
- [Kids] Seven seconds.
- [Teacher] Face the recorder.
Got it? Okay. Very good.
Keep going. You're ready
for your second trial.
Okay.
- [Boy in dark blue] We're done.
- [Teacher] Y'all already done five trials?
Okay. Well, let's just stop for a minute.
What comes down. Let's pull together here.
Let's talk. I want you guys
to talk about why you think it worked.
- [Girl] Because the big hill helped.
- [Teacher] The hill? What force is that?
- [Boy with glasses] The hill was enormous
so it gave it more momentum.
-[Teacher] Good job. So gravity pulled it down.
- [Teaher] What did you say?
- [Boy with glasses] I said the hill's bigger
than the hoop
so it gave it more
momentum so it would go.
- [Teacher] To make it through the loop.
Right.
And the force pulling it down was what?
- [Kids] Gravity.
- [Teacher] Gravity. Good.
Now talk to me about the order
that you put it in.
Why would you-- you kind of just did.
- [Boy with glasses] We put the hill here
so the hill would go
faster to go in the loop.
- [Teacher] To get more speed behind it.
Good.
- [Boy with glasses] And the turn would--
- [Boy in dark blue] Make it slow down.
- [Boy with glasses] Yeah.
- [Teacher] So what do you think would
make the marble stop
down there at the end?
- [Kids] Friction.
- [Teacher] Friction. Okay.
Very good. We got all five trials.
You guys need a knee. Start
recording your information.
- [Boy in black] It went really fast.
- [Teacher] "Really fast."
- Just three seconds.
- Did it work on the first trial?
- [Group 3] No.
- [Teacher] Okay. Tell me what
happened on the first trial.
-[Boy in black] It was like that.
And it just went off right here.
- [Teacher] Okay. Why do
you think it fell off?
What was going on right
here to make it fall?
- [Boy in jacket] Twist?
- [Teacher] There was a twist in it?
So you just had to fix it
so that it went straighter.
And so you pushed it?
- [Boy in jacket] Renny put it
like this, like around here.
- [Boy in black] Pushed it in.
- [Teacher] So it might have been
a little to steep too.
That incline might have been too steep.
What order did you put your elements in?
- [Kids] Hill, loop, and turn.
- [Teacher] Okay. And why'd
you put the hill first?
- [Boy in jacket] Because it's higher.
And it would give more speed.
- [Teacher] What force is
giving it more speed right here?
- [Boy in jacket] Gravity.
- [Teacher] Very good. Okay.
And then talk to me about
why you put your loop
right after that hill and not your turn.
Why didn't you put your turn there?
- [Boy in jacket] If we turn,
there's not enough speed.
- [Boy in black] For the loop.
- [Teacher] Okay. Y'all both
said the exact same thing.
Repeat that to me so I understand.
- [Boy in black] If we put the turn first,
it won't have enough speed for the loop.
- [Teacher] Good. Very good.
All right. Good job guys.
Have you got five trials?
- [Boy in jacket] It's all three seconds.
- [Teacher] All of 'em were the same?
That's interesting. Very good.
We'll talk about that after you each
need a knee and record your information.
Anthony, what was your job?
- [Anthony] Record.
- [Teacher] So you were the one that
found that they were the same each time?
Make sure you get written down everything.
Okay guys. Talk to me.
- [Boy] We got three.
- [Teacher] Did the first one work?
- [Girl in black] No.
- [Teacher] Tell me what
happened on the first one
becuase I didn't see it.
- [Girl in black] The first one, we had this open
and we had it sitting right there
and we had the chair right here
and when we set it down,
right here, when the
chair was right there,
it kept on falling off.
- [Girl in blue] So it just dropped.
- [Teacher] So you think
the incline was too what?
- [Girl in blue] Straight.
- [Girl in black] It was too steep.
- [Teacher] There you go.
That's the word I'm looking for.
It was too steep.
- [Girl in black] Because it was right here
and it was going all down.
- [Teacher] Very Good. So
what did you do to fix it?
- [Girl in black] We kept on sliding
it down a little.
- [Teacher] Did you have to
slide it down more than once?
- [Girl in black] Yes.
- [Teacher] Good job guys.
So did you get it to where
you could do five trials?
- [Girl in blue] Yes.
- [Girl in black] And we got three for each.
- [Teacher] Three seconds? They did too.
They got the exact same for all of 'em.
How about that?
But look at your coasters.
They look different.
- [Kids] Yeah.
- [Teacher] That's interesting too.
'Cause their incline
is steeper than yours.
Lets talk about the order that
you have your elements in.
What's first?
- [Girl in blue] The hill
because it gives more speed
when it's going down a hill so you don't--
- [Teacher] But that's on what force?
- [Girl in blue] Gravity.
- [Teacher] Good job.
And why'd you put your
loop right after that?
- [Girl in blue] Because it
would have the most speed
to keep going and then the turn return it.
Because if we did the turn,
it wouldn't have enough
speed to make the loop.
- [Teacher] Good job. Good job.
Need a knee, record your information,
and start figuring your speed.
Have you guys got all five trials?
- [Kids] Nope.
- [Teacher] Uh oh. What happened?
- [Girl with glasses] It stopped because of the friction.
When it get right here, it
started getting out of friction.
- [Teacher] Friction right here?
What's causing friction right here?
Can I watch it?
- [Boy in sweater] Its gonna work
this time because we taped it down.
- [Teacher] Why do
you think it's gonna work?
- [Boy in sweater] Because we taped it down.
- [Teacher] You know what?
I want you to use that one.
How long did that take?
- [Boy in black] Seven.
- [Teacher] Seven seconds?
All right. Do it again.
Let's look at it again.
So it was stopping right here.
- [Girl with glasses] It always was stopping right there
and then I taped it down.
- [Teacher] Oh you taped this down.
- [Boy in black] That
thing could be higher.
- [Teacher] Okay. I think
you should try that.
- [Boy in sweater] We can use this clock.
No we need some more.
- [Girl with glasses] I was
gonna get one of them books.
- [Teacher] Guys, you can use any state.
So what are you doing to the hills?
- [Kids] Making it bigger.
- [Girl with glasses] So the
speed will go more faster.
- [Teacher] More faster? So
that it'll increase the speed?
All right. Let's see what happens.
Let's see if this one works.
- [Videographer] Angel,
what are you doing?
- [Angel] Timing. Ready? One-- Oh.
- [Boy in sweater] We use good team work.
- [Teacher] You are using good teamwork.
I'm proud of it.
- [Angel] Ready? Set. Go.
- [Boy in sweater] It didn't start
from the beginning.
- [Angel] I did not start that one.
- [Teacher] Let me ask you this.
Just to give you a different idea
because you've already tried to change
in the elevation of your hill.
- [Angel] Maybe how big the loop is.
- [Teacher] How do you think that'll help?
- So the-- will go faster
and will make it go through.
- [Teacher] All right.
We're gonna try this.
Help her out guys.
So we're making the loop smaller
and that's gonna --
So now you might want to move
this up a little bit there.
You see how this is gonna have to go --
There you go.
- [Videographer] What about your taping?
If it's -- will the --
- [Teacher] Yeah.
Let's try again.
Wait. We were gonna time that, honey.
Now you're ready to go.
So what was the solution to your problem?
- [Girl with glasses] To make the loop smaller
so it would go through much faster.
- [Teacher] All right. Good job.
Now you're ready to time five trials.
- [Angel] Ready? Go.
- [Teacher] Look, how beautiful.
Good job, guys.
- [Girl with glasses] How many seconds?
- [Angel] Four.
- [Boy in sweater] Four seconds. That's good.
How many trials?
- [Girl] Three. We got two more.
- [Teacher] I want to know. You got
three seconds on each one.
So your speed was the same.
Where did your distance come from?
- [Girl] We did how many feet
and then we found out how many inches.
- [Boy in glasses] And times it by 18
because it's 18 on there.
- [Teacher] How long was each tube?
- [Kids] Six feet.
- [Teacher] Six feet.
How many inches is that?
Let's work it out. Make sure
you've got it right on here.
- [Girl] 72.
- [Teacher] So, you've got 72 inches.
- [Boy in glasses] We only did one tube.
- [Teacher] And how many tubes are there?
- [Boy in blue] There's three tubes.
- [Teacher] So 72.
What would you do next?
- [Girl] Times three.
- [Teacher] Yes. 72 times three.
How did you guys get 216?
You did 18 inches instead of six?
I mean 12. Okay.
So now you'll have to go
back and redo your speed.
Figure in your speed.
So how do you find speed?
- [Girl] I still got 216.
- [Teacher] Well then you were right.
That's right. So you guys are ready
to go on to make a graph.
Let's talk about the graph
you're gonna make. Let's
talk about the graph
Thinking about what you've learned in math
and what you've been
doing with graphs in math
using this data table right here.
What is this right here?
- [Boy in blue] Time.
- [Teacher] I want you guys to
think about what we
talked about with graphs.
I want you to decide what
kind of graph you should make.
- [Girl] Line graph because it's over time.
- [Boy with glasses] Yeah.
Line graph. I decided.
Yeah we decided to put a line graph
because it's time.
- [Teacher] So any time you use time,
the line graph is the one to use.
Very, very good.
- [Girl] Do we write the numbers on here?
- [Teacher] Yeah. How are you gonna know
what numbers to put on there?
Think about it.
You've got the trials,
the distance, the time,
and the speed. Do you need to use these?
You're probably just gonna
use your trial and your speed.
So you'll label your line graph.
One will be the trial and
one will be the speed.
And do you remember when you
did the race car activity?
Not the race car activity. I'm sorry.
Remember the Stanley the Sluggish Snail?
What did that line graph look like?
- [Girl on right] It was a straight line.
- [Teacher] Because it
was a constant speed.
So what do you think
this is gonna look like?
- [Girl] Constant
speed. A straight line.
- [Teacher] Good.
- [Boy in blue] Okay.
- [Teacher] You've got your trial.
You got your times.
Let's talk about your speed.
First we need to look at your distance.
How did you figure distance?
- [Boy in jacket] We need
to divide by those speeds.
- [Teacher] But your distance is
how far the marble traveled; right?
- [Boy in jacket] 18.
- [Boy in white] Yeah.
- [Teacher] 18?
- [Boy in jacket] Yeah because
you said each was six feet.
- [Teacher] Six feet.
You're doing it in inches.
- [Kids] Oh.
- [Teacher] So let's go
back and refigure that.
I want you guys to talk
about how to do that.
'Cause we want it in inches.
So what is the first thing you would do?
Y'all talk through it.
Y'all talk to each other.
Let's talk about it.
After you're done erasing.
- [Boy in jacket] I was thinking like
how many inches each--
- [Teacher] Okay. There
you go. Talk about it.
Anybody know how many
inches are in a foot?
- [Boy in jacket] 16?
- [Teacher] Nope. Try again.
If you have a ruler.
- [Boy in jacket] 12.
- [Teacher] Yep. Good.
- [Boy in jacket] So that's 12 x 3.
- [Teacher] Good.
- [Boy in jacket] 36.
- [Teacher] Okay. So 36 inches
and then how many of these are there?
- [Boy in black] Three.
- [Teacher] Uh-huh.
- [Boy in black] 36 multiplied --
- [Teacher] six speed.
So you need to do 6 x 12.
- [Boy in black] 6 x 12 is --
- [Boy in jacket] 72.
- [Teacher] Make sure you got it right.
12 x 6. Do it on your paper.
- [Boy in jacket] I did it before. It is 72.
- [Teacher] So now you will do 72 times...
- [Kids] Three.
- [Teacher] Good. Do it on your paper
72 x 3.
- [Boy in white] It's 216 inches.
- [Teacher] Okay. Now
what are you gonna do?
- [Boy in white] Write it down.
- [Teacher] And then what?
- [Boy in white] Multiply 216 to this.
- [Teacher] So how will you figure speed now?
- [Boy in black] Divide.
- [Teacher] Divide what?
- [Boy in jacket] Three to 216.
- [Teacher] Very good.
- [Videographer] Can you
tell me that again, Jeffrey?
You're gonna do what?
- [Boy in Jacket] Divide 216 into three.
- [Teacher] And you'll only
have to do it how many times?
- [Boy in jacket] One.
- [Teacher] Because you got
the same speed each time.
You can do three into 216.
- [Boy in jacket] 72.
- [Teacher] And no remainder.
That's nice. Isn't it?
Now, knowing what we know about graphs,
what we're doing in math.
Jeffrey, are you listening?
Y'all stop writing
for a minute and listen.
Knowing what we know about graphs,
what we talked about in math,
and using this data and speed,
what kind of graph do you
think you're gonna make?
- [Boy in black] Line.
- [Teacher] Why did you say a line graph?
- [Boy in black] Because it's the same.
- [Teacher] I want you to
think about this right here.
Over time. We discussed we
need to use a line graph, okay?
When you make your line graph,
which two columns --
there's only two columns
that you can use on there.
Which two do you think you're gonna use?
- [Boy in black] This one and --
- [Teacher] Well you've already figured that out.
This one and which other one?
And speed, good. Right.
Because you were figuring
all this for speed.
What do you think your
line's gonna look like?
- [Boy in black] Straight.
- [Teacher] Straight. Because
it was the same every time.
Good.