(Background chatter)
- Alright.
I heard the term velocity.
So, I think that sounds pretty good.
(teacher murmurs)
Velocity of a skateboarder,
the more important you're going to have.
I like velocity.
Keep talking amongst yourselves.
I'm just kind of here to guide you along.
Make sure the people here,
I don't want anyone to have
their back to each other.
I know the room is difficult to do that,
but if you guys could try to
make sure you look at everyone
inside of the group.
I know it's difficult.
- Wait.
The whole class?
- Oh, yeah.
I want the whole class to discuss this.
- I thought you were doing
like table and table?
No, no, no.
I want everyone to talk.
Sorry.
- Okay.
- You guys can talk, just
like I talk across the room.
Feel free to do so.
(students murmur)
- [Teacher] So, someone,
when we ask their velocity.
- [Student] You need more
length to the tracks.
- [Student] Steeper.
- [Teacher] You don't
have to raise your hand.
If you're looking in that person's eye,
or you're looking in my eye,
feel free to....
- [Student] You need a longer track.
- [Student] Distance.
(students murmur)
- Is it the friction?
(student murmurs)
- [Teacher] I will tell you that we're
not going to look at friction
as part of the system.
(students murmur)
- Let's look back at that
proposal for one second.
Just want to make sure
I didn't miss anything.
(students murmur)
It's always good to look
at what they give us.
(students murmur)
Let's see.
What science terms are in there?
- [Student] Quantitative.
Qualitative.
- [Teacher] Okay.
- [Student] Energy.
- [Teacher] Oh.
We got energy in there.
- [Student] Energy transfer.
- [Teacher] Oh, energy transfer.
Okay.
So, I think they want
something to do with energy.
- It said quantitative.
We should probably use
the formulas for kinetic
and potential energy, right?
- [Student] Do we have them?
- Yeah.
- [Student] We do?
- It's half mv squared, right?
And then...
(students murmur)
- What Christina said, we're
going to be collecting data,
quantitative,
we'll probably have to use some formula
that associates with this.
- I agree.
- Okay.
- [Student] Okay.
- [Student] He gave us the formula.
(students murmur)
- E sub k 1/2 mv squared.
Energy due to the gravitational
field, E sub g mg.
Alright.
Let's make sure we
know what each of these
letters stands for.
M, mass and the unit.
Kilogram.
G?
(students murmur)
- Acceleration due to gravity.
- Lauren said force of gravity.
(students murmur)
Okay.
You want me to write that in?
Which one is it?
(students murmur)
Oh, its the effect from
the gravitational field.
Okay, that's fine.
You will sometimes see
textbooks that read
gravitational force, but
what are the units for this?
(students murmur)
Meters per second squared.
So, that can be kind of confusing,
if they're calling it gravitational force,
and then they're saying
meters per second squared
because what do you think
when you see those units?
- Acceleration.
- [Teacher] Acceleration, right.
So, I'm going to put
acceleration due to gravity.
Okay.
Good.
- [Student] H is height.
- [Teacher] Yeah, h is height.
And that's in?
(students murmur)
- Meters.
Sounds good.
Okay.
So, now we go over here.
Mass and kilograms and then,
velocity, and that's in
meters per second.
Good.
And then, if you remember that
force doesn't like careless errors,
so, maybe we should make sure that we get
from these fundamental
units the derived units.
So, what are the units
that we're going to have for
E sub g and E sub k?
(student murmurs)
What is it?
- [Students] Joules.
- Joules.
Oh, that's right.
How do you remember that?
- [Student] I'm smart.
- Okay.
That's good, too.
(teacher laughs)
(students murmur)
- Oh, there was a pretest
that had that on there.
That sounds good.
(students murmur)
- Okay.
Great.
You're taking that prior knowledge.
- [Student] Energy is a jewel.
- Energy is a precious jewel.
Alright.
You want precious?
Okay, there's jewels.
There's semi-precious
and there's precious.
What are they, diamonds and rubies?
So, energy is a precious jewel.
Kilogram times a meter per second squared.
- [Student] Newton.
- [Teacher] Newton.
Good.
Newton times a meter?
- A joule?
- A joule.
Right.
Over here, mass and kilograms.
Kilogram times meters squared
over seconds squared,
don't forget the square.
Kilograms times a meter,
again is a newton.
Newton times a meter,
that's going to be kilogram times a meter
over seconds squared is a newton
and then, multiply that by that meter,
and, again, you get joules.
Okay.
We want to make sure that we don't,
did everyone see how we
got that joule there?
(students murmur)
- Meter times another meter, right?
- [Student] Yeah.
- Because kilogram times a
meter per seconds squared
gives me a newton.
Times a meter, remember
this is meters squared,
because of that.
- Oh, okay.
- Okay.
So, you know the boss
doesn't like careless errors,
so let's make sure that we
have the appropriate units.
Okay.
I don't mean to interrupt you guys.
Why don't you continue with that?
You've got some formulas here now.
- For potential energy,
wouldn't mass and
acceleration due to gravity
be constants, so height
is the only one that
that could manipulate.
So, if the height is the
greater distance from the Earth
then it would have more potential energy
because they're directly proportional.
(student murmurs)
- [Student] Yes.
- Let me ask you guys...
I can't help but interrupt
once in a while, right?
But, I just wanted to...
If I put this marker on the table,
does this marker have potential energy?
- What is the reference point?
- Oh, oh, oh.
The table.
- No.
- The center of our planet.
- Yes.
- Okay.
So, I heard a fight, I
think that's a good thing.
(students murmur)
- The more danger, the
more fun I thought, right?
- Yes.
- They're going to wear their headgear.
Is this guy wearing any head,
oh he's wearing head protection.
(students murmur)
Why is that important, by the way?
- So, the force doesn't
apply to your head...
(student murmurs)
- Okay, I like that.
- Ah.
Inversely proportional, right?
I like that, yeah.
So, it increases the amount of time,
decreases the force.
So, yeah, danger is an aspect here,
but this guy seems like he's doing okay.
He's got his headgear on,
but, that's definitely,
if you're designing a park,
you want to make sure
that the people that visit the park
aren't going to be injured.
There are going to be
accidents with skateboards
but they'll wear their gear.
I'm going to step back
and let you guys continue
your thought earlier.
- [Student] Okay.
So, how high do we want the...
- If we want it to have a
bigger potential energy,
transferring the bigger kinetic energy,
we might want to have the height
from the reference point,
which is the ground and kind of higher.
- [Teacher] I heard reference point.
Let me see if I can put a
reference point on this.
(students murmur)
I did just put a little, click a button
and get the reference point, okay?
- [Student] I think the thing
should be on the ground.
(student murmurs)
- [Student] Yeah.
- The weight's, like it's
safer and it's possible.
(students murmur)
- Do you want me to just to extend the...
We've got a couple of
things going on here.
I'm sorry.
A couple people said yes,
they wanted me to put that on the ground?
So, if those people could say that again,
that would be great.
Say that again?
(students murmur)
You want to put it on the ground.
And, I think I heard
a dissenting voice in the crowd.
Someone that said something else?
- [Student] I did.
- Oh, okay.
- [Student] I said that if
you increase the height,
it's still possible to
have it above the ground
because you would have two
supports on either side,
technically, you'd be
able to go back and forth.
(students murmur)
- [Teacher] They haven't
brought in the supports
for this herculean innovation.
That's right.
I mean, I don't think it
really is going to affect
the design structure, so...
- Whether it's on the ground or...
- [Teacher] I'll just pull that down.
That's fine.
(students murmur)
Yeah, I don't think that's
going to make a difference.
That might make it easier for the person
to step off the track,
too, when they're done.
You know, this guy's
going to get really tired.
There's no friction, so
he won't have to step off
on the nice safe track.
- But, you notice how as
long as the track is longer
he doesn't go back up as
high, so if you have...
(students murmur)
- [Teacher] Alright.
One at a time.
I like this.
Someone said something.
Christina said something,
and I think Karuna wanted to add to that.
- He goes just as high...
(student mumbles)
like there's no change because
there's no friction. So...
- Yeah, then he doesn't go up to the top.
(animated conversation)
(students murmur)
- [Teacher] I could put
the pie chart in, sure.
- And, can you start him at the top?
(students murmur)
- [Teacher] Alright.
So, I'm going to put the pie chart in
and then you want me to,
he's going to climb up the ladder, right?
There's like, a pretend ladder here.
And then, how's that?
- Yeah.
- [Teacher] Okay.
Now, I noticed when I did
that, something happened.
- The pie chart.
(students murmur)
- Oh, yeah.
Why?
(students murmur)
Sounds like a height
there that's increasing,
reference point is greater, I like that.
Okay, I'm going to let him go.
(students murmur)
I don't know if I can do that, actually,
but I will try.
Yeah, we can play around with it.
- [Student] Make the sides taller,
then he'll have a greater
distance to travel
and it'll actually be more.
- [Teacher] I don't know if I can,
yeah, I don't think I can do that.
I don't think it'll,
it only allows me to click
on the blue dots there.
- You have to add track to do that.
(students murmur)
- You want me to pull
those off to the side?
Okay.
(students murmur)
So, you made a little
bit different half-pipe.
(students exclaim)
Oh, no!
Alright.
So, you don't want to,
look there's some thermal energy.
What's going on with that?
(students murmur)
Okay.
That might've happened.
But why do I now see red in the pie chart?
(students murmur)
Yeah.
There's a force that will allow
for the energy to transfer.
Good.
Let's get him back on that half-pipe and
you know guys,
I don't think that it makes
much of a difference in the
design or engineering of this, whether
we make the bottom hit
the ground or have it up.
So, I don't really think that is going to
make much of a difference.
But, we do need to collect some data, and
start with this proposal, so...
Where did we leave off?
I think there was something that we were
looking to collect there.
- [Student] Height.
- Okay, good.
Let's continue with that, please.
- Well, measuring tape.
- Oooh!
There is a measuring tape.
I don't even see these things.
Measuring tape, oh.
It even says fet, okay good.
So, how's that look?
- No, no!
- [Teacher] Well, what do
you want me to do with it?
(animated conversation)
Going to the ground.
(students murmur)
That's not the ground?
- From the reference point.
- [Teacher] Oh, alright.
I'm right on the reference point!
- Go up a little.
(students murmur)
- [Teacher] So, what do
you want me to measure?
(animated conversation)
Well, where am I going to measure?
From what to what?
- The reference point
to the highest point.
- [Teacher] Okay.
I think the highest
point would probably be
the center of him,
but they do have that
nice, little red dot.
Can we just agree that we're
going to go with the red dot?
- Yes.
- [Teacher] Yeah.
Why don't we go there?
- It can't be diagonal.
- [Teacher] Okay.
(students murmur)
Is that good?
- Yeah.
(students murmur)
- [Teacher] Yes.
Shut the lights off for this measure.
Okay.
(students murmur)
Now, this measuring tape is
a little tricky to work with.
I wonder if there's any easier way for me
to get this.
(students murmur)
Oh.
Oh, that's pretty neat.
I suppose I could use a measuring tape or
I actually have that,
so maybe that will help make it
a little bit easier, if
it could speed things up.
So, what do we want to say for the height?
- Seven.
(students murmur)
- I don't know if I'd say seven.
So, we all agree it's somewhere
between six and eight, yes?
- Yes.
I'd say 7.2.
- And it does go over the
seven a little bit, so
height equals seven point...
(students murmur)
Two.
Four.
Six.
Zero.
42.
(students laugh)
You tell me or it's going to go forever!
65.
Let's start over again.
Seven.
(animated conversation)
I don't think it goes to the half mark.
7.1?
(students murmur)
Maybe we need a show of hands on this?
Who believes it's 7?
Who believes it's 7 meters?
No one's raising their hands, that's good.
How about 7.1?
7.1 meters?
Alright.
I got one person there.
Now, I'm looking at this
from an angle, right?
And anytime you want to make a measure,
you do want to have your eyes
right above what you're measuring
and obviously...
(teacher mumbles)
I'm just going to move over here,
just so I can get,
a little bit better.
And then what else can I do
to try to really measure this well?
- [Student] Pause it.
- Yeah.
I think I'm going to pause the animation.
Now, if I was making
an actual measurement,
I'd make sure my eyes were
perpendicular to whatever
I was measuring.
What do we say about, oh, that's good.
What do we say about these measures
that we make in science?
- [Student] They should be,
you're only as good as your measures.
- [Teacher] Yeah.
You're only as good as your measures.
What does that mean?
Kristen?
- It means that if your
measures are not precise
and consistent, then
everything else won't be
precise and consistent.
- [Teacher] Can someone
elaborate on that a little bit?
Or do you want to add to that?
- No, someone else can elaborate on it.
- [Teacher] Okay.
Are you sure?
I can give you a little more...
- No.
(Kristen murmurs)
- [Teacher] Okay.
Let's see.
Who haven't I called on at all today
because I want to make sure I get everyone.
(students murmur)
- You haven't called on Jill.
(students laugh)
(Jill mumbles)
- [Teacher] Alright.
I'm sure she doesn't mind
repeating it for you.
(Kristen mumbles)
I think you said, you're only
as good as your measures.
(Kristen mumbles)
- Because if your measures aren't precise,
then all your other work
that you're using the measures for...
(Jill mumbles)
Yeah, if you measure
something for speed...
(Jill mumbles)
It would be wrong.
- [Teacher] Why?
- Well no, if you...
- [Teacher] It could be, you're right.
If you make some poor measures,
and then you go to graph it.
- No.
If you take distance and then
multiply it by time, then
speed would be wrong.
Like, if you had the wrong distance,
then speed would be wrong,
and then making it after that,
your graph would be wrong.
- [Teacher] Well, it would be wrong,
right from the perspective, you said,
distance times time,
and speed is distance divided by time.
Did everyone hear that?
- Yeah.
- [Teacher] That's okay, though.
You're saying,
we don't want to get
off the main idea here.
If you're getting these distances wrong
and then you're going to graph,
your slope is going to be incorrect, yes?
So, remember in science, we collect data.
From that data, we put
it in a nice data table
to organize it and then we look at trends
and patterns, graph it,
look at trends and patterns.
So, if everything starts
from our measures,
those next steps aren't
going to be correct.