- [Teacher] Today we're gonna work
on soccer special olympic skills, alright?
We've done this a couple of times before.
Inside we did it on the gym floor
and the ball moved real fast.
It'll be a lot easier out
here today on the grass, ok?
You guys are gonna be awesome,
we'll have a good time.
First thing we're gonna do is dribbling.
When you dribble, I want you to use
the inside of your foot, right here.
Inside of your feet, keep the
ball real close to your feet
and dribble.
When I say go, you're gonna start
right here at the start line.
And you'll dribble,
stay in between these yellow cones,
all the way down to the finish line
where this other orange
marker is, alright?
Once you get here, put your
foot on top of the ball
and stop the ball.
And that's when I'll
stop the clock, alright?
That'll be it, you just go from the start
to finish then stop right down there.
First time you do it,
you may have to walk and go slow.
Then we'll do it again,
and you can probably
get a little bit faster
the second time.
Alright, Taylor you wanna go first?
- [Taylor] Yeah.
- [Teacher] Show us how it's done?
Alright, let's go.
Wait till I say go,
and then you'll be ready to roll, alright?
On your mark, get set,
go!
Doin' good, keepin that ball close.
Staying between the cones.
Good soft touches.
And stop it.
Awesome, good job.
14 seconds.
- [Taylor] Yeah.
- [Teacher] And next time you
dribble a little bit faster
and you'd do even better.
- [Taylor] Yeah!
- [Teacher] Alright, good job.
Colin, you wanna go second?
Yeah, come on.
We'll start right here by the start line,
right behind the start line.
You know what you're gonna do?
When I say go, what are you gonna do?
- [Colin] Um.
- [Teacher] Whatcha gonna do when I say go?
- [Colin] I'll just, start.
- [Teacher] Yeah you're gonna dribble
to that finish line, right?
When you get there,
stop it with your foot.
Stop the ball with your foot, ok?
You ready?
On your mark, get set, go!
Good, Colin.
Keep on dribbling it.
Inside the feet.
Good job.
Almost there.
Get across the line and stop it.
Good job.
Good job, Colin.
Faith, you ready?
Yeah, let's do that.
Can you get it up that hill?
You got it, Jessie?
Alright.
(grunting) You gotta be strong to do this.
Jessie's my helper, my assistant.
Yeah, go Faith.
Alright, Faith, you ready?
Let's get that ball in there.
Is that good?
That feel good, doesn't hurt?
He did?
Alright, y'all ready?
You ready Faith?
You ready to burn it up?
On your mark, get set, go!
There she goes.
Cross that line.
Stop.
Whoo!
- [Faith] Yeah!
- [Teacher] How'd you do that?
Magic, good job Faith.
Alright.
Thank you, Jessie.
Alright, now it's your turn, Jessie.
See how fast you can do it.
I'll push Faith back
so you can get in there
and get ready.
Alright?
Was that fun?
You're doing a good job.
Alright Jessie, you know what to do?
- [Jessie] Yup.
- [Teacher] Go right there.
Alright, on your mark,
get set, go!
Go, go, go.
Jessie's flyin'.
Get there and stop it.
Get over the line, boom.
8.8
That's awesome.
Good job.
Alright, Taylor come on.
Let's go one more time.
And go even faster this time.
- [Taylor] Yeah!
- [Teacher] Yeah.
The speed of light.
Are you ready?
On your mark, get set, go!
Oh, she's flyin'.
Keep it inside the cones, whoah.
Whoo!
So much faster, how'd you do that
so much faster?
That's five seconds faster.
That's awesome!
Colin, come on.
You ready?
Yup.
Alright.
You know what you're doing, right?
Dribble down there and stop.
She's over there.
You ready?
Alright Colin, on your mark.
She's just sittin down right now.
On your mark, get set, go.
Good job.
You're doin' good, Colin, keep going.
See if you can get across that line
and stop it.
Bottom of your foot, boom.
Good job.
Hey, that was faster than last time.
Alright, Faith, you're up!
Faith's turn.
Faith is excited, I can tell.
Turn a little bit more
just so I can get the head straight ahead.
(mumbling) There you go, just like that.
Alright, Faith.
You let me know if you're ready?
Is that good, Faith?
Alright.
On your mark, get set, go!
Uh-oh we're stuck in the grass.
Must be in a little hole there.
There you go.
(Faith giggling excitedly)
- [Teacher] Faster than last time.
Good job, Faith.
How'd you do that?
How did you do it?
Good job.
Alright Jessie, you get back.
Get ready to go.
I'll push Faith back.
Good job Faith.
Awesome.
- [Faith] I'm doing great today, huh?
- [Teacher] You're doing great.
Doing great.
Alright.
Here you go, Jessie.
Last one, then we'll go to shooting.
On your mark, get set, go!
Fast as you can go.
He's flyin'.
Good job.
Gimme five on that.
Alright, y'all ready to
move to the shooting?
Colin, come on over.
You wanna push Faith over, Jessie?
I'ma let Faith go first on this one.
Ok?
Faith, you're gonna go
first on this one, ok?
Alright guys, the way this one works,
we're gonna be shooting on that goal.
Everytime you make a
goal, you get ten points.
You guys are gonna get
a lot of points today.
Now when I say go, shoot
five balls, alright?
When I say go, I'll put a ball right here,
and you'll start at this line, you run up,
shoot in the goal.
Then you'll come back to this line,
i'll put another ball down.
You run up, shoot it in the goal, ok?
Kick it in the goal.
That's right, Taylor.
Faith is gonna go first.
Are you ready?
On your mark, get set, go.
Come all the way up to
get the ball, Jessie.
Alright, throw it in there, Faith.
Oh yeah, that's ten points.
Goin in, goin in. Whoo!
Good job.
Alright, that's good.
Go Faith, go Faith.
Ooh, you're throwing them hard today.
Three more.
You must've had a big old breakfast.
You got lots of energy today.
Go, go, go, three in the goal.
Two more.
Good job Faith, throw it hard.
Uh-oh that one hit a bump,
went sideways.
Last one.
Throw it hard, hard, hard, hard.
Yeah, good job.
That one's in the net.
Good job, Faith.
Good job.
Jessie, you ready?
I'ma let you blast the net.
That's fine like that.
Alright,
don't break my goal.
Don't kick them so hard
you break the net, alright?
Are you ready?
On your mark, get set, go.
Fire that thing in there, boom.
Good one.
Boom, two good ones.
Boom, three.
You're bombin' em.
Four.
Last one.
Five for five, awesome.
Alright, get those balls.
Who wants to go next?
Taylor, I knew it was gonna be you.
Think you can make all five, Taylor?
Do you think you can make all five of 'em?
- [Taylor] Yeah!
- [Teacher] I do too.
Whoops, score a backwards goal.
Alright, thank you Jessie.
Alright, Taylor.
Here's the challenge, you ready?
On your mark, get set, go.
Boom, that's one.
Number two!
In the goal.
Number three.
Another goal.
Number four.
What in the world?
Number five.
Woo! Awesome, good job.
Alright Taylor, you can get those?
Taylor, you decide not to get 'em?
Silly?
Thank you.
Alright, Colin.
It is your turn.
Big Colin.
See if you can kick 'em all in.
Are you ready?
On your mark.
Start right there on that line.
Soon as I put the ball
down you're ready to go.
Mark, set, go!
Boom, good kick.
Back to that line.
Next one, shoot it in.
Good shot.
Colin's a lefty.
Alright, shoot it in, next one.
Whoo, good one.
Two more.
Number four, in the goal.
Good job, Colin.
Last one, let's do it.
Whoo, good job.
Alright, lets go one more time.
Then we'll move to the dribbling,
I mean the run and kick.
Ok, so Faith's up first, come on.
We're gonna do this one more time.
Practice it one more time.
Yeah, Thursday.
Y'all goin'?
Y'all better be.
Alright, you ready?
Go!
Alright, Faith.
See if you can score
some more goals.
There's a good one.
That one's in the net.
Good job.
Alright.
All the way up and get it.
And shoot it in, Faith.
Oh yeah.
It's in, good shot.
Come on.
Strong as you can,
all that muscle you've
been workin' on the arms.
There you go, good job.
You made that one easily.
Two more.
Remember, all that muscle
you've been working on
on your arms.
Shoot it there.
Look at you!
You've been hidin that strength from me.
How'd you do that?
Alright, last one.
Shoot it in.
Guess all that exercise is payin' off.
Good job, Faith.
Good job, how'd you do that?
It's magic.
Jessie, you're up.
I'll get these, you get ready.
Alright Jessie, you ready?
Big man?
On your mark, get set, go!
Fire it in there.
Poof, power!
Next one, fire it in there.
You got the hardest shot, that's for sure.
Go!
Shoot like the guys on my team.
Go.
Boom!
Last one.
Good job.
Who's up now, Taylor?
And then Colin, alright.
Whew!
Got me runnin all over.
Alright, Taylor's turn.
On your mark--
Can she make five in a row again?
- [Taylor] Alright.
- [Teacher] I bet you can!
You little athlete.
On your mark, get set, go.
No, I messed up.
Go.
Holy cow, you almost kicked that one over.
How'd you get that so high?
Doing the chip shots.
Two for two.
Uh-oh.
Scoopin it.
Three for three.
Better be careful you
don't go over the goal.
You might kick a football field goal.
There you go, four for four.
Last one.
Ooh, good job.
Awesome, you help me
get the balls this time?
- [Taylor] Yeah.
- [Teacher] Thank you.
Alright Colin.
That was good, Taylor.
That was incredible.
Colin's turn
to shoot 'em again.
Alright, thank you Taylor.
- [Taylor] You're welcome.
- [Teacher] Alright Colin, you ready?
Mark, get set, go!
Shoot it in there.
Whoo, good left foot.
Alright, back up.
Go.
Good job.
Alright, number three, back on up.
Alright, go.
Good job, Colin.
Back up.
Number four.
Awesome, last one.
Good job, buddy, that was awesome.
Alright, y'all ready to
move to the next one?
Let's do it.
Ok, that sounds good.
Alright let's head this
way to the run and kick.
This is the one that's kinda tricky.
Y'all remember this one?
You gotta know which direction to go in.
Four balls going in a circle.
Is Jessie going first?
Alright.
Alright, last one.
Last event.
You guys remember this one, right?
Run and kick, you're
gonna start. (laughing)
Start right here in the middle, alright?
Arrows going to number one first.
When I say go, I start the clock.
Fast as you can run up to this ball.
Just pass it through those two cones.
Then we're gonna go this way
following the arrows to number two.
Same thing, pass it through those cones.
Number three, pass it through these cones.
Then to number four, pass
it through those cones.
And as soon as you kick
that ball, the clock stops.
Alright?
Remember, you don't have to
hit it real hard on these.
Just kick it easy, nice and soft
and aim it between those cones.
Jessie, you're the first one up.
You ready?
Start on that arrow in the
middle and I'll say go.
On your mark, get set, go.
Boom, alright.
Go faster if you can.
I know you can go faster than that.
There you go.
Alright.
13 seconds, that was flying.
You wanna get that one
right there, Jessie?
Taylor, can you get that ball?
Colin, you get that ball right there?
We're gonna set 'em up and go again.
Alright, Taylor.
You wanna go next?
Ok.
Yeah, you can do that if you want.
That'd be great.
Thank you.
Colin, you ready to go after Taylor?
Alright Taylor, are you ready?
- [Taylor] Ready.
- [Teacher] On your mark, get set, go!
Boom, perfect.
Beautiful.
Awesome.
Terrific.
13 seconds, you were flying.
Good job.
Get that ball for me?
Good job, Taylor.
Aim it right in there,
nice and soft.
Thank you for getting that ball, Colin.
I don't know, are you?
- [Colin] Is it my turn?