- [Teacher] Most friends have
finished their first trials.
I wanted to talk real
quick about what's happened
on your first trial.
Who wants to share
what happened on your first three trials?
And I want to know
was it something that you
predicted would happen?
Cody?
- [Cody] At first we kinda got a little,
it kind of got a little complicated.
Since you came around
it fixed it a little.
- [Teacher] Why was it complicated,
cause the rest of the group
didn't see your experiment.
Why was it complicated?
- [Cody] Because it keep turning
and the wax paper was--
- [Teacher] What kept turning?
- [Cody] The car
- [Teacher] Your car kept turning?
- [Cody] Yeah and the wax paper
kept coming off and turning it.
So it was a little complicated.
- [Teacher] So after you got it fixed,
and after I helped you
then what did you find out?
- [Cody] That it was kind of easy to do.
- [Teacher] So did your measurement,
did that end up being what you
predicted it was going to be?
When it closed did you think
the car was going to travel
that far or did you think it was gonna
go a shorter distance?
- [Cody] We thought it was gonna--
I thought it was gonna go very far.
Because that's a little bit slicker.
- [Teacher] Because that it's slippery.
Well I was listening to another
group talk about something,
I think it was at Bhavana's group,
raise your hand if you're
in Bhavana's group.
And really deep had
really good observation.
Because they were thinking that
it was gonna go a little bit farther too.
But you told me something
about the surface
that we were testing on.
- [Girl] I said the...
the wax paper was a little bit smooth
and the carpet was a little bit rough.
- [Teacher] So do you guys agree that
the wax paper being smooth
and the carpet that we're
testing on being rough,
if you agree that that has anything to do
with how far the car's going to travel,
give me a thumb's up.
I think that makes a difference.
Lucy, why do you think
it makes a difference?
- [Lucy] The carpet, there's a
feel of bumps if you could feel it,
and the wax paper is slippery.
So that's how it makes the difference
cause slippery kind of makes stuff fast,
like if they have wheels or something,
it makes stuff fast.
- [Teacher] That's true.
So as we get ready for our next test,
you probably only will have
time to do maybe one trial.
But I want you to predict,
now that you've kind of
explored the wax paper
and you know how far the car will travel,
looking at your information,
your measurements,
I want you to talk with your group about
how far you think the car
will go on the bumpy surface.
And we're choosing to use
the shelf liner today.
The black shelf liner in your tub.
Do you think the car's going to go farther
or a shorter distance
than what you measured
on your first trial?
We may only get through one trial.
And that is okay.
Alright but I want you to talk about it
with your groups first and then start.
So Lawson what are you gonna do first
before you test?
- [Lawson] Get in a group meeting
and sit down and meet
- [Teacher] Yeah and talk
about your predictions first.
That's what good scientists do.
They're always making
really good predictions
about what they've observed.
Alright. Go.
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] I'm setting the timer.
- [Lawson] I think it will go really bumpy,
well not really bumpy but a little bumpy.
And it might go just a
little less than the smooth.
- [Girl] I think that it will go
slower because the surface
it's really bumpy and one time
I went on this bumpy slide
and I did not go down very quickly.
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Don't worry about
recording the information
right now but we'll
record in a little bit.
- [Voiceover 1] I think they're
gonna go a little bit far.
- [Voiceover 2] I bet slower.
- [Boy] Hey, you can't pick off of me!
- [Girl] I think that it's gonna
go farther and faster.
- [Girl in Glasses] I think it's gonna
go a little bit farther
and a little bit faster.
- [Boy] I think it's gonna
go a little bit slower.
- [Girl in white] I think it's
kind of gonna go,
since it's bumpy it's gonna slow it down.
- [Boy in blue] I think it was gonna go farther.
- [Voiceover] Group meeting's over!
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] So you think it's gonna go faster
than it did on the wax paper?
- [Mary] No I think it's going
a little bit slower
but still a little fast, like medium.
- [Teacher] So you don't think
it's gonna change that much,
why do you think that?
- [Mary] Cause it doesn't feel too too bumpy.
- [Teacher] It doesn't feel too too bumpy,
she's making a really good observation.
What do you think Jaylin?
- [Jaylin] My predict is
when you put the car on it
it's gonna kinda go medium,
it might go a little bit
slower and a little bit fast,
and then when it gets to the
carpet it's gonna go slower
and then it's gonna turn.
- [Teacher] It's gonna go a lot slower
and then it's going to turn?
- [Mary] I think like that fast.
- [Teacher] Okay.
- [Mary] Not too fast, not as
fast as the wax paper
- [Teacher] Go ahead and test
but let's think about your setup here.
Before you move this,
let's look at your setup.
As the car rolls, what would happen maybe
if it stays in motion until
it gets to that green rug?
What might happen?
- [Olivia] It might get stopped.
- [Teacher] Remember the
car's going to continue
to move until something makes it stop.
So what might you want
to do with your ramp?
- [Mary] We might want it to
be here so it will go straighter?
- [Olivia] But it might bump
into the black box.
- [Teacher] It may, well you
know the rug is going to--
- [Mary] I don't mean there, but I mean...
- [Jaylin] I know what we could do,
we could do it this way so it won't crash.
- [Teacher] Well you
could either move it over
just a little bit so that
it has nothing in its way.
- [Olivia] Javier could you go get us some tape?
- [Teacher] It may not even need tape
it might cling to it without the tape.
Try it and see.
- [Olivia] Let's try it without some.
- [Mary] Yeah it doesn't even need tape.
- [Teacher] Who's the task manager here?
- [Girl] Me
- [Teacher] Look out he's
doing the first test.
- [Girl] I think it should be Jaylin.
- [Teacher] Okay, Jaylin
now do you test sideways,
we talked about this yesterday
when you wouldn't agree.
And you guys talked about
that if some friends tested sideways
and some friends teted behind the ramp
that it may make a difference.
Then you guys said you
wanted to keep it the same.
- [Girl] Javier can
you move out of the way?
- [Jaylin] You ready?
- [Teacher] Now wait a
minute, wait a minute.
Cause I bet you probably got his on tape.
Jaylin show me how you did that again,
go get the car.
Watch what he did with his popsicle stick.
Cause I hadn't seen that before.
Do it just like you did the first time.
What did he do with his popsicle stick?
- [Girls] He flipped it down
- [Teacher] Do you think
that makes a difference
in your test if he flips
it down or raises it up?
Why might it make a difference Olivia?
- [Olivia] Because it might, when you put it down
you're putting it down fast and I bet
it makes the car go a little bit faster.
And it gives it some force.
- [Teacher] Did it give it more force?
So, Jaylin is this surface
the same as this surface?
Is this the same as this?
- [Jaylin] Yes, I think
- [Teacher] Is this popsicle stick
the same as this here?
- [Jaylin] No.
- [Teacher] So if you test the car on this and this
is that going to be the same as
testing it on something bumpy?
- [Jaylin] No.
- [Teacher] So what do you need to
do with the popsicle stick?
- [Jaylin] Raise it up.
- [Teacher] You might want
to raise it up next time.
Alright? Try it again.
I'll come back and see
if you guys are ready.
- [Kids] One, two, and go!
- [Mary] Wow that was great!
- [Voiceover] Now let's start measuring
- [Voiceover] Now we're
gonna start measuring.
- [Jaylin] Okay
(Background Chatter)
- [Voiceover] Okay, one, two...
- [Girl] No, Tessa's gotta do that.
- [Voiceover] One, two three ready.
- [Lucy] Oh my gosh we were right.
(Background Chatter)
(Laughter)
- [Boy in plaid] Our first prediction is
one, two, three, four,
five, six, seven, eight!
(Laughter)
- [Voiceover 1] It's eight!
- [Voiceover 2] Oh my gosh!
- [Voiceover 3] Why's it eight?
(Background Chatter)
- [Voiceover 1] And ours
keeps getting a mess up!
- [Voiceover 2] I predicted eight, too, see?
- [Voiceover 3] I predicted seven mostly.
- [Boy in plaid] We got eight cubes on this one
- [Teacher] Eight cubes, really?
Before we clean up I would
like for you to have a quick
group meeting about what you learned
about the different surfaces so far.
Quickly sit down with your group
and have a quick group meeting.
I'm gonna come around and be watching.
Quick, quick, quick!
It's almost time for us to go.
- [Voiceover] About what you learned?
- [Teacher] What you learned today
about the wax paper and the bumpy surface
that you used, the shelf liner.
What did you learn from what you tested?
- [Girl] I learned that the
bumpy surface made it go,
that bumpy makes things go slower
and that smooth makes things go faster.
- [Teacher] How do you know that?
- [Girl] Because when we use the
smooth it went further
- [Teacher] How far did it go?
- [Girl] It went about--
- [Other kids] eight cubes.
- [Girl] No
- [Boy in plaid] I think
it actually went seven.
I don't know we didn't
put the lines behind it.
- [Girl] 36 about further than this
because it went 36 or so and
this only went eight cubes.
So that makes it the point
where bumpy is slower.
- [Teacher] So 35 on the wax
and only eight on the bumpy?
The shelf liner?
- [Boy in plaid] I think it
was seven on the bumpy.
- [Teacher] Big difference isn't it?
Is that what you predicted?
- [Lawson] No I didn't predict eight
- [Voiceover] I predicted 16
- [Lawson] No I didn't predict on the bumpy,
but I predicted...
I predicted one
and I got the right
answer for it on smooth.
- [Teacher] Alright. Well
you guys have two more
trials to do so we'll see
if your numbers are close
when you use trial two and three.
Alright? Go ahead and get cleaned up.
- [Voiceover] We already
cleaned most of them first
- [Teacher] Well no you need
to clean all your things up
everything back in your tub.
You can go ahead and record your data
but we're gonna get cleaned up.
Go ahead and get cleaned up.
- [Olivia] Alright push the red button,
you can push the red button.
Mary, come over here.
Tell us what you learned.
- [Javier] Okay Mary, come over here.
- [Olivia] I learned that different surfaces
can make something different,
whatever you're testing
make it go fast and slow.
-[Javier] Mary what did you learn?
- [Mary] I learned mostly the same thing
except when we did that,
you know how this is less
bumpy than the carpet?
It makes this go faster than the carpet,
which makes a difference.
- [Javier] Yeah. Jaylin what did you learn?
- [Jaylin] I learned if you put the car on this
it's gonna go a little bit faster.
If you put it on this it's gonna go
a little bit almost fast.
And it's gonna stop and go slower
and that's why it went right there.
- [Javier] Okay does
anybody have anything else?
- [Olivia] Javier what did you learn?
- [Javier] Well I learned that
if it's smoother it's quicker.
But if it's a little bumpy, it's slower.
That's it.
- [Olivia] Alright everyone put
your things in the bucket.
(Background Chatter)