- That's what I want
you to do to prove to me
that you understand that
beyond just telling me what,
you know, maybe the book would say.
Beyond just a definition, right?
If you're going down the right path here
and you know what that is,
I see you're making a
nice Venn diagram here,
comparing and contrasting, that's great.
What I want you to do
is on this sheet here,
cause this is what you're
going to need to present
to the class in a couple minutes.
Put down these thoughts,
these words that you've got.
You can even draw your
Venn diagram on here.
But, explain what that means.
What does that mean, bubbles
floating inside the lagoon?
What does that mean?
It's escaping off the top.
When we think of matter,
what do we actually think of in our heads?
Conceptually we're thinking
of a chunk of matter,
a beaker of liquid, so there's
some space and what else?
(students chattering)
And what?
So matter has mass and volume.
What's matter made up of?
(students chattering)
Okay. Atoms, molecules.
If it helps you, you can decide
okay let's think of
this in terms of water.
Just so it's a known right?
Okay, good. Yeah that's
a good way to do that.
So, draw some pictures.
When you say it's escaping off the top,
what does that look like?
Okay, so try to get it into some visuals.
- [girl student] Okay.
- I'll come back.
(students chattering)
- Matter, like I don't really understand.
- [Teacher] The definition of heat?
- Yeah.
- [Teacher] Okay, so what is heat?
(student's chatter drowning out boy)
- [Teacher] It's what?
(students chattering)
- Heat is like the transferring of energy
from a warmer thing to
a colder thing, right?
- [Teacher] So you want to
separate what something is
from how it behaves?
So you're saying heat
is the transfer of energy.
Transfer is how it behaves, right?
What is it?
- [girl student] It's just energy.
- It's energy, right?
So heat is a form of energy,
and you're absolutely
right. It can move around
in the environment, between
systems, in and out of the system
(inaudible).
So let's say you've got a beaker of water
sitting on the counter and it's hot, right?
It's sitting in a cold room.
What do you expect to happen?
What will happen to the temperature
of the water, for example?
- It will (inaudible).
- Okay, so the water will get colder
and the air right around
the beaker will get warmer
til they level out?
- Yeah.
- [Teacher] Okay, equilibrium, good.
So, you understand that heat is energy.
And you understand that it can move around.
So the question here is
how does adding heat energy,
for example, matter cause changes
to temperature and changes of state?
So not that it does, but how?
So, what you need to do
is think about your ideas
about matter. What is matter?
- Something with a mass or volume?
- [Teacher] Occupies
space, has mass or volume. You know.
You just said it.
- Okay.
- [Teacher] Yeah, see you know.
Okay, matter has volume,
it takes up space, right?
And it also has what?
- [Student] Mass.
The property of mass.
Do you guys have any kind of
a conceptual model of matter,
like if you think of it...
Obviously this is matter right,
but if you zoom in on that is there a way
that you think about what matter is?
Do you guys think of matter as being
made up of smaller things?
- [students] Yes.
- Okay, atoms, molecules.
What would happen if you had one atom
and you add some energy to it?
(students chattering)
- Remember this isn't rights or wrongs,
this is what are you thinking right now
so that you can make sense of this.
So what if I have two atoms
and I add more energy to them?
What if I have hundreds of atoms
and I make them all move faster?
(students chattering)
Well, I mean that's what I'm asking you guys
to think about as best you can.
How would that occur?
- We said if the
molecules have more energy
and they move faster then that leads to...
- And they get warmer.
Oh, that's the same thing
as adding more energy right?
- Then they move faster and that
leads to changes from liquid.
- [Teacher] I would say add some pictures.
I think you guys are thinking
some good thoughts here
about the structure of
matter, what it's made of.
So why don't you draw me some pictures
of what that would look like
in, say something that is changing state.
Maybe take a chunk of something solid
and then draw what you guys see,
as being a series of steps,
getting it from here to here.
So start with a lump
of solid matter, okay something like that.
Take it all the way to a gas.
- [Students] Okay.
- How do you see that matter.
- Okay, alright, let me give you guys
a couple minutes to do that.
- Start with an atom,
and build like a box...
- [Teacher] So folks, I want to take
a couple more minutes
and then have you guys share
your thoughts with each other.
(students chattering)
- [Teacher] Theorizing is good.
Why don't you draw me some pictures
of what might be happening here?
Yep? Did I take your pencil?
I'm sorry (laughter).
Okay we have a pencil thief.
So, you're saying there's
some specific temperature
in which all phases can
exist at the same time?
Water would be evaporating,
ice would be melting,
and vapor would be condensing.
So, I just want you to
tell me a little bit more
about your theory.
How would that work in the environment
in terms of the physical conditions
that the ice and the water
and the vapor would be under?
Yesterday, we talked about
some things that affect phase,
what were they?
What was one thing that we said affects
what phase of matter something is in?
Okay, temperature. Anything else?
- [Male student] Pressure.
- Pressure maybe so is there a way
that you can describe to
me in terms of pressure
and temperature, and the matter
itself, how that would work?
Okay, you may need to
mentally zoom in on matter.
What is it, what is ice,
what is water, what is gas?
If you zoom in and we look
at it beyond just a chunk,
what do we see on the "inside"?
What's it made up of
at a very small level?
(students chattering)
Does everybody here see
matter as a collection
of atoms or molecules?
Like you can visualize that?
So bring that in here.
If you do that then
show me how your theory
would apply to that.
Try.
Okay?
- [Male student] Okay.
How's that sound?
Okay a couple more minutes.
(students chattering)
Seems like you guys have gotten
your thoughts wrapped around this,
and you're working on presenting it?
Okay.
(students chattering)
- [Student] How am I supposed to do this?
- Oh god, I can't draw cups.
- [Teacher] Remember you
have to explain to everyone
what you're drawing's showing,
so it doesn't have to be perfect.
- Oh, okay.
- Don't worry about perfection.
You're gonna get to stand up there
and say this is what I drew.
And they just have to believe you.
- [Student] Okay, that's
how bad it's gonna be.
- [Female student] Okay,
so there's like the water.
- [Female student] I think
I have the difference
between the molecules.
(students chattering)
- Okay, so that shows that,
that's gas and liquid.
(students chattering)
- What is the big red arrow?
- [Female student] It's like
going up out of the liquid--
- What's it?
- [Female student] The molecules.
- Okay, molecules.
- [Female student] Yeah, that's
what this is supposed to be.
- So the only thing I
would like for you guys
to add to your explanation here
is something about why, like why or how.
What are the factors in
the physical environment
that are allowing or
not allowing the things
that you're drawing to happen?
(students chattering)
That's up to you, what
you think is making...
I think that's quite good actually.
That explains it to me really well.
The things that you think
are having an effect
on what's actually going
to or not going to happen.
- [Female student] Like
this amazing flame?
- Like that amazing flame.
So you might want to label that
or make sure that you explain that.
- [Female student] Label it F-L-A-M-E.
(students chattering)
- You've vibrated, those are
actually quite good vibrations.
- [Female student] That's our gas.
- They're awfully close together.
These are closer together
here than they are here.
Is that something that you intended?
- [Students] No.
- [Male student] There
supposed to be really spread out.
(students chattering over each other)
- It's up to you what
you're going to write.
I'm simply asking you a question
because it seems like
between liquid and gas
they got closer together.
- [Female student] We
didn't mean to do that.
I can draw more.
- What do you think?
(students chattering)
So, we've shown them closer together.
Do we want to revise this
or do you think it doesn't matter?
(students chattering)
So they could be closer together?
- [Female student] They
could be closer together
as long as they're moving more.
- Okay.
- [Female student] So I think
being like spreading out
and occupying all space available.
- So if you're thinking that,
you should include that somehow,
and it seems like then you
and Katelyn, and Ignesia's
have different ideas about this.
And that's important to acknowledge
because those are two different things
so we want to think about...
What are you doing?
Oh, you're adding to it.
So, I hear Lindsey's
saying that you thought
they'd be more spread
out, occupying more space
and I hear you guys saying the spacing
of them doesn't really matter.
So that's worth thinking about,
because that's two different
ways of looking at this.
That's two different
Anyway, we don't need
perfection right now.
We need your initial thoughts,
but somewhere I'd record that discrepancy.
I would record here that you're still
thinking about that issue.
You think one thing,
you guys think another.
That's important.
So you guys, I think I'd
like to have groups...
Don't worry if you're not totally done.
I would just like groups
to kind of explain
what they've got so far.
And we're going to go in numerical order.
So I am going to ask everybody
to come back to the tables though,
and give your poster to one group member.
Let's do that now.
Don't worry if it's incomplete.
This is a work in progress.
Come on back to the tables.
Don't worry if it's not
finished. You get to explain it.
And we're gonna keep these
around so you can add to them.
Come on back to the tables.
- I count two.
- Alright, so group one, I'm
gonna have you guys come on up
and hang up your poster.
You guys let's load
towards the front of the room
so that we're all closer.
You don't need all your stuff,
just come on up and sit a little closer.
Let's squeeze in, in all these front tables.
(students chattering)
Yeah, you guys are gonna
explain a little bit to us
of what you're thinking was.
So, everybody come on
up as close as you can.
Let's squeeze in at these tables.
Let's get a couple people here,
let's get a couple people here.
Pull a chair on up.
(students chattering)
- [Teacher] Come on up.
Somebody come sit here, somebody sit here.
So, we've only got a
little bit of time left
and I want every group to have a chance
to tell us a little bit
about their thoughts.
You guys may, on your pre-think
sheets, take some notes.
Remember this isn't about right or wrong.
This is about how do
we think we understand
this system right now.
And this is all leading
towards trying to understand it
more thoroughly and better and correctly
by the end of the unit.
So, their question, the first one
is how does adding heat
energy to a sample of matter
cause changes of temperature
and changes of state?
So, you guys tell us a little
bit about your thinking here?
- Okay, so we were thinking that
something about adding heat
would have to do with the boiling point
and the freezing point.
And we were also just
listing facts that we knew
that would probably help us
determine about our question.
We were thinking about specific heat.
The equation for specific heat.
Also, we said based on the
specific heat of the substance,
an amount of energy will
raise the temperature
by a certain amount, and we
thought that was important.
- And it varies for the substance
because each substance
is like a difference
between the heat.
So if you add one it will raise one gram
of a different substance
by a certain degree,
and then a different substance
by a different amount.
- And we also thought about
how solid, liquid, and gas,
that it has to do with
the change of space.
- And the solid, they're
like locked in place
but they're still vibrating a little bit.
Then, if you add more energy
we think it goes to a liquid,
where there's more freedom of movement,
but they're still sort of contained,
and then in a gas.
- And in a gas the molecules
will be occupying all space
available and moving faster.
And they're not like moving
in a certain direction.
- What questions do
you guys have for them,
or comments about what they're thinking?
- Why would different materials
have different specific heats?
- You don't have to know the answer.
Does anyone have thoughts on that?
Guesses?
Maybe they're different what?
- [Male student] Different
types of material,
I mean substance.
(students mumbling)
(student chatter)
- So I think that maybe they
have different specific heats
because the atomic structure is different.
So they can kind of
collect heat differently.
- How does that sound
to folks, reasonable?
Is it true that atoms
bond in different ways
for different substances?
Okay, so maybe that's
something worth looking into
as we study this and see why that,
why that physical
property of specific heat,
why isn't it the same for everything?
- [Female student] And so we
were actually still thinking
in our gas drawing here, because
you can see that we drew
all the molecules, really close together
compared to the solid and liquid I guess.
And we weren't sure
whether or not in a gas
they could move freely.
And it doesn't matter
how spaced out they are
as long as they can,
they're not stuck in one
space like solids are.
They can just move wherever.
Or whether they have to be
more spaced out and so...
- [Female student] Didn't
occupy the whole space.
- Do you guys have thoughts about that?
What they're saying?
Do you guys understand the
point Katelyn's making?
How far do they have to be to be a gas?
- Well I think that that's
actually a lot like ours
because we were thinking about pressure...