(children talking over each other)
- Tyler pushed the ball.
- [Miss Henderson] Okay,
well how does that,
how does that
affect the ball?
- It makes it go faster.
And make it fall.
- [Miss Henderson] So
why is that a problem?
- Because she ran because
she, because she pushed it.
- [Miss Henderson] I know, but why is it
a problem that she pushed it?
- Because
it goes faster.
- [Miss Henderson] And
that's a problem because?
Because why?
- She didn't win.
- [Miss Henderson] Oh,
what do you mean win?
- She win the game.
- [Miss Henderson] Oh, did
you all make a game out of it?
- Uh uh, we didn't turn a game into it.
- [Miss Henderson] Okay, well
what are you doing then?
He's playing a game, what
are you doing Kylie?
- He's rolling and see, not playing a game.
Just rolling and seeing where they go.
- [Miss Henderson] Wait a minute what?
Rolling them to see what?
- How many sticks it takes.
- [Miss Henderson] So
did you push all of them
or are you all taking turns doing each one?
- Taking turns.
- [Miss Henderson] Oh, okay.
So do you think that
to find out really how far they go
everyone either needs to push them
or everyone needs to not push them?
- Not push them.
- [Miss Henderson] So is
that what you're saying,
it wouldn't be fair if she pushes hers,
but no one else pushes theirs?
Because pushing makes
it go faster you said.
Okay.
Alright so,
it makes it what?
Makes it go farther okay.
Alright, so do you wanna,
do you want,
was anybody else pushing theirs?
- [Kylie] Rebekah.
- [Miss Henderson] Okay, do
you want Rebekah and Kylie
to do theirs over again?
Alright, show them how
you and Todd did yours
so that everybody can do theirs the same.
- Now I guess I'm gonna
have to get our ball.
(children talking over each other)
- I need ball number two. We need a Captain.
- Miss Henderson, can I be the Captain?
- [Miss Henderson] We
don't need a Captain.
You're all doing what,
you're being what?
We're not being Captain's,
we're being what?
- [Todd] Scientists.
- [Miss Henderson] Scientists.
So work together.
(children talking over each other)
- [Miss Henderson] Wait,
don't pick up her ball.
She hasn't measured it yet.
- Five, six, seven, eight,
nine, 10, 11,
12, 13, 14, 15,
16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21.
21 inches that my ball went.
- [Miss Henderson] 21 sticks.
- Where is 21?
- [Miss Henderson] You looking
for it on the hundreds chart?
Are you looking for it on the calendar?
You can get up and point to it.
- [Todd] I got 18 sticks for my ball.
- [Rebekah] I can't find it anywhere.
- 18 sticks.
- I'm going to see how many sticks I got for my ball.
- [Miss Henderson] Okay, how
would you find 21 on the chart?
- I don't know.
- [Miss Henderson] Where could you start?
- By one.
- [Miss Henderson] Okay.
(counting)
(children talking over each other)
- 20,
21.
- [Miss Henderson] Oh, you found it.
Do you need more sticks honey?
- 17, yes.
- [Miss Henderson] Okay,
go ask another group,
can you borrow some sticks?
- Another ball.
(children talking over each other)
- 12,
13,
14.
So it takes half of 14.
- Because she said, "No, I'm using it."
And she, and I said I have a idea
and she said no.
- [Miss Henderson] What
was your idea John?
- I was just trying
do it on my head, like on
my back of my head then down.
- [Miss Henderson] Use
your head as a ramp?
- Uh huh.
- [Miss Henderson] And where
did you have the ball hun?
- In her pocket the whole time.
- [Miss Henderson] Why Em?
Does the ball belong
to you or to the group?
- Group.
- [Miss Henderson] So
if you're not using it,
should you let someone
else in the group use it?
Okay,
go ahead.
(children talking over each other)
- Roll it on my back.
And now roll it.
If it does it...
Right here.
No, I mean like right here.
- [Miss Henderson] Where
do you want them to,
where do you want them to start the ball?
I think is what they're asking.
- In my head,
somewhere like right here.
- [Miss Henderson] Because
a ramp starts where?
- On the top.
- [Miss Henderson] Up high.
And goes down.
So if you're using his head?
- I would lay like this.
- [Miss Henderson] Oh.
Did that work?
- Yeah.
- [Rebekah] What do we do
with it, after we do our balls?
- [Miss Henderson] Okay, you
can just keep experimenting
with the balls and the ramps
and we're gonna clean up
in just a second.
Put your name at the top
of your paper please.
- [Child] We used it on this one.
- [Miss Henderson] You're supposed to do
all four of the balls.
Ball number one, ball number two,
ball number three, ball number four.
- [Child] We would do
ball number three?
- Number one is this one.
How about number one?
- But this one.
Which number is that one?
- So get number three,
we'll have a race and we'll...
(children talking over each other)
- [Miss Henderson] So what are
you all doing with the ramp now?
- We're putting it on the chair.
And whoever gets it, whoever
gets down to the bottom first.
(children talking over each other)
- We were actually gonna roll off it.
- [Miss Henderson] Well, why
won't it roll off that ramp?
Because why?
What stops it?
- The block.
- [Miss Henderson] The
block stops it, okay.
So.
- How much does it go?
Try the little one.
Whoever is in front of me move.
- I got 10.
(children talking over each other)
- Miss Henderson,
everybody is taking our balls.
- [Miss Henderson] Okay,
guys I would like for you to
clean up your things please.
I saw some great science learning,
science work, put everything
back in your basket
and then please meet me on the rug.
(children talking over each other)
Put your paper at your seat.
Quickly.
Let's see how quickly we can clean up.
Id like for you to come to the rug
and share some things you've learned.
John, you have to put everything
back in your basket buddy.
All the sticks and balls please.
And then you may put your
basket on the art table.
(children talking over each other)
Thank you to everybody
who's moving quickly.
(children talking over each other)
Okay, let's come to the rug and let's share
some things that you learned today.
Move that way please.
I said put your paper
at your seat for now.
- Miss Henderson, Braxton
said this isn't whistling.
(whistles)
- [Miss Henderson] Okay,
well we're not gonna debate
whistling right now.
Okay, thanks so much for
everybody coming back to the rug.
Okay, I would like to know
who learned something about
balls or ramps or forces
in your science work today?
Tell us something you did,
something you figured out.
Bryson.
- If you push the ball
it goes farther.
If you don't push the
ball it goes not farther.
- [Miss Henderson] Okay, alright.
Who else learned something else
through their science work?
John.
- That when you put like
a stick in front of it
and then you put another
ball in front of it
and then like you roll the ball
and see how much it goes.
And then you try another ball
and see like if it gets to the stick
and if it doesn't get to the stick
then it gets farther and,
and we tried whoever gets to the stick.
It goes, it's the same height
then we just rolled it
and then the green ball got the farthest.
- [Miss Henderson] Okay, the green, okay.
Todd, what's something you learned today
through your science work?
- If you push it it'll
go farther and that's it.
- [Miss Henderson] Okay,
alright anything else
we haven't mentioned, Eli?
- There's a block
in front of it
and if you move the block a little it,
it will go past it.
If you make a ball,
if you make a block go
all the way across it
and you have a big ball
it might bounce across it
or it might stop.
- [Miss Henderson] So the
block stopped it sometimes?
- Yes.
- [Miss Henderson] Sometimes
the ball was going fast enough
to jump over it?
- Yeah.
But sometimes it stopped it.
Okay,
Grayson.
- Well, sometimes what I did was
I kinda put the ramp like that
and a little block across
and then I was rolling this big ball
and once it hit it, it kinda like
jumped up in the air and went--
- [Miss Henderson] Harleigh.
- And moved in.
And for like three
blocks for three sticks.
- [Miss Henderson] Okay, Preston,
what did you learn today?
- If you, like if your hand go fast,
the ball goes fast.
If your hand goes slow,
the ball goes slow.
- [Miss Henderson] If your hand goes fast,
what do you mean by if
your hand goes fast?
- Like if you're at the bottom
and (mumbles)
and you do that.
And go like that it goes fast.
- [Miss Henderson] What is
that called that you're doing?
- Pushing the thing.
- [Miss Henderson] So if you
push the ball fast it goes fast
and if you push it slow, it goes slow?
- The force.
- [Miss Henderson] Interesting.
The force of pushing, okay Chloe.
- I learned that
when you lay it diagonal
it goes--
- [Miss Henderson] When
you lay what diagonal?
- What is it
called again?
- [Miss Henderson] What?
- A diagonal line.
- When you lay it down diagonal
it goes down faster.
- [Miss Henderson] What is she
talking about Eli, the what?
- She's talking about a ramp.
- [Miss Henderson] Oh the ramp,
when you lay the ramp diagonal?
- Uh huh.
The ball goes fast.
When you lay it straight
it doesn't go fast, it just sits there.
- [Miss Henderson] Oh, so if it's,
if it's less.
If it's a lower ramp it goes less.
If it's a higher diagonal
ramp you're talking about,
then it goes farther?
Interesting, Brody?
- We tried it with our heads like down
and the ball goes down like that.
- [Miss Henderson] So you made,
you made ramps with your bodies?
So did it go-