- Brooke, what did you choose?
- [Brooke] The cylinder.
- [Teacher] Why?
(mumbles)
Okay, five, and what about you, Ms. Leah?
- [Leah] Cylinder.
- [Teacher] Why?
- [Leah] Because it has two faces.
- [Teacher] It has two faces,
and what about you, Ms. Cecilia?
(Cecilia is drowned out)
The sphere, and why,
you need to write your words down.
Okay, so write your words down so you guys
can hand in your sheet.
- [Girl] Who thinks wants to cut?
Who think will cut?
Here, what about Samantha, then you?
Okay, and then me, then Brian.
Okay, but he goes, you too.
You called...
You want to hold
and stretch?
Well, that's the one you're
doing, and you'll be cutting.
Okay, so Katie cuts, then
Samantha, then me and then Brian.
He is going to roll the
shapes down the hill.
I'll stretch,
and you can hold, okay?
(children chattering)
Samantha...
Wait guys, this is...
- [Girl in Pink] Guys, it's the sphere.
Spheres.
Those are spheres.
- [Girl in Black] That's the cylinders.
No.
- [Girl in Red] This is the
sphere color, you already got...
- Here, how about I'll be...
(drowned out by chatter)
Who wants cylinder, raise your hand.
Who wants
sphere?
Who wants cylinder?
So, it's three versus one.
So, do the cylinder first
and then use... (mumbles)
- [Girl in Red] Fine, I'll get on it.
- [Teacher] You guys working it out?
Alright.
(all talking over each other)
- [Teacher] Yes, Blake, what do you need?
- [Blake] We need more string.
- [Teacher] You need more string?
Okay, alright.
Keep that one right there,
and roll one of your other shapes
and I'll get you a longer piece of string.
- [Brooke] Okay.
(all chattering over each other)
- [Teacher] Hold on, I got it right here.
I'll tie it on there, how's that?
(teacher laughs)
Okay, is that going to work for you?
Alright, Isaac, go
ahead and stretch it out.
- [Girl in Pink] How long it was?
- [Boy in Black] We need to hang that up.
(all chattering)
- [Girl in Gray] You can cut this tie.
- [Girl in Pink] Okay, I'll cut this time.
I'll have...
Don't roll it now.
I can measure it.
I'll cut it.
Now, Leila roll it down.
- [Boy in Black] Move
the cylinder! (shrieks)
(class chatter)
- [Girl in Pink] Blue,
blue, oh we have only blue?
- [Teacher] When you guys are measuring,
who's doing the holding?
You are?
Okay Foster, hold it.
Who's doing the stretching?
Because you're going to have to stretch it out,
you can't cut it until it's stretched.
You're stretching, and so Sierra's cutting?
Okay Foster, you hold it,
you gotta stretch it all the way out.
Yeah, okay, cut it right here.
Like that.
Here, there you go.
Open it a little bit more.
There you go, okay.
And Foster go put it up on the graph,
and Sierra you can throw away the extra.
Okay, good job.
What shape is this, Hunter?
- [Hunter] Sphere.
- [Teacher] Sphere, alright,
and what do you know,
what's special about the sphere?
It rolls, and what's
really special about it?
- [Hunter] It has no faces.
- [Teacher] It has no
faces, you're brilliant.
(class chatter)
Okay, the next one...
(drowned out by chatter)
- [Girl in Blue] Whoa!
- [Hunter] You can cut it.
You may be able to...
(drowned out)
- [Girl in Blue] I want to straighten it.
Measure it.
(drowned out by chatter)
- [Teacher] The sphere went the farthest?
So, was your prediction right, Jackson?
Was your prediction right?
- [Girl in Blue] Yes.
No.
- [Teacher] No. (laughs)
So, you want to circle no,
and you want to circle yes.
Anthony, was your prediction right?
Okay, so you want to circle the check mark
for yes, your prediction was right.
And then you guys can get some crayons and
draw your observations, and what you saw
in your experiment.
(class chatter)
- [Girl in Green] I think...
The cylinder.
- [Teacher] Okay, who's letting this go?
- [Cecilia] Me.
- [Teacher] Okay, you can't
measure it till she lets it go.
Ready, go Cecilia, let her go.
(laughs)
Look at the poor little cube.
Why do you think it doesn't go very far?
- [Both Girls] Because it has sides.
- [Teacher] What kind of sides?
- Squares.
- [Teacher] And they're what?
- Flat.
- [Teacher] Flat, alright, but
now you've picked it up and
you can't measure it.
(laughs)
Alright, who's doing the holding?
Okay, now hold on a second Leah,
so when you measure you want to turn it
this way, so the edge is right up against
the ramp, and then you hold it tight,
and then you can cut it right here, okay?
Alright, so who's holding, you are?
Okay, alright--
- [Girl in Blue] You
hold this, you hold that.
Okay, can I go hang that up?
Now, we do some...
(class chatter)
- [Teacher] Okay, hold
on, can you hold this away
for a second while she sends it down?
Ready?
Okay, ready?
Alright, now are you the holder?
Okay.
Use the stretcher.
- [Girl in Red] Try and stretch the...
- [Teacher] So, Katie,
you took Brian's turn
last time, honey, so it's his turn.
Okay, girls, what shape is this one?
- [Girl in Pink] Rectangular prism.
- [Teacher] And what's special about it?
- [Girl in Black] Because...
Because...
Because it has...
Because it has rectangle.
- [Teacher] Rectangle what?
- Faces.
- [Teacher] Faces, and they are...
- [Girl in Pink] Flat.
- [Teacher] Flat rectangles, right,
so did it go very far?
- No.
- Did anybody pick the rectangular prism
to go the farthest?
You picked that one?
Okay, so now you know,
it didn't go too far.
Alright, so now you're going to try your...
- [Girl in Red] Cube.
- [Teacher] Cube, okay good.
- [Girl in Black] Who's cutting now?
- Who?
Who's sliding it?
Samantha!
- [Girl in Black] No, I
didn't slide it down before.
- [Girl in Red] Samantha didn't...
- [Teacher] So, were you right Leila?
- [Girl in Pink] Yeah, you did!
- [Teacher] Yes or yes ma'am?
- [Leila] Yes ma'am.
- [Teacher] Alright, so you
can circle your prediction
was correct, and then,
was your prediction correct, Isaac?
No, you guys said the
cylinder went the farthest.
Was your prediction correct?
Okay, so you circle here, your prediction
wasn't correct, and then,
was your prediction correct, Aspen?
No, and what about you Blake, yes?
Okay, so now you guys
can go ahead and clean up
all of your stuff, and then you can get
one of the crayon caddies
and draw a picture
of what happened.
Blake, I want you to
help your team clean up
before you start drawing
your observations.
(class chatter)
Good job team!
- [Girl in Blue] Hey, that's mine!
That's my pencil!
(class chatter)
- [Girl] Wait, I'm not ready
yet, I'm not ready yet.
- [Girl in Blue] I got it right.
I got it right.
- [Boy in Red] Yeah, I got it right.
- [Teacher] So, which
shape do you guys have left?
What is that?
- [Girl in Green] Cone.
- [Teacher] The cone, and
what's special about the cone?
(girl in green mumbles)
And so what happens to it?
- [Girl in Green] It slides.
- [Teacher] It does slide on its face.
What else is special
about the cone, Cecilia?
- It rolls in a circle.
- [Teacher] Why?
- Because...
- [Teacher] You okay?
- Because it has a flat face.
- [Teacher] Mm hmm, and
what else makes it roll
in that circle, Leah?
- It has a point.
- [Teacher] It has the point on it,
so this is your last one to measure?
- [Leah] Yes.
- [Teacher] Okay, yes or yes ma'am?
- [All] Yes ma'am.
- [Teacher] Alright, good luck.
- [Boy in Black] You throw that away,
I'll throw it away.
- [Teacher] So, was your
prediction correct, Hunter?
- [Hunter] Yes.
- [Teacher] Yes, so the
cylinder went the farthest
for you guys?
Okay, so Sierra, if the
cylinder went the farthest,
your prediction wasn't
right, so now you're gonna
circle the X.
Does it matter that you are right?
- [Sierra] No.
- [Teacher] No, you're just
predicting, and that means you're
guessing, you don't have to be right.
Circle the X, and then go ahead and draw
your pictures.
- [Ciara] It's orange.
- [Teacher] So, you guys are gonna show
the cylinder going the farthest.
- [Sierra] Just do it.
Do it here.
- [Girl in Green] Now, I don't
know what's going the farthest.
- [Leah] It was probably cylinder.
- [Girl in Green] Yeah...
(drowned out by chatter)
- [Teacher] Okay, so what
shape went the farthest
for you guys?
- [Girl] Um, the cylinder.
- [Teacher] The cylinder, so
was your prediction correct?
Was yours?
- [Girl in Red] Mm, no.
- [Teacher] What shape did you predict?
- [Girl in Red] Um, the sphere.
- [Teacher] Sphere, but the
cylinder went the farthest,
so were you right?
No, so did you circle the little X
on the bottom?
And then you can do your picture.
Was your prediction correct, Brian?
Okay, so circle the check mark
and draw your picture, and then you guys
can copy the graph from the board
on the back, so you can show your parents
what happened.
Good work team!
(class chatter)
All right, so this team's all set?
Okay, so which one went
the furthest for this team?
- [Girl] The sphere.
- [Teacher] The sphere, okay, so was your
prediction right, Cecilia?
- [Cecilia] Yeah.
- [Teacher] Okay, was yours right, Brooke?
So, does it matter if you got it right?
Not at all.
Alright, so then draw your
observations, draw what happened,
and then you can draw
the graph on the back.
(class chatter)
- [Girl in Green] Now we have
to draw the graph on the back.