[Background chatter]
- Oh, water, or more?
- [Voiceover] I guess.
- [Voiceover] And what
gets thrown into the pond?
- [Voiceover] The pebble.
- [Voiceover] Is there a pebble?
Oh, that's so cute, okay.
So, wait, what order these,
do these rings show up?
- What order?
- Yeah, like, what's the procedure
when this was like, like
this, and then this one,
or then this one?
- They start small,
and bigger, and bigger.
- So, drop your pebble in
the pond, there you go.
- And it gets bigger as it goes up.
- [Voiceover] Okay, and so
now, maybe talk through...
(bell ringing)
Maybe talk through what is the given,
what's the constant rate of change,
where you're looking for
it, and how would that
be seen, visually?
- So, the rate is increasing constantly
at one foot per second.
- Per second.
The ADT is two pi R, BR, the first.
- [Voiceover] Which one are you guys on?
Number one, okay, good.
- In order for you to find
for QR, may define the ADT.
We need to find the ADT of different orbs.
- [Voiceover] What?
- [Voiceover] The ADT
concentrating with them.
- [Voiceover] So, it's like, four for DR.
- Okay, so.
- What did you do with your sand?
Show me what happened here.
- [Voiceover] Okay, air is
gonna come into the clear hole,
and then right into...
- You picked the sand problem,
tell me about your sand problem.
- It's talking about sand quality to a,
how to apply it at a rate to be permanent.
- Okay.
- And out of the following,
the diameter of the base in it.
Is...
- [Voiceover] It's going
to make the shape of a cone
when you pour it in one
spot, that's the idea.
- [Voiceover] And the shape of the cone
will be approximately
three times however high
the sand is being poured from.
- Okay, so, our cone has been smooshed,
but you see how it's still kinda narrow,
a little mountain in sort
of the shape of a cone?
- Right.
- And what's the unknown,
what are we looking for here?
- We're trying to find the
rate of the height of the pile.
- [Voiceover] Oh, you can do it.
- We said that's possible.
- Okay, so, Kathy, you're
able, would that be
DVDT, DHDT, DRDT, all these DTs,
we can kinda run together?
- [Voiceover] Just blow it up?
- Can we do AHDT?
- Sure, AHDT because you're looking for
a rate of change for the height.
Now, you're actually
on the hardest problem.
This is the trickiest problem,
and you have correctly
chosen the cards for these.
But, here's what makes it tricky.
I want you to read through this slowly,
and let's figure out the unknown,
and if they give us, what
other rates they give us.
Now, you actually just told
me what the unknown is, right?
- DHDT?
- DHDT.
Okay, what other variables
do we have on this card
besides DHDT and the rate of change?
- AR, ARDT.
- ARDT, and DVDT.
Okay, now, you read it again
while y'all are listening
and see if you can pick out, maybe do DVDT
or DRDT.
- What was that?
- For both.
- At a sand and gravel
plant, sand is falling
off the conveyor and onto
a conical pile at a rate of
10 feet per minute.
- Plus?
What information did you just get?
You can say it again if you need to.
- Sand is falling off a conveyor and onto
the conical pile at a rate
of 10 cubic feet per minute.
- Okay.
Good, that's DVDT 'cause it's the amount
the volume changes, and
the label kinda gets
screwy, too, right?
Okay, so now, we're listening for DRDT.
We hope we hear DRDT because
we need that also, right?
- The diameter of the base of the cone
is approximately three times the altitude.
So...
(mumbling)
- Okay, so it's giving us information
about radius compared to altitude,
but it doesn't seem to
be giving us DRDT, right?
Which means we don't have DRDT.
- [Voiceover] And the radius is two feet.
- And the radius is two feet.
- [Voiceover] So, what's the height again?
- It's the height of DT.
So, we need to find how fast
the radius is changing...
- So, this right here is the decision.
- Nice.
The DVDT equals four pi R squared
to the DRDT.
- [Voiceover] So, this is the hardest
when you get to the math.
- [Voiceover] What we need to find is DRDT
when the radius equals two feet.
- [Voiceover] Okay.
- [Voiceover] All right.
I guess the next one we
can figure out right now...
- How many cubes we got?
- Three.
- Three, okay.
All the edges of the cube are expanding
at a rate of three centimeters per second.
How fast is the volume
changing if each edge
is one centimeter?
- [Voiceover] We have you
doing the edges of a cube,
the radius of an aired balloon.
(mixed chatter)
- So, the radius, one...
- 370
- 370?
- 370.
- So, D, DS over DT is three?
- Right.
- Plug that, we can just plug that in
'cause it's not a constant.
- Tell me a little bit
about the problem you're on.
Does it have three cubes in your problem?
Like, why does it have
three cubes in the box?
- We started with that, this other one.
- [Voiceover] Okay.
- And it shows after a
second, it would be that big.
And then after another
- Oh, good, okay, so, it's
showing that it's the same cube,
and it's getting bigger.
It's like three stages in an environment.
Very good, very good.
Correct interpretation.
Yes.
- And...
It also shows the volume of the...
(mumbling)
- Now, what does this question ask you for
at the very end?
What are you gonna be trying to find?
- How fast the volume changes
when it enters from...
- Yes.
I have a question for you,
here's a think about it question.
Cause you're finding DVDT when
it is exactly one centimeter,
right, that's what the question's asking?
Do you think DVDT would
be greater or smaller
when it's past one centimeter?
Do you think the rate of change of volume
will be getting bigger
faster, or will it slow down?
- Slow down.
- My challenge to you is
after you do the math problem
and you have your equation to work with,
try two centimeters and
see if you were right.
Yeah, so, go above and
beyond the question.
Was your conjecture right,
or were you like, oh, no,
we were backwards?
Kay?
- Okay.
- [Voiceover] The base is
gonna be point oh eight
with the ball, at a descending rate.
And it is asking how fast the
pouch is moving to the wall
in the last part.
- [Voiceover] Oh, you look great.
- [Voiceover] D two?
So, okay, let's pour the sand again.
So, what, five?
So, it's pouring at 10
cubic feet per minute.
- [Voiceover] Talking
about the change in output.
(mumbling)
- So, what's constant?
- Its cubic feet per minute.
- So, that's the...
- The sand being poured in it.
- So, that's the volume?
I don't know.
Okay.
We have choices as to who can't...
- I have four.
And zero to bring it down.
Yeah, I'm just gonna bring it down.
- [Voiceover] Problem number what?
Problem one?
- [Voiceover] Okay, next problem.
Are we agreed?
- A ladder 25 feet long is leaning against
the wall of a house.
The base of the ladder is
pulled away from the wall
at a rate of two feet per second.
How fast is the top moving down the wall
when the base of the ladder
is 24 feet from the wall?
- So, then...
- [Voiceover] You definitely
got the demonstration item
perfect, that's right, that's
exactly what's happening.
- All right.
Okay.
You guys are gonna get this one.
It's what's supposed to be a...
Length.
- [Voiceover] And what
made you pick that one?
- [Voiceover] It's the
Pythagorean theorem.
- [Voiceover] And then why would you wanna
use the Pythagorean theorem?
- [Voiceover] Because it's a three sided,
it's equal to the right triangle.
- [Voiceover] Yeah, exactly, uh huh.
- [Voiceover] All right.
(mumbling)
- Okay, now I've got a question for ya.
Is there any part of that equation
that will always give
confirmation we want to,
that you would actually be
able to substitute a number in
at the very beginning?
Okay, good, good.
- All right.
- What would that mean
about your derivative card?
What would you know for sure?
If you put 25 right there.
- [Voiceover] Get a constant
rate of one foot per second.
- Anything special for
this derivative card?
- DZ over DT equals...
- [Voiceover] Well, if the original,
if your ladder is 25 right here,
where would the 25 originally be put?
- [Voiceover] In the Z.
- [Voiceover] In the Z, okay.
I that would say that X squared
plus Y squared equals 25.
Now, take the derivative of
this with respect to time.
Would it look exactly like
this or a little bit different?
- [Voiceover] One, we're
at a constant rate.
- Right.
And so, when you do your
math, you can go ahead
and put that as zero, and
then just work with those.
Good.
That's good.
- [Voiceover] So...
- [Voiceover] What's the...
- The balloon's increasing.
- Yeah.
- [Voiceover] Following the radius.
- It's the, what's the
radius, it's four feet.
The radius, yeah, you have to find
what the radius is at four feet, and...
- [Voiceover] Find the radius
when it's at four feet.
- [Voiceover] Which one are you on?
P two?
- When the radius is four feet,
at what rate is the total area
of the disturbed water treatment area?
So, you would define the area.
- [Voiceover] Wait, which, are you on...
Okay, so you have three balloons.
- [Voiceover] Right.
- [Voiceover] And you could
use those three balloons
if they are different sizes to show what?
- [Voiceover] Okay.
- [Voiceover] The rate of change.
So, if you have one balloon
and put one back into it,
and then that's when you have...
- Okay, let's see what they look like.
So, let's see if we can
have different stages
of our balloon here.
You look like you must
be at the last stage
'cause that looks pretty big.
Okay, that must be the beginning.
That looks like the beginning, too.
(laughing)
Can one of 'em get middle stage?
I think you've got the
baby balloon, though,
I think that's the biggest
that guy's getting.
- I didn't know they were different sizes.
- Yeah, they are actually different sizes.
One more.
Do it!
And you let some out, maybe you got it.
Oh, perfect, okay.
Tell me about what's going
on with this balloon.
What's goin' on?
- Oh, increase...
- Four cubic feet, and they...
- [Voiceover] Oh, what are they?
- I think I'm thinking of the wrong one.
Like, it's not...
(mumbling)
Like, it's not measuring each breath,
it's something...
- No, you are thinking right.
This is, is this like what we had?
- Two days ago?
- Yeah, a couple days ago.
Like, is, what was
constant a couple days ago
in our activity?
- Air is being continuous air pulled away
by the rate of...
- Yes.
So, like, the volume, the rate of change
of volume is constant.
Is that true on this or is
that a different problem?
Okay, and so, what is the unknown
that you are trying to figure out?
- The change of the radius.
How the radius is...
- And what do you predict will happen
with the rate of change of radius
with the larger the radius gets?
- It'll stretch out.
- That, I'm sorry?
- It'll slow down.
- Yeah, I think that's a good conjecture.
That would be like what
happened the other day
when we looked at it, slowed down quite a bit
the bigger the radius got.
Sounds good.
And it is because it was what?
- [Voiceover] The volume...
- [Voiceover] 'Cause the volume...
- [Voiceover] Yeah.
(mixed chatter)
- F four for that, that'll go on the left.
F four and D six.
- [Voiceover] Have you gotten
to the balloon part yet?
Let's talk about the other one, okay?
One.
Okay, the other balloon
problem was about surface area?
Is that right?
Have you done this one yet?
- Yes.
- Okay, how many, blow up the balloon
and let's see what's
happening in that balloon.
Kevin, what was happening on this balloon?
- [Voiceover] It's the rate of the...
- [Voiceover] The puddle?
- B, a formula problem.
- Okay, so, how is Jesse gonna show us
the surface area of DVDT?
Okay, so let's demo that.
Causing ripples.
Thank you, nice demonstration.
(laughing)
What is constant on this problem?
- [Voiceover] The area and then...
Yeah, the radius?