- Can you make some shadows?
I see light, how will you
make a shadow?
How are you making a shadow?
How are you making a shadow Alicia?
- My hands.
- What is your hand doing?
- Making a shadow.
- How is it making a shadow?
- I don't know.
- How is it making a shadow Brandon?
- Because your hand is stopping the light.
- Your hand is stopping the light.
- And it's small 'cause your hand
is far away from your body and...
More light comes around your hand.
- What happens if you move
it close to the light?
- It has it big because
it stops more light.
because it stops more light.
- It's stopping more light,
you're right.
Let's go see what
these guys are doing.
What are you guys doing?
- Blocking the light
from the light in there.
- You're blocking the light?
How are you blocking it?
- We're going
forwards and backwards
to make it little.
- So I see your shadow is changing.
How is it changing?
- Because you're closer to the light
and then you're...
When you get close it gets bigger.
- It gets bigger?
- And when you're far it gets littler.
- Okay, why does that happen?
What's happening when
you're down here?
- It gets big.
- It gets bigger.
- Why does it get bigger?
What happens to the light?
- The light can't go through
your hand.
- And and and it's blocking it.
- It's blocking more light?
What happens over there then?
- It's blocking a little
bit of light.
- Okay.  So more light
gets around it, right?
Alright very good.
Can you guys make
different shadows?
- It's a turkey.
[laughs]
That looks like the
red nosed reindeer.
- [laughing]
The red-nosed reindeer?
How are you changing your shadow?
- You have to make
shapes of the animals.
- I don't know what to make.
- [laughs] That's okay,
make anything you want.
You guys go ahead,
make 'em big and small,
and I'll be back in a little bit.
Duwant is helping you.
- Duwant!
- What's happening over here?
Doing some measuring?
What are you measuring?
How come you guys are
measuring down here,
and not in the window?
- Because....
- Are you able to see the box?
how come you're not
measuring the fifth one?
Where's the sun?
- The sun is on the other side.
- Other side of the building?
Way over there?
So we can't measure the
shadow sticks today, can we?
That's why you're making
shadow sticks on the ground?
Okay, show me a shadow stick.
Okay Bristava you can
handle the light,
what can you do?
Can you hold the stick up for us,
Julie, to make a shadow?
Okay, can you do the measuring?
Okay, go ahead and measure it.
Put your hand down here
so we can see the top.
Can we measure that stick?
No we're gonna measure the shadow.
You wanna measure the stick first,
and then compare it to
the shadow? Okay.
You gotta hold that
real still, don't you?
Is your light high or low?
- Low?
- It's lower--
what happens if you put it lower,
what happens to the shadow?
- It turns big.
- It grows.
- It grows? It gets longer.
What if we put it high?
- It's gonna be fat.
- Gonna be short?
is the shadow longer or
shorter than the stick?
I need to you to measure it.
Okay, let's record it.
You measure the shadow.
Measure the shadow.
Whoops! 'Scuse me!
Let's measure the shadow,
measure the shadow.
Is that long enough or
do you need another?
Hold it still Bristava.
Is that long enough?
Is the shadow longer
or the stick longer?
Let's compare.
There's the shadow measurer
and there's the stick.
What do you notice?
- It's the same size.
- It's the same size, it sure is.
What if you did it down here though?
Would it be the same size if
you put the ball down here?
No, the shadow would be
much longer wouldn't it?
Good work guys, keep measuring!
Try a different stick,
use that pointer stick.
Or another stick. Here's a stick.
Here's some more
sticks for you to try.
[Background Chatter]
- I'm done with these
things already.
- it's okay.
Okay, what are we doing?
Can you guys guess what that is?
- Scissors!
- How did you know it was scissors?
- Because the shadow.
- Okay, the shape of the
shadow told you,
didn't it?
- She put on some blocks.
- Okay.
- No.
Oh, she says no it's not blocks.
Is she tricking you?
- Yeah.
- Sometimes the shape is hard to tell,
can you guess?
- Adam, no.
- Take a look at this one, Adam.
Take a look at this one,
oh nope, not from up here.
What do you think that is?
Know what this is? Bryce?
What is that one?
Can you tell from the
shape what this one is?
- Gluestick.
- A gluestick you're right!
Good guessing, how could you tell?
- Shadow of the lid.
- You saw the shadow of the lid?
Good job.
- Bryce's turn.
- Okay, now are you guys gonna play
the takeaway game?
Okay. Remember, she's gonna put a whole
bunch of objects on there, sit down,
and you grab a good long
look and then close your eyes
and she'll take one away,
and you'll have to guess
what shadow is missing. Okay?
Alright, what are we
doing over here, guys?
What are we doing?
You're making shadows?
- Shadows
- You're checking out
different materials?
- Yeah.
- Okay.  So what is that one, Shelby,
what did you find out about that one?
- Goes through.
- What goes though?
What goes through?
- The light.
- The light goes through,
so does it make a shadow?
- Yes?
- Which part of it makes a shadow?
Boys and girls, check your voices please?
Thank you.
- This part.
- Okay, that thick part
makes a shadow, doesn't it?
What about the thin parts?
Doesn't make a shadow does it?
The light goes right through.
What else did you try?
What are you trying Takori?
Tell me about it. Show me.
Why don't you try this, Trayshawn.
But wait, Takori was trying something!
Just a minute.
What have you got, Takori?
- A tissue.
- It's what?
- A tissue? Is the light
going through it?
Or did it stop the light?
- Stopped the light.
- It stopped the light,
so it made a shadow, didn't it?
Did it make a light
shadow or a dark shadow?
A dark one.
Okay Trayshawn, your turn,
what are you trying?
- The box.
- is it stopping the light?
Get back here so you can see.
Put it down here.
Can you see it?
What do you see about it?
- It's making a shadow.
- Which part is making a shadow?
- The whole thing.
- is that a dark shadow
or a light shadow?
- A dark shadow.
- Is this part dark or light?
- Light.
- Okay why is this part light?
- Becuase it is a light shadow.
Can't hear you babe.
- Because it's a light shadow.
- Why is it a light shadow?
Why isn't it a dark shadow?
What's happening to the light?
Some of the light going through it?
- Mm-hmm.
- What do you think, Cooper?
What's making that shadow?
- Um, the light.
- Okay, the light is
making the shadow.
What are we using, what is this?
- A box.
- Okay,
is it clear or colored?
- Clear.
- Okay, so what happens to the light?
- It goes through.
- Okay, it goes through it, doesn't it,
so it only makes a
little bit of a shadow.
Good job.
Did you guys write the things over here,
did you find anything new to write down?
Let's try that Shelby.
You and Cooper come over here
and try that.
Okay Cooper, you may
go to the bathroom.
What do you see, Shelby?
- Sorry.
- You see a light shadow?
Why is it light?
- 'Cause it goes right through.
- Is any part of that dark?
- This part.
- That part?
Why do you think that part's dark?
- 'Cause it has a wrapper.
- The wrapper, and what's the wrapper
doing to the light?
- It's stopping the light
and it's making a shadow.
- Exactly. Very good Shelby, thank you.
[student clapping]
Go right here, okay?
What's our time?
- We have two minutes left.
- We might wanna go back and see--
Hey what'd we find out?
Raja, what are we doing here?
- Measuring.
- What's your shadow doing?
Can you change your shadow?
How do you change your shadow?
- By moving.
- By moving? By moving the object?
How else could you change your shadow?
What about the light?
What would you do with the light?
- Move it?
- Move it? I'll hold your stick,
and you move the light.
How is your shadow changing?
Getting bigger?
What else could you do?
Move your light some more.
Move it up or down.
Ooh, what happened to the shadow?
It got shorter?
Oh, now what's happening?
Got longer, didn't it.
This is making a shadow
that's easy to see.
Look at that shadow.
When the light is high,
the shadow is?
- Shorter.
- Short. And when the light is low,
the shadow is?
Alright now measure that. Measure that.
How many cubes lie on that shadow?
- One, two three, four,
five, six, seven.
- Is the shadow longer or shorter
than the stick?
Longer or shorter than the stick?
- The same.
- Oh it's the same!
I think our--