- [Voiceover] What?
- It's a dark color.
- [Voiceover] So what does that mean?
- We think the sun might hit
it or light might hit it faster
so it might melt faster.
- [Voiceover] Keegan, how
are you going to figure out
how much it weighs?
- Maybe, it will melt
faster because the water.
- [Voiceover] What about
that, explain your thinking.
- Because...
- You've stolen her even.
Now we got to count it.
One, two.
- No, now you're taking them all.
- Three, we got to count, four, five, six.
- Here.
- Seven, eight, nine, 10, 11, 12
13, 14, 15, 16,
17, 18, 19, 20.
- [Voiceover] Freeze for just one second.
Let's switch and have the boys keep on.
You stopped at 20.
Boys, finish counting.
They stopped at 20, finish counting.
21.
- 21, 22, 23, 24.
- But they're not counting,
they're just putting it in.
It's not working.
- They're just putting
it in in the same time.
- [Voiceover] So freeze gentlemen.
So how do you think you could fix that?
- Put it back in.
- [Voiceover] You might
want to try to remeasure.
Definitely want to.
- [Voiceover] Miss T look.
- [Voiceover] Guys, we need
to take a bunch of it out
because it's not really getting weighed.
- You might need to use something heavier.
- [Voiceover] Oh, remember,
you're not supposed to touch
that nob on the back.
That's not how you, how
would you figure out
how to weigh it?
- What happened?
- [Voiceover] What's going on Daniel?
Tell me what the problem is.
- It has too much, oh sorry.
It has too much water in it.
- Yeah.
- [Voiceover] Well, can we
change that scientists?
- No.
- [Voiceover] What can we change?
- We can take out a lot.
- It's too heavy.
It was reaching on that side.
- Six halves.
- This is heavier.
- [Voiceover] Wait, say that again Brayden.
What did I just hear you say?
- I said it's heavier.
- This is heavier than the
blocks, so we put more in.
- [Voiceover] Oh.
- Yeah, we're going to put more in.
- Oh way too much, way too much.
- Whoa, look.
- Uh-uh.
- Ms. Teacher, Ms. T, I
think it's six and a half.
- [Voiceover] What is six and a half?
- The measure.
- [Voiceover] Oh, is that your
predication, that's your what?
- That's my hypothesis.
- [Voiceover] Oh, how
are you going to find out
if it's true?
- What do we do?
- [Voiceover] Can you
maybe explain to Teagan
what she needs to do?
- Just balance it.
They're like working on it.
- There we go, got it.
- Got it.
- [Voiceover] Daniel,
what were you saying?
- We were going to like...
- We just figured out how
much blocks it weighs.
- Hang on, it'll get there.
- [Voiceover] So what did you discover?
- We discovered we had, we
discovered we had to take...
- We had to take one, two,
three, four of the blocks out.
- Five.
- Five of the blocks out to make it weigh.
- [Voiceover] So how much does it weigh?
- So let me count the blocks.
One, two, three, four.
- Do you want me to hold the
balloon so it doesn't fall?
- Five, six, seven, eight, nine, ten.
- How many does it weigh?
- Okay, I'll start wearing this.
I mean I'll start writing it.
- [Voiceover] No, I got it.
- [Voiceover] What are
you doing there Abigail?
- Well, I'm weighing and
it's not showing up yet.
- [Voiceover] What are
you using that tool for?
- What tool?
This tool?
- To see how cold it is.
- [Voiceover] So did you already weigh it?
- We have to hold it from the top.
- [Voiceover] Oh, so
do you think it's going
to weigh more now that
you taped that to it?
What's your prediction with that?
Do you have a prediction?
- I have a prediction that
it might be really cold.
- [Voiceover] And that's
going to tell you that?
But have you weighed yours yet?
- [Voiceover] No.
- And it's going to turn to ice.
- [Voiceover] So, but should
you keep that thermometer on
it while you weigh it or
do you think it'll change
how much it weighs?
- I think it will actually
change how much it weighs.
- [Voiceover] Can you
explain your thinking.
- Because, because the
thermometer is heavy too
and it would change how much...
- One pound.
- ...it was so we should
probably get the thermometer.
- One pound.
- So we can, so we can,
so we can weigh it and
then we can put it back on.
- My hypothesis is it's
going to be 20 degrees.
- My hypothesis is this
is going to change it
because it's only one pound.
- [Voiceover] Oh, so what are
you going to do to test that?
- Weigh it.
- [Voiceover] Okay.
- Put it here, put it here.
- [Voiceover] Oh, are you guys discussing?
What are you guys discussing?
- Where we are going to put our balloons.
- [Voiceover] So first talk
to me about your balloon.
Why did you choose this color?
- Because it was a
light color and we think
it might melt faster.
- We will think it will melt slower.
We think it will melt slower.
- [Voiceover] Why?
- Because.
- Because it's a light color.
- The sun is attracted to the dark colors
so that's why we picked pink.
- [Voiceover] So what
are you doing right now?
- Doing a hypothesis.
- [Voiceover] Oh, can you
explain what's your hypothesis,
Teagan?
- It will be warm because
we're going to put it
next to the heater.
- That's what I was going to say too.
- [Voiceover] And so
what's your hypothesis?
How will that change the balloon?
- Because maybe you said
we're going to put it in
the freezer and then when we take it out
we'll put it in the heater and
we think it'll melt faster.
- [Voiceover] Okay.
- What about us?
- It's almost in the
middle, take out one more.
- [Voiceover] Now I'm going to count.
- [Voiceover] What were you
guys just doing down there?
- [Voiceover] She was
thinking about the weight.
- [Voiceover] What does that mean?
- Like in the middle.
- [Voiceover] Okay, so
how will you figure out
how much it weighs?
- We need to take this
out and we'll count them
and then we'll write it on the paper.
- [Voiceover] 32, 32.
- 12, 13, 14.
- [Voiceover] Brayden?
Brayden?
- Hi.
- [Voiceover] Hayden?
- [Voiceover] Is there
any group that's measuring
the length of their's?
- 28, 29, 30, 31, 32,
33, 34, 35, 36, 37.
- Almost there. 43, 44, 45, 46, 47.
It's there, it's there.
- [Voiceover] What does that mean?
- So it means that they
weigh the same thing.
- Okay.
- Now we have to count them.
- Let's let Will only do it.
- Two, three, four, five, six, seven,
eight, nine, 10, 11,
12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19.
- 64, 64.
- [Voiceover] Teagan, be
working in your group.
- 23, 24, 25.
- I measured my balloon by using tiles,
like tiles when I measured it.
Tiles.
What should we do now, Mrs. T?
My balloon is filled with matter.
- [Voiceover] Why do you say that?
- Because everything is matter.
Well, there's water inside the balloon
so it's like solid and liquid.
- [Voiceover] Why is it solid and liquid?
What were you saying?
No, keep explaining your thinking.
- [Voiceover] I have a question.
- [Voiceover] One second.
- Water is a liquid and
pushes on the weight.
- [Voiceover] Oh, so is
that kind of tying in
to your hypothesis?
- Light turns into water,
solids and liquids.
- My hypothesis is, my hypothesis is
if we like, if we...
If we lose the like point
it will not melt faster.
- [Voiceover] Why?
- It's a darker color.
- And when you think about
it, dark colors will melt
faster on their own.
- Is that cubes, the
(mumbles) has the cubes?
- [Voiceover] No, that's the weight.
Pass it on.
Have you all measured yours yet?
- [Voiceover] Yes.
- [Voiceover] How'd you measure it?
- With the tape thingy.
- [Voiceover] Would you
mind showing me what you
decide to do?
- My hypothesis is that
it will melt faster
because we're putting it by the sun.
- [Voiceover] Did you make a
hypothesis by the length of it?
No?
- Ours was six and a half inches.
- [Voiceover] How do you know?
- Because we measured it
with the measuring tape.
- [Voiceover] Can you
show me how you did it?
Oh, there's an extra one Will.
- Did you say not to touch the balloon
without the thermometer?
- [Voiceover] Now do we
draw a picture of what it
looks like right now?
- [Voiceover] These have
bigger numbers you know.
- [Voiceover] So what are
you thinking there Abigail?
- I'm thinking that not really.
- [Voiceover] But what were
you saying there with
the bigger numbers?
I didn't understand.
You held up the number line and you said
those have bigger numbers.
- I mean like you can see them very well
and you also can tell. 30.
- 30?
- 30, he should start now.
- [Voiceover] So how big is your balloon?
- We got to start at one.
- [Voiceover] Oh why
did you change it Julia,
from your first measurement?
- Because we accidentally
started from the 30.
- [Voiceover] Oh.
- And now we have it upside down.
- [Voiceover] Okay, you got it?
It was, it is, move your finger for me.
It is...
- Now let's send this back here.
- Okay, I think we should
do my idea for taking
that thermometer off.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, I'll hold the thermometer.
- I'm trying to take it off.
- My hypothesis is it's going to be warm,
but then not attracted to the light.
- Cold water is in there.
- Because sunlight can only make warmth.
Right?