- [Instructor] Do not put any button caps
in the center of the ridge.
Put them right on the
bottom edge on each side of
that felt.
(hammers banging)
- [Man] Do I get a lot now?
- [Instructor] You get what?
You can't do anything down here.
You need to help him roll that out.
He's going to need help right there.
You can put one in one
side and then pull it down
through there.
One right there.
When in doubt, put a button.
If you're wondering if
it should be in there,
it should be.
We're a little far apart, right here.
You definitely need to
put one, right here.
- [Man] So it's under.
- [Instructor] Reach down
right here and put one in.
- [Student] This back end going to um...
Wrinkle?
Before you put a nail there.
- [Student] Can I nail
the top part of this?
- [Instructor] Yes, absolutely.
- [Student] Because if I--
- [Instructor] Your feet need
to be on a button, regardless
on which side you're on,
you need to be on the button.
- [Student] Please, nail
that one right behind you.
- [Instructor] This sun,
coming out like this,
makes this felt?
- [Student] Hot.
- Hot and soft, and it'll tear easily.
Now this is 30 pound felt,
it's not 15 pound felt.
So it's a lot thicker than what,
you got two common kinds
you're going to be putting on.
15 and 30.
Okay.
Okay how are we doing over here?
- [Student] If you lay it up
there, the top won't fly down.
- [Instructor] That's right.
That's good.
Communicate.
Communicate with each other, right there.
(hammers banging)
Did that work out, work for you?
- [Student] Yeah.
- [Man] Stand this way.
- How many rinds do we need?
- [Instructor] You got your left rind.
Now, we need our interval
going up to the roof.
Tell us what it is.
What you need to do on a three tab.
How far, what is our interval here?
Remember?
Can you remember?
What is it?
Speak up.
- [Student] Five.
- [Student 2] Five.
- [Instructor] Five inches, okay?
Don't be scared.
You know it.
You shout it right out.
Five inches.
Five inches up.
Every five inches.
Be sure to measure from
the top of the seam.
Don't measure from here.
It's got to be from right here.
Measure up five, 10, 15, 20.
Just go ahead and mark it up you're roof.
Get your layout there
and your layout there.
Double check each other.
Check behind each other.
If the layout's not right,
and we have to tear shingles
back off, are those shingles any good?
- [Student] No.
- What?
- [Student] No, sir.
- They're not any good.
Let's make sure we double
check behind each other
and get the layout correct.
Remember.
Team work, just like on the job.
(hammers banging)
Anybody can make a mistake.
You have a couple of eyes on it.
Checking behind, that's a lot better.
(hammers banging)
You can mark on this side.
It's not going to hurt a thing.
You can put a bigger
mark on there, so you can see it.
- [Student] Alright.
(hammers banging)
- Something like that.
- [Student] Okay.
- [Instructor] You can see that.
That's not small and tiny.
That's big.
Look at the difference
right here, Enrique.
My marks, and your marks right here.
You can, especially, I mean,
this is relatively new felt.
This felt gets marked up and scratched up.
If you put a large crow
foot mark, on here,
you're going to know exactly
where to hold that thing.
Make sure that you get
it where you can see it.
We're going to cover this stuff right back up...