- [Teacher] Okay guys, good morning
and welcome to class today.
We're going to continue
our discussion on energy,
but we're going to extend
it to cover some new points
that we haven't talked about yet.
So what I'd like for you to do first
before we get started with out discussion
is look at the big idea, the big idea
for just a moment.
So the big idea that we're
going to talk about today
is how do you think the sun
is going to help you
shoot the stretchy lizard
across the table?
So everybody's got their
little stretchy lizard.
Without shooting them,
we're not doing anything
with them yet, I'd like for
you to talk in your table group
and see if you can come
up with a big idea.
I'm going to give you
30 seconds to do that
and then we'll just go around
and see what you think.
Okay, so 30 seconds to think
about what's the big idea.
(Background Chatter)
[Teacher] Do you know who your
spokesperson is going to be?
- [Student] (mumbles)
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Alright guys, it's been 30 seconds.
I'm going to go to each table.
If you could just have
your spokesperson ready,
you could just tell me
what your big idea is.
We're going to put it up here
and we're going to come back to it
at the end of class
and see how we've done.
Alright, so how about we'll
start with you guys back here
since there's just two of you.
Alright, what do you think?
Shawn, are you going to speak?
- [Shawn] The sun would warm up the lizard
and make it go across the table.
- [Teacher] Okay, so the sun might
warm up the lizard.
I just put L for lizard, that's alright,
and make it go across the table.
Robert, how about your table,
who's your spokesperson going to be?
- [Student] The energy from the sun,
once it shines on the lizard
it would give the lizard energy.
- [Teacher] Okay, the energy from the
sun will shine on the lizard.
Right, is that okay?
Who's your spokesperson?
- [Student] We said that the sun
might make the lizard melt
and make it sticky and then maybe it would
shoot across the table.
- [Teacher] Okay, so it might make it melt
and sticky and that'll make
it shoot across the table.
Is that what you said?
Alright, Kendrick who's your
spokesperson going to be?
- [Students] Blaire
- [Teacher] It was unanimous.
Alright, Blaire, what do you guys have?
- [Blaire] We were
going to say things like
the other people said that
like the energy from the sun
is going...
- [Teacher] Is going to do what?
- [Blaire] Like the energy
from the sun would like
shine on the lizard and it's going
to make it jump
- [Teacher] Okay.
Shine and make it jump.
Nicole, did you guys decide
who your spokesperson's
going to be?
- [Student] Arrington.
- [Teacher] Arrington.
- [Arrington] The sun would
gives energy to the lizard
to help it sling.
- [Teacher] Okay, so the sun
gives energy and I didn't
hear the last part.
You want to tell me?
- [Student] That helps it.
- [Teacher] That helps it, okay.
And last but not least, Jada?
- [Student] We think that the sun
give heat to the (mumbles)
and make it more elastic
so it would stretch.
- [Teacher] Okay, so the sun would give heat
to make it more elastic?
I'm sorry, what was the last part again?
- [Teacher] Like make it more elastic
so it will stretch more.
- [Teacher] So it'll stretch farther, good.
Alright, so what I'd like to do now
is I'd like to just kind of
recall some of the things
that we might already know about energy.
So if I call your number, I
would like you to think about
what do you know about, let's
start with potential energy.
What do you know about potential energy?
So if I call your number just
tell me one factor, one thing
that you know about it
or an example of it.
Alright, we'll start with 15.
- [Student 15] When an object is
like still, it doesn't move,
it's holding it in.
- [Teacher] Okay, still, doesn't
move, it's holding it in.
How about number eight?
Robert.
Something you know about potential energy
or an example of it.
- [Robert] The lizards.
- [Teacher] Alright, very good.
When the lizard is still?
When it's moving, what do you think?
- [Robert] Still?
- [Teacher] Alright, very good.
19.
- [Student 19] It's stored energy.
- [Teacher] Alright, it's stored energy
and I'll do one more, number two.
Potential energy.
An example or something
that you remember about it.
- [Student 2] The pencil is still.
- [Teacher] The pencil is still.
Alright, very good.
Now I know we haven't
talked about these topics
too much yet, but I know from your pretest
you guys had a lot of
background knowledge on it.
Okay, the next thing I'd like to know
is what do you know, what
examples do you have,
what can you remember
about kinetic energy.
So we talked about potential.
Now I'd like to know a couple
things that you might know
about kinetic energy.
Alright, so if I call
your number let me know
what you think.
Number 20?
- [Student 20] A car moving.
- [Teacher] A car moving.
Alright, number 13.
- [Student 13] A paint can being dropped.
- [Teacher] A paint can being
dropped, alright, very good.
Number 14.
- [Student 14] When you
push a pencil and it rolls.
- [Teacher] Alright,
when you push a pencil
and it rolls, very good.
And how about number
seven, we'll do one more.
- [Student 7] Like the energy of motion,
like the (mumbles).
- [Teacher] The energy of motion?
- [Student 7] Yeah.
- [Teacher] Thanks.
Alright, and if I didn't call your number
and you want to contribute
about either potential
or kinetic.
Anybody have anything
else to add about it?
Dylan?
- [Dylan] Kinetic is when like the stored energy
from the potential energy leaks all out
and it starts pulling.
- [Teacher] Alright, very good
and that's a great way to
start into the next part,
what we're going to use
the lizards for today.
Alright, so what I would
like to know from you guys,
is everybody has a bucket
on their table, right?
- [Class] Um-hum, yeah.
- -Teacher] Okay.
And you can raise your hand for this part:
how can you, from your seat,
how can you make the stretchy lizard
get into the bucket?
Anthony.
- [Anthony] Shoot it.
- [Teacher] You can shoot it.
- [Student] You can just toss it in.
- [Teacher] You can just toss it in there.
- [Student] You could pull its tail.
- [Teacher] You could pull
its tail and stretch it.
- [Student] You could drop it in there.
- [Teacher] You could just drop it in there.
It's not too far away.
Anybody else?
Okay, how about, and I'm not asking
for a demonstration yet,
we'll get to demonstration,
I promise.
How about if I asked you
guys, instead of in the bucket
at your table, how could
you get it into a bucket
at your neighbor's table?
At your neighbor's table?
Javious, what do you think?
- [Javious] You could toss it.
- [Teacher] You could toss it.
Arrington.
- [Arrington] You could sling it.
- [Teacher] You could sling it.
Wilson.
That was your idea?
Alright.
- [Student] Walk over
there and put it in it.
- [Teacher] Yeah that's true.
I didn't say you had to
stay in your seat did I?
You could walk over
there and just put it in.
Gavin.
- [Gavin] You could like throw it.
- [Teacher] You might throw it.
Is that what you were going to say Dana?
Alright.
- [Student] Shoot it.
- [Teacher] You could shoot it, alright, very good.
- [Student] You could bend it back.
- [Teacher] Yep, you could bend it
back and shoot, very good.
How about if I asked you to shoot it
from one side of the room to the other?
Jade, I'll start with you.
- [Jade] Sling it.
- [Teacher] You could sling it.
Lewis.
- [Lewis] Like you
said, you could shoot it.
- [Teacher] Yeah, you could shoot it.
Anthony.
- [Anthony] You could throw it.
- [Teacher] You could throw it.
So we're kind of hearing
the same things, right?
We're kind of hearing--
Go ahead.
- [Student] You could
walk over and drop it.
- [Teacher] You could walk over and drop it.
I didn't say you had to stay in your seat.
Alright.
What would be the
difference, though, between
the bucket at your table,
the bucket your neighbor's table,
shooting it across the room,
going out on the football field
and going for distance?
What would be the difference
between what you did?
What difference would you
have between this bucket here,
the bucket at your neighbor's
table and so forth?
John, what do you think?
- [John] The amount of energy
you're putting into it.
- [Teacher] Can you just
show me without actually
shooting it, for example?
- [John] Like if you're trying to
get it into this bucket,
I only have to go like
this or drop it in there.
If I were trying to
send it across the room
I'd have to really stretch it out.
- [Teacher] Okay.
- [Student] The distance away from the bucket.
- [Teacher] Okay, so what
would you do differently
to make it go a different distance?
- [Student] Stretch it more.
- [Teacher] I might stretch it further,
is that what you two were going to say?
- [Student] The more potential energy
or kinetic energy it has.
- [Teacher] The more potential energy,
the more kinetic energy it has?
So when you talk about the lizard,
what do you mean when you say
the potential energy that it has?
How's it getting potential energy?
What does that mean?
- [Student] Before you sling
it, it's just sitting there--
(mumbles).
- [Teacher] Alright, so when it's just
sitting there it's potential.
What about when you stretch
it, what do you think that is?
- [Student] Kinetic.
- [Teacher] Okay, have you let it go yet?
- [Student] No.
- [Teacher] Alright, so we'll think
about that for a little bit.
What I'd like for you guys to
do is talk to your neighbors
at your table, or if you don't
like what they have to say,
you can think about it on your own.
I'd like for you to make a hypothesis
and I'd like for your
hypothesis to start with
"I think" and then think
about what we just said
about how you would get
the lizard in the bucket
at your table versus
your neighbor's table.
What do you think you
would do differently?
"I think if I", do what to the lizard
it's going to go in the bucket at my table
versus the one at the next table.
So make a hypothesis
about how you could test
how can you get the lizard in that bucket
versus the next one.
- [Student] By slinging it.
- [Teacher] Yeah, talk amongst yourselves
and see what you guys think.
Alright, I'll give you
30 seconds to do that.
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] But then compare it to
the next table as well.
What would you have to do
differently to the lizard
to get it in this bucket
versus the next one?
That's what I want you to do.
Okay, alright.
So let me just have...
Let's hear one table. Gavin,
I kind of liked what I
was hearing from yours.
Ready guys?
Gavin, I liked what I was
hearing from your table
when I was walking around.
Tell me what you guys came
up with for a hypothesis.
- [Gavin] That if you were
shooting it at your table
you'd only pull back a little
bit, but if you're shooting
it across to another person's
table, you'd have to pull
it back farther.
- [Teacher] Okay, any other
table have a similar hypothesis?
So their hypothesis then
was if they want to shoot it
into the bucket at their table,
and correct me if I'm wrong,
they'd only have to
stretch it a little bit,
but if they wanted to shoot
it at their neighbor's table,
they'd have to stretch it further.
Did anybody have a similar
hypothesis to that?
You guys did.
How about you guys,
what did you say Nicole?
- [Nicole] We said that maybe we'd have to
aim our trajectory much different
that we would between tables.
- [Teacher] Okay, so not only
the amount of stretch,
but also the trajectory
of how you aim it.
Alright, very good.
How about you guys over there?
- [Student] You'd have to really aim
and focus on how much
power you put into it.
- [Teacher] Alright, very good.
And I know you guys were
coming up with the same thing.
So we're going to do an
experiment in just a minute
to test that hypothesis
about the amount of stretch.
Is the amount of stretch
related to how far
your lizard can fly?
Okay, so if that's your hypothesis,
I think the amount of stretch
that I give the lizard
will make it fly a different length,
what would the manipulated variable be?
What would the thing be that you change
between the different steps?
Anthony.
- [Anthony] How far you pull it back.
- [Teacher] How far you pull it back, very good.
How far you pull it or
can I put stretch also?
Good.
What would our dependent variable be?
What are you going to watch for?
How do you know if that
stretch has made a difference?
Jada?
- [Jada] (mumbles)
- [Teacher] Alright, very good
and where else might it go?
- [Jada] (mumble)
- [Teacher] Right, but you're
talking about your bucket
and you're also talking about--
- [Jada] (mumbles)
- [Teacher] Very good.
So we're talking about--
- [Jada] Distance.
- [Teacher] Alright,
so can I put that down
for the dependent?
- [Jada] Yes.
- [Teacher] Okay, good.
How about some constants.
What are some things that
have to stay the same?
Guys, don't let that table
do all the work, come on now.
Alright, Ada.
- [Ada] The type of lizard.
- [Teacher] The type of lizard, very good.
Would it be fair if I gave
one table battery powered
and the other table not, right?
Alright, very good.
Sierra, what else?
- [Sierra] The size and shape of it.
- [Teacher] Size and
shape of it, very good.
Anything else that has to
stay constant or the same?
- [Student] How big is the container.
- [Teacher] Alright, very good.
How big is the container.
Wilson?
- [Wilson] How stretchy it is.
- [Teacher] Okay, how stretchy it is.
Alright, I'm going to give you 30 seconds
and what I would like for you
to do with those 30 seconds,
is I'd like for you to practice.
Alright, I'd like for you
to practice at this point
just at your table.
If you want to practice
on moving the bucket
to one end and you guys
try from the other end,
that's fine, but I would like for you guys
to control the lizards so
they stay at your area, okay.
Alright, go ahead.
Without hitting your neighbor.
Maybe move to the side, Kendra.
30 seconds.
Go ahead and practice and
see the amount of stretch
you give the lizard makes a difference.
30 seconds.
Gavin.
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] See if you
have some information
when you're done besides that it sticks
to your neighbor's head.
Alright, hold on and we'll try it again.
I promise we'll try it again
at further distances
in just a minute.
Let's think guys.
Can anyone make a
conclusion that starts with:
"When I change the amount of stretch..."?
Can anyone make a conclusion that starts--
Good job.
Nicole.
- [Nicole] When I change the amount of stretch...
If I change the amount of stretch far
then it goes further.
- [Teacher] Okay, if I
change the amount of stretch
when I make it further, it goes further?
Alright, Lewis.
- [Lewis] You might
plan for it to go one way,
but the way that you shoot it really,
it doesn't exactly go where you plan.
It's all over the place.
- [Teacher] But if we just focus back
to the amount of stretch and the distance--