- [Vincent] I'm not gonna have no peace with that.
If you feel something,
I don't know, something (mumbles)
like done bothered me
that done made me like...
brought me down to the point
where I was crying about it
The first thing he say, "I
ain't gonna tell nobody,
"but I feel where you coming from."
He tell me it shouldn't
get to that point
where you mad over something
that doesn't matter.
If it's good or not, that
seriously don't matter.
That's in the past; the
past ain't gonna do nothing.
The past can't hurt you.
- [Teacher] Okay. Alright.
- [Vincent] That's what I'd tell him.
- [Teacher] So, really
this kind of conversation
should've been held with
what kind of friend?
- [Vincent] A pretty good friend.
- [Teacher] A pretty good friend,
or maybe even your best friend.
Nope? Not your best friend?
- [Vincent] (laughter) Oh yes, my best friend.
You already know who I'm talking about.
He's my best friend.
Now, he one of them people that
he done did some stuff
to me that made me mad.
I ask him, "Man, why you doing this?
"I thought you was different
from everybody else."
But, not once have I
actually went out there
and played the cards while I'm at home.
How I'm not gonna tell nobody,
and then come two days later,
everybody and their
momma walking up to him,
and asking him questions.
"Uh, why you did this to her?"
- [Teacher] So, let me ask you this.
So, your saying you've had conversations
with your best friend before,
and then he's divulged
information that you've said to him?
- [Vincent] No, from time to time, he might get mad,
and he'll say something,
then we have to have that one on one talk.
"OK, this was between me and you.
I don't want to hear this
coming out nobody else's mouth."
Cause then I know point blank
that you done said something.
- [Teacher] Let me ask you this,
if you would have that
conversation with someone,
is he truly your best friend?
Is that a conversation that...
Jay, chime in any time.
If you got to keep reminding him
that, hey man,
if you tell somebody something
and you gotta be worried about
whether their gonna tell it
to someone else,
- [Jay] Honestly.
are they really your best friend?
- [Jay] No. Like I said before,
that's another acquaintance,
because you can't trust him like that man.
He telling you he ain't gonna tell nobody,
but he going back on his word.
- [Vincent] He going to get a friend to
turn on you in a heartbeat,
that's why I said it's about you.
- [Jay] Johnny? No.
- [Vincent] Between what you say...
- [Jay] I don't blame Johnny.
- [Teacher] If he's
truly your best friend...
- [Vincent] He won't tell nobody.
- [Teacher] He won't tell anybody.
- [Vincent] But then, you got like...
it's a boundary between stuff you tell.
You can tell your best, best friend
something deep,
but it's a certain boundary between
that which you wouldn't
tell him certain stuff.
I tell my best friend almost everything,
but certain stuff.
he don't need to know.
- [Teacher] Right,
cause certain things we...
- [Vincent] My business don't need to be his.
He have one of those days
when he feeling down,
then I come over there,
"Blah, blah, blah, don't
say nothing to me."
Then, he flips out on me,
and he wanna tell something
that's so deep to me
that I'm sitting there looking like,
did he really just say this.
- [Teacher] Cause your shocked.
You're in shock, and...
- [Vincent] You don't never expect,
well anybody wouldn't expect
their best friend to spill
the beans or say something
that's not meant to be told.
Me, I would never
expect Chris to say anything I tell him.
So far, he has been a best friend.
He don't tell nothing I say.
I don't want to have to
tell what he tells me,
because we got that best
friend relationship.
- [Voiceover] Cause a best
friend should be loyal,
all the way to the end.
- [Vincent] Not when it's necessary or needed.
- [Teacher] That's right.
Not when it's necessary,
but at all times, right?
- [Vincent] Yes ma'am.
- [Teacher] Okay. Alright.
Let me go to the next scenario.
You decide you would
like to take in a movie,
but you choose not to go alone.
You finally reach someone by phone,
who is just as bored as you,
and is dying to be in the
company of someone pleasant.
You both enjoy yourselves so much,
you plan to do this again.
Where is that person at
on the grading scale?
- [Jay] I'd say that's a group thing,
because they interested in the same thing
that you're interested in.
- [Vincent] Group friend.
- [Teacher] Okay.
Alright, group friend?
- [Vincent] Group friend.
- [Teacher] Someone that you
know through association.
Now, in this scenario, it's
just you and that person.
And, it could be someone that
you met through the group.
Or, it could be...
It's not necessarily your best friend.
- [Vincent] You just started hanging
out out of the blue.
You met them, and when
your friends not around,
y'all started to talk a little
and get to know more
about each other then.
- [Jay] I'd say that's a pretty good friend.
- [Teacher] Pretty good friend?
- [Vincent] I could say a pretty good friend,
cause I would hang out
with a pretty good friend.
- [Jay] A pretty good friend you can
take on the outside of school
and you can go do activities
that both of y'all enjoy.
- [Teacher] Yeah, because
a group friend is normally
someone you hang out with in a group.
Kind of like we're together.
Because, once again, you know that person
through association of someone else.
But, a good friend is someone
that you actually can call up and say
- [Vincent] "Okay, you want to go out?"
- [Teacher] Yeah "You wanna go out?
Let's go..."
It's nothing between you guys.
If its a girl, you
understand that she just want
to see the movie, and I
want to see the movie.
We laugh, we joke, we go
out eat pizza together,
but it's nothing else there.
We ain't trying to be
boyfriend-girlfriend.
- [Vincent] You can't try to make
it more then what it is.
- [Teacher] Right. Then,
if it's just a friend,
one of your dudes that you hang out with,
y'all like the same movie.
Like, I...
You know...
You can't call me, cause
we're not on the same level.
I'm your teacher at all times.
Even though you know I like
the same type movies you like,
and we always discuss
the same type of movie,
we're not going to go
to the movies together.
- [Vincent] Cause you on the adult level,
we on the young people level.
- [Teacher] Right, and
we're different types of...
Our friendship scale is different.
- [Vincent] Is not even up here, it's...
- [Teacher] Right. Okay?
Now...
Someone approaches you about
going to see an exhibit at the museum.
You were glad to hear it,
because it just happens to be
an exhibit that you wanted to see anyway.
So, your parents tell
you both that you can go,
and you can...
The exhibit is in a different city.
Your parents tell you
both that you can go,
and you can spend the
night over out of town.
What kind of friend is that?
Is that just an acquaintance?
- [Vincent] That would probably be with
like with my best friend.
I wouldn't go out of town with somebody
that's not by best friend.
- [Jay] I ain't going to go out of town...
I got to go with somebody that I know
is going to speak to me.
You know what I'm saying?
- [Teacher] mm-hmm
- [Jay] Got to be somebody I can trust.
I don't have to many friends I can trust.
I don't know why, but all my
friends is just the reason
why I don't get too close to them.
I can't exactly tell you why.
I just don't.
Because, I can't trust everybody.
- [Teacher] Okay. Alright.
- [Jay] Because, you'll never know who will be
your best friend today.
and, they might turn on you
tomorrow, so you'll never know.
- [Teacher] Okay.
So, that's why this is a good piece to do.
Because, we got to figure out who is
just an acquaintance,
who is someone we that we
will just see on the hall,
"hi, how you doing, bye".
Got to figure out who is the acquaintance,
and then we got to figure
out who is the group friend,
who is a good friend,
who is the best friend.
Because, there's somewhere...
There's a fine line, like you
guys said, there's a fine line
between all five of them,
but you got to know the line.
You got to know where the line is drawn.
You got to know the conversations
to have with all of them,
because there are certain
conversations that you would have
with that best friend...
- [Vincent] That you want to tell somebody
that you just met in the hall.
- [Teacher] Right! Right!
- [Vincent] 'Cause there like, "you just
telling me your whole business,
but you don't really know
my name or nothing about me."
That's something...
The stuff you telling
me, I wouldn't tell you.
I would tell it to my
best friend, but as far as
what's going on in my house,
I'll probably let you know
I got sisters and
brothers, the basic stuff,
but not oh my momma's strung out,
or doing this and that.
Cause everybody's business
is not your business.
Your business is not (mumbles) are you.
- [Teacher] That's right.
We always got to keep that in mind,
because so many times I'll
get calls from parents,
and they'll say, "So and so...
Just talking too much."
Especially when people are
getting into a lot of issues,
or getting into confusion at school,
or what have you.
And, a lot of that comes from
the fact that they don't know
when to be quiet, or they
don't know what to say,
or how to say it, or who to approach.
Because, if someone says to you...
stand up for a minute.
In the morning, when you first come in,
and the first thing I say to you is what?
- [Vincent] Good morning.
- [Teacher] Good morning. Good morning, Vincent.
How you doing?
- [Vincent] Good morning Ms. Jenson.
- [Teacher] How was your weekend?
- [Vincent] I went to my cousin house,
I got to spend time with my Godmother,
and I went grocery shopping.
- [Teacher] Okay. so that...
Now, you told me...
I didn't say what did you do.
- [Vincent] Oh.
- [Teacher] I said how was your weekend.
- [Vincent] It was good.
- [Teacher] It was good.
And, that's basics of that conversation.
It should not be oh guess what?
My momma...
My momma and her boyfriend was fighting,
and they threw the cat out the window,
and then the police came over.
Because, at that moment,
you have just did what?
- [Vincent] Stepped out of bounds.
- [Teacher] You've
stepped out of bounds.
You've divulged way...
- [Vincent] Too much.
- [Teacher] Too much.
- [Vincent] You done opened the book
before it could be read.
- [Teacher] (laughing)
Or you done read the book
before it could be bought.
Because, really, I didn't
buy into all of that.
I didn't want all of that.
- [Vincent] You just wanted to know your name,
and how was your weekend.
- [Teacher] I just
wanted the generalities of
it was a good weekend.
And then there are times
that we could probably
get a little deeper.
- [Vincent] But you not asking for that.
You just asking for the simple.
- [Teacher] That's right. That's right.
Jeremy, I'm going to ask you....
Stand up for a minute.
Jay...
'cause you're a pretty secretive guy.
-  [Jay] Mmhm.
- [Teacher] So normally we got to
pull stuff out of you.
'Cause I said to you earlier, I said,
"Your Dad called.
And what was that about?"
- [Jay] (mumbling)
(laughing) I was stuck on the river.
- [Teacher] And he said,
"I was stuck on the river."
My first thought was Jeremy got a boat?
(laughing)
So I said, "You got a boat?"
That's what I said, right?
- [Jay] Yeah. I was over there
at the Wafflehouse,
over there by Brian Gates behind
over there at the apartments.
I went to see someone.
- [Teacher] And so
he went to see someone,
but again, sometimes you got to know
when to hold your conversation--
- [Vincent] ...and when to divulge it.
- [Teacher] --and when to divulge it.
Because, even though
he went to see someone,
he didn't give me no elaborate details,
yeah this honey, she was...
Because a lot of times,
- [Vincent] You don't need that.
- [Teacher] I don't need that.
- [Jay] You just wanted to know where I was at.
- [Teacher] Just wanted
to know where you was at.
I want to make sure you was okay.
Make sure that your Dad
got in touch with someone
to be able to say, "Jeremy's okay".
Okay? Alright?
- [Vincent] Alright.
- [Jay] Yeah.
- [Teacher] You can have a seat.
- [Vincent] That was a good conversation.
- [Teacher] Huh?
- [Vincent] This was a good conversation.
- [Teacher] This was a good conversation?
You thought this was a good lesson?
- [Jay] Today was a good day.
It was a good day.
- [Vincent] Because some people
don't know their boundaries
of talking and telling it all.
- [Jay] Some people just give
up too much information.
- [Vincent] Some people around here got to even say
what (mumbles) did to you and everything.
- [Teacher] From here
we're going actually,
the next thing we're going
to discuss is conversations.
That's where we're going to go from here.
I wanted us to...
because, the other day,
we kind of looked at friendship,
but I wanted to go a little deeper,
because I know....
I want us to realize that friendships...
they should be reciprocal.
- [Vincent] Not always.
- [Teacher] And when I say reciprocal,
everybody understands what I'm saying?
- [Vincent] The same.
- [Jay] No.
- [Teacher] Should be the
same, like how I feel about you,
you should feel that same way about me.
- [Vincent] I feel like you trustworthy,
but you feel like I'm going
to tell on you any chance I get.
- [Teacher] Right. Exactly.
But, they're not always reciprocal,
but...
keep in mind that friendships
are always changing.
Because, who you put down
on your friendship scale
on Thursday...
- [Vincent] It change.
- [Teacher] It changed.
You gave me a whole different...
not a whole different set, but you gave me
some different people,
and you actually moved some people.
Where you had Yolanda as a good friend,
she became just a group friend
four days later.
Okay, and you had valid reasons,
and keep in mind that things do change.
Just because someone was a
best friend last week....
- [Vincent] Don't mean they going
to stay your best friend.
- [Teacher] They're not.
Nine times out of 10, I promise you guys.
When I was in high school,
I could.....
there were three, there was four of us,
and I considered them
my very best friends.
Now, I don't know how deep
they would've had my back,
but I considered them my good friends.
We talked on the phone, we
shared secrets, we shared stuff,
you know, when we was
sneaking and doing stuff.
We shared those things, but today,
I really can't tell you where they're at.
Now, there was some friends
that I met in college
that we're still friends
to this day.
They're friends that I've had
since I came into teaching,
that I don't know where those people are.
Because I've been teaching...
when you think of teaching for 18 years,
people have friends...
people have come and gone
in the teaching profession,
but I haven't kept in
touch with all of them,
because there has to be a...
there has to be something in common
that's going to keep you friends.
It can't just be, I see...
if I see them just at school,
and that's all we ever
talk about is school,
and schoolwork, and complain, and fussing,
and about lesson plans and stuff,
then nine times out of 10
those are just my associates.
Those are just acquaintances,
people that I pass in the hall.
We laugh, we joke, but we don't share
any intimate conversation.
Okay?
I'm glad this was a good
exercise for you guys,
and next time we're going
to look into conversations.
The type of conversations you have
with each one of those type people.