- [Teacher] Okay.
- [Boy in orange] What's
the next one, Zach?
- [Teacher] (speaking inaudibly)
- [Girl in blue] Jen, you can put
on a 50-line poem on that one here
if you wanted to.
- [Boy in orange] I got that.
- [Teacher] You have (inaudible)
- [Boy in orange] Okay what was the main?
What was the summary?
- [Teacher] What would be
a good summary sentence?
- [Girl in gray] (speaking inaudibly)
- [Zach] Well, they competed in a game
known as the Memoriad.
- Uh huh.
You guys had that one, don't you?
You have the names and faces there.
That was great.
- [Zach] The game.
(inaudible)
- [Girl in blue] Are you
doing the vocab though?
- [Girl in gray] No.
- [Girl in blue] Okay.
- [Blonde girl] So wait, hang on.
Should we do the pictures
or the vocabulary words?
- [Teacher] You can just do
anything from that article.
The pictures were just to
get you thinking about it.
That's why we did the words.
And the vocab was just
to help us understand.
So it doesn't have to go off the vocab.
But the vocab kind of
connects with an idea.
So it may kind of work out that way.
You'll have to let Zach see,
because you took what he had,
which is great, and you added to it.
- [Girl in blue] Do we
put the name of the movie?
- [Girl in gray] I'm doing (inaudible).
It's a song.
The croak part is a song.
- Mm-hmm, that was part of the.
- [Girl in blue] Okay, I was getting.
- [Girl in gray] There, there's the song.
- [Girl in blue] (laughs)
- [Girl in gray] I was stuck
on the reading one too.
- [Teacher] Got one left.
- Zach, what's the text structure?
- Sharpening his pencil.
(pencil sharpener grinding)
Just go like that.
- [Girl in blue] So
was the Puppet in 1970?
Or was it?
- Yep, 1970.
- [Boy in orange] That must have been old.
- 1968 is when the Yellow
Submarine came out.
Yep.
- [Boy in blue] (inaudible)
- All right.
Do you guys want to put
your pyramid up there?
Zach, do you want to help do that?
Do you agree that he was
right on the text structure?
- [Zach] Yeah.
- See if you can build it.
I tried to size it just about right,
as close as I could get.
So it should fit in there pretty good.
- [Zach] I don't think
it's sized up very well.
- [Teacher] What?
I just got it as close as I could, Zach.
It may not be 100% perfect.
And then the person that
didn't read the story
can read us what you guys
put for your answers.
- [Girl in blue] That means
we got to do another one.
- You each got a chance to read.
- [Girl in gray] Yeah,
that's the tone one.
- We need one more detail.
Did I make it a little too big,
or is it pretty close?
- [Boy in orange] It's a little long.
- [Teacher] Could be a little long, huh?
Had a little extra at the bottom.
Next time I'll shrink
it up just a little bit.
- [Zach] We still have one more.
- That's fine.
And who read it?
Was it Zach?
- [Boy in orange] (inaudible)
- We'll let Zach read those
when the girls get done.
- [Zach] Okay.
Do I read the summary?
- [Boy in orange] Do you
just want me to read?
I don't know if he knows.
- [Teacher] Start with the details.
- [Zach] Memoriad is an
unforgettable competition.
Memoriad games is memorize 50-line poems.
People compete in the
games called Memoriad.
The game is to memorize it.
(inaudible)
Memorize names and faces and memorize
a 50-line poem.
- Very good.
And what was your text structure?
- [Zach] Description.
- Description, because they were
describing all about (inaudible)
- [Boy in orange]
(inaudible) He just talked.
- He did the talking, you did the writing.
Somebody gave you ideas.
- Kinda maybe.
- It was a good partnership.
The girls are just about done.
We'll let them read theirs.
And then we'll do our Jeopardy.
- [Boy in orange] Can we
tape the Jeopardy game?
- Mm-hmm, yep.
- [Girl in blue] We have
the same people in Jeopardy
that were in here.
- Yes, it is the same group.
Okay, let's not have a
sword fight right now.
She has one more task there.
She's got it all grammatically correct.
- [Girl in gray] Okay. (inaudible)
- Let's just, Judy over here.
- [Girl in gray] Do you mind
if it's off to the side?
- [Boy in orange] There's another one.
- There's two of them.
Oh, did it fall off?
Well, we can put a little
piece of tape over it.
Oh, here it is.
There you go, that should hold it up good.
All right, see if you agree
with what the girls have here.
Are you listening, Zach?
Got a pyramid all set up.
- [Girl in blue] Our text structure is,
wait, do I start at the bottom?
- Start at the bottom,
and the details kind
of add to the summary.
- [Girl in blue] (inaudible)
The movie they were talking about
was the Yellow Submarine, starring.
Is it starring or staring?
- Starring, I bet.
- [Girl in gray] Starring the Beatles.
- [Girl in blue] The Beatles, okay.
Their song called Being Green
was made in 1970.
Summary, the television was made in 1953.
Kermit was in 1970.
Stoplight was made in 1920.
They all had one thing in common.
They were in a color.
- Very good.
I love that last sentence.
They all have that in
common, they're in color.
- [Girl in blue] Text
structure is sequence.
- Sequence because?
- It tells the order of them.
- All the years, very good.
Okay, one of you guys
go grab a marker board,
one from each team.
And I'll go get Jeopardy.
And you'll need a marker to
write on the marker board.
I will pull the screen down.
All right, Zach, Zach.
- [Boy in orange] Where are the markers?
- [Teacher] You can grab one back there.
There's one up here.
As long as you got one
or two for your group,
you can take turns.
Now, these questions I think
will flow pretty well today.
- [Boy in orange] Whoa,
I can't even see it.
I think the yellow is better.
I know with the lights
on, it's a little harder,
but it helps to have the lights on.
- [Boy in orange] Did we run review?
- [Girl in gray] What?
- [Girl in gray] (inaudible)
- [Zach] Text structure!
- [Teacher] My music didn't come on.
- [Zach] Confucius says!
Vocab.
Text features.
- [Teacher] Features.
Thank you, Zach.
Yes, they're different.
- [Zach] Confucius says?
- [Teacher] Yeah.
Okay who started first last time?
Was it the guys?
- [Girl in gray] Yeah.
- [Teacher] Okay, we'll
let the gals start today.
- [Girl in blue] So do
I do text structure?
- [Zach] Oh, you're gonna win.
- [Girl in gray] Text structure 500.
- [Teacher] Text structure 500.
- [Girl in gray] Yeah,
what's the "Confucius Says"?
- [Teacher] We had done
these little matching things
way back at the beginning of the year
when we did this unit,
they were little sayings,
and you decide just which
text structure they go with.
- [Girl in gray] So that
might go with text structure.
- [Teacher] Yes, it'll be a
text structure question, yeah.
- [Zach] (humming)
- [Teacher] Is that what you guys wanted
was text structure, right?
- [Girl in gray] Yeah.
- [Teacher] Okay.
- [Girl in blue] In our
state, dams have been built
- [Teacher] Zach.
- [Girl in blue] on many rivers.
These dams are used to product
electricity we need.
But they also create problems.
- [Teacher] Scoot your chair
closer to your partner.
Scoot your chair back.
- [Girl in blue] Prevents
the other wildlife
near the rivers.
Therefore, we should
not build any more dams.
Instead, we should use solar energy,
or energy from the sun,
to produce electricity.
This will help us protect our wildlife
and enjoy the natural beauty around us.
- [Teacher] Hmm, which of
the five text structures?
- [Girl in blue] We think
it's problem solution.
- [Teacher] Problem solution, correct.
Give yourself 500 points
- [Girl in blue] Because
it said problem in there.
- [Teacher] All right,
what would the guys like?
Hey.
- [Boy in orange] Sorry.
Zach, what do you want?
- [Teacher] They did text structure 500.
It'll pop up yellow after
I click on the next one.
- [Zach] Vocab for 500.
- [Teacher] Vocab for 500.
Want to read that one, Zach?
- You should take some
time to ponder the question
before writing your response.
- [Teacher] Hmm, what does ponder mean?
- [Boy in orange] You think.
- [Teacher] Ahh, perfect.
To think about.
Give yourself 500 points.
All right, what would the gals like?
- [Girl in blue] Should we
try the Confucius question?
- [Girl in gray] Yeah.
- [Girl in blue] For 500.
- [Teacher] Okay, Confucius says for 500.
And Marissa can read this one.
- [Marissa] Confucius
says, "A beautiful sunset
is treasure for the eyes."
- [Teacher] This is one of
the five text structures.
- [Girl in blue] Description?
- [Marissa] Yeah, description.
- [Teacher] Description, very good.
And I'll just set these out.
I got something that might help you guys,
since a lot of these have them,
you just kind of have
your choices right there.
What would the guys like?
Very good.
- [Zach] Text features.
- Text features 500.
- [Teacher] Text features 500.
- Which text feature is an alphabetical
listing of subjects, people,
and places you find in a book?
Index, table of contents, title.
- [Teacher] What do you guys think?
Alphabetical listing.
- What do you think, Zach?
- Index.
- (laughs) Index.
- [Teacher] Index would be correct.
Good job, guys.
What would the gals like?
- [Girl in blue] Oh, 500.
- [Teacher] Yeah, I just did that 500.
500s are gone.
- [Marissa] Should we
text features for 400?
- [Teacher] 400, okay.
All right, Judy can read this one.
- [Judy] What text
feature gives definition
for vocabulary words?
- [Marissa] Wait, what is it?
Wait.
- [Judy] Yeah, what do you mean for that?
- [Teacher] Oh, I didn't,
that one doesn't have
the choices like the other one did.
It would be an index,
a glossary, or a title.
- [Judy] Glossary.
- [Teacher] Glossary is correct.
I put the choices on the other ones.
I just must have missed that one.
Very good.
All right
- [Zach] Confucius says for 400.
- [Teacher] Confucius says for 400.
Could you go for Mrs. Lloyd's
for just a couple minutes?
Okay.
- [Boy in orange] I
wanna go tell Mr. Debush.
- [Teacher] That's all right.
I'll just get you guys a
pass here in just a second.
We'll do a couple more questions here.
All right, whose turn to read?
- [Boy in orange] It's Zach's.
- [Teacher] Zach's turn?
Okay.
- [Zach] Confucius say,
"First feed the lion,
"then enter cage."
- [Teacher] Hmm.
- Sequence.
- [Teacher] Sequence?
Do you agree with him?
- Yeah.
- [Teacher] Yes, very good.
Sequence.
All right, what would the gals like?
- [Marissa] What one did they do?
- [Teacher] They just did
the Confucius says for 400.
- [Marissa] I want to do that one for 400
or for 300, right?
- [Judy] I think, yeah.
- Confucius says 300?
Okay.
- [Marissa] Yeah.
- [Teacher] Okay, all right.
- Oh man, basketball.
- [Teacher] Whose turn to read?
- [Marissa] Confucius says, "Net in soccer
"is much larger than net in basketball."
- [Judy] Compare and.
- [Marissa] Yeah, compare and contrast.
- [Teacher] Very good.
300 points for the gals.
All right, so they did this one, Zach.
What would you guys like?
- [Boy in orange] You
want to do vocab for 400?
- [Zach] Vocab for 400.
- Yeah, vocab.
- [Teacher] Vocab for 400?
Okay.
- [Boy in orange] Many
professional golfers
first began playing as amateurs.
- [Teacher] Very good.
Just a second.
What do you think?
- [Zach] First players.
- [Teacher] Okay, the first players.
You're exactly right.
- Oh, my gosh.
- People who have done something
for the first time and
they don't get paid.
They're amateurs.
All right, what would the gals like?
They did vocab.
- [Judy] Structure.
- [Marissa] Yeah.
- [Teacher] Structure 400?
- [Teacher] They want the big point ones.
- [Judy] Is it my turn?
- [Marissa] Yeah, I think so.
- [Judy] Living in the
country is very different
than living in the city.
A city dweller need to
be careful of traffic
and other people.
In the country, there are
fewer cars and people.
In the city, many people
can walk to the movies,
stores, and other activities.
In the country, people must
drive to get to places.
- [Marissa] Compare and contrast.
- [Judy] Yeah.
- [Teacher] Compare and contrast?
And she agrees.
Very good.
All right, what would the guys like?
- What do you want, Zach?
Vocab for 300.
- [Teacher] Vocab for 300.
- Oh, it's your turn, Zach.
- I depleted my savings when I bought
my new basketball shoes.
- What do you think?
- [Teacher] Hmm, what do you think?
One for depleted.
- [Judy] Oh, I know this one.
- Drained?
- [Teacher] Drained, yep.
Empty, gone, you used all your savings.
And basketball shoes
can cost a lot of money,
so I can see that happening.
What would the gals like?
- [Marissa] Confucius,
oh wait, no, no, no.
Did they do text structure 300?
- [Teacher] Nope, he just did the vocab.
- [Marissa] Okay, I want to
do text structure for 300.
- [Teacher] Features for 300?
- [Marissa] No, text structure.
- [Teacher] Oh, text structure.
I can go back.
Structure for 300.
- [Marissa] The eye is
made up of many parts.
The white part of the eye is called the
- [Teacher] Sclera.
- [Marissa] sclera, and the
colored part is called the iris.
The iris comes in many colors,
including brown, blue, green, and hazel.
The iris is covered with the cornea,
which is clear and round.
Description.
- [Teacher] Do you agree?
- [Judy] Yeah.
- I should know about the eye,
because my stepmom's a, she
works at the eye company.
- [Marissa] Wait, did we
just pass text features?
- [Teacher] Oh she does?
They just.