My big goal is to be...
is to: All my
homework, Get better grades,
Study harder than I did.
Okay! It's a big,
excellent goal. I like that.
Okay!
So one of the things that helps
me when I'm working on a goal is to
write it down and make a plan
for how to accomplish that goal.
Organizing.
Good job!
So what do you think today
if we work on
making this goal
a permanent part of your plan
and taking some steps to
really be organized with it?
Does that work for you?
mm hmm...
Wonderful.
Okay. So the first thing we want
to do is write down your goal.
So you just said to me
in really nice words your goal.
Yes. It's to study more harder
than I used to.
Okay! And let's get real
specific about your homework.
What did you say
about your homework there?
Check over it.
-Okay.
But before you check over what
you need to make sure you do?
All of it.
Get it completed, right?
Okay, awesome.
So your goal would be to...
Get homework completed.
-Wonderful!
Okay!
Excellent! Okay!
Now I brought
some extra markers
and stuff here because
I know you're a visual learner,
that you do a good job remembering things
that you figured out on your...
learning styles test.
So this is for you to do.
You can choose any colors to make
it look however you want. Okay?
So you've got your goal
and then we need to figure
out why is that goal important.
So your goal is to
Get all homework done.
Excellent.
And why is that important?
Because when
you're in fourth grade
you don't get all
your homework done
and you on fence and
when you get on the fence,
I've been there
a couple of times
and is not very fun,
and for the good achievement you get to go to Hot Wheels.
hmm...
So if you don't do your homework,
You're on a boring fence.
Okay! You have to stand
by the fence at recess.
And if you do do your homework,
you go to Hotshots.
Homework Hotshots.
And that is...
What do you have to do to
qualify for Homework Hotshots?
Do all your homework for all the...
Oh! Wow!! So...
All your homework
throughout the nine weeks
and then you get to go..
get to be a Homework Hotshot,
which means you
go to Hot Wheels
and enjoy the day skating.
Excellent! Okay!
So you just brought
up a good point.
umm...
So this goal is important
because not only do you
not want to stand by the fence,
and you want to
be a Homework Hero.
What's going to happen
if you do your homework?
You go to Hot Wheels.
You go to Hot Wheels
and what do you think...
What effect is that
going to have on your
report card here?
If you're doing all your homework,
what's going to happen to those grades?
You get all the grades go up.
like the 100 - 200.
That's right. Very good.
All right.
So, go ahead, write that down. Why
you think homework is important.
Excellent
So this goal is important because
you can always get good grades.
and homework is
a way that teachers
help the students
reinforce the things
that they are learning in class.
So that's an excellent
way to get good grades.
Okay! So we know our goal
and we know why it's important.
So let's think about
what kind of rewards we're
going to get for reaching that goal.
You get achievement awards.
You go in a limo
with the principal.
And you go out to eat.
and Hot Wheels too, right?
So those are some long-term goals
over the next nine weeks.
You get to complete your
homework the next nine weeks.
You get to go to Hot Wheels
and might even be on
the principal's honor roll
to take the limo ride.
Pretty cool, huh?
Okay!
So that's here.
We've got
Don't forget one thing, that you get
to drink soda while you're going.
You do?
I didn't know that.
I've never been in there.
I've never been in the limo, but I heard.
Oh, my goodness!
Well, that certainly is a nice incentive,
something to motivate, huh?
Good!
So that's kind of
a long-term motivation.
We've got to work
hard all these nine weeks
to accomplish that, right?
Okay! So we've got here.
When I meet my
goal for the quarter,
Quarter is another way of saying
the nine week time period.
you will what?
What do you get to do if you
do all your homework
over the nine weeks?
I will go in a limo.
Well, that's for principal's honor roll,
which is definitely an option.
What's specific for homework?
umm...
When I meet my goal,
for the quarter,
I will go to Hot Wheels.
Go to Hot Wheels.
Awesome!
Excellent.
So the nine weeks
sometimes it can feel like
long way away, can't it?
Okay!
Because nine weeks is not easy.
They are not easy
to do your homework
Because it's a long
time before you go
to Hot Wheels and we only
have eighteen weeks in school.
So it's easier
sometimes to stay motivated
and work towards a goal
if you have some
incentives that come on
more of a short-term basis.
Meaning that instead
of waiting all nine weeks
to go to Hot Wheels,
which you will get to do,
if you meet your goal.
Let's think of something that
we can do maybe, once a week.
That would be
a good incentive for you
Study.
Okay! Well, studying is
part of your homework plan.
Let's say that you study
and you turn all your...
you do all your homework
and at the end of the week
when I check in with you,
when I check in with Miss. Butler,
and I check in with your granny,
and I'd say,
So how did Annamarie do? Did she
get all her homework done?
mm hmm..
And they say- Yes, she did.
What do you think might be
something that you're willing
to work towards here at school
that would be
a reward once a week?
I will come to you
and I will help you.
You'd like to help me?
All right.
So could we agree that
let's say, I check in on Fridays
with your teacher
and your granny and you
to find out-
did she do her homework?
What are they going
to tell me? -Yes. Yes
And then on Fridays you
get to come and help me.
mm hmm..
That'd be wonderful.
Now I teach a first grade class
every day at 12:10.
I know you do a really good
job helping out at home
with your niece
But she...
I do not get to
see her Monday, Tuesday,
Wednesday, Thursday
But on Friday, I do.
Because my mom...
My mom watches her.
And sometimes when
my sister and I
and the baby's not here
we actually look at
photos of her because
we really miss her and
we talk to her on phone.
Awesome! She's lucky
to have an aunty like you.
Awesome!
Well I know because you do
such a good job caring for her
that you'd be
an excellent helper
for me and my first graders.
Will that be
a good goal for you?
Okay! So our next section here.
Can you read this?
When I meet my goal
for the week, I will get to
go to... go to Hot Wheels, I think.
Well, Hot Wheels is
for the whole nine weeks.
But each week..
Remember our...
What we're working towards on
Friday, that you get to come...
Help you.
Right. So you get to
come help Miss. Charles.
on Fridays
Okay!
You have very nice handwriting.
Thank you.
Okay!
-So do you.
Thanks.
Okay. So this goal
is something that
you're in charge of, right?
You're in control
of achieving this goal.
But you're not in it alone.
Because there's of a lot of people
who want to see you reach that goal.
and to see you doing an
awesome job at school.
So who are some of the people
the adults in your life
who are on your team
who can be helpers for
you as you reach this goal.
My grandma, my aunty,
my uncle, my mom and my sister.
Wonderful!
You have a lot of people.
So these are people at home
that can help you
reach your goal, all right?
So let's go ahead and put those
down for supporters at home.
Awesome!
All right. So you've
got a lot of people
supporting you at home.
I've got five.
And how about here at school?
Who's on your team?
Miss. Butler and Miss Charles.
You've got it girl.
I can't wait
to support you on this goal.
Okay! So the people
who can help me at school
is Miss. Charles
Is it okay if I put in Miss. Ficker?
my assistance teacher,
because she helps too.
Definitely.
That's a great person to add.
And so are you.
Thank you.
Okay!
I just realized something.
What's that?
All these teachers
name has a "R" in it.
Miss. Charles,
Miss. Butler, Miss. Ficker.
It's a good attention
to detail you have there.
Okay! So we know
that our goal is to
get all my homework completed.
Okay!
And it's important because
you can always get good grades.
Excellent.
Now on the short-term
if you're doing a great job getting
your homework done every week.
Each week you will get to
come help... come help
Miss. Charles on Friday.
Excellent. And I will know that
you're doing a great job because...
you can ask Miss. Butler,
my grandma and me.
That's right. Okay.
And over the whole nine weeks
when you do a good job
getting all that homework done
what's your reward?
I get to go to Hot Wheels.
Awesome.
And then although you're
the one in charge of this goal,
there's a lot of
people on your team.
Who are those people
on your team from home?
My Mama, my granny, my sister,
my Uncle TJ
and my aunty (unintelligible)
People on you're side.
All right! And then when you're
here at school, who's on your team?
Miss. Charles, Miss. Butler, Miss. Ficker
Awesome. All right.
So what do you think?
How's the school going to go?
It's going to be great,
because I will follow all of these.
Good. and I'm here to help, okay?
All right.
Well, I think the first step
towards achieving this goal is
to make sure that we
manage our time really well.
And I know we
talked a little bit before
about kind of your month.
We looked at
the month of February
and figured out what
big things you have coming up.
What portions of
the day you spend
here at school or at Church,
and what you do, how you help
out taking care of your niece.
So that's the month of February.
So what we're going to do
today is really focus on this week
and make a plan.
So what I've done here is
based on the information
you told me before,
we've got this week
starting with today
Monday, February 7th
and you will notice I've the time of
day all the way from 6 in the morning
throughout the day till
Yeah, 10 at night.
So I have these spaces blocked off
So what are you usually doing
Monday, Wednesday,
Friday from 7 to 4?
Come to school.
You're at school, right?
So this whole area
Is school?
Is school. That's right.
You're here at school.
Will you write school?
-Sure.
Sometimes it's easy for
me if I just draw a line
to show that.
Like that.
Okay. School.
Okay!
So knowing that you're in school
from 7 to about 4 O'clock,
and we also need
to think about some other
regular things that
you do during the week.
So you told me before
that...