- So, these two are gonna combine
and make six X squared?
- Yes.
- Okay and then what about this guy?
- Just bring him down.
- Alright, what about her?
- You can bring her down.
- Okay.
- That's a four X to the fourth,
not four X squared.
- Ah, thank you.
Four X to the fourth.
And is this term positive or negative?
- Positive.
- And what about this term?
And what do we call this guy?
[inaudible]
Rock on, okay good, good, good.
Alright, easy one, you ready?
Three X times X squared plus
four X minus two.
And this time
we're multiplying, what
kind of monomial is that?
- Linear.
- Linear, good.
Times a quadratic what?
- Trinomial.
- Trinomial, awesome.
Go ahead and distribute
that and see what you get.
When you think you have an answer
do you wanna show it to
the person next to you
and see if you agree or disagree
with each other?
Alright, alrighty. So.
Any exciting disagreements?
- No.
- Nothing.  No one differs
from anyone else?
- No.
- Larry Thayer.
- He just forgot to write
his [inaudible] down.
- Okay, but now you're cool?
So, everybody either feels
like they got the same thing
or they fixed what thought they had?
Alright, that's boring.
Okay, so what do get when
you your first product done?
- Three X cubed.
- Alright, and then?
- 12 X squared.
- And then?
- Six X.
- Nothing, it's simplified.
- It's done? Okay.
So, we ended up with a cubic trinomial.
Now, here's what I wanna show you.
Somethin' a little different,
because what's the,
raise your hand if you can
tell me the verb we did here.
- Cubic?
- We been talkin' the verb.
- Distributed?
- We distributed
and we also what?
- Simplified.
- Which one's right?
They're both, we simplified
and we used distributing
in order to simplify.
Okay, so I'm gonna put a verb up here.
And I'll even put distribute because
that's specifically what we did.
Now, here's what I'm gonna do,
I'm gonna give you a different thing.
I'm gonna give you this.
I'm gonna give you
four A cubed
plus two A squared
minus 10 A.
And I'm gonna spice this
up just a little bit,
I'm sorry about that,
change that 10 A to a 40 A.
Alright.
- It's already simplified.
- It's already simplified, okay.
So, I can't give you simplify for a verb.
I'm gonna give you a different verb.
Now, there's a better word
than what I'm about to put up here.
This isn't really a math word,
we're gonna replace it with
a better one very shortly.
And here's a clue.
Undistributed.
How do you undistribute?
Let's shove this expression
that you said's already
simplified, in a time machine.
Imagine you got like a,
have you guys ever seen like
fast feed photography
where there's a seed?
And it's like they speed
up the footage
and you see the seed germinate
and you see the little stem grow,
and it's kind of all jerky
and everything.
Okay, can you imagine
playing that backwards
and you have a little sprout
and it goes back in and it
ends up as a little seed.
Right?
Imagine that this was on the page
as a final answer
and we put it in backwards
to see how it might have
started as a math problem.
- Do you use the [inaudible]?
- You can do that?
- Do you use like the factor tree?
- Say that a little louder, Alec.
- Do you use the factor trees?
- Alec, that's interesting
that you asked.
Alec is asking about our
warm-up problem today,
which was a throw-back to when you guys
were in elementary school
and you talked about
things called factor trees.
And with factor trees we talk about
how you can take a number
and use a sledgehammer
and kind of bust it up
[claps hands] into it's what?
- To it's factors.
- To its factors and we keep goin'
until we can't do it anymore, right?
Huh.
- The deal with that is
you have to figure out
what was originally inside and
outside of the parentheses.
You just gotta kinda
ignore the A, I guess.
- Even ignoring the A like,
I don't know if putting
it in a facts tree
you really put it into parentheses.
'Cause you don't really have a
whole lot to work with there,
to put it back into
parentheses, I don't know.
It's kinda going against
every fiber of my being and--
- [laughs] Like why would you
make a math problem out of
a perfectly nice number?
- Yeah.
- Okay, that's interesting,
we'll come back to that cuz
that's a really good point.
Why would you take like a 12
and turn it into a math
problem, what good does that do?
Yeah, what good is that?
We'll come back to that,
that's an excellent question.
With big answers.
Yes sir, what do you think?
- I forgot what I was gonna say.
- Ya sure?
Lauren, what d'ya think?
- Isn't this
kinda like checking it?
- Lauren just said something interesting.
She said "Isn't it
kinda like checking it?"
So, when you check an equation
for example, what do you do?
- Put it back in [inaudible].
- So, when you solve an equation,
it's kinda like tying a knot.
And then when you put it
in, put in the solution
and you check it it's kinda like
untying the knot to see
if comes out the same way.
- But we don't have an equation
to plug those into.
- You're right.
Carolyn, what were you gonna say?
- Okay, so you know how yesterday,
I know this is kind of off subject but I--
- That's okay.
- You know how yesterday like
you showed us this problem
on our worksheet and it was like
three times the binomial or whatever?
When you said we were
gonna do those today?
- Can you be specific with the problem
so I know what exactly.
- It was number 50 on--
- Oh, oh you mean the problems
that look like this.
- Yeah. the ones that we said
we've already done
but we really haven't.
- Like this?
And you guys wanted to make this,
what did you wanna make this?
[Inaudible]
X squared, oh it feels
so right, doesn't it?
We'll come back to that in a second.
That is sort of related to this.
What were you gonna say Zach
and then we'll take a closer look.
- I was just gonna say,
couldn't there be different,
like when you unsimplify that,
couldn't there be different answers?
Or is there only one correct answer?
- Can someone
restate what he's sayin' here?
Or what do you think he means by that?
Sam, what do you think he means by that?
- I think he means that
when like you unsimplify it
it can be with the two parentheses
or it can be with one parentheses
and the term in front of it.
- So, you're sayin' maybe
it's like this and there's
something here.
Or maybe, it's like this?
- Yeah.
- 'Cause this looks, I'll tell you,
this looks an awful lot
like the answer we got here.
And this didn't start off with a number
that was distributed
necessarily like this one.
It started off like this, didn't it?
- How do you figure out how
to throw it backwards?
'Cause that's just like...
- You know what,
let's start with the easier one.
Which one of those is less complicated,
the blue one or the orange one?
- The blue one.
- I'd agree, let's start with this way
and then maybe we can
go up to the orange.
So if I wanted to, again
this is not a math term,
we're gonna use a better
term in a little bit.
If I were to quote undistribute,
or use a vacuum cleaner
to suck something out
of all three of these terms,
would you agree that it
has to be the same thing
that we suck out of each one?
In other words, can I
pull a four out of this
and an eight out of this?
- yeah.
- Okay.  Any suggestions?
Let's just focus on the coefficients,
any suggestions on what I can pull out?
- A two.
- A two, okay.
Anything else?
- Four?
- Can I pull a four, let's go door to door.
Can he give me a four?
Can she?
So, if there was a four out there
I would have to think what was in there
to distribute a four two to make two.
I'm gonna avoid fractions here.
- Yeah see, he's avoiding fractions.
- I could,
I could technically pull out anything.
But with the factor tree we
did at the beginning of class,
typically when you talk
about, that's a good point.
When we talk about factors
we stick with whole numbers.
Okay?
Or maybe even integers,
but we usually don't go into fractions.
Sam, what're you thinkin'?
- To unsimplify it,
couldn't you put in one of those boxes
that we did yesterday for the terms?
Like put it in the middle
and then find
what it is?
- Oh yeah.
- Why, you're talkin'
when we were doing
[Background Chatter]
this.
And then ask ourselves
what would go here, that's
a weird question mark.
What would there
and what would go there?
That's interesting.
Alec, what are you thinking?
- Couldn't you take
out an A with that two?
Like on the problem?
- Since it all has A's?
If you can take out a,
can you put out an A,
like you took out the two?
[Background Chatter]
- Can he give up an A?
- Yes.
- She give up an A?
- Well, let's try that, let's
try that, that's interesting.
So if I were to quote, and again,
we're not gonna use this
word much after the next.
Would you, if you were
to quote undistribute
a two A from four A cubed,
what would that look like?
What would have to be here?
- It would have to be a two A squared.
- Well okay, let's keep goin'
and then we'll check to
see if this makes sense.
I'll get your question
in one second, Caroline.
So then what would be next?
[Background Chatter]
So, the two from the two
would leave a ghost one.
And then the A from the A
squared would be a what, Oscar?
- I was thinkin' one A.
- One A, alright I'd like that.
And then the two A from
the negative 40 A
would be a what?
- Negative 20.
- Negative 20 A?
[Background Chatter]
So, now we're back to
what Justin said.
We've taken a perfectly
nice, simplified polynomial
and turned it into a math problem.
Let's see if this is even right.
What do you think we could
do to check ourselves
like Lauren suggested?
- Do the problem.
- What do you mean do the problem?
- Simplified.
- Okay, so let's simplify it real quick.
What's two A times two A,
and no peeking?
- Four A squared.
- What's two A times two A cubed,
I mean squared?
Four A cubed, good.
And what's two A times A?
- That's two A squared.
- What kind?
Positive two A squared.
And two A times negative 20?
- Negative 40 A.
- Oh, it worked!
- Yeah. [clapping]
- I have a question.
- Yes, ma'am.
- What exactly is the point of this?
- That's an excellent question.
Shhhhhh, ready?
Why on earth would you
do such a horrible
rotten thing?
[Background Chatter]
Well, one day, shhhh.
One day what if you had this beast?
- Holy Cow!
- Whoa!
- Do you guys know where to start?
No, I don't know.
But, check this out.
Didn't you just say we
could take this and turn it?
That's the same thing we had, right?
So, can I factor that and turn that into
two A times two A squared
plus A minus 20?
Are you cool with that?
Are you okay if I just
leave the bottom?
Two A squared plus A minus 20.
Anybody have an idea
what might happen now?
[Background Chatter]
Did you guys know that
you've been doin' that
since the fourth grade?
- No.
- Yes, you have.
Just with much less obnoxious numbers.
What does 16/32,
what does that, let me use another.
What does that simplify to?
Here's why, you guys
probably already knew this.
Let's leave the 16 alone,
and isn't 32 two times 16?
- Yeah. Ohhh!
- That's the math.
That's the math that justifies
simplifying fractions
like you've been doin' since
you were like eight years old.
- That's cool.
- What other occasion,
this is gonna be helpful.
How do you undo plus or adding
when you're solving equations?
- Subtraction.
- Subtraction, you call in
the opposite, right?
How do you undo multiplication?
- You divide.
- Divide, well here's what
we're leading up to.
How are you gonna undo the squared?
Factoring busts up the squared for us.
And it's gonna be a very important tool
when we're solving,
what kind of equations
do you think we can call these?
[Background Chatter]
Think about it.
Look at the degree.
- Oh, quadratic.
- Quadratic equations.
[Background Chatter]
Alright, let's take a look
at another one.
Let me have you
undistribute one again.
We need a better word for this.
Did we call this unmulltiplying?
- No.
- What did we call the verb here,
what was the verb on this?
- Division?