-(background chatter)
- What if it comes from like
a polluted creek or something,
or some kind of bad water system
in the ground?
- Number three... (inaudible).
- I say crystal clear and filtered.
- I said how dirty the water gets.
- How good the water is for you?
-(background chatter)
- It doesn't have stuff dying in it,
it's crystal clear and it doesn't smell.
- [Teacher] Okay, class, if we can
pull back together please,
as a group, I was hearing
excellent discussions
between each of the three questions,
and I think we have some
very valuable points
to go ahead and talk about.
So, what we're gonna do is kind of create
a little bit of a list up here,
to help us remind later
when I go to show you something.
So, we're gonna start again
with that first question,
and I'm looking for you
to participate and share
some of those questions together.
So, it says again, how do you
know if water is safe or not?
And I heard wonderful responses,
so can I hear some of those please?
Brandon, please start us.
- Color and odor.
- [Teacher] Okay, so you
know if water is safe or not
depending on again, the color and the odor.
Good, what are some other responses?
Brandon?
- Remember where you got it from.
Like, if it was in a
creek that looks fine,
it's probably safe to drink,
but if it's from a polluted creek that has
a really weird color to it,
or it's in a weird location,
don't drink it.
- Okay, so I'm commenting here, I have, it
depends on the source
you're getting it from,
and so if it's a creek that
looks to be clean or clear,
then you know it's probably okay?
And if it looks to have like a weird color,
I think you mentioned again to it,
or polluted or in a weird location,
then maybe it's not safe.
All right, what were some
of your other responses?
Jack.
- Um, if it goes through a quality filter?
- Okay, if it goes
through a quality filter.
And Jack, can you maybe
think of an example
of a quality filter?
- A Culligan filter
for the drinking water?
- Okay, so a Culligan
filter that you can use
to filter out the water.
Okay, good. Madeline?
- There's no large pieces of
trash or anything in the water?
- [Teacher] Okay, so you
can look for visible signs
of large trash, and
Madeline, what was the second
part of that?
- Nothing that looks unnatural in it.
- [Teacher] Okay, so nothing
that looks unnatural. Great.
Anybody else, any answers for number one?
Again, how do you know
if it's safe or not?
Lexi, I think you had another answer that
may have been covered up here.
What did you say when I
was talking with your group
about... ?
- The smell?
- [Teacher] Okay, the smell,
again, the odor of it.
Okay, great.
Brandon, you thought of another one?
- If there's something dead in it.
- [Teacher] If there's
something dead in it,
so again, we're going
based on those visual
aspects of it. Good.
Well, we're gonna come back
to that here in just a moment,
so we'll move on to number two.
When are times when the
water might not be safe?
Walker?
- After an earthquake or another disaster?
- [Teacher] Okay, so after an earthquake.
And Walker, can I have
you expand a little bit?
What would be so significant
after an earthquake
or another disaster that
would make the water
not safe?
- Because maybe something fell in the water,
or, I don't know, I
just heard that before.
- [Teacher] Okay, so you heard it before,
and if something fell in the water.
Did you happen to see at all, in Japan
after the tsunami came through there?
Do you remember any of those images?
- Yeah kinda, they were different colors
and yeah...
- [Teacher] Okay, and I
think I heard somebody else
say that they remembered seeing a point
that maybe we can add onto. Elvis?
- [Elvis] At the beach.
- [Teacher] At the beach?
What do you mean by "at the beach?"
- There's different times where the water
might not be safe.
- [Teacher] Okay, can you
think of a specific example,
like have you experienced
a time when you weren't
allowed to be at the beach?
- When somethings dangerous in the water.
- [Teacher] Okay, if something's
dangerous in the water.
Sometimes they might tell
you that it's not safe
to be there. Okay.
Any other times that might
make the water not safe?
Amelia, can you think of
any times where the water
might not be safe?
- I have, after storms, like um, Walker did.
- [Teacher] Okay, what
are some things then,
because this is something
I'm hearing so far.
What are some things
after the storm that might
be in the water besides, I
think you said some stuff
can fall in the water.
What are some of the things
that might be in the water
that would make it not safe?
Aashi, can you think
of something that might
get in the water?
- Um, like tree branches or animals?
- [Teacher] Okay, so tree
branches and animals,
that's good.
Can you think of anything else that might
get in the water that maybe
wouldn't normally be there?
Kris?
- Trash?
- [Teacher] Trash, okay.
Can you think of a specific kind of trash?
Lexi?
- Glass?
- [Teacher] Glass. And
what would be the danger
of glass getting in the water?
- It's sharp and can cut yourself.
- [Teacher] Okay, so there's
a chance of getting injured
if you cut yourself.
What else... think outside
the box a little bit more.
What else could get in the
water that you would not
normally want in your water?
Madeline?
- Plastic bags and then
you can suffocate animals.
- [Teacher] Okay, so
plastic bags that they
suffocate animals,
something along those lines.
Elvis?
- Oil and gasoline?
- [Teacher] Oil and gasoline, good.
Brandon?
- Toxins.
- [Teacher] Toxins, okay. Jack?
- Plastic six-pack holders?
Because it strangles
the fish and everything.
- [Teacher] Okay, now lets think...
I'm glad you guys are all concerned
about the fish and the
animals and all of that,
but what about we as
humans, can you think of
anything that would get
in the water that would be
potentially harmful to us afterward?
Go ahead.
- Pesticides?
- Pesticides, okay. Brandon?
- Fertilizer?
- [Teacher] Fertilizers. Elvis?
- A car?
What is it again?
- A car.
- [Teacher] A car, okay.
All right, well we'll come back
to those in just a minute.
So, looking at... we've kind of
come up with a list here
of how you would determine
if things are safe or not.
So, then I guess my question would become,
if you look at it's color
and you look at if it's in
a source that looks safe or
not, how would you be able
to determine if something
is safe to drink?
So, maybe that might
change your perspective
a little bit.
So, is there a difference
between being able to drink
something, and maybe being
able to swim in something?
In fact, let me give you just
a minute to talk about that
with your partner for a minute.
so, my question to you again,
is it... are there different things
we should look for in water
that we drink, versus maybe
water that we swim in or take a shower in?
And I want you to talk
about that with your partner
and jot down a couple notes
about that, so go ahead.
- (students talking with each other)
-(background chatter)
- [Student] That's
interesting to hear you saying
shower water isn't as filtered
as your drinking water.
- Our pool is safe, they
put a water cover over
our pool so it was different.
At our pool they changed from...
too much chlorine can burn people's eyes,
so they changed it.
Yeah, definitely a bigger job,
but they put a small
amount of chlorine in it,
so all the bacteria that's on us,
if you go swim in the
pool it wouldn't matter,
as opposed to in the shower
because it's different.
- Even if you do have a water cover,
still it could seep through,
and that's how they clean it.
- When they open the
pool it takes like a month,
because they have to go
through the water thing,
and all the filters.
- [Teacher] Okay, we'll come
back together as a group
one more time.
Thank you all, again I hear
great discussions going on.
So, let's talk about this.
There's some very neat
ideas of whether you think
something is safe to drink
versus whether or not
it's okay to shower or to swim in.
So, what were some comments
you were talking about
in your smaller groups?
Again, I heard some great
discussions going on.
Mikenna, what did your group talk about?
- Shower water isn't as
filtered as drinking water.
- [Teacher] Okay, so in
their group they believe
that shower water was
not as filtered as what
the water is that you drink
in, so if it's not as filtered,
where would your drinking
water be coming from
that maybe your shower
water isn't coming from?
Okay, is there a reason
that maybe you thought
along sometime where the
shower water is not as
filtered as your drinking water?
- No.
- [Teacher] No, okay.
It just makes sense to
you that maybe the stuff
that comes out of the tap
to drink, is not necessarily
the same thing coming out of
your pipes for the shower?
Okay, what were some
other comments about that?
Larry, what did you guys talk about?
- (inaudible)
- (beeping)
- [Announcer on loud speaker] May I have
your attention please?
- Would all Spelling Bee winners
please report to the
auditorium at this time
for the Spelling Bee.
Again, all Spelling Bee
winners please report
to the auditorium at this
time for the Spelling Bee.
Thank you.
- [Teacher] Okay, so Larry,
to expand upon that,
and I think he brought
up a really good point.
He said that maybe the water that you...
were you saying, Larry,
swimming or showering?
- [Isaiah] He was saying
that the water we drink...
- Hold on just one second,
Isaiah, just one second.
- (inaudible)
- Okay good, I wanted to
make sure I wasn't saying it
incorrectly.
So, what he was saying is, in other words,
when you shower or when
you are going swimming,
that water is not necessarily
going in your body,
you're not consuming that water,
so there would be a difference possibly,
between the water you're swimming in
versus the water that
you're drinking. Walker?
- I said that you would
swim in darker water
than you drink or shower in.
- Okay, so sometimes you
think that the water you've
been in when you swim is darker.
So, going back to the
color difference that
talked about here.
Okay, interesting. Lexi?
- The shower water and
the water that we drink
I think is sort of the
same, but they go through a
different process, but
if we go swimming at our
community pool, it's
different because there's more
chlorine and stuff, so
you have bacteria on you
and you're just swimming,
you not really intaking it.
But at your house when you
drink or take a shower,
it's different.
- [Teacher] Okay. Would you say that...
Because I think it's
probably safe to say you guys
mostly agree that there
is a difference between
drinking water and water
you would shower in
versus water that maybe
you would go swimming in.
So, what are some of those differences?
What might be... what might
they have to do to that water?
Lexi was talking about
maybe it would have to be
treated differently, or that
there would be chemicals
added to it.
So, can you think of what
they would do to the water
in a swimming pool, versus
water that you drink
to make it different?
I think Jack mentioned about filtering,
and Mikenna also brought
up the point about
it being filtered different.
Brandon?
- Well, they put more
chemicals in the swimming pool,
because there's gonna be more germs
and when people swim in it, so
that will kill off the germs.
As in drinking water is
not as much chemicals
because there's not really any germs,
you're just drinking it, so...
- Okay, good. So, what I'm hearing
is the amount of something...,
so would you all agree, as a class,
if we were to drink swimming
water, would you die?
- [All] No.
- No, probably not, right?
But the amount of the
chemical that is in the water
might be something that
would cause some effects
or cause some harm to you.
So, do you think that there is chlorine
in your drinking water?
Because we said it's in
the swimming pool probably
to help kill off bacteria.
Do you think that... and
I'm hearing a little bit
of a disagreeance here,
so I'd love to hear
your conversation in just a minute.
Elvis, what do you think?
- There is chlorine in the drinking water,
but then they purify it, so...
- [Teacher] So they
purify out the chlorine
after they put the chlorine
into the drinking water?
- Yeah.
- [Teacher] Okay, good.
And Isaiah, what were you thinking about?
I think you were saying no,
that there isn't the chlorine.
- My question is, if there was
chlorine in drinking water,
I mean, you can purify it,
but it may still stay around
that water, then why would you drink it?
I mean, sure, it can knock out
the bacteria and germs,
but why drink it if it has chlorine in it?
Because that's not good for you.
- [Teacher] Okay, and going
back to the amounts of it,
and you're thinking that
even the smallest amount
might not be healthy for
you to put in your system.
Okay, Jack?
- Well, for a normal tap system,
I think it's the last, or
second last step they do,
is they insert really
small amount of chlorine
into all tap water,
usually in a normal town.
And, so then a lot of people have chlorine
in their drinking water,
but for some people who
have specialized filters
for drinking water, they're
designed to filter out
all of the chlorine so
that it's mostly just water
that they're getting.
So, some people have a filter installed.
- Okay, and would you be able
to tell based on the color,
because that seems to be what
a lot of people are using
as their indicator of good water.
Would you be able to
tell just by the color
whether or not there's
a lot of chlorine in it?
- [Elvis] Maybe, maybe not.
I don't know if this contributes to it,
but sometimes I look at
my drinking water compared
to the tap water, and the tap
water is a lot more foggy,
so I don't know if that's
because the chlorine
or because it's aerated or
something, but I don't know.
- [Teacher] Okay good,
thank you for sharing that.
Elvis.
- You can buy those little
filters that you can
screw onto your taps
so that way it filters
down the water.
I have one and it filters out tap water.
- [Teacher] Okay, and it's
filtering out more of the
amount, or maybe none of it at all. Okay.
Let's go back... oh, go ahead Madeline.
- I would just like to
say to Isaiah's comment,
we sort of have to have
chlorine in our water
because there would be
more bacteria if we didn't,
so there's a reason for
it, and it's not that much.
So, it would do you less harm to have
the chlorine in the water
than to not have it.
- [Teacher] Okay, so the
benefits of what you're saying
is that you would at least
have to have a little bit
to kill off the bacteria, and
that would outweigh the fact
of you not having anything at
all, and then being exposed
to maybe whatever is in the
water that the chlorine
is not killing off,
right? Okay, very good.
Let's look at...
We've used, again, some
criteria, and let's look at
that final question of,
what is your definition
of water quality?
So, in other words, I think Jordan,
I heard in your discussion,
could you read your answer
for us one more time
about what you think water
quality is to you?
- Water quality is how
good the water is for you
to drink.
- [Teacher] Good, how good
the water is for you to drink.
Can I hear another
definition of water quality?
Kris, what did you decide?
- [Kris] How clean the water was?
- [Teacher] How clean the water was, okay.
And how would you determine
if the water is clean or not?
What was your number one indicator?
- [Kris] When you drink it.
- [Teacher] When you drink it, okay.
So, if you drink it and you
know that it's clean,
then it has good water
quality to it. All right.
Isaiah?
- My definition of water
quality is how much of the water
is polluted, and how much
of the water is pure.
- [Teacher] So, polluted versus pure
and then kind of a ratio of if
it's polluted and more pure
then it's better water quality. Okay.
Rachel, how about your
definition of water quality?
- We said that water quality
was how much of the water
is pure water, and how
much of it's polluted.
- [Teacher] Okay, so going
back to that same definition
together as you all talked.
And Ashani, what did you
think water quality would be?
- How good the water
is because some water,
it like tastes different, you can tell.
- [Teacher] Okay, so the taste.
Have you ever experienced
where water might
taste a little different,
can you think of an example?
- My aunt's house, when we go to her house
it's always different from our house.
- [Teacher] And what kind
of taste would you say?
- It's gross.
- (laughing) It's gross water.
Maybe back to when we were
talking about well water
in here versus the regular city water,
and it has a different taste to it.
So, what we're gonna do,
is using your ideas so far,
you guys have told me
again based on color,
and you mentioned about the smell of it,
and you've mentioned
about tasting the water.
So, I have here three different
liquids that I'm going
to go around and show
you, and on your paper,
you're going to determine
if these liquids are safe
or if these liquids are not.
And since we have already
discussed that there's
probably different qualities
for your water versus
the water you drink versus
the water that you swim in
or the water that you are
going to take a shower in,
so when you comment upon
whether those liquids are safe
or not, I think it would
probably be a wise decision
to comment if you think
they're safe to drink versus
safe to shower or to swim.
So, I'll start here with cup letter A.
So, you can go ahead and
mark "A" on your paper,
and then I will walk around
so you can just take an
observation of the liquid.
And you determine, again,
if you think that it is safe.
- [Teacher] All right, so what do
you all think? Logan?
Do you think that this is safe to drink?
So, if I gave this to you right now,
you'd go ahead and drink it
because it would be safe?
- [Logan] No.
- [Teacher] No? What would make you change your answer then?