- You each have your own set
And I'm going to ask you to put them out in front of you
in... in... so you can see all the words.
Can we put them in two rows?
One, Two, three, four, five, six. Let's put
them in two rows.
One, two, three, four, five six. Now..
- I wanna play-
- Wait a minute, show me, I'm going to ask you to point.
So get your pointer finger in, show me, 'under'.
Yes, under good. Take a look at the word, under, good.
Wait, keep it there. Show me... now be careful.
We want to get all the letters. Show me 'there'.
Listen to the word, good Jessica. 'There'
That's Okay, he's gotta look. He's gonna do it.
Very good. Put it down. Good. Ready? Alright.
Be careful with this one, listen to my words.
Ready? Show me 'Saw'. Good. Excellent, alright.
Show me, ready? 'They' alright. Excellent. Alright.
Show me 'was'. Wow. That's good. Show me 'want'
Alright now. You did a great job. Now we're going to
hide your words so turn your cards over all by yourself.
Now you can't see them, right. Keep them in the rows.
Good. Alright, keep them in a row. Alright now, oh
your going to do it that way?
Okay, wait a minute now.
Now we're going to take turns. Let's see who's
sitting nicely. Alright.
You're going to turn over a card, Lewis, and
tell me what the word is.
Put it down. 'Want' I want my toys. I want my
toys, yes, good. You turn over a card.
Oh, what's your word?
- 'Under' - I see the cat under the bed,
alright. Lewis, turn over another card.
- 'under' - oh you got under as well, what's
your sentence? - [Lewis] I am hiding under the bed.
- I am hiding under the bed, that's a good one.
- Under the table.
Let's see Jessica, go ahead do another one.
Now think, look at your letters.
- [Jessica] 'was'? - Yes
- I was eating. -[Teacher] I was eating, Good.
Look at your letters, let them help you. Don't help.
- 'They'- 'There' - There, yes!
- There is my toy in the bed.
There is my toy in the bed, Okay, alright,
how about you Jess? Oh what do you have?
-'There' - Good, can you use it?
- [Jessica] There is a car in my mail.
- There is a car in your mail? Wow!
That would be interesting.
Alright Lewis, your turn. Now look
at your letters, let them help you.
-'They'?
- Yes! - [Lewis] They was a cat in my car.
Okay, this, there was a cat in my car.
They tried to get the cat out of the car.
Okay? They belongs... means people. They, Okay?
Let's see what you have. Oh look at you.
- Today is the day. Aaah, this word is 'they'.
The children, that would be they. Let's take
a look at this word, this is one we are misunderstanding.
They. Jessica and Lewis, they came to
the reading group. Okay?
They had turkey for Thanksgiving.
They have, alright?
- They came to my birthday. - They came to my
birthday. Can you think of a sentence for they?
- They...
- What did your brothers do?
- They play basketball. - There you go, they
play basketball, there you go, that's better.
Okay. You have another card to turn over.
- But it's my turn.
- I got mixed up. - [Jessica] I got Lakers socks.
- You got what?
- [Jessica] Nothing.
-Say that again?  What did you say about the...
- I got socks.
- No, this is 'saw'.
This is I saw you when I, I saw a movie.
- I saw a big alligator.
- I saw a big alligator
-I saw a dinosaur
- I saw a dinosaur. Last one.
- 'was'
- was , Okay
- Where was my friend?
- Where was my friend, good.
- I want candy. - I want candy, Okay. Now watch what
I'm going to do. I'm going to put the cards together.
I'm going to mix them up and I'm going
to turn them over.
We're going to play our matching game,
okay? Alright. What happened?
My brother put gum in there and when
I point I can't get out of there.
Oh boy, alright, now, Jessica,
you went first before, right?
So we have Lewis go first this time?
Would that be fair?
-Yes
Alright, Lewis, you're going to turn over a card,
you're going, now listen to me.
Listen to me. This is how we're going to play.
You're going to turn over a card, and you're going to read it.
Then you're going to turn over another card,
then you're going to read it. Wait a minute, wait a minute.
If, look at me sweetie. If, you get a match,
you want to keep the pair.
You have to put the word in a sentence.
Can you do that? Let's see. Go ahead.
Okay, take a look. Take a look, take a look.
Shh don't tell him, don't tell him.
'Was'. This word is 'was'. Let's see, okay, now pay
attention Jessica, so you can remember where they are.
Your turn. Pick another card Lewis.
Oh, it's so close. What word is this? - Saw
- saw. Okay. Here is was. Turn it over, turn it over.
And here's saw. Good, Okay, Jessica's turn.
- 'Want'
- Good, 'want'. She read it.
- They. - Not a match. Good, wait a minute, wait a minute,
wait, before you do that. Wait, before you do that.
- They want
- They want candy.
- Okay, watch Lewis. Who remembers what was this
one? What was this one? No peeking.
Do you remember what it was Jessica?
- 'Was'
- Was, good. What was this one? Saw. What was this one?
- 'They' - [Teacher] and what was this one?
- 'Want' - [Teacher] Good, alright.
- 'They' - No its not they. Careful,
take another close look. Look at the whole word.
There. Now sorry about that. Good... good...
- 'They!' - Is it a match, is that a match?
No, but we've seen that word. What's this word?
They. Go to your chair now and sit.
Okay. There and they.
I'm going to hide them again.
Now let's see if Jessica remembers.
- They and they. - Okay now stop. You want
to use it in a sentence. Let's see how we do.
- They have a dog. - They have a dog.
Good job. Alright you get that one.
Okay, Lewis, let's see how you do. Go ahead.
You can do it. Oh! What's that word?
- Under. - [Teacher] Under, Pick another one.
- 'under' !
- No way! Alright! Under. Okay, let's see a nice sentence.
I'm going to listen for a good one.
- I am under, my brother can't find me because
I'm under the table.
- Your brother can't find you because you're
under the table. Can you give me a sentence for under?
Um, I hide under the bed.
- I hide under the bed, excellent, okay. Now it's Jessi- Oh!
- Want.
- Do you remember where it was Jessica?
Wow! Now wait a minute, let's see if
you can think of a sentence. Jessica first.
- I want a cake.
- I want a cake. What would you want?
- I want a brownie- - I want a ice cream.
- [Teacher] Okay, Okay, alright, try another one.
Oh! Is that match?
- No
- No, what's this word Lewis? - [Lewis] They
- Come back over here and take a good look at it. This word is saw.
- Jessica's going to get it.
- Now wait a minute, maybe not, maybe not.
- 'saw'
- uh-eh-eh-ah-uh. - [Jessica] 'was'
Was, okay. Yeah, but that's okay, those two we mixed up.
Let's take a good, close look at them.
Which one is was?
Which one is saw? Okay, alright, now listen to
your first sound.
I'm going to hide them again. Let's see
if we can remember. Go ahead Lewis. Your turn.
- Was - and which one? - [Lewis] Was.
- There you go, was. Give me a sentence for was.
- I was in my bed.
- I was in my bed. Let's hear Jessica's sentence for was.
I was... I was in the bus.
- I was in the bus, alright. Let's see,
pick another one. Take a look at the first letter.
- Saw. Okay, and what's that one?
- saw.
- Okay, now a sentence for saw. Wait a minute,
before you count your card. A sentence for saw.
I saw.. something you see.
- oh, I saw a, saw a... candy.
You saw a candy, where was the candy?
- On the floor. - I saw candy on the floor?
Did your little brother dump it on the floor?
Okay
- I would eat it.
- You have the last one.
- They. - It's not they, I want you to think again.
Look at all the letters. Don't tell him, don't tell him.
There. Okay, give me a sentence,
wait a minute, give me a sentence with it.
- There was a huge table.
- There was a huge table where?
- In my kitchen. - There was a huge table
in my kitchen, before you count your cards,
can you give me a sentence with the
word 'there'?
- There is a snowman at the window.
There is a snowman on the window,
what a great sentence. How many cards do you have?
- one, two, three, four, five, six, seven.
- I got six.
Alright, we're going to do one more thing with these
words to practice.
We have a word that we are having trouble with.
We're going to come over here. Over to the board.
We're going to take a look at this word that we're
having trouble with.
Thank you for getting her a marker. I'm going
to ask you to write this word on the board.
Oh a line, you know what she's telling you, right?
Okay, let's take a look at this word. Are you ready?
This word is, Jess, that's good. Alright.
This word is saw. Let's see if we can write it.
Saw. Jessica, I want you to write saw.
Look at the word. There it is. Saw, Okay.