- And why face changes are
different at different pressures.
And so I think that at a certain
pressure, they're so close
together that they
aren't a gas anymore
and they become a liquid.
- Cool.
- Because the difference
between a liquid and a solid
with the atoms is that the solids or,
the difference between a
liquid and a gas with the atoms
is that the gases are more spread out.
And the liquids can still move freely,
but they're more close together, so.
- Okay.
- We thought that in a liquid, they can't
move as freely as it can in gas.
- Yeah.
- Well, another gas has to expand,
well it does expand to fill
its container.
- Yeah.
So does that have anything
to do with how they move?
- Well, you said that some,
tried to, sometimes they
don't always expand
as much as they can,
but I think they do.
My guess is probably
the distance between
the molecules is based
on how big the space is
'cause you think of pressed gas.
- What are you guys all thinking about
of what you're hearing?
- Well...
- Do things sound reasonable?
- Yeah.
- Is this a question that we need to
maybe think about a little bit more?
Just how spread out do things
have to be to be a gas?
At what point does that
matter or not matter?
- Uh-huh.
- Okay.
[students laugh]
We're gonna keep that one on the books
for something we need to check into.