- [Teacher] Read.
- I want to go first.
- [Teacher] I want to go first. Read.
- Let's play a game.
- [Teacher] Let's play a game. Let's read.
- Put the picture on the table.
- [Teacher] Put the picture on the table.
Read.
- [inaudible]
- [Teacher] What? Say it again.
- Your turn.
- [Teacher] Your turn. Read.
- No match.
- [Teacher] No match.
- I go again.
- [Teacher] I go again.
- I got a match.
- [Teacher] I got a match. Very good,
Alex. Last set. Read.
- Will you...
- [Teacher] Sit up! What--
- [Teacher] You--
- You win.
- [Teacher] You win, good. Read.
- Good game.
- [Teacher] Good game. Good, read.
- All done.
- [Teacher] All done and read.
- I win!
- [Teacher] I win. All right, Alex. Put
these here. All right, ready? Alex, let's
shoot.
- Let's?
- [Teacher] Let's--
- Let's play a game!
- [Teacher] Let's play a game, all right?
- Put the pictures on the table.
- [Teacher] Put the pictures on the table.
So let's put the pictures on the table.
I'm going to give you some, I'm going to
give you some, and I'll take some. And
let's put them in a line. Like this, Alex.
There we go. Right here, start right here.
There we go. I'll start down here. Good
job. Don't look at them. Good job. Put
them there. There we go. There we
go. Put-- you start right there, Shanidra. All
right. Put them right here, Alex. Put some
right there. There we go, put one right
there. Put that one here. There we go. Put
that one there. There we go, Alex. Put one
right here. And put the last one right
there. Good job. Let's put these right
here, all right? What do you say?
- I want to go first.
- [Teacher] I want to go first. Okay.
Here.
- I got--
- [Teacher] Hold on, let's. All right. You
ready? Okay, you wanted to go first, go
ahead and go first.
- Hot dog.
- [Teacher] Hot dog.
- Dinosaur
- [Teacher] What?
- [Teacher] --saur. What do we say?
- No match.
- [Teacher] What?
- [Teacher] No match.
- Your turn.
- [Teacher] Look at her and tell her.
- [Teacher] Your turn. Go ahead, Shanidra.
Oooo, dinosaur. I think we saw that one.
Where was it? I don't remember.
What do you say? You got a match, you get
to go again. All right, go again! See, she
got a match, Alex. She gets to go again.
- Cheese.
- [Teacher] Cheese? What is this Alex?
- [Teacher] Okay.
- Crayon.
- [Teacher] Crayons.
- No match, your turn.
- [Teacher] My turn. Hmm. Crayons, hot dog!
Did I get a match, Alex?
- No.
- [Teacher] No match. No match. Your turn, Alex.
- Butterfly.
- [Teacher] Butterfly.
- Presents
- [Teacher] Presents.
- No match.
- [Teacher] Anybody else, say it?
- Your turn!
- [Teacher] Make sure you look at
her, there you go. Say it again!
- Your turn.
- [Teacher] And look at her.
- [Teacher] Your turn, very good.
- Crayons
- Trains.
- [Teacher] Trains. Does she have a match,
Alex?
- No.
- [Teacher] No.
- No match, your turn.
- [Teacher] My turn! Cheese, hot dog! No
match. Your turn, Alex. What is that?
- Train?
- [Teacher] Train.
- Train!
- [Teacher] Train!
- I've got a match. I go again.
- [Teacher] I've got a match, I go again.
Put them here, let's face them this way.
All right, go again.
- Bicycle.
- [Teacher] Bicycle.
- Fish.
- [Teacher] Fish.
- No match.
- [Teacher] No, no put it back. Put it
back. Flip it over, what do you say?
- No match.
- [Teacher] And then?
- Your turn!
- [Teacher] Good job, Alex.
- Bear.
- [Teacher] Bear.
- Watermelon.
- [Teacher] Ah, watermelon. No match.
- Your turn.
- [Teacher] Your turn. Come on, Alex.
Flower, monkey. Is that a match?
- No.
- [Teacher] No! Your turn Alex.
- Bicycle.
- [Teacher] Bicycle.
- Cookie.
- [Teacher] Cookie.
- [inaudible]
- [Teacher] Say it again, I can't hear!
- No match.
- [Teacher] No match.
- Your turn.
- Cheese. Crayons
- [Teacher] Did she get a match, Alex?
Alex, did she get a match?
- No.
- [Teacher] No, she did not get a match.
- I know where crayons is.
- [Teacher] Okay, you know where the
crayons are? Let's put these up and
let's watch the game. Watch. Ball. Hot
dog! That hot dog was somewhere over
here. Hot dog, no match. Your turn, Alex.
- Hot dog!
- [Teacher] Right there, face them
down, there we go. What do we say?
- I got a match.
- [Teacher] A match. You go--
- I go again.
- [Teacher] You go again.
- Ball. Cake.
- [Teacher] What is that? I didn't see it.
What is that?
- Cake.
- [Teacher] Cake. Good, there we go. What
do we say?
- No match?
- [Teacher] No match, and then?
- Your turn!
- [Teacher] Very good. Crayons and?
- Butterfly.
- [Teacher] Butterfly!
- No match, your turn!
- [Teacher] My turn. Crayons and crayons.
Woohoo! I got a match. I go again! I'm
going to go again. Cake, oh, it was
somewhere over here. Let's try that one.
Oh, cake! I've got a match! I
go again! Fish, watermelon--
- I know where the other fish is!
- [Teacher] You know where the fish was?
No match. Did I get a match, Alex?
- No.
- [Teacher] No. Your turn, Alex. Well
you've gotta wait - put it there until you get the match.
- Fish!
- [Teacher] There you go, now you can get
it. What do we do? There we go. What do we
say?
- I've got a match!
- [Teacher] I've got a--
- I go again.
- [Teacher] You go again. Okay, go again,
Alex. Those go there. Oh ho! What is that,
Alex?
- No match.
- [Teacher] Was that a match?
- No.
- [Teacher] So put it back.
- I put this...
- [Teacher] Yeah, I'm betting you're
thinking you know where it is. So what do
you tell Shanidra? You said, 'no match!'
so what do you tell Shanidra?
- Your turn!
- [Teacher] Oh! It's not there either! She
didn't get it either. What do you tell me?
- No match, your turn.
- [Teacher] Hmm. Pencil, teddy bear.
Uh-oh, that's where it was. No match,
Alex. Your turn!
- Butterfly, butterfly.
- [Teacher] Wow, I haven't seen the
butterfly. What do we do, Alex?
- I've got a match!
- [Teacher] All right. Put it there.
- Hey, good.
- [Teacher] Yeah, very good! And what do
you say?
- I've got a match!
- [Teacher] No, I've got a match.
- I've got a match, I go again.
- [Teacher] You go again.
- Teddy bear. Got it!
- [Teacher] You got it.
- All right!
- [Teacher] All right, Alex! What do you
say?
- I've got a match.
- [Teacher] Match.
- I go again.
- [Teacher] All right, and what do we do
with them? Very good, we put them there.
Good job. All right, go again.
- Pencil. Cheese.
- [Teacher] Cheese.
- No match.
- [Teacher] No match.
- Your turn!
- [Teacher] Very good, Alex!
That's the same one you picked out cheese.
No match. [Sneezes]
Ah, bless you, Alex. All
right, go ahead. Do a tell me.
No match.
- Your turn.
- [Teacher] Very good. Cheese. Monkey.
- Monkey.
- [Teacher] No match! Your turn! Pencil?
- Cookie.
- [Teacher] Cookie! What do we say?
- No match.
- [Teacher] What do you tell Shanidra?
- [Teacher] Look up there. Look at her,
now tell her.
- Your turn!
- Very good!
- [Teacher] Flip it over. Try. How about
pencil, do you remember where that one
was? Try that one. What do you say? You
got a match?
- I got a match.
- [Teacher] You get to go again, there you
go. Go again. She got a match, Alex. She
gets to go again. What's that, monkey?
- Watermelon.
- [Teacher] Watermelon.
- No match, your turn.
- [Teacher] My turn. Presents.
Oh, I don't remember where
they were! Bicycle! No match, no match.
Your turn, Alex.
- Flower.
- [Teacher] Flower.
- Monkey.
- [Shanidra] I know where the monkey is.
- [Teacher] Oh.
- No match?
- [Teacher] Look at her, what do you say?
- Your turn.
- [Teacher] Look at her, look at her.
- [Teacher] There you go. There we go.
- Ball. Presents.
- [Teacher] Presents.
- No match, your turn.
- [Teacher] My turn. Hmm, I think, hmm.
Let's see. Monkey? Oh, I forget which one
it was. Oh, flower! It wasn't that one.
Did I get a match?
- No.
- [Teacher] Did I get a match?
- [Teacher] No. Your turn, Alex. What is
that?
- Monkey.
- [Teacher] Monkey? Monkey. Good!
- You're right!
- [Teacher] You got it, you're right. Put
it there. What do we say?
- I got a match.
- [Teacher] Match. Take your finger. All
right, what do we say?
- I go again.
- [Teacher] I go again. Ball.
- Ball.
- [Teacher] Get another match?
- I got a match! I go again.
- [Teacher] There you-- that's it. Go
again, Alex.
- Cookie, cookie! You got it.
- [Teacher] You got another one. Put it
down, what do we say? What do we say,
Alex?
- I got a match, I go again.
- [Teacher] Put it there.
- Ball, ball.
- Oh, Okay!
- [Teacher] You got one. What do we do? We
put it down. What do you say?
- I got a match. I go again.
- [Teacher] All right. Go again.
- Bicycle.
- [Teacher] Bicycle. What?
- No match.
- [Teacher] No, take your fingers out of
your mouth. What do we say? No match?
- Your turn!
- [Teacher] Try that one. Cheese. Let's
put that that way. There we go.
- I got a match.
- [Teacher] You go again. Go again. Hmm.
Bicycle.
- No match. Your turn.
- [Teacher] Right. Let's see. Did she get
a match, Alex?
- No match.
- [Teacher] No, my turn. Bicycle. Bicycle.
I got a match. I go again. Watermelon.
- Presents.
- [Teacher] Presents. Did I get a match?
- No. No match.
- [Teacher] No match. Your turn, Alex.
- Watermelon. Watermelon.
- [Teacher] You got it.
- I got a match. I got a match. I go
again. Presents. Presents. Very good!
- [Teacher] Very good! All right, put them
right there. Put them right on. And then,
now it's over, so what do we say?
- All done?
- [Teacher] All done, we're all done. Now
let's count how many matches. Let's start
with Alex, Okay? Put your matches this
way, Okay? Let's count the matches. Let's
count Shanidra's. Ready? Let's see how
many she got. Ready? Count with me.
- [Together] One, two, three.
- [Teacher] Let's see how many I got.
- [Teacher] Now let's count Alex's, ready?
- [Children together] One, two, three,
four, five, six, seven, eight, nine--
- [Teacher] Eight.
- [Together] Eight, nine, ten.
- [Teacher] Ten, eleven. Let's do that one
more time, Alex. Point to each one.
- [Together] One, two, three, four, five,
six, seven, eight, nine, ten, eleven.
- [Teacher] There you go, 11. What do
you say?
- I win!
- [Teacher] You win, good job. Give me
five! Give me five! Give Shanidra five!
Good job guys.