- [teacher] How do you know?
- Because my dad works
[inaudible].
- [teacher] Oh, okay. See, I want us to
think about that, because that was
something that came up yesterday.
Sometimes we think, "Oh that's only stuff
men do," or, "That's only stuff women
do." But, especially mechanics working on
engines and stuff like that, we think,
"That's a man's job." But you said your
dad works with a lot of women, and Kyle,
your dad's a kind of a mechanic, too, and
he works with a lot of women, too. So
girls, think about that kind of thing.
Okay, thank you, very good. All right, now
Carter come up, please, Carter?
All right, Carter. Tell us
about the job.
- [inaudible] works on
people when they are injured, firefighters
work on burning equipment and carrying
test hydrants, and inspect businesses.
- [teacher] Okay, so your job is... ?
- [inaudible]
- Say it real loud so they can hear you.
- A firefighter and a paramedic.
- [teacher] Okay, and what are the skills
that that job uses?
- Math, reading, writing,
computer technology.
- [teacher] There it is.
- Be proactive, begin with the
end in mind, first thing's first, think
win-win, synergize, [inaudible].
- [teacher] Great, okay. So all of the
seven habits, right? Okay, interesting,
who's next? And are there women
firefighters
- Yes
- [teacher] and paramedics? Absolutely.
Good job, Carter. Okay, Taylor, Taylor
Green.
All right, Taylor, tell us the
job.
- A machinist.
- [teacher] And tell us a little bit about
what they do.
- Repair and [inaudible]
turbine engines for helicopters and tanks.
- [teacher] Helicopters and tanks, and
they use what?
- Math, technology, be proactive.
- [teacher] Okay, very good. Do you think
women can do that kind of job?
- Yes
- [teacher] Absolutely.
Okay, so we said math, technology are big
ones there working on the helicopters,
tanks, things like that. Okay, next let's
have Lexi, Lexi Wilson. All right, Lexi.
All right, tell us about your job.
- Furniture showroom manager. I
assist customers with furniture,
purchases, inventory, the furniture we
have on hand, update customers' orders.
- [teacher] All right, and we use what
skills?
- Math, science.
Oh, I wasn't watching you.
- [teacher] That's okay, not so much
science.
- Reading, writing, computer
technology.
Be proactive, put first things
first, think win-win and synergize.
- [teacher] Okay, now I'm gonna ask you a
hard question. Science, the person with
that job indicated they use science in a
furniture showroom management position.
How do you think they use science?
- Maybe they make the furniture.
- [teacher] The materials maybe they use,
and stuff like that. Good, good job, all
right, thank you. Okay, so we can see that
all of the skills that we're learning in
school right now, especially technology
skills, computer skills, reading, math,
even science, our parents are using those
jobs, uh, skills in their jobs right now in real
life. So someday, you're gonna be using
exactly what you're doing right now in a
job, as well as our personal skills, our
seven habit skills, being in charge of
ourselves, thinking about things ahead of
time, planning ahead, putting first things
first, good job.
All right, now we're gonna
take our group cards, and on the cards you
have a job listed, one of the jobs that
you're looking at in your group, and a
skill that goes along with that job. What
I want you to do is, as a group discuss,
how can we show the use of that skill in
our job that we have, okay? So look at
your cards, figure out how you're gonna
use the skill listed on the skill card,
and then we're gonna role-model to the
rest of the class the use of our skill and
show how we use that skill in the job
that's on that card, okay? So start
discussing, and then in a few minutes, I'm
gonna call you back and we're gonna start
showing the rest of the class our skills.
- We're the paralegal. We could
do, well for reading skills, we could do
filing or we could prepare bills for
clients. But to prepare bills for clients,
we'd have to read you know, who they are,
and then for filing we'd have to read
whose bill it was.
- [intercom] Class, when your children get
ready for heading where they go down to
gym for the program this morning, we are
right now in the process of calling
kindergarten, we're gonna get them to head
down the hallway to the gym first, and
then we're going to have second grade come
on down, third grade, fourth grade and
fifth grade [inaudible].
- Okay, so Payton is gonna lay on
the floor, and then I'm gonna get to do a
knee surgery on him. First I'll like get a
pencil, pretend I'm cutting the knee open
and pulling it, and then cutting the
muscle, and replacing the broken parts of
the knee bone with--
- Like using our skills, we can
measure the wire right here.
- And we could measure how long
it could be for the house electricity
circuits, and we can measure how long the
wire is, and somebody could be in the
house and we could measure how long the
wire is.
- So, let's do the thing we did
yesterday. When you're laying on the floor
and I'm trying to put the breath back in
you, and then I ask Carly what happened,
okay.
- So you two are doing it. Do you
think maybe a table and chairs, and maybe
a couch,
- Yeah, a sofa.
- and then you'll get over behind
the table and everything, and then I can
say what day and what time.
- [teacher] And that's writing down what?
Writing skills.
- Writing skills.
- Very good, very good.
- We're gonna show like you, you
would be like typing on the computer and
you would be, and I would come up and ask
what you're doing, and so the other people
would know what you're doing on the
computer, I would come up and ask what
you're doing and you would say, "I'm
making a blueprint."
- Like, 'cause if we did use set
up machines for production, and we use
synergize, we'd have to work together to
do it, and how do we do that? Miss
Kimberly?
- [teacher] Yes ma'am.
- How do we act out setting up
for productions, setting up machines?
- [teacher] Well, since you're act, you
want to show synergizing, now what does
synergizing mean?
- Working together.
- [teacher] Okay, so you need to
involve... ?
- Working together.
- [teacher] Yeah, okay. And
certainly with being a mechanic, you're
working on, what?
- [together] Machines.
- [teacher] Machines, and so what you
wanna try to demonstrate, is everybody
working together.
- To build a machine?
- [teacher] Possibly, that would be a good
one, I think.
All right, we're going to go
ahead and start our demonstrations. So I'm
gonna ask Morgan, Landon and Abby's group
to show us their skill. And tell us what
your job is, tell us what's your job?
- A paralegal.
- [teacher] A paralegal and your skill is?
- [together] Reading.
- [teacher] Okay. Let's see how they're
using reading.
- [intercom] Second grade and third grade,
please come on down to the gym, thank you.
- [teacher] Okay great, that's good. Now
what were they doing?
- [together] Filing, reading...
- [teacher] Filing, exactly, very good,
good job. Okay, let's have Luke, Destiny,
Payton, and where do you guys wanna go?
- Up here.
- [teacher] All right. Tell us your job.
- Certified surgical tech.
- [teacher] Wonderful, and your skill?
- Put first things first.
- [teacher] First things first, okay.
- Clear!
- [teacher] Okay, great. So what were
some, Luke, what was the first thing you
did? The first thing first.
- I had to gently cut his knee
open and pull it apart.
- [teacher] And then...
- Cut his muscle and pull it open,
and then get a mini saw and cut the pieces
of the knee bone and replace it.
- [teacher] Okay and then what would
be the last thing that a surgeon does?
- Stitch the knee back together.
- [teacher] Okay, all right, good job.
- Clear!
- [teacher] Good job, first thing's first.
Okay, all right, now we wanna see Reagan,
Mackenzie, and Logan, let's see y'all. And
where do you wanna go? In the middle?
Okay, that's fine. And tell us your job.
- Electrician that uses math skills.
- [teacher] Okay, electrician.
- Come in.
- It's over here.
- He's measuring how long the wire is.
- 3 feet.
- [teacher] Okay, okay. Now what were they
doing?
- [together] Measuring the wire.
- [teacher] Electrician, and you were, say
it again. Say what you were...
- We were measuring the wires.
- [teacher] Measuring. Measuring, okay so,
and measuring is part of... ?
- [together] Math.
- [teacher] Math, very good. All right,
good job, good job. Okay, all right, let's
have... let's see, it'll be Josh, Alyssa
and Taylor G.
- Our job is maintenance mechanic--