- I want you to go ahead
and put a "C" over your 10
at the top of this if you haven't.
And I want you to take
a look at the part one
on your paper.
Yesterday, we looked at how pressure
could effect the mantle,
but now we need to look
at something different.
I want you to answer
number one and two first
and then we'll talk about it.
This is just what you know
before you come in my room
to get you into the lesson.
So, number one wants to
know list a few things
that you have seen float before.
Number two wants to know
what do you think
might cause these things to float.
So, first just make a little
list of two, three things
that you've seen floating before
and then tell me on number two,
if it's a hypothesis you may
not know for sure that's fine,
but what do you think
causes them to float.
Nathan.
- Are we allowed to write both?
- Yeah.
Yeah, so right now,
you're just going to make
a little list on number one
and then number two,
you're going to tell me what do you
think actually causes these things
that you wrote down to be able to float.
We're going to start with that first.
This is just to get us thinking
about what we're doing today.
One and two, please.
What do you think causes them to float?
You might not be sure of the answer
to number two, but I still
want you to make a hypothesis.
You don't have to write
"I think because,"
but you can tell me what
you think causes that.
Number two's going to be harder
than number one.
- Yeah.
- Let's take four things,
tell me four things that
you've seen float before.
We'll take four, because
we can probably sit here
and name like 100.
Cole, give me one.
- Ice cubes.
- Ice cubes. Sadie?
- Boat.
- A boat. Alex.
- Shoes.
- Shoes. And Emily?
- Dog toy.
- Dog toys, okay.
Now, we know things can float
and that's great.
But, what do you think
causes these things to float?
Why do you think dog toys
and a boat and ice cubes
and things like that,
why are they are going
to be able to float.
Ebony, what do you think?
- The air in them.
- The amount of air that's in them.
Anybody else?
Dylan?
- They are less dense.
- Okay. Sean?
- Surface tension.
- Little air pockets that are in them.
- Okay, air pockets.
- I was thinking like the less density
inside of it.
- Okay,alright, we're going to
take a look at that today.
So, you've got a kind of idea,
we're going to look at what
causes something to sink
and what effects if something floats.
Alright, we have two parts
that we are going to be going
to our last stations for.
So, let's take a look at part two
last station observation.
You have two setups at your lab station.
You have a black tray that
has three objects in it.
You've got a bouncy ball, a
marble and a styrofoam ball,
alright?
You also have a setup
at your lab station
that has liquids in cups.
This is for part three.
Alright, I don't want you
touching this stuff yet.
We're going to come back later
and you're going to
look at that stuff.
I don't want any of the
cups knocked over,
objects put into the cups, okay?
These two things are separate,
your black tray and the piece of paper
with the cups are separate.
What you're going to do first
is use the black tray
and the objects in it.
You're going to tell me
with the marble, the bouncy
ball, and the styrofoam ball
if we were to put these in water,
which we are going to test them,
but if we were to put
these in water,
do you think these objects
would sink or float?
So, you just go through
and if you want
you can just write an "F" or an "S."
You're going to say what you think
and I want you to wait until
you get to your lab stations
so you can pick them up, feel them
to see, that might make a
difference in your guess.
Then, I also want you
to tell me why.
While you are at your lab station,
float or sink in water
and why.
You're not going to do
the did it actually float
because we're going to look
at that when we come back.
These are our results.
So, you're going to do
the first two columns,
float or sink, why, float or sink,
why, float or sink, why.
- Then we are going to come to that?
- And we are going to come back,
and we're going to do an
observation together.
So these two columns have
got to be filled out
before you get back to your seats.
Got it? Let's go.
- Marble, sink. Rubber, float.
[Background Chatter]
- Rubber, float.
Styrofoam, float.
- The marble will probably sink,
it's heavy.
- It has no air in it.
- Bouncy ball.
The bouncy ball probably can float.
- Yeah.
- I mean it's not light,
- It's gonna float.
Bouncy ball, same thing.
- Bouncy ball, heavy.
Marble, heavy with no air pockets.
No--
- This one will definitely float
because it's lightweight
and it has these little pores.
- This bounces a lot,
his bounces a little bit
and this bounces not at all.
- Yeah, but this one, but this one
[Background Chatter]
- If this one can float,
then why not think
that one could float?
- Okay.
- If you don't go
with your group,
that's okay, but you still
need to a connection.
If you are finished before the timer goes
off you need to come back to your seat.
- This will float.
- This will fall.
[marble ball hits surface]
- Fail.
- If you finish, you need
to come back to your seats.
You guys all finished?
I want to go ahead
and take a look,
before we see the results.
Before we look at the
results and test this,
I want to see what we think.
So first off,
let's start with the marble
since it's at the top.
Raise your hand if you
think the marble will float.
Okay, so we're all together
on this one,
it's not going to float.
Who can tell me why
they're thinking
it's not going to float?
We'll take like three
guesses, three explanations.
JC?
- It's heavy, with no air pockets.
- Heavy with no air pockets, good.
Frayla?
- It can't capture air,
it can't float.
- Can't capture air, can't float.
Alright and Emma.
Heavy and solid.
- Heavy and solid.
Alright, now what about the bouncy ball.
Raise your hand if you think
this is going to float.
Alright, there's a mix.
- What, that's heavier
than the marble.
- Well, let's hear --
[Background Chatter]
Somebody give me an explanation
for why it would float.
If you guessed float tell
me why you thought that.
Sean.
Because there's air inside.
- Okay, there's air inside.
Alex.
- I dropped it in the pond
and it still floated.
- Bouncy ball floated in the
pond when you did it before.
Ali.
I've seen it happen.
- Okay, you've seen it happen.
Now, some of us said it would sink.
Why did you say it would sink?
Matt Weaver.
- Because it's heavy.
- It's heavy.  Frayla.
[Background Chatter]
Okay, Jared.
Okay, so prior experience.
Now, last one is our styrofoam ball.
Float, raise your hand.
Alright, somebody give me a
reason why it's going to float.
We're all together on this one, too.
We all agree the marble is going to sink,
we all agree the styrofoam
ball is going to float.
Matt Cook.
- It's light and has air pockets.
Alex?
[Background Chatter]
You're talking alot of things,
the pond was last time, okay.
Frayla.
It's very lightweight
[Background Chatter]
- Okay, alright, let's test it out.
We're just going to test
it out upfront here,
so I'm just going to
use this big beaker.
What do we want to see first?
- Marble.
- Bouncy ball.
- Alright, record sink for your actual.
I guess we'll do bouncy ball,
we'll just go in order.
Alright, bouncy ball, ready?
The moment of truth.
[cheers]
And styrofoam ball.
- Yeah.
- A different bouncy ball didn't float.
- But you saw the bouncy
ball I was using, right?
- Yeah.
- So, it was fair, right?
- Very simple, but let's take
a look at what's going on.
For number four,
I'd like you to tell me,
I want you to answer first
and then we'll discuss.
What I'd like you to tell me,
why do you think some of these
objects were able to float,
while others were able to sink?
And I want you to be specific.
At the beginning, I asked
you the same question
on number two in prior knowledge.
Why do you think some
of these things float.
I want you to revisit
that question again.
So, why do you think the
marble and the bouncy ball sank
and the styrofoam ball was floating.
I want you to be specific on number four.
I want you to answer first on your paper
and then we're going to share, okay?
What kinds of things did
we say for number four?
Now that we've looked at
this in a different way.
Before, I just asked you to
think of things in your past
that you've seen float.
Now, we've looked at our marble,
our bouncy ball and
our styrofoam ball.
What did you say?
Nick.
- Bouncy ball didn't have enough air
to keep it up and it was too heavy.
- Okay, anybody else say anything.
Nick said, bouncy ball
didn't have enough air
to keep it up so it sank.
Anybody say something different?
Ebony?
- Density and buoyancy.
- All right, what do you mean
density and buoyancy?
Okay, Frayla?
- I said that some objects
had air holes
and some were just solid.
- Okay.  Now let's think of
this in a different way.
We've got this really small marble
and we've got a much
larger styrofoam ball.
So, normally if something's smaller,
you think it's going to be lighter,
it should float.
Something heavier,
this is much larger,
but it didn't sink.
If I have one book,
if I'm carrying one book
versus carrying five books,
that's different because
five books are bigger
than one book.
So, what is going on with the
amount of stuff in the marble
and the amount of stuff
in the styrofoam ball.
Is it the same amount of stuff
in the same amount of space?
Does the marble have
the same amount of stuff
in the same amount of space
that the styrofoam ball does?
Which one has more stuff,
more matter in a smaller space.
I want you to talk with the
person sitting next to you
for one minute.
Okay, so, we've done this before.
Okay, so, marble's number one,
styrofoam ball, two.
Which object has more stuff,
more matter,
packed in a smaller space?
On the count of three, right here,
marble one, styrofoam ball two.
One, two, three.
- Marble.
Good, marble.
So, let's write that down.
This is pretty much what
number five is asking you.
So, when comparing the
marble to the styrofoam ball,
which one has more mass,
more matter, more stuff
in a smaller amount of
space, which we call volume.
That would be the marble, alright.
People today, if you flip
over to the next part,
I've heard the word
density a couple times
and density is kind of.