- Okay, so for our first trial,
we just wanted to see
how long it would take
for 25 milliliters of magnesium hydroxide
to turn into acid by adding HCL,
and it took 73.5 milliliters.
- And for our second trial,
we had the same amount
of milk of magnesia,
but this time, we diluted it
with 100 milliliters of water.
And it took less HCL, hydrochloric acid than in
the first trial that we did.
- And, the first time, we
only added five drops of
phenylthalene, and the second
time we added ten drops
just to see if it would make it different,
and the ten drops
definitely made it pinker,
but we don't think it affected the results
because phenylthalene
is just the indicator,
and not part of the reaction.
- You guys actually
brought up a good point.
How many groups added phenylthalene
in large quantities?
(laughter)
How many think that you didn't add enough?
Let's just ask that.
(scattered mumbling)
Or, how would you know if you added
too much or not enough?
Alright, go ahead, Will.
- Well, as long as it turns pink,
you know that the indicator's working.
- [Instructor] What if it's pinker?
- It wouldn't matter because
it turns clear towards the end.
- [Instructor] What do other people think?
Alright, Vivian?
- I feel like if there's
not enough indicator
that when you add more and
more HCL to the solution,
it becomes, the pink
color becomes so diluted
that you can hardly
tell when it turns clear
and when it turns back to very pale pink.
So, I don't think there's such a thing
as adding too much indicator.
Our group added about five drops,
and that was enough.
- [Instructor] Okay, what, Tad?
- Actually, adding too much indicator
is bad for the experiment
because that would
distort the actual
concentration of reactants.
So, in an extreme case,
if we added like 100
milliliters of indicator,
that would definitely
distort the concentration.
- [Instructor] True, what
do people think about that?
Alright, Jimmy?
- The indicator doesn't
participate in the overall reaction
so it doesn't really make a difference.
- [Instructor] What do
people have to say to that?
Alright, why don't you take
30 seconds with your group.
Discuss, would adding too much indicator,
would that affect your concentration?
Like, in terms of volume,
maybe you're adding
to more volume of your reaction,
would that affect the
concentrations of your reactants?
(children talking loudly)
Okay, thoughts?
Alright, Jerry.
- I feel like if you added the indicator,
it would dilute the
solution because it would be
somewhat like water, if
you added, let's say,
100 milliliters of water it
would change the concentration.
- [Instructor] Okay, alright, Stephanie?
- I think it would, like,
because if you started out
with 25 milliliters of milk of magnesia,
even if you add a lot of phenylthalene,
it would still be 25
milliliters of milk of magnesia
and that's what's reacting.
So, I don't think it affects it.
- Alright, Mackenzie?
- Isn't pH determined by the concentration
of hydroxide or hydrogen ions?
So, if it's, it would
be moles over liters,
so if there were more liters,
it would be a smaller
concentration, right?
- Alright, Corey?
- It's mostly about the moles
because if the moles of each of
the acid and the base
combine, they will neutralize.
It doesn't really matter, the over liters,
as long as the moles are equal.
- [Instructor] Okay, Rick?
- Well, since phenylthalene
is an indicator,
it doesn't actually
participate in the reaction,
just like water, so adding it
would just increase the volume
which, as he said, which
would dilute the solution.
Adding a lot would have a profound affect,
but adding a little bit wouldn't
actually make a difference.
- [Instructor] Okay, Richard?
- It would, because there's
a lower concentration,
it would take a lot
longer for it to react,
meaning that it greatly
increases the risk of error.
Because, when you're using a
burette, it's continuously
dripping so then, if you're swirling
and it doesn't react as
fast, then you have more
that goes in before you
actually realize it.
- So, those are all good
thoughts that you guys
came up with, and all reasonable.
It does affect the
concentration, and when you add
a few drops, just like Vivian said,
if you don't add enough,
then it's still indicating,
but in terms of the overall concentration,
the concentration of the phenylthalene
would be relatively small,
and so that's why you see,
like a very faint pink,
but it's still indicating.
Now, if you add more drops,
of course you're going
to have a darker pink, but
the overall reaction volume
would increase and so, if you
add drops of phenylthalene,
if you're adding like, five
drops, compared to your
overall reaction volume, it wouldn't be
that big of a difference.
So you would still have
some source of error, but
since you're only adding
five drops as opposed
to five million drops,
five million drops
could conceivably double
your reaction volume and
then your concentration
on a greater scale would be affected.
You know, it would make
it so it's more diluted.
Okay, does that make sense to everyone?
Alright, those were all good comments.
Anyone else have a comment?
Alright, so let's go to table two.
- In last week's experiment,
we were testing how much
HCL it would take to
neutralize 25 mL of milk of magnesia.
First, we measured 25
mL of milk of magnesia
using a graduated cylinder
and add the milk of magnesia
into the flask, and then we add three drop
of phenylthalene as
indicator to the flask.
Then, we slowly used the
burette to drop the HCL
into the flask and it
took us 55.5 mL of HCL
to clear the solution.
- Every time we'd see that it's clear,
it took the solution longer time.
So, the first time, we stopped putting,
we stopped adding HCL,
but then it only took
about one second to turn back to pink.
But then, after the third
or fourth stop that we made,
it took longer than one second,
so by the time it took,
so like, towards the end,
it didn't turn pink anymore.
- So, for the second trial, what we did,
instead of using just 25
milliliters of milk of magnesia,
we just used 15 milliliters,
and diluted it with
ten milliliters of water to see if there's
a change in the amount of HCL we used,
and it did, because it took a lot less,
which was 35.5 milliliters of HCL
as compared to the first
trial where we used 55.5.
- So, we thought there might be a relation
between the concentration of
trial two versus trial one.
It was roughly, 35.5 is
roughly two thirds the amount
it took for the m.o.m
to come clear as over
55.5 milliliters of
HCL, and we were kind of
surprised by the results
because we didn't expect it
to keep going back to pink
after it turned clear once.
- Do you think you did something wrong?
- Well, we kind of did,
but then we remembered
that this reaction was
actually reversible,
so then we tried it again
and then we eventually
made it all clear.
(group members agree)
- Did anyone else, did any
other groups think that,
when the reaction was happening,
that you had done something wrong?
Or were surprised by the results?
Alright, Ian?
- Oh, no, just saying yes.
- [Instructor] Okay,
anyone have a comment?
- We thought something
was going wrong because
it took a lot of HCL for the
indicator to start working.
- [Instructor] What do
you mean start working?
- To start turning opaque,
because it was pink for a long time.
We had to add extra HCL to the burette.
- We actually thought that
it wouldn't stop turning pink
because we stopped it
for about three times,
stopped the burette from running,
and every time it kept changing color.
So, we thought that happened
throughout the experiment.
- Did you think it was
going to go on forever?
- Yep.
- Okay, any other groups?
Alright, Andrew?
- We noticed that, yeah, what they said.
It changed to clear, and then
after we stopped stirring it
it would go back to pink.
We thought it was the
reversible reaction rates,
but then, like we were surprised
at how big a difference it was,
because it was really clear
when we were stirring it,
but once we stopped, became really pink.
- [Instructor] Okay, alright, Will?
- There was also a transitional
phase where it turned light,
and we thought that was the
phase it would turn into,
rather than clear, so we
actually stopped it there,
but then we looked around
and realized that people
with a less concentration turned clear,
so we started adding more.
- [Instructor] Okay,
alright, group three?
- First, we used 25 milliliters
of milk of magnesia,
and then we took 200 milliliters
of water to dilute it
and then we added five
drops of phenylthalene.
It took about 7 milliliters
of one molar HCL
to actually fully, huh?
Yeah, it took 70 milliliters,
and then it stayed clear from there.
- For the second trial, we want to see
if we added less milk of magnesia,
would it, would the time decrease?
I mean the time to neutralize decrease.
And so, we add 15 mL of magnesia
and the same amount of H2O,
and so we used up about
38 mL of HCL.
- So, I heard something about timing,
because I heard the first couple groups
timed some of the things.
What did you guys time,
and why did you choose
to time that?
Here, let's start here because
you guys timed something.
What did you time,
and why did you choose to time that?
- Well, basically, I think we're
just measuring the amount
of HCL we used up, and see how many times
we need to stop the burette for.
- Well, we observed that it
kept changing from pink to clear
but the more HCL we
put, the faster it was,
from the switch, so we kept adding HCL,
and it turned all clear.
- It turned all clear, the faster--
- The previous times were milky white,
and then towards the
end, it becomes clear.
Like, totally clear.
- Okay, did anyone observe
something different,
in terms of the amount of time that it took
for it to turn back to pink?
Okay, table six?
- As we added more HCL, the white color
persisted longer and it took longer for it
to turn back to pink.
- [Instructor] Okay, so, yeah, Rick?
- I don't think time really
matters in this experiment
because the changing of
the colors in the reaction
depended more on the
amount that was added,
rather than the time you left it in there.
So, if you add more, of course
it's going to change quicker
but it doesn't matter, like
how long you have to wait for.
- So, you guys were saying that
when you added the HCL,
that it changed quicker to white,
and then it took longer for
it to turn back to pink.
Okay, Gabriel?
- We timed it because we
think that there might
be a connection between the time it takes
each time to turn back to pink
and the concentration of the reactants
because the longer it
takes to turn back to pink
might mean that there are less reactants
and therefore, it will take a long time
to get back to the reactions,
right back to the products
which turns it to pink.
- [Instructor] Okay, alright, Corey?
- I was saying that it was
faster turning back to pink.
- The reaction was actually,
it was slower going back to pink.
That's okay.
Okay, let's go to table four.
- In our experiment, in
our procedure, actually,
we had two beakers of
the magnesium hydroxide,
and one beaker, we would
heat, instead of diluting it,
we would heat up one beaker
to around 50 degrees Celsius,
and we would perform the experiment with
adding HCL using the burette,
and in the other beaker,
we would leave it in room temperature,
which is around 25 degrees Celsius,
and we would do the same procedure,
adding the HCL with the burette.
- Our purpose for heating it was to see
whether the reaction was
an endothermic reaction
or an exothermic reaction.
- What we found was
that when we heated it,
it actually, changing from pink to clear,
it actually took less
time than when we did it
at room temperature, so we don't know
if it accounts for the
exothermic or endothermic,
or maybe the molecules
are just moving faster
so it'll react faster.
- We also did not dilute
the milk of magnesia
like most of the groups did,
so that may have skewed our
answers a little as well.
It took us a lot longer, and more HCL,
to turn the solution clear again.
- [Instructor] Comments?
Does anyone think that,
so this group didn't dilute.
How many groups diluted
and added distilled water?
Okay, so all the other groups did.
(laughter)
Do you think that their
data would be affected
because they didn't dilute,
and because you did?
What are your thoughts?
Alright, Nina?
- We diluted our second trial,
and it didn't affect the
amount of HCL needed.
- [Instructor] Why do you think,
well, from your
observations, that's obvious,
but does anyone know why?
Or think why that might happen?
Why would your data not be affected?
Or think that maybe theirs was a fluke?
And, your data should have been affected
by diluting it with water?
Alright, Joey?
- Is it because the HCL only reacts
with the milk of magnesia?
So, it doesn't affect how much water
because it doesn't react with water?
- [Instructor] Okay,
what do you guys think?
Alright, Katie?
- I think it will affect it
because the concentration's
higher and the milk of magnesia by itself
is more dense so there's less
surface area, I would say.
- [Instructor] Okay, less surface area.
Okay, that's a possibility.
Alright, Gabriel?
- I think it wouldn't
affect the amount of HCL
that would be added, but it
will just affect the time
because with water, it
will take longer for the
reaction to take place
because there's more volume,
and without diluting it, their group just
made it straight up so it would be faster
for the reactants to go back to pink,
and then at the end, it
will just turn clear,
either way.
- [Instructor] Why do you
think it would be faster
if they didn't dilute it?
- Because there would be less volume,
and the smaller the
spaces, the molecules will
react faster and have
less room to move around.
- [Instructor] Okay, reasonable, yep.
- So, our group kind of did both.
We had a control, we
redid the same experiment
for number one, and then
we measured how many
milliliters of HCL it took,
so if you change the concentration,
it does affect the amount of HCL it takes
to neutralize it.
- [Instructor] Alright, Michael?
- We diluted it, and it
took longer for us to,
we added more HCL for it to neutralize,
and I feel like if you
dilute the milk of magnesia,
there would be less molarity,
and if it's not diluted,
it would be a stronger weak
base than if it was diluted.
It would become weaker.
- You can't change the
strength of an acid or a base
because it's based on what,
it's by definition.
You can't make a strong base weak,
but that's okay, Wintel?
(laughter)
- In our case we did two
solutions, different concentration.
The amount of HCL that's needed
to neutralize the solution shouldn't be,
should be the same, but in this case,
the time delay causes the
solution with low concentration
to take more HCL because
during the delay, the reaction,
the HCL hasn't still reacted
with milk of magnesia yet,
and because of that delay,
there's more HCL that's needed
to compensate for that.
- Okay, so there's a little
bit of stoichiometry going on,
where the number of moles or the amount,
the amount's still the
same, regardless of whether,
of milk of magnesia,
regardless of whether or not
you added distilled water or you didn't.
So the amount's still the same.