- Let's talk about the advantages
and disadvantages of each company.
Let's start with T-Shirts R Us.
Okay, who can explain
to me what's going on
with T-Shirts R Us?
Devon?
- [Devon] You have
to pay a 50 dollar copay
and you have to pay six dollars per shirt.
- Okay, so you've got to pay
50 dollars up front, right?
And then what do you pay per shirt?
- [Devon] Six.
- Six dollars per shirt.
Okay, what are the advantages of that?
How is this one in some way
better than top of the line?
Allegra, what's better about this company?
- [Allegra] You only have
to pay six dollars per shirt.
- You only have to pay
six dollars per shirt.
So, you're telling me six dollars per shirt
is definitely better than
eight dollars per shirt?
Right?
Okay, what's the
disadvantage to this plan?
Who can tell me the
disadvantage to this one, Sarah?
- [Sarah] You have
to pay 50 dollars first.
- You have to pay 50
dollars up front, okay?
So, if I were going to buy a lot of shirts,
let's say I was going to buy 200 shirts,
which company do you
think would be the best
for 200 shirts?
Taylor?
- [Taylor] I think the
T-Shirts R Us would be better,
because you only have to pay 50 dollars
and the shirts are only
six dollars per shirt.
- Yeah, for this one
the more shirts you buy,
the better deal it becomes, right?
But for this one, if
you're not going to buy,
if we were only going to
buy for say 10 people,
would we want to pay
that 50 dollars up front?
Are we probably going to buy enough shirts
to make up that difference?
Probably not, okay.
So for top of the line
tees, our initial charge,
the nice thing about top of the line,
what's the advantage of top of the line?
- [Students] They're eight dollars.
- That it, raise you hand.
Kevin?
- [Kevin] They're only eight dollars.
- They're already eight dollars
but is that their advantage?
- [Students] Yes.
- [Patrick] No.
- [Teacher] Patrick says no.
Patrick, is their advantage
that they're eight dollars
per shirt?
What's the advantage for top of the line?
- [Patrick] Isn't it because the design
is free?
- Is free, so do we have
to pay anything up front?
- [Students] No.
- No, so if Cameron, if you
and I were the only people
that wanted to get shirts,
that would probably
be a good place to go,
right, because for eight plus
eight we pay 16 dollars,
but up here two shirts
is going to be expensive, right?
Right?
- [Students] Yeah.
- Yeah, it would be
over 60 dollars, right?
- [Patrick] 62.
- That's not a very good
price for shirts, okay.
Brett?
- [Brett] I kind of
brought this kind of up
in my group even though
it like wasn't really part
of the data.
- [Teacher] Okay?
- [Brett] Another thing I kind of thought whenever
I was working on this last
night, was if they're charging
money for the graphic,
couldn't it possibly be
like a better graphic, but...
- It could be.
It doesn't necessarily mean that it is,
and I think for this we
would probably be assuming
that the quality would
be at least comparable,
maybe not identical but
at least close, okay.
All right.
So, let's look at a couple
of different things, okay?
Let's start with these tables.
You guys have had a minute
to look at these tables.
What, the first question
says, which of the following
tables represents T-Shirts R Us?
With this being our given information,
which one of these
tables is T-Shirts R Us?
Tell me how you know, Amanda.
- [Amanda] The first
one because the cost
starts at 50 before you even buy any shirts?
- Okay, so Amanda says that
this one is T-Shirts R Us,
and how did you know that?
You explained that in a
really interesting way.
How did you say that?
- [Amanda] Because the
costs are 50 before you
buy any of the shirts.
- Yeah, Amanda says this one has to be
T-Shirts R Us because
you can see in the table
the initial charge of 50 dollars.
Do you guys agree that you
can see the initial charge
of 50 dollars?
- [Students] Yes.
- Okay, that's one way to say it.
Is there another way?
Lindsay, you had something
interesting on your paper.
What's the other way that we can tell
whether or not that's T-Shirts R Us?
- [Lindsay] I divided 30,
divided by five equals six.
- Can you tell me where you
got the number 30 and five?
- [Lindsay] In t-shirts there were
a five dollar difference.
The t-shirts goes up by five.
- Yeah, so this one goes up.
- [Lindsay] And the cost up by 30.
And I just divided the two numbers
and it told me which
of the companies sells
the shirts for six dollars.
- So she said that she found that the cost
was going up 30 every time
the shirts went up five.
So, then to figure out
how much each shirt was,
she divided the 30 by six and figured out...
Oh no, not by six, 30 by five
and figured out that each shirt was
six dollars per shirt.
So, one way to figure it out
is look at the rate of change,
right, and another way to figure it out
is to look at the initial cost.
Like, what is it that you
have to pay up front.
So, in this problem can we see both?
Can we look at this table and see
here's what you have to pay up front
and then here's what you
have to pay per shirt?
Can you see that?
- [Students] Yes.
- Okay.
Write that down.
All right, so look at
the table and let's talk
about the original question that we asked.
The original question that I asked you,
and this was just a pick.
Which company did you think would be
the better option for our 25 students?
- [Student] T-Shirts R' Us.
- What did you find out when you really,
really investigated?
Casey?
- [Casey] They're both 200 each.
- You really find out
for exactly 25 students
they both cost...?
- [Students] 200 dollars.
- 200 dollars.
So, if we were just buying
t-shirts for our class,
would it matter which company we chose?
- [Students] No.
- No.
What if we decided we wanted to do all
of my math students?
If we decided we wanted to
do all of my math students,
which one of these tables would favor
the option of buying it for all 100?
Bree, what do you think?
If we were going to buy
t-shirts for all 100 students,
because at 25, the cost
is the same, right?
Which one of these is
going up more quickly?
- [Bree] The one on the left.
- The one on the left's
going up more quickly?
What do you think?
Nahla says she disagrees.
Nahla?
- [Nahla] The one
on the right is going up
more quickly because it's going up by 40.
- Yeah, this one's going up
how much every five shirts?
- [Students] 40.
- Yeah, this one's going up 40,
and at that same time,
this one's only going up?
- [Students] 30.
- 30, right Bree?
So, Bree, which one's going up faster?
- [Bree] The right one.
- Yeah, so they're the same here.
Do you guys see they're the same here?
You see that Bree?
But if this one's going up faster,
if I'm going to buy a
whole, if I'm going to buy
a lot more shirts, what's
going to eventually
happen with this one?
- [Bree] It will increase.
- It's going to get increasingly
more expensive, okay.
So, somebody summarize this for me.
What did we just figure out about tables?
What did we just explain about tables?
What can you find on tables?
Sierra, tell me what we can find
by looking at a table?
- [Sierra] Y-intercept.
- [Teacher] We can definitely
find the Y-intercept.
Can you tell me how we can
find the Y-intercept?
- [Sierra] When the X value is zero.
- When the X value is zero, that's going
to be our Y-intercept.
That was an excellent explanation.
Guys, what else can we
find from the graph?
We can find the Y-intercept,
what else can we find?
Samantha?
- [Samantha] We can find the slope.
- [Teacher] We can find the slope,
and can you summarize
how we found the slope?
- [Samantha] We found the
differences between the y column
and the x column and then
we put in the rise over run.
- Yeah, we found the
differences between the y column
and the x column and then
wrote them as the ratio
rise over run.
Excellent job, okay.
So, that's tables.
Cameron, question?
- [Cameron] Is it okay
on the table where it says,
like, t-shirts in the
columns, is it okay to put
x and y over them?
- Cameron, if that helps
you understand it then yes,
that's completely fine.
But you need to understand that
x and y represent something.
Right?
It's okay for you to
think about it as x and y,
but just keep in mind that x represents
the number of t-shirts and
y represents cost, okay?
That's a good question.
All right, now let's look at the graph.
Okay, suppose these two
graphs were given to you.
Okay, look at the graph.
Is everything on the graph the same
in terms of the way the graph's set up?
Does the scale set look the same?
- [Students] Yeah.
- The x-axis is identical
and the y-axis is identical.
So, let's talk about
the graph for a second.
Look at the graph.
Adam, can you look at
that graph and tell me
which thing, which one of these two graphs
do you think is top of the line?
- [Adam] The one on the right?
- The one on the right.
Can you tell me why,
because top of the line,
keep in mind, the initial charge was zero
and the cost per shirt was
eight dollars per shirt.
How did you pick this one
to be top of the line?
- [Adam] Because it started at zero?
- Okay, so one of the
things that's important
was that you realized it started at zero.
So, he looked at this and recognized
that my, he said starts... at zero.
Okay?
That's important.
How else could we figure
out that that was,
how else could we figure that out?
Allegra?
- [Allegra] I said that
since it was five times eight,
well, that's the first
coordinate it would be.
- Oh, okay so the first
coordinate was five, 40,
so you said five times eight is...?
- [Allegra] 40.
- 40, okay, what about this one?
- [Allegra] That is 80.
- 10 times eight is 80?
Okay, is that an interesting
way of thinking about it?
- [Students] Yes.
- And does that also work?
Does that make sense with this problem?
Starts at zero and every
shirt costs eight dollars,
so she said five times
eight, 10 times eight,
and that pattern would
work all the way up.
Is there other ways that I
could identify that this
is top of the line, Amanda?
- [Amanda] I went
down there on the table,
that the rate of the pulse goes up faster,
- Uh-Huh?
- [Amanda] so, like, when you said how...
- Did you guys here the word
she used to describe that?
She said she recognized
that this rate is going up
faster than this rate.
Do you guys agree with that?
- [Student] The line's more steep.
- Yeah, the line has greater
steepness is the word
you used, steep, right?
Yeah, so this one, not
only does it start at zero,
so we can recognize it that way,
but we also recognize that
it's going up more quickly.
This one's going up
eight dollars each shirt
and this one's only going
up six dollars each shirt,
because, let's look at the
rate of change for this one.
If we went from zero to five,
that went over five, right?
And then from 50 up to 80, is what?
- [Student] 30?
- That's... from 50 to 80 is...?
- 30, and so 30 over
five gives me how much?
- [Students] Six.
- Six per shirt, okay?
Nahla, you had your hand up?
- [Nahla] Yeah.
- Go ahead.
- [Nahla] I was gonna say, that I understand
that it started at 50?
So, that would be T-Shirts R Us?
So, if that was T-Shirts R Us,
then the other one had
to be top of the line.
- Guys, did you hear what Nahla said?
Nahla said she looked at this graph
and noticed that this one started at 50,
so, because that one started
at 50 it had to be what?
- [Students] T-Shirts R Us.
- [Teacher] T-Shirts R Us, okay?
So, so what're we talking about?
We're talking about looking at a graph
and finding two things.
What are the two things that
we need to be able to find
from our graph?
Greg tell me one.
- [Greg] Slope.
- We need to do our final slope.
Emanuel tell me the other one.
- [Emanuel] The Y?
- We need to be able to find the slope
and the y-intercept, okay?
Emanuel, can you summarize for me how
to find the y-intercept?
How do you look at a graph and find
the y-intercept?
- [Emanuel] Where the
line crosses the y-axis?
- Where the line crosses the y-axis.
So ,Sierra told us when we're on our table,
we're looking for where...?
- [Students] the x is zero,
- The x is zero, but on the graph that
means that it crosses
the y-axis.
Okay, nice.
Can somebody tell me from a graph,
how to find slope?
Stella, I haven't heard
from you for a minute.
How do we find slope from a graph?
- [Stella] You use the slope triangle.
- You use the slope triangle.
- [Stella] Uh-huh.
Then it leads your eyes, for example,
can we talk about this one?
- It doesn't matter, you pick
whichever one you'd like.
- [Stella] So, it will
be the rise and speed,
it's going up.
- Yeah, so this is our rise, okay.
- [Stella] And the run
is how far it's going out.
- And the run is how far it's going out.
- [Stella] It's rise over run.
- And then you write it as
a ratio, rise to run, okay?
Excellent.
Guys, I have one final
question on the graph.
So, we picked these, we
did our slope triangles
from those blue ones that are drawn right?
And for this one we got 30 over five
and figured out that that was six, right?
Would it matter if I did...,
went too far I think.
Would it matter if I did that?
- [Student] No.
- I heard no.
Can someone raise your
hand and explain to me
why that's no?
So, why does it not matter? Sydney?
- [Sydney] Because it's the
same shape, it's just larger.
It's a similar figure.
So, I guess if you were
finding rise over run
and once you simplify
it, it would be the same?
- Did you guys hear what Sydney said?
Sydney used the word
similar, or used the phrase,
similar figures.
What do similar figures mean?
What does that mean, Greg?
- [Greg] Like, two
figures that have the,
like they're, they
don't exactly have to be
the same size?
It's like, basically a
dilation of the other.
- It's essentially a dilation.
Okay, so the first one we
did went up 30, over five.
Right?
Well what about the red one?
The red one went from five to 20.
How much did it go over, if
it went from five to 20?
Cameron?
- [Cameron] 15?
- It went over 15.
So, if this one goes over 15,
you sort of used that word,
dilation, right?
What's the scale factor from five to 15?
- [Student] Positive 3.
- That's times by positive 3, right?
So, likewise, what should this be?
If my run was 15, what should my rise be?
Raise your hand if you know.
Jaylynn?
- [Jaylynn] 90?
- It should be 90.
Okay, so let's check and see if it is.
So, we went from five, so that went 15,
and then we went from 80 up to 170.
Now, what's the difference from 80 to 170?
- [Jaylynn] 80 to what?
- 80 to 170.
- [Jaylynn] I don't know.
- That's okay.
What's the difference?
Who can tell me the
difference from 80 to 170?
Sierra?
- [Sierra] 90?
- The difference is 90.
So, if I looked at those two ratios,
so, if I looked at those two ratios,
one would give me 90 over 15
and the other one would
give me 30 over five.
Are those equal?
- [Student] Yep.
- Yes, that is, let's check it.
Are each of those giving
you six dollars per shirt?
- [Students] Yes.
- Yeah, so how do we
find slope from a graph?
Taylor said we make the slope triangle,
and does it matter
which triangle you pick?
- [Student] Nope.
- No, because they should be proportional.
They should be dilations
of one another.
Okay, it be a good reference to something
that we learned.
- [Student] Can you
show us how to start out
like the first one?
Or the first few pages?
- So, the question was,
do you have to start out
at the first one?
- [Sydney] No.
- Sydney, why no?
- [Sydney] Because,
if the pretense is that
the initial charge is 50
dollars, then you don't have to.
Unlike the other one, it started at zero.
- [Teacher] Mm-hm?
- Are you talking about
the final slope, Nahla?
- [Nahla] Yes.
- Okay, Nahla, you can
start at the first point,
but you don't have to,
because if it's linear,
should the pattern ever change?
- [Nahla] No.
So, if the pattern never changes,
does it matter which two points you pick?
- [Nahla] No.
- Any two exact points you pick,
should still give you
the same rate of change.
That was a great question.
Okay, all right.
So now, this is a different one.
So, on the last one, I gave you the verbal.
Right, I did, I said T-Shirts R Us
and gave you the verbal expression.
This time I'm not giving you that.
This time, we've got a
third t-shirt company.
The third t-shirt company Tee Time,
they explain to us, this
is their function cost.
Cost is equal to 4.50x, plus 25.
My question is, what does that mean?
Who can tell me what it means to do 4.5x,
plus 25?
Samantha, start me.
- [Samantha] We would charge
25 dollars for the graphic,
and 4.50 per each t-shirt.
- Okay, so what do we have
to pay no matter what?
Patrick, what is the one
thing we have to pay?
If we ordered a shirt,
what's the one thing
they're going to charge us?
- [Patrick] For the design?
They're going to charge
us that 25 dollars for
the design, right? But then...
- [Student] Each time?
- Huh?
- Well, that's a great question.
Do they charge us 25 dollars every time?
That's a great, great,
great, great, great question.
No, why not?
What's the 25 dollars for?
- [Student] It's for
the design on every shirt.
- It's for the design, and that
is the design that we're
going to use for all of our shirts.
So, that's an important question.
Does the y-intercept explain
anything about change?
Will the y-intercept change?
Will it move up or down?
No, the initial cost is whatever
the initial cost is, okay?
That was a great question.
Who can tell me a little
bit about what this graph
would look like?
What would the graph look like?
- [Student] It looks like a zero,
but I think
it'd start at 25 here.
- It would start at 25.
So, it's go to start somewhere
right in here, okay?
And I'm not sure why those numbers are
on the table, but they shouldn't be there.
Okay, but that's okay.
We can move forward from it.
We can do this.
What should the cost be initially?
- [Students] 25.
- The cost should initially
be 25 dollars, okay.
Then if we buy five shirts,
how can we figure that out?
Who can tell me how to figure that out?
Ah, (inaudible)?
- [Student] You can
plug in the value of five
in the equation thing.
- You can plug into the equation?
Ooh, I know what we can use.
Oh, we can use...
I heard somebody say this earlier.
We can use a calculator right?
Where would I put this
information in the calculator?
- [Student] Y equals.
- I'd go to y equals, excellent.
Okay, and I put it in there my function.
Right, so I've got 4.50x, plus 25.
- [Student] And then you press second?
- Yeah, what am I trying to look at?
I'm trying to look at my table.
Let's go back for just a second.
Look at the table that's
already given to us.
What do they do in their table?
- [Students] It increases by five.
- They increase their x values by five.
So, do I want to set
mine up to go by fives?
- [Students] Yes.
- Yeah, so how do, didn't I,
how do I set up a table?
- Where do I do that?
- [Student] It's a
second and it's on top of a window?
- Yeah, it's second and
it's on top of a window,
we've got a table set up.
Where do we want to start our table?
What's the first number we need?
- [Students] Five.
- Okay, because we
already know zero, right?
And then how much do we
want to increase each time?
- [Students] Five.
- We want to increase
each time by fives, okay.
Are we okay with that?
Now, where do I go to
actually have the calculator
give me the information?
Sydney, where do I go?
- [Sydney] You press second and then
you press the graph button?
- Second, graph, which
will give me the table.
So, I will give you a minute to make sure
that your table is still being corrected,
because I'm going to need
you to help me with mine.
I don't know why I put
the wrong table up there.
Okay, we good?
All right so we used the
calculator to help us
get our table.
What was it in fives?
Who can help me with this?
Help me with this, Cameron, real quick.
- [Cameron] 47.5.
- That's 47.5, or 47.50, right?
What about tens?
- [Cameron] 70.