- Room 221. Students enter through a small
entryway. To their right are inspirational
displays and to their left is the entryway
to a traditional darkroom. This classroom
is shared by two teachers. Storage space
is limited. In this room, I teach three
sections of Photography, Advanced
Placement Studio Art, and Advanced
Placement Art History. As we open up into
the main part of the classroom, storage
areas are visible for each class'
photographic prints, a whiteboard is
visible with posted assignments, and
storage space where students retrieve
gloves and archival sheets for their
negatives. As I pan the room, you can see
heated dryers for prints and negatives
clearly labeled and accessible. Bulletin
boards are set up for project
instructions, visual examples, and
critique displays. Along the back of the
room is a dry-mount press and negative
developing chemicals with directions and
safety instructions posted throughout.
Hanging from above are art history
displays created by students to aid in the
analysis of modern art movements. Cabinets
along the back of the room are clearly
labeled for easy retrieval of student
supplies. In the center of the room, the
printing press is stored for AP Studio Art
and set up to allow for safe and organized
used. Along the right-hand side of the
room, there is a drawing rack for students
to store work-in-progress and a light
table for the preparing and viewing of
photographic negatives. There is an
exhaust fan here for safety as well as a
paper cutter with a safety guard to avoid
accidents. The file cabinets are clearly
labeled for storage of student binders.
The large cabinet in the back of the room
is locked to safely store blades and other
potentially dangerous supplies. And at the
front of the room are storage bins for
students to retrieve missing work or work
that they might have been absent to
accept. And at the front of the room is
the computer for student and teacher use.
The projector screen lifts to reveal a
whiteboard for demonstrations and
instructions.