- [Child] Ti ti.
- [Teacher] Okay, why don't you come up
and try that? Click on the heart. Oops.
It's not quite high enough. Hold on one
second. Let me minimize it. Okay, now try
to get it. A little harder.
And you have "Ti ti." All right, let's
try the second beat. Don't raise your hand
yet. We haven't done it. Sing it and clap.
- [Together] ♪ Locket ♪
- Okay. Let's see. Hunter, will you come
and put Locket up? Which one do you think
it is, Hunter?
- [Hunter] Ti ti.
- Good job. That's fine. ♪ Lost her ♪
♪ Lost her ♪ Morgan...
Oops, let's try it again. You did it
right. Sometimes it's just a little
tricky. Thank you. ♪ Pocket ♪ ♪ Pocket ♪
Bear...
There you go. Good job.
♪ Kitty ♪
Ashley?
Nixon, sit on your bottom, bud.
♪ Kitty ♪
We're going in the second line, beat one.
Try again. Oops. Sometimes it's a little
tricky.
♪ Fisher ♪
Griffin...
Oops. I think that might've been a little
too hard. Tap on it again. Good.
♪ [Tound] ♪
Andrew...
Yep. Click on it again.
Thank you, Andrew.
And, It. ♪ It ♪
Riley...
Good job. Now, boys and girls, I would
like you to put your sticks on your
shoulders and even though we're not
finished with the heart chart, I want you
to clap your ti ti and your ta for each
beat. Make sure you're looking up here and
you know which one to clap and say. We're
going to clap and say it. Ready? Go.
- [Together] Ti ti. Ti ti. Ti ti.
Ti ti. Ti ti. Ti ti.