(crosstalk)
- You're not doing your job.
Follow the arrow.
(crosstalk)
Good.
Just a little bit.
Why? Why do we say the wiffle (crosstalk)?
- Because it (mumbles).
- Because nothing in it. It's holes.
Then is it the holes
and nothing in it makes it heavy or light?
- Light.
- Light. Good.
- Next, what do we have to do?
We have all our arrows down. Good.
Exactly.
Okay.
(crosstalk)
Thank you. Someone
needs to hold this here.
(crosstalk) I have a job
for you. Come hold the clip.
Hold this here.
Come around here.
Come here sweetie. Right here.
Hold this.
(crosstalk)
Okay, now let's count.
Go to there and I'll help (crosstalk).
(crosstalk)
Okay. Good.
Good boy.
- Oh, no.
- Uh, oh.
(crosstalk)
- Put it in the basket.
Put it in the basket.
Good.
(crosstalk)
You have to help her count.
I need to hear you.
Should I could count 30?
- No.
- No. It's not far (crosstalk).
(crosstalk)
When this is 20.
- 21
- Good.
(crosstalk)
Is that more than the wiffle ball?
This one? More than this?
Is this one more?
Sebastian?
Yes.
Good.
(crosstalk)
Good. 52. Write your 52 down.
What's the problem?
What?
What have you done here?
(crosstalk)
Okay.
I see (crosstalk) working on her turn.
She hasn't done anything?
Because we're not helping?
What?
Which one did you roll?
(crosstalk)
You don't need this (crosstalk).
You're not to this point yet.
First you're doing the rolling.
Okay.
You need to move to the side.
(crosstalk)
Now, help her.
Okay.
Good.
Wait, wait, wait. Oh, okay.
(crosstalk)
Good.
Now, it's (crosstalk) turn.
(crosstalk)
Okay, now.
You help her by holding the end.
(crosstalk)
No, it's fine. I can tell what it is.
You're doing a good job.
Someone needs to hold this end.
(crosstalk) right here.
Hold the end right here.
Okay, now. Perfect.
Now, we have to help her count.
So she can write her numbers down.
Okay, start with the
first one, the wiffle ball.
How far is the wiffle ball?
(crosstalk)
Starting 10 here? Is this 10?
Where's the 10? Good.
You think that's how far it is?
Okay, so write that down.
Put in wiffle ball.
- [Voiceover] I said I'm next.
I said I'm next.
- I'm looking now at (crosstalk).
(crosstalk) asked about yours.
I think you have your
numbers in the wrong spot.
Which went further?
Wiffle ball? Which one?
Which one went far?
The baseball, okay.
Because I think on our list, you
have them written backwards.
We'll fix them. We'll find
them with the right picture.
(crosstalk)
Okay, let's see what the problem is.
The one's got to go on this side.
Please help her count
where the baseball is.
Count with her.
- 14
(mumbles)
- Is there a faster way
we could've done that?
By doing what?
Exactly, by counting by 10s.
We could've started here and gone
10,
- 20
and then count (crosstalk) from there.
You're right.
Good.
So, who's next?
Steven.
(crosstalk)
Now what's going on here?
Sarah was saying something (crosstalk).
What's happening?
(crosstalk)
No, remember, you did this (crosstalk).
Together, count them.
- 20
(crosstalk)
Well, let's look.
It does look like (crosstalk).
- 3.
- Yes. Good.
(crosstalk)
Write it on the board.
But you two can start (crosstalk).
And then you two can start.
You hold the (crosstalk).
(crosstalk)
Good.
Mark it. Good.
(crosstalk)
Where does the ball go?
Put it in the basket.
(crosstalk)
Excellent.
Help the boys now.
You can hold the ramp. It
looks like it's about to fall.
Too late (laughter).
Wait, wait.
All the things to say.
(crosstalk)
Now with the rubber ball. Exactly.
This one's called the what? Wiff-?
- Wiffle ball.
(crosstalk)
What happened with the balls?
Hold it.
Let me look at yours.
You got yours done?
What happened with yours?
What happened with the baseball?
- It went (mumbles).
- Which one went the farthest?
- This one.
- How about yours?
Which one of yours went the farthest?
Yeah, the baseball.
Remember, we talked about that.
(crosstalk)
The ball should be in the basket,
so it doesn't go under the chair.
(crosstalk)
- (crosstalk) counting. What happened?
No, but what happened here?
Someone has to hold it, you're right.
Can you hold it? Good.
That's better.
- 30
- This is 50.
- 50
53, 54, 55
(crosstalk) start again.
(crosstalk) each one.
50.
- 51
- Pablo.
Which one of the balls went furthest?
(crosstalk)
The baseball?
What did we talk about when we said
at the beginning?
Which ball did we think was
going to go the farthest?
The baseball.
Why did you think it was
going to go furthest?
- Because (crosstalk).
(crosstalk) right?
- Yes.
- How about yours? And, Sarah's too?
Did the baseball go the farthest?
(crosstalk)
That far?
That was a hard push, exactly.
(crosstalk)
That was a soft and that was a soft.
Which one was the softest?
- Two.
- Which one was a really soft push?
The wiffle ball.
Why? Why did we say that?
- Because, the ball (crosstalk).
- Just a little bit.
What happened when you weighed the ball?
When you put them in the balance?
- The baseball get's heavier.
- The baseball was heavier.
Baseball needed nine
magnet weights, you're right.
You remember.
It was heavy. Good.
(crosstalk) you're absolutely right.
(crosstalk)
Okay, help him count to his wiffle ball.
Hold the end.