(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Everybody's
using their directions,
they have their tools
and their charts out!
We've found today's date,
so we know where we're
going to record today.
It's Wednesday, March Ninth.
(Background Chatter)
-[Student] I know what numbers
down of zero mean.
They are negative numbers.
That's what are numbers that
are down from zero.
(teacher clapping rhythmically)
(students clapping in response)
- [Teacher] OK, I have most
friends with their hands
on their heads, I want to make
sure everybody's listening
and ready to move on.
We can keep all of our materials out
so we can actually use them.
Excellent.
I'm waiting on a few more people
to have their hands off of their materials
and on their heads, so we can concentrate
on the teacher.
In each group I have one team member
that will be measuring temperature.
If you are measuring the temperature,
please hold up your tool
that you'll be using.
Those of you measuring the temperature,
what tool are you using? Everybody?
- [Students] Thermometer!
- [Teacher] Very good!
The people that are
measuring the temperature
with the thermometers,
please line up at the back
door of the classroom.
When you get out there, boys and girls,
are you going to be able
to see the temperature
as soon as you get out there?
What are you going to have to do?
- [Students] Look at the thermometer.
- [Teacher] And you can also
compare it to the thermometer
that's been outside, so
go out there and you can
let your thermometers adjust
to the temperature of outside.
If you have a windsock and
you are going to measure
the direction of the wind,
I would like you to line
up quietly at the back door
of the classroom.
You guys can use the
compass and work together,
go ahead out and see what you observe.
If you have an anemometer
to measure wind speed,
you may line up.
If you have a ruler to
measure precipitation
in our rain gauges, you may line up.
You may all go.
And last but definitely not least,
if you are measuring the(Background Chatter) .
(Background Chatter)
- [Student] When we
look at this (Background Chatter),
our thingy goes away!
- [Student] No, yours is 61!
- [Student] No, it's the
Fahrenheit, not the Celsius.
- [Student] There's something in there.
- [Student] What team are you?
- [Student] 66.
- [Teachers] You guys, we need
to wait for how many seconds?
- [Student] It's not ready yet!
- [Teacher] You've been doing it at home.
What is it that you've been waiting?
- [Student] How can it be 110?
How can it be?
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Now we are
going to set the timer
for 10 seconds and we are going to count
how many times it went around. OK?
So see where your (mumbles) is
and get ready to start counting.
(Background Chatter)
- [Student] Look at the bee!
- [Teacher] I've heard both
of these ladies say two.
What you need to do is you
need to use that chart in there
and see what it means.
What is the wind speed if the anemometer
goes around two times in 10 seconds?
- [Student] Look with
your eye, with one eye,
look at this one.
-[Student] I can't see!
- [Student] I think it's going West.
- [Teacher] When you
have completed measuring,
you may walk back to your
group to record your data.
Quietly.
- [Student] I got 66.
- [Teacher] Can we compare it
to what's on the wall there,
and see what we have?
- [Student] It got 66, then it got 65,
and then it got 64!
- [Teacher] Victor, could
you explain it all to me,
why you think you
thermometer keeps going down?
- [Student] Because it gets colder.
- [Teacher] And where has the thermometer
been sitting all day?
- [Student] In there.
- [Teacher] And do you
think it's cooler out here,
or is it warmer out here?
- [Student] Cooler?
- [Teacher] Exactly! So
our temperature is going?
- [Student] Down!
- [Teacher] Good! So let's
go ahead and look right here
to make sure we can tell the temperature
from our thermometer that's
been staying outside?
- [Student] It's getting brown!
- [Teacher] What do we think
the temperature is there?
- [Student] It says the
temperature is 46 degrees.
- [Teacher] That's probably
our most accurate reading
since it has been staying
outside all day long.
All right. You can head
back in and record.
(Background Chatter)
- [Student] I don't know
which number to choose!
- [Teacher] The one on the
outside, the whole time.
(Background Chatter)
- [Student] What's your --
- [Student] Gym? It's on
Wednesday, March Ninth.
- [Student] It was West!
(Background Chatter)
- [Student] The wind direction was West.
- [Teacher] Very good.
I think that you have
an accurate reading.
- [Student] What's the wind speed?
- [Student] It's cloudy.
- [Student] Wind direction, temperature!
- [Teacher] Team Three
is working together,
and Team Two, and Team One!
Nice job working together!
- [Student] I think you have to change it.
- [Student] Temperature! Victor!
What was the temperature?
- [Student] 40 degrees.
- [Student] 46 degrees Fahrenheit.
- [Student] It was 50!
- [Student] What was the wind speed?
- [Student] It's not raining.
- [Teacher] So what did you
guys think the (Background Chatter) was?
- [Teacher] I agree with you.
Why would we forecast that it might rain?
(Background Chatter)
- [Student] What's the weather?
- [Student] The weather is rainy!
- [Student] West! Put West!
(Background Chatter)
- [Student] It was West.
- [Student] It was West?
- [Teacher] We found
out that the wind speed,
we said it went around
about that many times,
so how fast is the wind actually going?
- [Students] Minutes!
- [Teacher] Miles per hour?
We don't go anywhere in a minute.
We travel, like we said,
in cars, in miles. Right?
Go back to your group,
they'll tell you on the chart.
- [Student] My thermometer's
higher than the one outside.
- [Teacher] We discussed that while
we were standing out there.
Why do you think that
that may not have dropped
as far down or might even be going back up
as you're holding it inside right now?
- [Student] Because
inside of you it's warm.
Because you told us that it was,
when you're holding the thermometer,
the thermometer only
feels what's around it.
And if we're covering the
thermometer it can't measure
any more temperature, only
how our temperature is.
- [Teacher] Very good.
So, Linda, if that answered your question,
that's why we compared it to
the thermometer that's been
staying outside that we check each day.
What are we going to say
that the temperature was
from that thermometer reading out there?
- [Student] 46 degrees Fahrenheit.
- [Teacher] Excellent, so
make sure you're sharing that,
and each person in your
group, use your data!
Linda.
(Background Chatter)
I think you've done an excellent job.
(teacher clapping rhythmically)
(students clapping in response)
- [Teacher] OK! We have a few minutes left,
and some groups are getting to the point
where they have finished
recording their data
after working with their
team members on each type
of weather and using the
different weather instruments.
I am going to pass out
your follow-up questions
and you're going to
use data from last week
and compare it to today's data
to do some equations on here,
and you do not have to finish today.
We will do this in our follow-up lesson
in our next science lesson. OK?
You may continue working.
Thank you.
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Write your
name and date and you can
put it back in your
packet when you clean up.
(Background Chatter)
OK, the wind direction?
Who should you be asking that to?
- [Student] Today's?
(Background Chatter)
- [Student] Last Wednesday
the temperature was
57 degrees Fahrenheit.
What is the degrees
between today's temperature
and the temperature last Wednesday?
Write an equation. Show your work.
Last Wednesday the wind speed
was eight miles per hour.
What is the difference between --
(Background Chatter)
- [Student] You already have your paper!
- [Student] I know!
- [Student] We can do it by ourselves.
- [Student] But it says to work as a team!
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] I like it! Good job!
"Keep working with your
team," I hear her saying.
Excellent! I like how I
see Brianna using her data!
And Grace starting to write an equation,
and Abby and Samaya have
the date on their paper!
You guys are all doing an excellent job!
(Background Chatter)
Who is the person on
your team whose job was
to measure what direction it went?
You should ask that person
as soon as he comes back,
he should have his data on his chart.
(Background Chatter)
What number did you put there?
- [Student] We worked together
and we figured it out.
- [Student] I know this
one! I know this one!
I know that one!
One second!