- [Voiceover] Approved
guided reading area.
Computer center.
Whole and small group area.
Writing center.
ABC anchor chart and new
high-frequency words.
Spelling Center. A-type
frequency word development.
Center chart. Colors represent student's
developmental level.
The pocket chart hosts a variety of games.
Library center. Big
books, retelling supplies,
decodable library books.
Science center. Students explore,
observe and record.
Browsing boxes contain familiar
reading materials.
Block area fosters oral
language development.
Home center. A variety
of printed materials
encourage oral language development.
Poetry center. Aids
phonological awareness.
Writing and anchor charts
for journal writing.
Listening center for fluency development.
Phonics center. Improves
alphabetic awareness.
Word wall. Words are attached so students
can remove and replace them.
- [Children and Teacher] X -
x-ray. Y - yo-yo. Z - zebra.
- [Teacher] Alright, I want you to find the letter
that makes the sound that you hear
at the beginning of the word "hedgehog."
Hedgehog.
- [Student] H.
- [Teacher] H. Very good. I want
you to find the letter
that makes the sound that you hear
at the beginning of the word "worm."
Worm.
- [Student] W.
W.
- [Teacher] What letter?
- [Students] W!
- [Teacher] Good job.
We have been talking about spring
and we have been talking about
the seasons of summer and winter
and springtime.
What season are we in right now?
- [Student] Winter.
- [Teacher] Winter. Very good.
Well this book, "Hedgehog is Hungry,"
that's written by Beverley Randell,
is about a hedgehog.
And he is asleep during the wintertime.
And he wakes up in the springtime
and he is hungry.
But first, look at this picture.
Have y'all ever seen
anything like this before?
- [Students] No.
- [Student] I saw a hedgehog in a book, but not real.
- [Teacher] You've seen a hedgehogs
before in a book but not real?
- [Student] Not me.
- [Teacher] Hedgehogs are pokey.
And when they curl up,
their little spikes poke out.
They pop up. That's right.
Why do you think they pop up?
- [Student] Cuz that means you're scared.
- [Teacher] That means they're scared.
- [Student] Nature protects.
If a person runs into
the pointy stuff, they'll say, "Ouch."
- [Teacher] That's right. And it protects them.
Well, as we are reading this book today
we're going to read this book to find
out what Hedgehog is going to eat.
What Hedgehog is hungry for,
and what he is going to eat.
I want you to look at your partner,
and I want you to tell your partner
what you think hedgehog might eat?
(Children discuss)
- [Student] I am thinking he, is
going to eat a worm.
- [Student] I think he is going to eat a snail.
- [Teacher] Okay. Alright. Well, I heard
I heard worm, and I heard snail.
And she said snail too.
Why do you both think the hedgehog
is going to eat a snail?
- [Student] Because there's one
right in front of it.
- [Student] I think it's going to eat a worm.
- [Teacher] You think it's going to eat a worm?
- [Student] I think he's going to eat a leaf.
- [Teacher] You think he might eat leaves. Okay.
Alright. So, we're
going to read this book
to find out what Hedgehog is going to eat.
Alright, why are we reading this book?
- [Everyone] To find out what Hedgehog
is going to eat.
- [Teacher] But guess what?
There's going to be some words
in this book that we might not
know how to read.
One of the words we are going to
work on today is new high-frequency word.
And remember, high-frequency words
there aren't any rules for them, are they?
We just have to learn the way they look,
so that we can learn to read them.
Can you read, tell me what this word is?
(Students sound out word)
- [Everyone] Here.
- [Teacher] This is the word "here."
I love how you decoded it.
- [Student] We already learned about it.
- [Teacher] We have learned about here.
Here is on our...
- [Student] Word wall.
- [Teacher] Word wall,
isn't it? Excellent job!
Well, today it is important that
you not only know how to read words,
but it's important that you also
know how to spell words.
So, I'm going to give you the letters
that you need.
I want you to dump them out,
and I want you to spell "here" for me.
I'm going to turn this around
so you can't look at it.
And I want you to spell "here" for me.
I hear Lilly saying it's (mumbles).
Here.
- [Student] I spelled it.
- [Teacher] Alright, I'm going
to turn it back around.
Are you all ready?
Alright, check it!
- [Students] H-E-R-E
- [Students] I did it!
- [Teacher] Are you all right?
(Students cheer)
What word did you just build?
- [Students] Here.
- [Teacher] Here. Alright, now we can build it,
so I want you to... write it.
I want you to write the word "here".
Not look at your letters. Okay.
Are you ready? Show me how you
write the word "here".
And then I'll let you check it again.
You're almost there.
What else do you think comes next?
- [Student] I think you push harder.
- [Teacher] You want to try pushing harder?
You think you got it, Natalia?
- [Student] I put an exclamation mark. Here!
- [Teacher] You put an exclamation mark at the end.
- [Student] I spelled it.
- [Teacher] You did? Alright, I'm
going to turn it around.
You all ready to check it?
(Students cheer)
- [Teacher] Did you get it?
Alright, read your word.
- [Everyone] Here.
- [Teacher] Here.
Very good.
- [Student] H-A-R-E, here.
- [Teacher] Here.
- [Student] It's not, A.
- [Teacher] Alright, now, one way that we can help
ourself is by looking at high-frequency
words, and learning all of
our high-frequency words.
Our high-frequency words
are on our word wall.
So, that's one place that you can look
if you get stuck.
Another thing that we can do
is we can look at the pictures
to help us with the tricky part.
So, we're going to go through,
and that's what we're
going to do right now.
We are going to look at the pictures.
Are you ready?
"Hedgehog is hungry". That's our title.
Now, what time of year do you think it is?
- [Students] Winter.
- [Teacher] Winter. It is definitely winter.
- [Student] Because all of the
leaves are off the tree.
- [Teacher] Because all of the
Alright let's look at the pictures.
Now, who do you see buried
down in the leaves there?
- [Student] I see Hedgehog.
- [Teacher] You see Hedgehog.
Is Hedgehog awake or is he asleep?
- [Students] Asleep.
- [Teacher] And you know why he's asleep?
- [Student] Because it's winter and he hibernated.
- [Teacher] And he's hibernating.
Very good, turn to the next page.
Now what season is it?
What season is it?
- [Student] It's spring.
- [Teacher] It's spring!
And is Hedgehog still asleep?
- [Students] No.
- [Teacher] No. Hedgehog is awake.
Let's turn to the next page.
And there he goes.
Here he comes. He's going out
for a little walk.
What do you think he's doing?
- [Student] Find something to eat.
- [Teacher] He's going to find something to eat.
Let's turn to the next page.
Hedgehog is hungry.
And what is the first thing he finds?
He finds a...
- [Students] Snail.
- [Student] I was right!
- [Teacher] Uh, you were right.
- [Student] And me.
- [Teacher] Okay, let's turn to the next page.
He's still hungry.
- [Student] He ate worms and caterpillar.
- [Teacher] Okay, now that is a very
big word, caterpillar.
How did you all know that
that was the word "caterpillar?"
- [Student] I saw it right there.
- [Teacher] Alright, listen closely.
You all just told me two strategies
you can use to help yourself
when you come to a tricky word.
You can get your mouth ready
for the beginning sound.
Or, you can look at the...
pictures. Tell me again.
You can get your mouth ready
for the beginning sound.
Or you can look at the...
- [Everyone] pictures.
- [Teacher] Okay, let's turn to the next page.
Now, what does he find?
What is that?
Okay, we talked about one of the
strategies is we can get our mouth
ready for the beginning sound.
- (Students comment)
- [Teacher] Alright, let's run our finger
underneath it now.
Let's look at it. Let me write it.
Let's do, "Bug". Let's spell bug and see.
How would we spell bug?
Get your arms ready.
- [Everyone] (word sounds)
- [Teacher] Is that going to be the word bug?
- [Students] No.
- [Teacher] No. So we're going to
have to look at that.
This is the word "beetle."
Can you say that word?
- [Everyone] Beetle.
- [Teacher] And look underneath it.
What do you see underneath it?
That is a slug. Ooooh.
Now, just like-- eyes are up here, Lilly.
Eyes are up here. Okay there we go.
Just like we can get our mouth
ready for the beginning sound,
you all also know how to decode words,
Is everybody's eyes up here?
So, we can get our mouth ready
for the beginning blend, which is, sl...
What sound is the U going to make?
- [Everyone] Uh.
- [Teacher] Because there's only one vowel.
And what sound's the G going to make?
- [Everyone] Guh.
- [Teacher] Let's blend it together.
Are you ready?
- [Everyone] Sl-u-g. Slug.
- [Teacher] Now, look at me.
You have three ways now.
You can look at the pictures.
You can get your mouth ready
for the beginning sound.
And you can decode words
that have one vowel in them.
Alright, let's close our book up.
All the way up.
When you are reading,
I want you to read to find out
what Hedgehog eats.
What is your purpose for reading?
- [Everyone] To find
out what hedgehog eats.
- [Teacher] Alright, start reading.
Hedgehog is hungry.
(Students reading aloud)
- [Teacher] What did we say he was?
Use the pictures to help you
with the tricky part.
We said he was a... asleep.
- [Student] Asleep.
- [Teacher] Good job.
- [Student] It wasn't doing that space in there.
- [Teacher] That's right because
"asleep" is one word.
(Student reading aloud)
There's our high-frequency word: "here."
(children reading aloud)
- [Student] I'm tricked.
- [Teacher] You're tricked. Alright,
so what will you do?
- [Student and Teacher] H-un-gry
- [Student] Hungry.
- [Teacher] Very good. Hedgehog is hungry.
(Student reading aloud)
- [Teacher] Good job.
(Students reading aloud)
- [Student] Slug.
- [Teacher] Good job.
(Students reading aloud)
- [Teacher] It does spell the word "spring."
Good job. Alright.
I love the way you all did two things:
I love the way you can
all use your fingers
to help you point.
I saw Lilly stretching lots of words out.
When she came to a word
that she didn't know,
she got her mouth ready and she stretched
those out just like we
did with the word "slug".
I saw Poniyota using the pictures
help her with the tricky part.
We are reading to find out what
hedgehog ate.
Do you remember what hedgehog ate?
- [Student] Snails.
- [Teacher] He ate snails. What was
something else he ate?
- [Student] A snail.
- [Teacher] A snail. What was
something else he ate?
- [Student] A bug.
- [Teacher] A bug. What was something else he ate?
- [Student] He ate a beetle bug.
- [Teacher] A beetle bug.
Alright, let's read it and make
it sound like talking.
- [Everyone] Hedgehog is hungry.
Hedgehog is hungry.
Winter is here.
Hedgehog is asleep.
Spring is here.
Hedgehog wakes up.
Here comes hedgehog.
- [Teacher] Let's all get together. Here we go:
- [Everyone] Hedgehog is hungry.
Here is a snail.
Hedgehog is hungry.
Here is a worm.
Here is a caterpillar.
Here is a beetle.
Here is a slug.
Hedgehog is hungry in the spring.
- [Teacher] Very good job. I am
very proud of you all.