- You're going to test
and be coming up here
for materials.
Okay, go.
- You just follow the lines.
- If, no, if the lines,
if red lines are drawn
on a white piece of paper, the termites
will follow the lines.
- We should draw, like a bunch
of different circles
and different colors and
see which one they follow.
- [Student] And we'll make it like this.
- Well, it's not going to be on a circle.
- [Student] It can be like this
and see if they'll follow that circle.
- [Student] Yeah.
- [Student] Would that
be a good, may I bother
you with this?
- [Student] I'm just covering them up.
- [Teacher] What are you saying?
- [Student] Yeah, well beside this one.
If termites... we'll place on a red piece,
on a white piece of
paper with a red circle
and red lines, then the
termites will follow the lines,
in the circle.
- Okay, so you're going to
use the color red line again.
What color paper would you use?
- White.
- White paper?
- Yeah.
- And I think since we've
already used colored paper,
I think that's a result of that.
- Well, again you
could do yours and yours
and tie them together.
Use different colored
papers, so what's the point
of your test?
- That depending on the
colored paper we'll determine
what the termites sight can do.
- I would think it's the color of the line
because that's what they're following.
- So, you think they're
following the color of the line?
- [Student] Yes.
- Yeah, but when they went to the end of
the white paper, they went to the black
and they came right back.
- [Student] Well, no, that's because
they knew what it was,
that's because I, like, kept hitting them back.
- [Teacher] Okay, so you're kind of
going along with the idea
of color.
How could you prove that color was...
- That color effects their...
- [Student] You draw a bunch of different circles,
draw a bunch of circles
about the exact same size,
but of different colors and
see which one they go to?
- I like that.
- Nice, okay.
- On a white piece of paper?
- [Student] Yeah.
- Again I've got colored paper.
The more tests you do, the more accurate
your results would be.
- All right, so let's do the same test
but on two different types of paper.
So, if termites are placed
on a white piece of paper...
- [Teacher] Put that on top of it just so we block
some of the light out.
No, that down.
Good, and there you go.
So, what were we thinking about testing?
- Um, putting tables in line
using different color.
- And to see if, we're not
going to finish the circle
and see if they follow it around.
- [Student] Oh, very nice.
- Yeah, because we drew a line
leading back to the thing
and they followed it down.
- [Student] They followed it down...
- [Teacher] Tricky, okay.
- [Student] They went, it's true.
- [Teacher] So they
didn't follow this part?
- [Student] Yeah, because it curves.
- [Student] No, because they...
- [Student] We drew the circle.
- [Student] They go, like, then
they curve and go down.
- [Student] And they came
here and went back up.
They all followed.
- [Teacher] Hmm, interesting.
Thank you, four.
You've got about two more, about a minute
and a half actually.
What are we thinking?
I'm going to go ahead and cover these up.
- We were planning on doing, um, like,
we think they're attracted
to the ink and I'm going
to test it with like
a marker, a pen, and a crayon.
- [Teacher] Okay.
- To see if, like, if they
follow the ink better
than the other ones.
- Nice, would you use
the same color of ink?
- Yeah, because it would be the control.
- [Teacher] There you go, very nice?
Um, what color paper are you going to use?
- Should we use regular?
- White.
- I would say white yeah.
- All right, good.
Okay, sounds good.
Where are your termites?
Stop playing with them and
we're going to actually cover
them to kind of get the light out.
What were you guys thinking about testing?
- Mainly, if they are going
to follow the red line,
then they must be attracted to red.
- [Teacher] They must
be attracted to what?
- [Student] Red.
- [Teacher] Red? Okay, so how
could you test that they
are just attracted to red?
- We're going to make two large circles.
- [Teacher] Two large circles...
- [Student] And some other lines.
- [Teacher] And some other lines...
- But, what are you testing again?
- If they go to the
red line then they must
be attracted to red.
- Okay, so you're talking
about the color red.
Um, would you use, so you
tell me what you're going
to set up.
I'm trying to follow.
- [Student] Probably just
a black one and a red one.
- Lines or circles?
- [Student] Circles.
- Circles? Okay, all right.
- Yeah, basically just for fun.
- [Teacher] Okay, okay, just for fun, all right.
Um, you should be collecting materials.
If pens and things aren't
working, let me know.
- (background chatter)
- [Student] Dude, get the line.
- [Teacher] What
happened to your situations?
- Well we put tape over
this and now it doesn't
follow it over here.
- [Student] I think
they like the color red.
- [Student] None of them are
following any of these lines.
- [Teacher] How could
you continue to test
that they like the color red?
- [Student] Put more red over here?
- [Student] I mean, we also put the tape there
and it doesn't like the tape.
It gets confused.
- [Student] And we have the
red paper and it didn't
follow the black lines.
- [Student] Or the pencil.
- [Student] Yeah, that's what I mean.
- [Student] None of them
here are even doing anything.
- [Student] They get tired
and just start standing
there twitching.
- [Teacher] Do you need some new ones?
No, there are still pretty lively.
- [Student] Yeah.
- [Teacher] So, what are some of the
conclusions that you're thinking?
Oh, Terrance, be sweet.
- [Student] Ah, be sweet.
- [Student] Ah, white on red.
- [Student] They only like that.
Also they only follow that type of pen.
They don't follow any other
type of pen or pencil.
Um, they don't necessarily
have an affiliation to red.
- [Teacher] Okay, how do you know that?
- 'Cause they walked off the red paper?
- [Teacher] Okay, they walked off the red paper?
So, you threw that one out.
How could you continue
to say that they like
that particular pen, and
not having to do red?
- [Student] We tried black pen.
- [Student] We haven't
tried another color
on white yet.
- [Student] See look,
it stopped at the tape.
- [Student] It's confused at the tape.
- [Teacher] No, Neal, what I
asked you is that a pen
or a marker?
It's a pen.
- [Neal] It's a pen.
- [Student] Oh, he's
following the other...
- [Student] We drew
it on the other side...
- [Student] We drew a
circle on the other side.
- [Student] It looked like he was following it.
- [Teacher] Is it
something inside of them?
- [Student] No.
- [Student] Like, what
the ink's made out of?
- [Teacher] How could you test that?
- [Student] Using the red pen on this?
- [Teacher] Okay.
- [Student] Taking two different pens...
- [Teacher] Go grab some more.
That's a good idea.
- Red color pen, red color pencil.
- You killed the ant...
- [Teacher] Gentlemen,
be nice to your termites.
- [Student] Oh, oh, wait... wait?
- [Teacher] Here Neal, let's get...
- [Student] All right,
group, here's a red pen,
colored pencil.
- [Student] Oh, look! That one's alive!
- [Teacher] Okay, now
then, so what are you
saying is going on?
- They're still following the red one.
Yeah, they're still following the red pen.
So, it's not necessarily an
affiliation to the color red.
- [Student] So, it is
something inside the ink.
- [Teacher] So, how can
you test if it's something
inside the ink?
- I just got the other colored pencil.
- [Student] Take another red pen.
- [Teacher] Go grab some.
- [Student] It's right there.
- [Teacher] That's a pencil.
- [Student] It's the color red, look.
- [Teacher] Stick with the, no, you
just threw out the idea
that it's red.
Stick with the color...
stick with the pen idea.
- [Student] We need a pen like this.
- [Student] No, I think
we have the exact same pen.
- [Student] No, no,
the blue one like this.
- [Student] They have
a blue one like that?
- [Teacher] Go see,
there's blue pens up there.
- [Student] Hey, can
we borrow a red pen?
I meant blue, you know what I meant.
- [Student] Bam, it's
a different type of pen.
- [Student] It's all right.
- [Student] Different type
of pen, but it's blue now.
- [Student] Did you get a blue one?
- [Student] No, I just got red ones.
I got bundles. (laughter)
- [Teacher] Nice.
- [Student] Now they're
going to follow it.
- [Teacher] Now, I thought
we were going to get away
from the red idea and go with the pen.
- [Student] I think it's that pen.
- [Student] I've got the same pen.
- [Student] They're still the red.
I think they are.
- [Teacher] Okay, try that one.
- [Student] There's a
hole there, by the way.
If you press through it, it will break.
- [Teacher] Go.
- [Student] Are you going to make it
intercept the line?
- [Student] Yeah I'm going to.
- [Student] Oh, look, he's
following the little one.
- [Student] Maybe it likes circles.
- [Student] Wait, wait.
- [Student] I still think
it's something inside the ink.
- [Student] Draw a square.
See if it follows a square.
- [Teacher] So, that would be able,
you would be able to throw out your idea
that it likes circles
if you drew the square.
So draw a square, see what happens.
- [Student] Yeah, draw a square.
- [Student] I've got another black pen.
I have all these pens.
- (laughing)
- [Student] Why not draw the square
inside of there?
- [Student] Inscribe
the square in the circle.
Terms...terminology.
- [Student] You're a professor now.
- [Students] Oh, it's following it!
- [Student] It is the pen.
- [Student] Curves are easier.
- [Student] It didn't
know where the line was.
- [Teacher] Okay, five, four.
- [Student] Um, we drew different lines in
the different types of pens,
markers, colored pencils.
- [Teacher] Did you do
it all on the same page
or on different pages?
- On different colored pages.
- [Teacher] Why would
you do it on different
colored pages?
- [Student] Ah, to make sure the tests varied?
- [Teacher] Okay, did
you use the same color
of ink on each page?
Describe to me your experiment web.
The whole group can chime in too.
- [Student] Um, like we drew, like a
black circle on a black
sheet of paper.
- [Teacher] Okay.
- [Student] To see if they could only like...
- [Teacher] Please don't be rude.
- [Teacher] Black circle on a black sheet of paper.
Keep going, what else?
- [Student] And that didn't work.
They could not see it
or follow it or anything
so we decided to go
with an experiment that
Christian came up with,
that take a white piece
of paper and we drew, like,
every kind of color their was all at once
and they seemed to only
the follow the blue
or red circles.
None of the other colors.
- What were the blue and
the red circles drawn with?
- [Student] I believe different types of stuff.
Mainly pen though.
- And this was all on one sheet of paper?
- [Student] Well, we tried it on
different sheets too.
- Okay.
- [Student] That's what started us off.
Um, did you have it all on one sheet at first?
- Yeah.
- Okay, what did you
realize was wrong with that?
- They were pretty much getting confused.
- As in we're going to
have issues with what?
Maintaining?
- [Student] A control?
- A control, good.
Only one independent variable, nice.
Um, Nick's group, how did you go through
the indentation?
- We drew several circles
using each of the utensils
and then I think we placed
the termites in the middle
and they all sort of, if
they weren't in the middle,
sort of eating off of the
wood or, like, just exploring
around, they were following the pen.
- Okay, um, your indentation
line, did you draw that
with just pens, different types of pens,
did you draw it with markers, did you draw
it with a paper clip?
- We just used the same color
but we used different things.
Like we used pens,
Vis-A-Vis, colored pencils,
stuff like that.
- [Teacher] Okay, and what was
your conclusion with that?
- They followed the pen
because we thought it was
the one that had the most
distinct indentation.
- [Student] Because they came, the
termites, into that line,
because we saw them go up to the edge
and because they would
feel there is a drop,
and I figured oh, well they must be blind
because they can't see
that there's a drop there.
- [Teacher] Interesting point.
Why might you have used
a paper clip as well
to create the indentation,
instead of a pen?
- Because it wouldn't have shown a color,
but it would have still left
the same indentation as a pen.
- Okay, so any components within that pen,
color, chemicals, type of pen, whatever,
if you would have used the paper clip
and then followed that indentation,
you would have been able to do what?
Pen verses paper clip.
- [Student]Pen would have looked, I
think it would have looked...
- [Student] The paper clip
would have looked deeper,
- but the thing is, like,
would it prove if you had
it or not.
- [Teacher] Had what or not?
- [Student] If they followed the dent or not.
Not just like, the color
or the like, smell,
or whatever.
- [Teacher] Very good, very good.
So, by using the paper clip
to create the indentation,
they would have been able to rule out
any type of color from the
pen that left the indent,
maybe the scent from the pen,
the chemical from the
pen that left the indent.
By doing the paper clip just by itself,
we would have been able to say okay,
that obviously doesn't
leave any chemicals,
it doesn't leave any color,
and if they're following
that indentation, we know that that's
what they are drawn too.
Okay?
Carly, your group had
an interesting set up.
- Um, we, well we kind of did two.
- [Teacher] All right.
- But the first one, we have
like a black piece of paper
and we bordered it with, like, white pieces
of paper and we drew a white circle in
the black piece of paper
to see if they would
go away from the white to
go to the darker paper.
And that didn't really work,
so we did the other one
and, um, with, like, the
different colors of circles
on a white piece of paper, and they only
went on the red pen one.
- [Teacher] Okay, what could have been
a variable in your experiment
that you just described?
As in something that might have thrown off
the results?
- Paper? I don't know.
- [Teacher] Well, notice in one of the experiments
you used a what, to create the circle?
- The pen.
- [Teacher] Okay, you used a pen
and in the other
experiment you used a what?
- Paper?
- [Teacher] But you used a...
Oh, white, yeah, you used
a white colored pencil.
So, by using a colored pen and then
a white colored pencil, what
are those two things now?
Added on what?
- [Students] Variables.
- [Teacher] Added on variables.
Okay, for one you're using pen and pencil,
another you're using colors.
So, how could you have made your experiment
a little bit more definite
that would of maybe
ruled out some of the other variables?
Gentlemen, calm down.
- We could have used colored
pencils the whole time.
- Okay, could have used the same color
colored pencil the whole time.
Good.
Um, what group haven't I talked to?
Matthew, explain to us
the set up of your group.
- Do you want to start?
- I don't know what to say.
- Oh, okay then we started off thinking
that they followed the
color and so we drew
with a different type of pen
and it did not follow it,
so we decided maybe it's not color.
So, we took a black pen, a big one.
Um, we took a black pen,
and then two red pens
of different type, and two
blue pens of different type,
and they only followed
the specific type of pen
red and blue.
It was the BIC pens, so
we decided there must
be something in that, in the chemical
structure of that ink
that's, you know, similar to some sort of
pheromone of some sort.
Um, and the termites followed it.
- Okay, um, did you think of the
pheromone thing yesterday?
- Yeah.
- After school.
- That was extracurricular.
- [Teacher] All right so...
- But we figured out the BIC pens.
We figured that out.
- Okay, good.
Excellent set up there.
Were there any variables that,
when I was over there earlier
you had different shapes
with the different pens?
- You got this?
- Yeah, we were drawing with different shapes
'cause it followed the
circle and then we were
trying to get them back inside the thing.
So, we drew a line pointing down there
so they would follow it.
And they did follow it
but then we realized
it might not be the shape,
it might be in the pen
or the color.
- [Student] They don't really
like sharp angles though.
We drew a square and they got lost.
- [Student] Yeah.
- They couldn't find the angle.
- [Teacher] Okay, interesting. So, um,
if any of you did do any sort of
research (inaudible), you were able to
find that the pheromone
that termites emit, and we
learned that those were what?
Pheromones?
- [Student] Enzymes.
- Enzymes, not enzymes.
What are pheromones having to do with?
We just spent three days on it.
- [Student] Animal behavior.
- Animal behavior, communication,
their chemical signals.
Okay, so we learned that termites emit
these pheromones.
We might have encountered this last time
and that's the same thing why ants
follow a specific trail.
Um, when honeybees sense danger, they emit
a warning pheromone that
tells everybody in the hive
to freak out, that danger's coming.
But the pheromone that
termite's emit to have
them follow each other in the hole trails
and all of that, the
chemical in that mimics
or the chemical in the pen,
in Bic and PaperMate pens
actually, mimics the
chemical in the pheromones,
which is why they followed certain pens.