- [Instructor] Clipart. Okay. You show me
... well, if we wanted to insert a Clipart
picture, where do you think would be
the best place to go? Click on insert. And
then where is Clipart? Here you go. And I
bet you we're going to find some really
cool spider pictures. Click on spi-- type
in spiders and see what you come up with.
Hold on, I'll be right over. Yes. Wow,
look at all those spiders. You have tons.
Oh, your project's gonna be neat 'cause
you have all kinds of neat pictures.
- Um... I think something in our
computer is off.
- Okay. Let's turn this off. These
computers sometimes get a little fussy and
it's making bad choices.
- When I get 'em, I just keep pressing
enter.
- Well, it's sort of like hitting an
elevator button. But you can't really make
it go any faster, but you feel a little
better about click, click, click, click,
click. So, go ahead and look over here.
Hopefully that will come up a
little faster. Sometimes it just is a
little slow. Start with... there you go.
You know what to do.
- Okay, there's a big picture.
- That's a huge picture. That's a neat
spider. I think that'll be a neat one for
your... for your project. Yeah.
- Okay. Um well, when we... when we
clicked on the... uh... and it asked
if we wanna include pictures from all the
ones before...
- Yeah. We did want to do that.
- We did? And we clicked no.
- Okay. So that's probably why. Okay. So
let's go onto Clipart office online and
you're going to be able to find some
really neat pictures here, too. This is
the same thing. Type in squirrel. Let's
see what we find. Make sure you spell it
correctly.
- Q-U-I-R-R-E.
- It's a hard word.
- I-R-R-E.
- And then the color.
- Can I put S?
- Doesn't matter.
- Hit scroll or anything.
- Okay. And see what you can find. Look at
all those squirrels.
- You should pick that one, a moving one?
- Yeah.
- Okay. So, you copy it to your clipboard.
Now here's the problem. You need to
accept the service agreement and you'll
have to do it again. Yes. Okay. Now, click
on your scroll and add it to your
clipboard.
- Three times.
- I... I know. Did you copy it to the
clipboard? Did you click on it? Okay. Then
go back to PowerPoint. Let's see if it
works.
- Uh.
- You know how to copy and paste
things, so go ahead and paste it in there.
- [together] Yay.
- He'll move, but not right now. When you
go to... make him a little bigger,
though, I would say.
- Make him fat.
- Now, you can check to see how he's
doing. If you wanna go to your
slideshow... and from the beginning and
see if he'll move for you. There he goes.
- [together] Yay.
- See? Now you know he worked.
- Yay.
- Good job.