- [Teacher] Do you want to
measure this separately?
Or do you want to measure
this with the ground water?
- [Boy in white] Should we measure this separately?
- [Cathy] Yea, 'cause that's the round rocks.
- [Teacher] Okay, what
were you saying Cathy?
Why is the ground water cleaner?
- [Cathy] Because the permeable rocks.
They clean the water on its way down
to the soil saturation.
- [Boy in white] There's 100 milliliters,
and you guys, could you
record the data real quick?
Write.
Ground-- oh no, but we've
got to add this first.
Yea.
- [Cathy] Wait, we've got to add.
Is it still...?
But, let's do the--
- [Boy in white] Is that too much?
- [Cathy] Let's do the
answer for number one
while we're on it.
- [Group] Okay.
- [Cathy] It says,
- [Teacher] Good job--
- [Cathy] "Describe what you would do..."
(Background Chatter)
- [Student] Stop.
- [Teacher] But why is
your head right down level
with the measurement?
- [Boy in gray] We're doing that so we can
make sure it's exactly even,
'cause if we go over, then we won't know
exactly how much it is.
- [Teacher] And are you measuring the
runoff, or the ground water
right now?
- [Boy in gray] Right now we're measuring the runoff.
It was about 380.
- [Teacher] It was about 380?
Is it okay to get an approximate
amount for the volume
for this, and not an exact amount?
- [Boy in gray] I think so, 'cause
then when we measure this,
we could still (Background Chatter).
- [Teacher] Exactly.
Ashlyn, which had more water?
Your runoff, or your ground water?
- [Ashlyn] The ground water.
- [Teacher] The ground water had more?
- [Ashlyn] Yeah.
- [Boy in yellow] Yeah, 'cause they're overflowing.
- [Teacher] Oh my goodness.
Have you measured your ground water yet?
- [Boy in yellow] Not yet, I think
you can see it for video.
- [Teacher] Where is your ground water?
Oh, oh I see!
Oh, so this really did overflow?
- [Boy in gray] Yes.
- [Teacher] So when you measure your ground water,
what will you need to do with the water
that's here in the tray?
- [Boy in yellow] I think put it in with the ground water.
- [Teacher] Yea, and measure that too.
Okay, this is your runoff?
- [Group] Yes.
- [Teacher] Okay, so so
far you have how much?
- [Boy in gray] About 380.
- [Jade] And then there's some in here.
- [Teacher] Oh, you've
already measured 380?
- [Boy in yellow] About.
- [Teacher] Oh.
(Sound of water being poured)
(Background Chatter)
- [Boy in gray] So that's 100.
- [Teacher] You are pouring
that so carefully Jade.
- [Both boys] Stop.
- [Boy in gray] Good.
- [Jade] Because we want
to have it exact so I
had to.
- [Teacher] Okay, Ashlyn.
So Jade put in 100 once,
and then she put 100 in a second time.
So how much water has
she put in there so far?
- [Ashlyn] 200.
- [Teacher] How did you get 200?
- [Ashlyn] Um.
- [Teacher] Be sure you talk nice and loudly honey.
- [Ashlyn] Because,
I got it because...
100...
plus...
it equals 200 because
you put two in there.
- [Teacher] Nice!
Good job.
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Looks like you're doing great kids.
- [Boy in gray] 60.
- [Ashlyn] Keep going.
Keep going.
- [Boy in gray] Looks like it might have been
slightly off.
Better watch it go.
(Background Chatter)
- [Boy in white] Okay, so,
maybe if we...
I think that's good but should we add the,
should I add the data in now?
- [Girl in white] No, we needed that,
did you pour on water, because
that also (Background Chatter).
(Background Chatter)
- [Boy in stripes] Wow, looks like
we're getting a lot of data.
Your recharge is high.
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Trial number one, why do you say
runoff had more water in trial number one?
- [Boy in white] I think because it, clay's more harder,
so it's kind of more difficult to
go through with (Background Chatter).
- [Teacher] So what is this number?
- [Boy in white] 790.
- [Teacher] What is this number?
- [Boy in white] 62.
- [Teacher] And which is greater?
- [Boy in white] 790.
- [Teacher] Yea, 790's greater than 62.
Good for you, honey.
How did you get this number dear?
- [Boy in white] I think,
we added them up.
- [Teacher] What did you add up honey?
- [Boy in white] 790 and 600.
I mean 62.
- [Teacher] To get this total?
- [Boy in white] Yeah.
- [Teacher] Great.
I have a question for this group though.
How much water did you pour in
on trial one?
1,000?
1,000 what?
- [Group] Milliliters.
- [Teacher] 1,000 milliliters?
But your total is only 852 milliliters.
- [Boy in blue] It's still in
the zone of saturation.
- [Teacher] Oh.
- [Boy in blue] Or it hasn't
collected off the first.
- [Teacher] Alright.
- [Boy in blue] But it's interesting maybe,
the water from last time,
since we only had 852 ending last time?
Maybe this time,
the second (Background Chatter), sort of.
Maybe it,
some might (Background Chatter) against the window,
if the water from last time,
I wonder if it came down, in the aquifer.
- [Teacher] I wonder.
- [Boy in blue] Maybe it's just
holding it in there.
- [Teacher] I wonder, it'll be interesting
to measure this time.
So what part do you have in your lab note?
- [Girl in maroon] We're adding, we're have to
answer question two,
and then we're measuring
(Background Chatter).
"Describe what you observed
when you poured the water
over the ground water the second time.
What changed?
Taylor, you go first.
- [Taylor] Um, well,
I think what changed is,
since the clay sort of got use
to the water the first time,
and there wasn't very much water
on the recharge water the first time,
and it got used to, the
clay got used to the water,
that there are little cracks, or the water
slipped through the sides and
it went, and now we've got more
recharge water than we had
on our first one.
- [Teacher] Do you think that could
happen in real life?
Do you think we could have
an impermeable surface
like clay, and then,
it could crack and let water through?
Why do you think that
could happen in real life?
Some place that might happen for real?
- [Boy in white] A bunch of pressure?
If it rains for like, millions
and millions of years,
maybe like cement, or gravel?
It would break it down,
and it would have like a little.
- [Teacher] Do you remember the term for that?
- [Boy in blue] Weather rock.
- [Teacher] Yeah!
- [Boy in white] Weather rock.
- [Girl in maroon] Like, what's in the middle of the road?
- [Teacher] Yeah, sure, yeah.
- [Taylor] Because when people drive on it,
it gets so much pressure.
And people keep driving on it,
and it cracks sometimes.
- [Teacher] Sure.
And I'm sorry, I interrupted you when
you were answering question number two.
- [Boy in blue] I wonder if the, I doubt
anyone would do this,
but if we put pollution on clay,
- [Teacher] If you put what, honey?
- [Boy in blue] Pollution on like, cement of something,
I would wonder if it would get through.
Like, sort of like water sometimes,
and since the clay's impermeable,
water can't get through it easily,
but I wonder if pollution would.
- [Teacher] That's a good question,
you might want to
do that experiment when
you're done with this one.
That'd be great to check.
Good job.
- [Taylor] The clay became more
permeable the second time
we added the water?
- [Teacher] Yes.
- [Taylor] And then we
should probably measure
how much is in here.
- [Boy in blue] Yes.
- [Taylor] Oh, that's kind of... (Background Chatter)
- [Boy in blue] Yea because it's like, soapy.
- [Taylor] It is sort of soapy.
- [Boy in blue] I think it's because
of the clay being wet.
Look on this side.
- [Taylor] Oh yeah, I can
see some of the white.
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] So why is the (Background Chatter)
about 120?
- [Girl in blue] Because it's not quite at 150,
but it's a little bit over 100.
- [Teacher] Is close,
close enough for this?
Or how do you know when close
is close enough for this?
- [Girl in white] Um, we know when it's
close enough for this,
because it doesn't really
have an exact measurement
for 120, so we know that it's
kind of half way between 150 and 100.
125 and it's just a
little bit lower than 125.
- [Christian] There's a lot more
recharge than last time.
- [Teacher] A lot more recharge?
- [Christian] Yeah.
- [Girl in blue] We had 760, now we have 435.
- [Teacher] Holy cow!
The first time you did this, you had 760,
760 what?
- [Group] Milliliters.
- [Teacher] Milliliters of runoff.
- [Girl in white] And this time
we had 435 milliliters.
- [Teacher] Oh, that is a big change!
I wonder, I wonder what
will happen with your
recharge, have you measured that yet?
- [Boy] Yeah, what was it?
- [Girl in blue] It was, I think it was 871.
140, 371.
- [Teacher] Oh my goodness!
Why do you think you had
so much more recharge
the second time you did this?
Christian?
- [Christian] Probably because the ground probably got
more moist, so it would make it easier to
slip right through.
- [Teacher] Do you remember the term for that?
When the ground gets all wet with water?
- [Christian] Soil saturation.
- [Teacher] Great.
- [Girl in white] Well yea, I mean the water level must
have gotten higher.
- [Teacher] Why do you say that?
- [Girl in white] Because the bigger the saturation is,
and the higher the water table is,
the more moist the ground is.
The ground is so the water
can go through easier.
- [Girl in blue] I think the first time we did it,
the water went through,
which made it easier
for the second time to go through.
'Cause it made it more moist.
And the rock pebbles were
kind of scattered around
probably mixed with the water.
- [Teacher] So that's the
pattern you're seeing.
What do you predict will
happen on your third trial?
- [Girl in white] I'm thinking that there will be
maybe, maybe possibly,
more recharge than runoff.
- [Teacher] More recharge than runoff?
Did you have more recharge
than runoff the second time?
- [Girl in white] No, but we always have the tape on,
and it's less than 100.
- [Teacher] So they started like
this, and now they're equal,
and now you think the third time they'll,
- [Group] Yea.
- [Teacher] Oh.
- [Girl in blue] Because probably, since the
soil's even more moist now,
that it will make it
go through the cracks.
- [Teacher] And Jasper, what
did your group discuss,
that you observed the second time
you poured in the water that was different
from the first time you poured it in?
- [Jasper] The runoff water was kind
of even with the recharge.
- [Teacher] But before you measured
it, before you were just
making your observations and watching,
what did you observe?
- [Jasper] That the first time, that there was
there was more runoff because the
dirt wasn't that moist.
- [Teacher] Oh.
Great, so that's what
you wrote down for your
number two?
And I have a question for you Christian.
How much water, are you the drain person?
- [Christian] Yeah.
- [Teacher] How much rain did you
pour in on trial number one?
- [Christian] 1,000 milliliters.
- [Teacher] So this is interesting.
How much did you measure
after trial number one?
- [Christian] 900.
- [Teacher] So what happened
to the rest of the water?
- [Christian] It stayed into the soil.
(Girls gasp)
- [Girl in blue] Oh!
So that's why the soil's all wet.
'Cause there's still water underneath it.
- [Christian] So it's like
100 milliliters there's about
100 milliliters left in here.
- [Teacher] How did you get 100?
- [Christian] Because 900 plus 100 equals 1,000.
- [Teacher] Good job!
Alright, I'll leave you to it.
(Background Chatter)
- [Girl in white] Four three five, would equal...
806.
Okay, we need to have less
water than the last time.