(Background Chatter)
- [Boy in white] That one hurts.
- [Voiceover] It says volume by, use the
formula to find the volume...
- [Amy] Okay, so.
I got 53 when I added up the numbers.
- [Voiceover] Yeah, I did, too.
- [Amy] I took it and divided by three.
- [Voiceover] 17.6666.
- [Amy] Just do 17.6.
- [Hayden] No, 17 point three sixes.
So, we'll just...
- [Amy] Just, no,
Hayden, we have to find 17.666
'cause all six of them, put 17.6.
- [Hayden] I know, but, we are now, let's
just round it up one to 18.
- [Amy] Okay.
- [Hayden] Yeah.
- [Amy] So, with average, it's 18.
Okay.
- [Amy] So, now, we have to do,
based on our average, how
close were you to your guess,
so, how close were we to
our guesses, so, like...
- [Alina] I was close by seven.
- [Hayden] I was close by nine.
- [Amy] We have 18 here, how
far was nine and 18?
- [Alina] I don't know.
Nine.
- [Amy] Nine plus nine is 18, right?
- [Alina] Oh, yeah.
- [Amy] So, write nine right here.
I was by five.
Okay.
All right, based on our average,
how many drops would it
take to make one liter?
- [Hayden] 18,000.
- [Amy] What?
Oh, yeah.
- [Hayden] You got
us correct a few times.
- [Alina] Multiply it by...
- [Hayden] If we had it to drops
times 1000, 'cause that's
how many milliliters
are in a liter, we get 10,000.
- [Amy] Okay, so now, we do water disposal.
Follow the directions to find
the volume of three marbles
using water fluid.
So, first, we have to add
20 milliliters of water,
milliliters of water to 100 milliliter...
So, we have to add 20
milliliters of water into this.
So, Giselle, you wanna do that?
- [Giselle] No.
- [Amy] Okay.
- [Alina] That, yeah.
- [Amy] Pour it so this gets to 20, okay?
- [Alina] I'll pour it then.
(Background Chatter)
- [Amy] Oops, whoa, okay.
- [Hayden] Try not to put too much.
- [Amy] I'll pour it out.
- [Hayden] Let's try
again, it, with a dropper.
- [Amy] No, you're supposed
to do it with a beaker.
- [Hayden] I know, but if
we're really, really close,
and we can't do it with a beaker,
then we're gonna have
to do it with a dropper.
- [Alina] So, we just do this.
- [Amy] Okay, we're at 20.
I think that's 20.
- [Alina] We're at 19
- [Hayden] I got it.
- [Amy] Okay.
- [Amy] Just...
Don't drop it too fast 'cause...
I, okay.
Okay.
So, now we have to add
the three marbles, so...
- [Giselle] We'll
bring 'em on this side.
- [Amy] Yeah, you have one, Hayden
has one, and I have one.
- [Hayden] No, let Alina have one.
You do...
- [Amy] Alina poured the water.
So, it's you, Amy, and Hayden.
- [Hayden] Okay.
- [Amy] Okay, so, we have to like,
tilt it to roll down the cylinder.
- [Giselle] I think I can do it.
- [Amy] Yeah, I know, but it's the easiest way.
- [Hayden] No, not
that much, you don't wanna,
don't wanna pour some out.
Sayonara, sucker.
- [Amy] Okay, the water level now is 26 exactly.
All right, so it went from 20 to 26.
So, the difference in volume is six,
and the volume of the three
marbles is six, right?
What do you think, Alina?
- [Alina] Yeah.
- [Amy] How do you think I got six?
- [Alina] I don't know.
- [Amy] Well, subtracted 20 from 26.
Because it's 20 before
the marbles and 26 after,
so the marbles must be...
- [Teacher] Okay.
- [Hayden] Kay?
- [Teacher] How we doin' over here?
- [Hayden] Pretty good.
- [Teacher] All right, I'm gonna ask you a couple
of questions about volume.
What have you learned about volume so far?
Whenever you...
Alina, look at the board
that I made for you, okay?
Whenever you drop drops of water
into the graduated cylinder,
what's happening to the volume?
- [Girl in yellow] What happened?
- [Teacher] What happened to the
volume of the water?
- [Amy] It was at 20 and then 26.
- [Alina] It got higher?
- [Amy] It went higher.
- [Teacher] It went higher,
okay, so we can say, then,
that volume does what?
- [Amy] What did it do?
- [Alina] Rise.
- [Teacher] It rose, okay.
Volume rises, okay, so, the volume rose,
good, and what did you find for the volume
of the three marbles
using water displacement?
Did you get that far yet?
- [Amy] Yep.
- [Teacher] Okay.
- [Amy] We got six because the
water was at 20 before,
and then after we put the
marbles in, it was at 26,
so, it's six 'cause you have to subtract
the 26 minus 20.
- [Teacher] Good, okay.
If you can switch places with me,
I wanna be able to hear Alina.
Okay.
All right, so, I'm gonna
ask you another question.
When you were doing-- if you got six,
if the volume of those three
marbles is six milliliters
according to what you have,
we need to change that
to a solid measurement, okay?
This is the solid measurement, cubes,
that we use to measure solids.
Marbles are solids.
So, Alina, can you, can anyone tell me
how we transfer that six
milliliters to cubes?
To centimeter cubes?
- [Hayden] Each one of
those is a gram, and if...
- [Teacher] Each one of these is
a gram, that's correct.
- [Hayden] And if one milliliter
is equal to one centimeter
cubed, and all, and in that
case, it must also be equal
to one gram, so that's why for this,
I wrote that the difference
in volume was six grams
and the volume of three
marbles is six grams.
I could also figure out that
these are our three marbles,
and we have six grams,
then each one of them
is 15 grams.
- [Teacher] Okay, but grams, is
that a unit of volume,
or is that a unit of mass?
- [Alina] Mass.
- [Hayden] Mass.
- [Teacher] Good, Alina,
it's a unit of mass.
So, what Hayden said is correct.
One centimeter, one milliliter
is equal to one gram,
one milliliter of water
but what do we know about
the cubic centimeters?
We need to put the units in this term.
So, if you got six
milliliters for the volume
of the three marbles,
then how can we change it
to centimeters cubed?
How many milliliters is this,
is one centimeter cubed?
Do you remember, one.
It's a one to one ratio, like
Eli told us in home room.
So, six milliliters must also be equal
to six centimeters cubed.
So, and this is the unit of
volume, but you're also right,
the mass must be, it will
also be equal to one gram,
but we're talking about volume, not mass.
- [Girl in gray] So, it's the weight, it's the volume.
- [Voiceover] Yeah.
- [Girl in gray] It has to do with three
times three times four.
- [Voiceover] But you have to explain why.
- [Girl in gray] Because...
- [Voiceover] So, how do we know this?
- [Girl in gray] (Background Chatter)
- [Ryan] But why do we do that?
- [Girl in gray] You don't know the answer right now.
- [Summer] Because it said that...
(Background Chatter)
- [Summer] Three cubic centimeters.
And a height of three cubic centimeters...
- [Ryan] I don't know if that's really a three
with a height of four.
- [Summer] Yeah, with a height of four.
So, we have to do our work.
- [Girl in gray] 'Cause we built the work right there.
And like...
(Background Chatter)
(door shutting)
- [Summer] Height from a...
(Background Chatter)
- [Girl in gray] And the height.
Hold on.
So...
So, Summer, three times three, and then...
- [Summer] Yeah, times four.
- [Girl in gray] I'm up to three times three.
That's nine, and then times four
gives you three times...
- [Summer] When I did this, it
was four times three,
I know that.
(Background Chatter)
- [Summer] Is...
- [Girl in gray] So, three times...
- [Summer] 16.
- [Ryan] No.
- [Girl in gray] Three times three is
nine, times four is...
- [Ryan] Okay, it's three times four--
Okay, it's nine times four.
Why would that be 60?
- [Summer] 36.
- [Girl in gray] Yeah, so, we did three times three,
we calculated nine times three.
- [Ryan] So, that gives you nine,
and then because there's a height
of three, you multiply by
four, which gives you 36
because it's a basic math problem.
- [Girl in gray] And it gives you 36.
(Background Chatter)
Okay.
So, explain why you know that.
And then...
- [Ryan] And then we go on to number two.
- [Girl in gray] But wait for her to finish.
- [Ryan] I am.
I'm just gonna be a little...
Change the length, width, and height
of the rectangular prism
without changing its volume.
Try and it and explain.
Of course not, because
we're gonna feel like
I think is something's wrong.
- [Girl in gray] Well, we can...
- [Ryan] Well, I guess if...
- [Girl in gray] No we can't 'cause you can take that one
off the building height.
- [Ryan] No, we could tip this
over this way.
and solve for--
- [Girl in gray] Why would you do that?
- [Ryan] What?
We're done with problem one.
- [Girl in gray] So, now...
- [Ryan] So, I guess we could.
Yeah.
But, no, but in, we'd still have,
we would still have the same volume.
- [Summer] All right, so the next
problem is can you change...
- [Ryan] Summer, are you still--
- [Summer] I'm fine.
- [Ryan] I know, but we already read it though.
- [Girl in gray] She can read, she
needs to read it, Ryan.
- [Ryan] So, what, say we couldn't
because the numbers,
we'll have to do the, oh wait, no.
- [Girl in gray] No, we could...
- [Ryan] No, because like, we won't...
- [Girl in gray] We're doing the height and we
turn it sideways.
(Background Chatter)
- [Ryan] Yes, we would.
It's true.
- [Girl in gray] Okay.
- [Ryan] So...
- [Teacher] So...
How are you guys doing?
- [Girl in gray] For number two, we wanted
to, we had it like this,
and we wanted to turn it sideways
'cause that would change
the height around...
- [Teacher] Okay, so let's talk about number two,
that's the one you're on?
- [Ryan] I'm completely knocked it over.
- [Teacher] All right, so, the
question is, on number two,
can you change the length, width?
Can you change the
length, width, and height
of the rectangular prism
without changing its volume?
Try it and explain.
Okay, so, first of all, the
first rectangular prism,
you built, so this
rectangular prism, okay,
was one centimeter, I mean,
three centimeters long.
- [Girl in gray] We did three times three, it was nine
because it had a line...
(Background Chatter)
So, three times three is
nine, then times four,
times height of four, I don't know.
- [Teacher] Okay, so this is the
rectangular prism you built
for number one, correct?
Okay, and then you just
multiply its length
times its width, times its height,
and what did you get, Summer?
- [Summer] I got 36.
- [Teacher] 36.
- [Ryan] And I'm thinking that more than one
thing can equal 36, like if we had...
- [Teacher] Okay, so, how many cubes
did you use to get this?
- [Ryan] Two for 36.
- [Teacher] This 36?
How many cubes were there in all?
- [Ryan] In all, that was 36.
- [Teacher] It was 36, you had to
count out the cubes, right?
So, can you use the same
36 cubes in number two?
- [Ryan] But have
like, a different height.
- [Teacher] But have a different
length, width, and height?
- [Ryan] Well yeah,
the answer would be yes
because more, there are multiple pieces,
you could do six like, well,
you do two, three, and six.
- [Teacher] Okay.
- [Ryan] Two times three
equals six, six times six equals 36.
- [Teacher] Two times three times
six would equal 36.
- [Ryan] Right, as long as the
three would be height.
(mumbling)
So, six could be this.
- [Teacher] Okay.
Summer, what do you think?
They think you can change these numbers
and it still be 36 cubes.
Could you still use 36 cubes,
build a rectangular prism,
and, but get different numbers here?
You can, why do you think so?
- [Summer] Because it has to change it
from, then, like, the 36
would still be the same.