- Now, what you just did
was
count how many times
you made a successful...
Eric...
...you made a successful throw
and how many times you
made a successful catch,
out of 10.
All right, we're going
to use that information
that you just gathered
to answer the questions on
this form that you've got.
You each should have your
own reflection sheet,
all right,
and I'm going to allow you to
as a group, as a partnership,
I'm going to allow you to
talk about the answers
together, which is just fine,
because with your partner helping you,
you might learn something
about your throwing ability,
or catching ability,
that you might not have
picked up on your own.
All right so... [inaudible]
Now,
if you look at the backside,
if you start here,
[inaudible]
each of you should have
your sheet in front of you,
OK
and you should have a pencil
or you have [inaudible]
and I'm going to read this to you
to help you best understand it.
This is a chart to help you gauge
your abilities
and for your progress
from the start of throwing
the Frisbee up to this point.
It's broken up into four categories.
One, you see where I'm pointing at here.
It says, Beginning;
Two, Developing;
Three, Proficient;
and Four, Excellent.
So the question you
have to ask yourself is,
"Am I still in beginning
stages of throwing Frisbee?"
In other words, do I use
correct Frisbee throwing form
sometimes?
Two, it says, "Do I use correct form
"some to most of the time?"
Three, proficient.
Do I use correct form
when throwing the Frisbee
or catching the Frisbee
most of the time?
And four, excellent.
Do I use correct form all of the time?
All right.
So this is what you are
going to test yourself on.
I'll read it to you,
and as I read it to you I
want you to mark the boxes.
Again, you can talk to your partner
and make this assessment with
your partner if you'd like.
So sitting with your partner,
you're talking about it.
I'm going to read it as we go.
Number one, movement.
Do you move to meet the
Frisbee's expected location?
Are you at the beginning stages of that,
developing stages, proficient stages,
or are you excellent at it?
Do you always move to meet
the Frisbee's location?
Sometimes, most of the time, or rarely?
Give yourself a check in the box
of where you think that belongs.
Body position.
OK, this is how you position yourself
to the oncoming Frisbee
aside from moving to it,
this is how you square your body with it.
Are you in the beginning stages,
where you rarely do it well,
are you in the developing stages,
where you do it sometimes,
the proficient stages, where
you do it most of the time,
or are you in the excellent
stage where you do it
all of the time?
Ask yourself that question.
Feel free to discuss it with your partner.
All right, so you should
be checking the boxes.
You should be checking the boxes.
That's right there.
- [Student in gray] The
boxes are already checked.
- Next,
Hand position.
When catching the Frisbee,
do you use proper hand positioning
with your palms together, fingers opening,
rarely?
That makes you in the beginning stage.
Sometimes?
That's your developing stage.
Do you do it most of the time?
That puts you in the proficient stage.
Do you do it always?
That puts you in the excellent stage.
What do you think? What is your target?
What would you put a grade on?
Now when it comes to the throwing,
the same things apply.
Your stance
and your elbow.
Are you at the beginning?
And I'm not going to go into detail
with each one of these now,
I think you get the idea of
how these check [inaudible].
Are you at the beginning stage,
the developing stage,
the proficient stage,
or the excellent stage?
When it comes to your stance
and your elbow position.
When it comes to wrist snap and point
OK
what stage are you at?
Are you rarely, sometimes,
mostly, or always?
Again, beginning, developing,
proficient, or excellent?
And then lastly, when it
comes to releasing the Frisbee
what stage do you think you're at:
the beginning, the developing,
the proficient, or the excellent?
So I want you to just think about that
reflect on that,
but I'm not grading you on this.
I'm not grading you on your ability.
Hey, Mike, would you sit up for me?
Thanks bud.
I want you just to reflect on
what you have learned and your ability.
All right?
Now, with your partner,
I want you to turn the page over
and it says Frisbee throw reflections, OK,
and then we have some questions
that we need to answer.
We discussed what angular momentum was,
we discussed what force absorption was,
and we discussed what force reduction was.
With your partner, I want
you to answer those questions
that you see, one through seven.
Number one: why is angular
momentum important?
Two: describe force reduction.
Three: describe force absorption.
Four: considering...[inaudible]
You don't have to do this...
I'm just reading them out
loud before you do it.
Considering the fitness
components of speed, agility,
endurance, and balance,
to which sports would you
compare Ultimate Frisbee?
If you think about when
we were playing Ultimate,
the game of Ultimate,
what sports would you compare that to?
- [Student offscreen] Football!
- No, you have...
do it with your partner.
And a couple more questions.
Where can Frisbee be played for fun?
What are two popular Frisbee activities
that you are aware of?
You already know one
that we played in class.
You might know of another two.
And then lastly,
based on the activity you
did just before we sat here,
how many times did you
catch your Frisbee out of 10
and how many times did you
accurately throw the Frisbee
out of 10?
OK?
So go ahead with your partner
and go ahead and start
answering those questions
to the best of your ability.
You guys should be working off one another
and sharing your answers,
ready, set, go.
(background chatter)
- [Student in red] Do
we basically [inaudible]
- No, just rewrite it.
- [Student in green] Force absorption?
- You absorb the force
when you [inaudible].
Describe force absorption.
- [Student in green] [inaudible]
- Yeah, OK, start with that
and maybe go a little farther
and describe what makes it...