[Voiceover] They're right angles.
Yes, yes, yes, yes.
- Okay, so...
- [Voiceover] They're equal
because of Right Angles Theorem
- You are skipping a step.
Again. Trevor, tell him the
definition of an altitude.
You tell me I have an altitude.
You have to tell me then
what's the consequence of an altitude.
Read the definition of
an altitude. Say it.
- The definition of an altitude is that
it intersects the
opposite side of the angle
at a perpendicular angle.
I don't know how to word that right,
but...
- Somebody help him out.
He's making sense, but somebody...
Yes.
- Alright.
It goes through the opposite vertex
and it intersects the
opposite line perpendicularly,
if that's a word.
- Don't say through because
an altitude is bounded.
It starts at a vertex and it goes...
Okay, so! Now, Isaac,
What should be the
consequent step two there?
- [Isaac] Right here?
- Yes.
Whatever they gave you
in those definitions,
Trevor's and the improved
definition by Trey,
nobody said anything
about congruent angles.
What did we talk?
- [Student] That
they're both right angles.
- [Isaac] That they're right angles.
- No, we didn't.
- That BD is perpendicular to AC.
- Ah-ha!
- That's what I got.
- Nice. That's what it is.
So, just write on top of that, honey.
- [Isaac] Right here?
- Yeah, the step two,
you should have that.
Right? You have to go with the definitions
when you have a justification
because that's what reason says.
It comes from a defintion.
- [Isaac] And why is that
because of...
- Tell him. Why is that?
- Definition of altitude.
[No dialogue]
- Okay. You see how when we were
working with the picture,
we put those boxes on the triangle.
What did those boxes say, indicate?
- [Isaac] That they're right angles.
- They're right angles, okay.
So, that should be...
And why do we have right angles?
Somebody tell me.
Why do we have right angles?
- Definition of perpendicular lines.
- Yes.
That's a consequence if you
have perpendicular lines.
- [Isaac] So, I'm going to write,
ADB and CDB are right angles?
- [Student] Yes.
- [Student] Yeah.
- Okay.
[No dialogue]
- [Teacher] You guys, the
rest of you might have started
with the fact that it's
an angle bisector, right?
- [Student] Yeah.
- And that's okay if
you started with that.
It's okay. Doesn't matter.
You could have started with
the BD is congruent to BD.
You don't have to start with a given,
but that's traditionally the way we do it.
[No dialogue]
- I can't believe I got this.
It's because of...
- [Students] It's the definition
of perpendicular lines.
[No dialogue]
- [Isaac] What's this?
- Okay, wait. Breathe in and out.
Now, let's go see what's going on.
Okay, step to the side.
ADB and CDB.
Okay. Still, you need to have
an angle, a side, and an angle.
Do you have a congruent angle?
After all that work.
- [Isaac] I'm going to do that now.
- Okay, what are you going to put?
- [Isaac] Angle ADB
is congruent to angle CDB
because the definition of right angles.
- [Student] Nope!
- [Student] Right Angle Congruency
- [Isaac] Right Angle Congruency Theory.
- Well, I haven't...
- What is the definition of right angle?
- That all right angles are congruent.
- What's the definition of a right angle?
- 90 degrees
- It measures 90 degrees
- Yeah, yeah.
All right angles are congruent
is the Right Angle Theorem
that he's writing.
[No dialogue]
Okay, let's see what we have.
If you would number them, that would help.
That's one. And what's the
consequence for after one?
- [Isaac] I'm trying.
[No dialogue]
I am old and somewhat blind from here.
But I know...
Is that a "2" right under that?
At the perpendicular line,
you have "2". What is that?
- [Isaac] AD is perpendic...
- No, after that.
- [Isaac] Angle ADB
is congruent to angle CDB.
- Wait. He wrote it.
- [Isaac] It's all jumbled up
and it's all there, so...
- But, wait a minute.
Let's make sense out of this
because it has to flow, okay?
You know when you have
your perpendicular line,
What should be at the
perpendicular line?
The direct consequence if
you have perpendicular lines,
is what?
- [Isaac] That the angles are...
- Somebody, somebody
- [Students] That they're right angles.
- [Isaac] I want to say that,
but then--
(Laughter)
I just don't want to say
something that's wrong
- No, you're fine.
You were not here yesterday.
And it seems you're doing great.
Hey, so, take the blue marker,
so that everybody can see.
Take the blue marker because
I would like to re-number it
so they can see it, okay?
So, re-number them again.
One is the given, the altitude.
- [Isaac] So, you want me
to write over?
- Yes.
And then that's two.
Now, what should be three?
Don't put three on that one.
What should be three?
Somebody tell him.
- The angles.
- The right angles.
- Yes.
- Okay, now, honey, after
you have right angles,
what are you going to say?
- [Isaac] That, uh, Definition
of Right Angle Theorem.
- No.
- Okay, so right angles. What
happens after right angles?
Because remember angles are angles.
I need to talk about angle congruency.
But, you haven't said that.
You talked about right angles.
So now, what are you going to say?
You have it there, honey.
- [Isaac] Angle ADB
is congruent to angle CDE.
- Okay, so that should be the next step.
- [Isaac] That's four.
- Okay, you remember. Good. Great.
Remember when I asked
you at the beginning,
when we first started doing
proofs, to keep track.
So, you have mentioned an
angle congruent to an angle?
- [Isaac] Yeah, right here.
- Not yet, we haven't
touched that guy yet.
We don't even have a number for that guy.
He's just floating in there.
What angle is congruent to what angle?
Have you mentioned that one angle
is congruent to another angle?
- [Isaac] Yeah, ADB is--
- You just did right?
- Okay, go cross out one of the As.
I don't think you specifically did this,
but I've noticed that some of you.
I've noticed in Abby
and I would notice in a couple of you.
Taylor, that you were always...
After you prove something, you
found it within your proof.
You would kind of cross it out in here.
Okay, I found this.
Or some of you would come over here
and actually write it here.
It's like you're taking attendance.
I need angle for an angle.
I already have an angle.
Keeping going.
See what I'm doing here. I
showed you this way back.
Yeah.
- He's probably getting confused
because of number three.
How he put ADB--
because it should be ABD
and DBC instead of ADB.
- [Isaac] Wait, what, what, what?
- Number three. The original number three.
- [Isaac] Yeah
- The B should be in
the middle instead of D.
- It should be ABD and DBC.
- That's right.
- [Student] That's why!
- [Student] That's why! Yeah!
- [Student] I didn't noticed that.
- [Student] Yeah, I thought he put that.
- [Isaac] You guys are smart.
Yeah, that's how you got confused
with everything else.
Okay, so now,
segment BE is congruent
to segment BE because of
reflexive property, so that's
another side.
And then it's given that
BD is an angle bisector,
so that means angle ABD
is congruent to angle CBD
- [Teacher] Okay, but the issue here is
he hasn't listed that as a given, right?
Just like people say, "Well,
you're making that up.
"How do you know that?"
And you just say, "It's given,"
but you didn't write it, --
- Yeah, he did.
- Yeah, yeah he did.
- It's right there.
- It's number four.
- [Student] He just did it wrong.
- [Student] It's backwards.
- [Student] It's all there.
- [Teacher] So, that should
be step... Wait a minute.
One, two, three...
four, five...
- Four should be one
- [Student] Whoa.
- Three should be two
- One should be...
- [Isaac] So, there's
a one, two, three, four...
and then five...
Wait, five, right here.
- [Student] Six right above it.
- [Isaac] six, seven.
- [Teacher] Okay, can
you change the numbers?
- [Student] Fix the numbers.
- [Teacher] Yeah,
please fix the numbers.
- [Isaac] It's there.
- Okay, we got it.
We have an angle bisector,
the consequence of an angle bisector.
We have an altitude, the
consequence of an altitude.
We have reflexive property, so
do you have them all?
- [Isaac] Yeah.
- So, what could you say now?
The triangle...
I'm going back to the black marker...
[Classroom chatter]
[No dialogue]
Okay, let's get him out
of the hot seat, okay?
Micah!
Yes, Micah.
You tell us, is he
finished with the proof?
- No.
- Why?
- Because you said no.
- Who said no?
- You.
- But okay, you're supposed
to tell me if there's something.
- Well, you have to put that...
it is the... I don't know.
- Frank to the rescue!
- He hasn't proved that
it's isosceles yet.
- And how do you prove
that it's isosceles?
- I don't really know.
- That sounded so tough, Frank.
- Yes.
- Okay, you say, segment AB and segment BC
are congruent by C...
Wait, how do you say it?
- CPCTC.
- Corresponding Parts of
Congruent Triangles are Congruent.
- I always mess it up!
- I can't do the CPC...
I can't do that.
I say the whole thing.
[Background chatter]
Okay, now, Frank, is he finished?
- [Student] I think.
- [Teacher] Is he?
- [Student] No.
- [Student] Not yet.
- [Teacher] No, he's not.
Okay, why? Tell him why.
- Since you have the two sides congruent
and the isosceles triangle
needs two sides congruent,
then you can say that the
triangle is isosceles now
because AB is congruent to BC.
- So what should be his number 10?
- Triangle ABC is isosceles.
And that would be the definition
of an isosceles triangle.
Yes!
- [Student] I'm so proud.
- It keeps getting better.
I told you it would get better.
- [Student] Teamwork.
- [Student] I was stressing
last night because I was like,
it's so hard.
- [Isaac] Okay, you guys
understand what this means, but
I'm trying to hurry it.
- [Student] Good job, Isaac.
- [Student] Yeah, Isaac, a good job.
- Very good, Isaac!
One big clap for Isaac, one, two, three
(One clap from everyone)
- Alright!
- Yeah!
- You did good!
(Laughter)
Okay, so. You know what?
- This is the proof, that the new
program where I give you...
because I want to
make sure you get it...
enough information to do
this on our own, okay?
And then, I'm not going to
write it out.
We're going to talk about how to do it.
And then you're going to
complete it tonight at home.
So, what do we need to do?
What is given there?
Jonathan. What's given?
- The middle one?
- [Teacher] This one, honey.
- CB is an angle bisector of ACB.
CD is an angle bisector of ACB.
- [Teacher] Okay,
what does that give you?
Once you have an angle bisector?
No, that's not it. Don't look at that one.
That's a totally different proof.
This is one that I'm
going to give you tonight.
So, what does CD being an angle
bisector of angle ACB mean?