- A lot of people thought the
mass of the water in the bag
would be less than the mass
of the ice cubes in the bag.
How many people?
One, two, just three of you.
Okay.
Cameron, do you want to start
us off with your reason why?
- Because the, 'cause you can
put water in a water bottle
to put in the freezer,
then that water bottle
will like, explode, because
it has so much ice in it.
- Okay.
So because the water,
when it freezes, expands,
then therefore, you're
saying it has more mass?
- Yeah.
- When it's frozen.
- Yes.
- But when it melts, it doesn't take up
so much space, so it has less mass.
- Yes.
- Okay. Michael.
Do you or are you on the
same idea as far as more,
as far as thinking there's less?
Was your reason the same
as his or do you have
a different reason why
it's going to be less?
- Mine was the same.
- [Voiceover] Same idea?
- Yeah.
- [Voiceover] Okay.
Hannah, you got a thought or something?
- Well, isn't it like, the same?
Isn't it, like, the same thing
because it's the same thing.
It's just expanding, but it's
going to have the same mass.
- [Voiceover] When you're
saying it's the same thing,
what do you mean by the same thing?
- Like, if you have
water in a water bottle,
like it does expand or
whatever, but it still
has the same amount of water
so it still has the same mass.
- [Voiceover] Okay, so Hannah's saying it
doesn't matter that it expands.
It's still the same amount
of stuff, and therefore
it should still have
the same amount of mass.
Is that correct?
'Kay.
Houston, idea on that?
- Well, about the water bottle thing,
it would be opposite to this 'cause
when you start with water, it
takes up the entire bottle.
But the bag, the ice is the one taking up
the minimum space of when
it freezes an entire bag.
So it wouldn't.
- So are you saying if we
let the ice cubes melt,
are you saying the mass is going to go up?
It's going to increase?
- Yeah.
- Okay.
Colby?
- I'd say that when a
solid turns into a liquid,
its form changes, but not its mass.
- [Voiceover] Okay, so kind
of the same idea as Hannah.
Only you're talking about
the actual forms then.
It can change form without changing mass.
Hannah says it's okay to expand
because it's still the
same amount of stuff.  Okay.
Michael's got another
thing thing to talk about.
- Well when you put, like, the
water in the bottle,
and then you, like, freeze it,
then you unfreeze it,
then there's less water
than what you started with,
and it probably would change the mass.
- [Voiceover] Why is it,
so you're saying the amount
of water you put in first
before you freeze it
is more than the amount of water
after you thaw it back out?
- Yeah.
- [Voiceover] Do you have a
reason why that might be?
- Well, no. it's just (mumbles).
- [Voiceover] Okay, any
other ideas on this one?
Okay, how many people thought the
mass would increase, then?
How many people said
the mass would increase?
A couple of you.
Jared, why don't you tell us why
you think the mass would increase.
- I thought the mass
would increase because
water weighs more than ice.
Like if you pick up a bottle
of water that's frozen, it
doesn't weigh as much as a
bottle of water with water in it.
- Okay.
So Jared says that water
weighs more than ice.
Correct?
Anybody else have a different idea?
Anna?
- [Voiceover] Well,
because ice floats on water
so that means it has less mass,
so if it thawed back out, then it'd weigh more.
- Okay. So Anna's using the example
that she's seen ice floating on water,
therefore she's saying the ice must
have less mass than water.
Correct?
Is that what your'e saying?
- [Anna] Mm-hmm.
- Colby, you got something
to say about that?
- I have something to say
about that. It will stay
the same going off of what she's saying.
- Oh, going off of what she's saying.
Okay, go ahead, then.
- Ice is pretty much
the same as, it's water,
it's frozen water, so
it still has the same
density as water, it's just colder.
So, if it's colder, it floats.
Ice because it's cold,
it floats in the water.
- [Voiceover] So you're
saying the floating of ice
has nothing to do with
its density or its mass,
it has to do with its temperature.
'Kay. Houston?
- Well, I think the only reason ice floats
is because an ice would weigh less
because ice isn't completely full.
There's some air in there.
- Okay.
So Houston's saying there's
some air trapped in there
that was not in the water beforehand.
Okay. Anybody else?
Anybody want to have any other arguments
about why the mass should stay the--
Oh, sorry. Anna.
- [Voiceover] Oh, okay.
I disagree with Colby how he said that
it floats because it's
cold when heat rises,
and so if it's cold, wouldn't it sink
if it had to do with the temperature?
- Okay, so Anna's saying that heat rises
and cold sinks, so you don't think
it has to do with temperature?
- [Voiceover] Yeah.
- Okay.
Colby, response to that or are you...?
- Well, in water, it works differently.
Warm water actually
sinks more to the bottom actually,
and cold water's more on the top.
- [Voiceover] Alright.
- So if you put cold in
ice, it will float above.
- [Voiceover] Okay.
Oh, I have some hands up now. Michael?
- Well, when you're in
the lake for example,
the warm part's on top,
and the deeper you go
the colder it gets because heat rises.
- [Voiceover] So you're using
your experience in swimming
or something in a lake.
- Yeah.
- [Voiceover] It's
colder the deeper you go,
warmer towards the surface, you're saying?
- Yeah, so the ice cube
must have oxygen in it
because when we hold
our breath, we float up.
- [Voiceover] Okay.
- When we have no air, we go down.
- [Voiceover] Okay, so
you're saying an ice cube has
air trapped in it, that's
what's causing it to float.
Is that what you're saying?
And Hannah, were you gonna agree with her
as far as the lake
water temperature thing?
- Yeah, so when you put
your sweater or something
in the water, it's like the top is usually
more warm (mumbles) colder.
- [Voiceover] Okay. Alright.
Now people who think the mass
is going to stay the same.
Who are those people?
Who thinks the mass will stay the same?
Gavin, why don't you
give us the reason why
you think it's going to stay the same?
- I think it's going to
stay the same because
nothing's lost when it melts.
Nothing goes away.
It's still the same thing.
- [Voiceover] He's saying it's
going to stay the same
because nothing is lost.
When it melts, it doesn't get lost.
Okay.
Anybody else who says it's
going to stay the same
have something to add?
Gabe?
- I said that...
- [Voiceover] Just talk louder.
- I said that it'll stay the same because
there's still the same amount
of water melted or frozen,
and even if it's in a bag,
if it melts, and tries to...
break down into gas, then
it's still in the bag
so it won't go anywhere.
- [Voiceover] So Gabe's saying
that it doesn't matter
if it's frozen as an ice
cube, if it's melted as water,
or even, he's even going as far as saying
that even if the water, liquid starts
turning into a gas, it's
still going to be the same
because nothing's leaving the bag.
Is that what you're saying?
He's going even a step further,
he didn't even mention anything
about turning into a gas,
but he's saying even if it does that,
it's still not going to change.
Right?
Houston.
- Well, I disagree with
that because if you
take a frozen lake the ice is only on top,
it doesn't freeze all the water.
- Okay.
Hannah.
- I agree with what he said.
Even if there's air bubbles in the ice,
then after it melts, the air
bubbles, it's still in the bag.
It's still concealed in the bag. (mumbles)
- [Voiceover] So sounds like
the people who are for it,
staying it's the same
are really sticking with
the fact that everything's in the bag.
Nothing's out of the bag
or leaving or coming in,
and then the people who are thinking
it's going to increase or decrease
have a lot of ideas about ice having
more mass than water as a solid,
and then some of that's
through the temperature.
Michael, one more before we move on.
- About how it all stays in the bag, well,
when you melt water it sweats.
So wouldn't it lose
some of that. (mutters)
- [Voiceover] So are you
saying some of the moisture's
going to be on the outside of the bag?
- Like, comes off the bag.
If you have it on the table,
then it comes onto the table.
- Like how it has a (mutters)
- [Voiceover] Okay, so here's
my question to you then.
That water that's on
the outside of the bag
that you're talking about?
You were saying that water came
from the inside of the bag?
- Well, it sweats from the...
the compression of the temperature.
- [Voiceover] So you're
saying that's what's
causing the mass to go up, then.
- Wouldn't that cause the mass to go down?
- [Voiceover] Okay, so that's
my question to you, then,
is where was that water on
the outside coming from?
- Inside?
- [Voiceover] How is it
getting to the outside?
- I don't know.
Some scientific theory. (laughs)
- [Voiceover] (laughs) Okay.
Does anybody agree with her idea
that some of the water
from the inside might
be getting to the outside?
- [Students] Yeah.
- [Voiceover] Do any of
you guys have an idea
of how that might be
happening to help her out?
James, how do you think that water
might be getting to the outside?
- [James] The moist is like, when it...
What's it called? Wait a minute.
The carbonate, the condensation,
it, like, seeps out, like
the air, it seeps out.
- So somehow you're thinking it's
seeping through the bag.
Colby?
- I know how that happens, actually.
Because the water in the air
will stick to the bag because it's colder.
So it'll stick there
and just condense there
so it'll look like it's (mutters).
It's just water from the air.
- So you're saying the water that forms
on the outside is not
coming from the inside?
It's coming from the
outside, which is different
than what they're saying.
Cameron, did you have any other ideas
how it might be getting out there?
'Kay. Alright.
So we got some different
ideas on that one.
Let's move on now to our
alka-seltzer problem.
(student mutters)
This time, last one we started with people
who thought the mass would decrease.
Let's start with the people who think
the mass will increase.
So people who think the mass is going
to increase with the alka-seltzer.
Who are those people?
Alright.
We're going to have Kyle
start us off on this one.
What's your reason why, Kyle?
- Well, when the tablet dissolves
I think after dissolving, (mumbles)
water will rise and make more.
- [Voiceover] Make more water?
- Yeah.
- Okay.
So Kyle thinks the reaction is going
to create more water,
and therefore, more mass.
- Sam, different idea than that for why
the mass is going to increase?
(Sam mutters)
- Okay, so you're thinking
it's going to increase
because you're adding
something to the water.
Colby?
- I think it's going to increase because
the alka-seltzer tablet will release gases
which will increase the
weight of the bottle inside.
- [Voiceover] Okay so the
gases that is going to be
created from the reaction
are going to add to the mass.
Jake, you had your hand up
for the mass increasing, correct?
Do you have a different reason
why it's going to do that?
(Jake mutters)
- So basically saying,
the same thing as Colby.
More gases.
Hannah.
- Aren't the gases from the water
in the alka-seltzer,
aren't they going to just stay the same?
- [Voiceover] Good question.
So what you're saying, then, is
if the gases are coming from the
alka selzter tablet in water,
so what are you saying the mass will do?
- I think it's going to stay the same.
Actually, it'll decrease.
- [Voiceover] It'll decrease?
Okay, why do you think
it's going to decrease?
- I don't know.
- Okay. (chuckles)
Who could come up with the reason
as to why it might decrease?
Cameron?
Why is it going to decrease?
- Because the acid from the,
from the, from the
tablet, the acid from the
tablet is going to release gases,
and the water will go out of the beaker.
- How is the water going
to get out of the beaker?
- Because the tablet
will react with water,
and the gases will float away.
- But isn't there a lid on top?
- Maybe the lid will pop off or something.
- Let's assume the lid
is does not pop off.
Let's assume I have it
on there tight enough
that it's not going to pop off.
- Then, since air is lighter than water,
then that means that the air,
that means the mass will decrease
because the water will
be like not as much,
and there will be more
gas in the container.
- So. Correct me if I'm wrong.
So you're saying that
assuming the top stays on,
it's still going to decrease.
That's the decrease, right?
Because the solid and liquid
are going to turn into...
- Gas.
- Gas, and gas is lighter
than solids and liquids.
Is that correct? What you're saying?
- [Cameron] Yeah.
- Alright.
Jared has something to say about that.
- I think that the mass
will decrease because
the tablet will disintegrate and that mass
part will be (mumbles) decrease.
- Okay, so he's saying that the tablet
disappears, then the mass will go down.
That piece that the tablet's bringing
to the table for mass is not
going to be there anymore.
Kevin, what are you thinking?
- Pretty much the same thing
that the tablet's going to dissolve
into the water.
- [Voiceover] And so mass will go down?
- [Kevin] Yeah.
- Okay.
- [Voiceover] Who thinks the
mass is going to stay the same?
It's not going to change.
Who thinks it will stay the same?
Why don't you tell us why
it's going to stay the same?
- I think it's going to
stay the same because
the water, the alka-seltzer piece
is a water, it's just in a different form.
But everything is still (mumbles).
- Okay.
So you're saying because
nothing's going away,
it's still going to be the same.
It's just in a different form.
So kind of like what some people
were saying about ice in the water.
Gabe, do you have a
different reason than that?
- No, it was a lot like hers.
- [Voiceover] It was the
same as hers, pretty much?
- Yeah.
- Okay.
Anybody got anything else they
want to input on the alka-seltzer one?
Why it might go up, down or
stay the same before we move on?
- Gavin?
- I said it would probably go down
because if you have a bunch of gas
in a bottle, it'll probably weigh a lot
less than a cup full of
water, like the same amount.
- [Voiceover] Okay, so you're
going again with the idea
that gas has less mass than
the water and the tablet.
And since we're turning them into
gases, the mass will go down.
James.
- I said since the tablet is
gonna be kind of shrinked,
once it mixes with the water, it'll stand,
making it a lot more liquidy and bigger
and then the mass will get higher.
- The mass will increase
because it'll produce the...
(James mutters)
Alright. Let's go to burning paper.
Alright.  Burning paper.
Let's start with the people,
this time, let's start with
the people who think the
mass will stay the same.
People who think the
mass still stay the same.
- Colby's the only one.
Morgan. Gabe.
Not very many. Jasmine.
Morgan, why don't you start us off
for why you think it's going
to stay the same.
- I said the mass will stay the same
because the air and everything else
is still in the jar and
it's not going anywhere.
- Okay she says it stays the same because
everything is still in the
jar not going anywhere.
Jasmine, you had your hand up.
Do you think the same
thing as her or do you have
a different reason for why
it would stay the same?
- I agree with her.
- [Voiceover] You agree
with what she said?
- Colby?
- Burning stuff does not add.
It's still the object, but
it's more spread apart.
- [Voiceover] Okay, so the
mass stays the same, you said.
It's just we're going to
take up more space with it.
Okay.
Michael? No? Yes?
- I was stretching.
- [Voiceover] Hannah?
- I disagree with that because
it, when it burns, (mutters)
I don't know if that's the
word for it, but how it's
(mutters) causing it all, when you burn
wood in a fire, eventually
all that will turn into ashes,
so I don't think it has
the same mass or anything.
- [Voiceover] Okay. James,
you got some more on that?
- When that paper burns, it'll turn into
charcoal which basically
is lighter than paper,
and then that'll make it
so mass will be decreased.
- Okay, so given the idea that
we're taking the solid things,
and we're changing them into maybe
non-solids, so either
liquids or liquid acids
they're not gonna have
as much mass as those.
Edward, what do you think?
Do you think this mass will
go up, down or stay the same?
- I think it will decrease.
- [Voiceover] Decrease?
- Yeah.
- [Voiceover] And what's
your reason for that?
- 'Cause when the paper burns,
it turns into a gas,
so some of it, and then
gas is, has less mass than solid objects.
- [Voiceover] Okay, so again, back to that gas is
less mass than solid objects.
Kayla, what do you think?
Increase? Decrease?
Or stay the same?
- I thought it would
decrease, like what Hannah--