And...
So I wanted to
talk about impulse which
I think is the important
part about brain injuries.
I guess, because it has to do
with the time you have
and the force you feel.
So as we know...
Impulse...
equals
force times the change in time.
So that's impulse.
So when you get hit,
if you have... anyone
ever played football,
you have little helmets or if you've ever
ridden a bike, they've little pads on there,
and whenever you get hit,
those pads are on there to
make the time be a little bit longer.
So if you have bigger time,
if you have a big force,
it's going to decrease.
Because it's force / time.
Right?
So what they're trying to do is
helmets is...
This is one of the questions.
We have what we tell 'em
and you use science to prove it.
It's... What will you
tell them to do?
So... -Edward, let me just say...
Sorry to...
But to clarify the design,
Yes, the design of the helmet
So how would
you design the helmet
so that you
could have less force?
Because if you have less force,
that means that
your brain is going to move
less because of momentum.
So you're going to have
less momentum coming at you.
And...
So is that completely inelastic?
Ask Ether
That's completely
inelastic, right?
When something is not moving
and then you just hit it and then...
Yeah.
All right. So we have
completely inelastic or inelastic.
So if you raise up...,
if you have a big force,
and you have small time,
which is what people have
when they get hit with helmet.
So if you didn't have a helmet at all,
you'd get hit right away, right?
But if you have your helmet,
you're not going to hit the other side of your helmet, so...
a little bit longer, because
it's going to take the padding.
So if you have lot of padding,
so if you have like a
huge helmet like this,
and you got hit,
you'd have to get...
The padding would have to
go all the way here, then hit you
and then it'd have to come over
here and hit the padding again.
So what would
happen to the force?
The force... If you have a longer time,
the force is still down.
So what I wanted
to ask you guys is-
How would you design
a helmet to make this?
So using this science,
to make it so that
people get less concussions
or the concussions
that are not as dangerous.
So I was looking in
materials to the helmets,
and I find out that
The problem is not the helmet,
the problem is the money.
(unintelligible) to have like
the 250
(unintelligible) the X1 is the
most expensive one.
So we also talk about-
there are more concussion
in high school football than in uh...
-NFL
Yeah...
So here's like... you can see that
the professional players who
can pay that money.
They're really rich,
so there's so much sponsors
that they pay for their helmets.
But like in... high school football
what they want is long pass
(unintelligible) cheaper material
So they don't
care much about
The health about the guys,
they want to go just...
Their problem is
the money of the helmets.
How much cost of helmet is...
like helmets with
Kevlar or that stuff.
like they use in
the military equipment.
(unintelligible)
So how can we combine
your thoughts and your thoughts
so that we can
save these thoughts?
So what kind of
ideas you guys have?
How could you design a helmet
so it's not this big
or really neat and super expensive?
The type of padding we use
So what ideas
do you guys have?
So what kind of...
So you play football...
What kind of padding right
now is inside of the helmet?
I mean they're not soft.
It's like it's air glove.
It's almost like a hard
balloon stuck to your head.
So it's just one on the side
and the whole top is full.
and one on the other side
and one in the back.
But that's it. I mean, you could
actually feel the hit.
But it... you just
don't get a concussion, unless
you're heavy.
So have
you ever been hit?
Have you ever had
a helmet to helmet contact?
So where did you get hit?
My head
Almost like right here.
On top of your head.
-Right, but there's padding there.
Oh, but you said
you could still feel it.
I mean, I could feel it for like
a quick couple of seconds or so.
Then it just goes away.
It's because of
the padding, I guess.
It's... umm...
It's like (unintelligible)
So is there any
way that you would change
the design of the
helmet that you have now?
Um...more cushion.
Okay. So that's
kind of going back to
what Angel was talking about.
So how can
we change the design
to make it more cushiony, but...
Because if you have
something that's too cushiony,
right, is that going
to decrease the time?
or increase the time
and decrease the force?
if it's really cushiony?
Oh, that's really cushiony?
-Yeah
Oh, you mean
like it will just go...
Yeah.
-No.
Right. So you're saying
you want it more cushiony,
you're saying you want it cheaper,
you're saying you want it smaller.
I think like what Matt's kind of saying is more
for comfort than for safety. -Right. Right.
So why... So can you relate sort of to what
Angel's saying and why if it is more cushiony
it would be more dangerous.
Umm, with the head rattling?
Like if it hits on this side,
it's quicker to hit the other side.
Is that what you mean?
what? So how...?
So think about how
the padding is right now.
How it's stiff
compared to something
that kind of gave.
So think about
relating this back to force
times the change in time.
You can ask...
If it's built too soft, it's
going to hit you with a stronger force...
So what could
happen to the time?
It's going to be slower, it's going to be faster.
It's going to be faster, so what's
going to happen to the force?
The force is going to increase...
So it's going to hurt even
more and it will
be more dangerous.
So what you need is like a stable
material that
not too soft, but at the same time
So besides Kevlar,
which you brought up which is
I was thinking like (unintelligible)
like for example
when you are hit
and you're hit you want that
like bulletproof
(unintelligible) that the force spreads in
all the space of the body of the helmet. So is you are
hit here, all the force is not concentrated in this place,
but is moving over all the helmet.
So it displaces the
force so it's not on one area.
So I was like
thinking like maybe
like this big, the helmet
then in the middle like
like a wave
like when it hits,
it spreads to all the helmet.
So that's you versus less (unintelligible)
you spread all the
force on your head
so you have like less
(unintelligible)
Something that will
transfer the motion
Yeah.
I like this idea.
But what I was thinking is that
we could put layers
so instead of hitting
the helmet right away
you hit something cushiony first
so have something
cushiony on the outside
so that it takes time
for you to hit the helmet.
And once you hit the
helmet, the small cushiony
so that it takes
time for that to hit
the other hard part
which would then hit cushion again
and then hit you.
So kind of
like an atmosphere.
Yeah, it will have
like little layers
It will probably have to make
the helmet a little bit like bigger.
But not like...
Don't make it like huge,
but have layers on there.
and then incorporate his idea
when you're making waves.
So something
like that first layer
could help
dissipate the force.
So we have cushiony
against cushiony like boxers use.
And then they have the
hard part on the bottom
when they do little wrapping.
So we have the
cushiony part first.
So it's going to take time and
I think that's what they use.
They put cushion on there,
so that it takes time for you
to actually feel the force.
So that the force will be less.
And if you have
cushion with cushion
It's because you
are increasing the time.
Yeah, because if you have two
helmets that are hitting each other,
that are cushion and cushion,
it will take longer for
them to hit each other.
And then the force
will be decreased.
My question for Matt is-
How big is the helmet?
Oh! The padding?
It's like thick.
It's kind of thick.
That's just the padding
and then you have the helmet,
which is like that
much more. -Yeah.
It's like that thick.
How heavy is the helmet?
Like when you're wearing it,
does it feeling like it's weighing you down?
Yeah, it takes time to get used to it.
And that day, you're neck will hurt.
That's how heavy it is.
Another version of like
what we are trying to do.
I think it'd also be cool.
Maybe like helmet
were like it was fitted to like the head
and then it'd have like
inbetween kind of like a net structure.
which is a part of uh...
kind of like what he had
but something that is hung.
I want to kind of
imagine it like the bridges.
How they have like
a whole bunch of
little columns
But just a whole bunch that
is attached to the
outside of the helmet.
I will draw it, and I'll show you guys.
You had your hand up, do you want
to share while he...?
Yeah I was wondering, since
we're talking about the injuries
and can you guys give an example of the
type of brain damage that you can get?
Just like an actual name.
Like I heard concussion.
Other injuries, other names.
Can you tell...
What a concussion is?
What is a concussion? Ask the group.
Well, a concussion is when...
It's when you...
your brain between your
actual brain and your skull
There is a liquid,
like Spinal fluid, is it?
and that's supposed
to cushion your brain from
touching the, or hitting, your skull.
But a concussion is when it's
hitting and it's going back and forth.
I mean gradually it will
go back to normal but...
That's my understanding
of concussion.
And you would have lost like feeling
for like one or two seconds
on the biggest
areas of the impact
So what part do you think
is the most dangerous part
to hit of your brain,
on your brain?
The sides.
What do the sides control?
Well, it wasn't like that.
I thinking like in
the structure of the...
of the skull.
So the sides, where
the nerves enter, like
Your optic nerves?-Yeah.
So I think that's like less pain.
It's like a really big hit here
can kill a man.
So I think that hit is worst.
You're saying the skull
is thinnest right there? -Yeah.
It's not as thick
as the other parts.
It's thickest, like right here...
What does your
frontal lobe control?
So that's what
kind of separates us
from other species
is that we have the most
developed frontal lobe.
And then on the sides is
more of your sensory stuff.
and then in the back is your
actually your Occipital lobe
for your eyes is in
the back, a long with
your movement,
your cerebellum.
So different spots,
that's why you have
padding here, and
here and back here,
is to protect all sides of the brain.
So a concussion is just like your
brain keeps vibrating, basically, after the blow?
So I like to think about it, and I meant to bring
this in
and I apologize.
So if you have...
Think about your Tupperware.
and inside the
Tupperware you have an egg.
You just cracked
a nice egg inside
and then you shake it.
So imagine
that egg is your brain.
And that Tupperware is your skull.
So the harder you rattle it,
what's going to happen to the egg?
It will break.
It's gonna break, right? The yolk's going to
break, right?
I mean your brain doesn't really break.
But you can think that
It's just kind
of the movement.
Because if you think about
what does Newton's first law say?
An object that's in motion will
stay in motion
unless acted upon by outside force.
So if the brain...
If you get hit here,
which way is your
brain going to go?
That way.
Until it hits the
skull and then it's going to *thunk*
So that's what they
call rattling your cage.
I was thinking of like
when I play baseball,
when I swing the
bat and I hit the ball, and my hands keep like,
I can feel it inside and
like even after
a minute it will keep rattling.
So now take that
and think about
how that would...
Okay! So David, can you uh...
Explain what you
have so we can...
This is kind of like the bridge
idea that I had where like
there's like different
columns that go around, like the frame.
So in this, it would kind of be like,
the head goes right here
and the helmet's right here.
And these would be like some kind of
material that's bendable.
So, when something
hits it, they would bend in
so, to absorb kind of the impact.
Kind of like a cage
in the racing cars.
Like how racing cars have a cage
inside of them.
Just in case they roll over,
the cage still protects the person.
Yeah kind of...
No, but...
Yeah kind of like that
but these are like cushions.
Yeah. So they
absorb the momentum.
So like a coil? Like for your bed.
The bed spring
that when you jump up on it,
you rebound back, so...
Wouldn't that be
more dangerous if it's...?
elastic?
Yeah, it's elastic, and when we did the little
cars
When it was elastic,
it completely transferred
all of its momentum
to the other car.
So when you get hit,
it will just like swing
and then all the
momentum will hit you.
instead of both
of you sharing it.
So if you share,
it'd probably be better.
But I don't know if that's...
(Multiple people talking)
Because I was also
thinking of mattresses.
A little sleep mattresses.
and how they talked about the coils
and how they give you pressure points
and it will be stronger
over here than over here.
and then they have the new
ones now that are like foam.
The Tempurpedic ones, Yeah.
So I was thinking also
if you like spread out...
where the momentum goes.
Saying if you spread out where
it won't be in one certain area.
Then you won't get hit
really hard right here.
And if you get hit
hard like over here,
it'd probably be better
than getting hit hard
just right there. -Yeah.
It will probably
be less of a force.
So when they
design like a helmet,
they've got one piece thing
where it's like your body
their shoulder pads
connected to their helmet.
So your body absorbs some of
that too, instead of just your head.
So that depends
how you turn your head
And would it be
good if your body...
have you guys ever heard
that people who
are like drunk drivers
they kind of walk
away from a car crash
and it's the passengers or the victims
are the ones
that get hurt the most...
So think about what's different between
their body in motion and
the other person's body in motion.
So they're looser, right?
They're not tightening their muscles
compared to someone who is
trying to absorb the impact.
We flex, right?
Just waiting for it, and
so, by being more rigid
your body doesn't move.
You're trying to
fight against the motion.
So you get more of the whiplash
and stuff like that.
Because you...
It hurt your body more
because you're
trying to fight against
what you're body is
actually going to do instead of
the other person
who's just like really loose
is moving with it,
so there's not as much impact.
Well, I've been playing football
and how you play
like you want to win.
You hit someone you want to.
After that
you're still going and
if you are like losing
the other person is stronger than you
can beat you up like...
I know. What he
is saying is like
if you see someone
about to collide with you,
you want to hit
him back instead of...
Yeah.
Why is that?
Related that to momentum.
Because momentum
is vector, right?
So you have to think
about the direction
and of the way
that things are moving.
So think back to...
When we were playing
with different cars.
So you had the greater mass
in one car going this way.
And had the smaller
mass going this way.
Right?
So what would you want to
do to the smaller mass
car to make sure that
the impact of the....
Raise his speed
Increase the speed, right?
And so by knowing that
you're going to get hit
you're going to
run a little faster.
So then what was the...
what is the ending result there?
So like if you have more speed
you hit the other object
that has more mass
Mean like....
how do you think is like...
Inelastic, I don't know, like
So what's going to happen?
Are they going to
stay stuck together?
(Multiple people speaking)
So it's elastic
so it comes off, right?
Think about it
like a rubber band,
an elastic rubber band.
You can stretch it, so...
elastic is, is saying, something
that's going to rebound.
whereas inelastic
you're just rigid.
There is no motion,
I guess, you should say.
I thought that was inelastic, when you
hit something, it will both go off
completely and
elastic it will stick together.
And inelastics magnets.