- Hi, welcome to the library
media center.
At the entrance, we post school community
events and have some newspapers
so that our readers can keep up with the
current news and community happenings.
At our situation desk we
have a suggestion box,
our series list, and magazines
and books to
entice students as they check out.
In our commercial seating
area we have state book award
nominees and winners, as well
as numerous magazines for
you in the library for your checkout.
For the teachers, I have a
professional library with over
3,000 books, DVDs, manipulatives
and kits,
developed to support the curriculum.
Fiction is concentrated on
the right side of the library.
The paperbacks, a student favorite,
arranged by genre just
like in retail stores.
All of the series books are
clearly labelled so students can
quickly find the next book in a series.
I give special consideration
to my reluctant reader's needs
if students interests
were looking for fiction,
or making sure we have quality literature
for all reading levels.
We have 13 desktop computers,
and a mobile laptop lab
with which students access the internet,
numerous databases, Impact,
and a variety of software.
On the school library website,
they find reviews,
blogs, links to resarch sites,
as well as
book suggestions, trainers, and podcasts,
many of which are created by the students.
On the left-hand side of the library,
the reference and the
non-fiction sections are located.
Our many biographies are housed on the
non-fiction side of the center counter.
I have many displays throughout the
library and around the school,
but two of the most effective
ways I encourage student
interaction with literature
is by display of their works
such as book reviews, or
projects, and by intermingling
related materials to encourage further
exploration of the topics.
I keep the collection
current and relevant through
annual reading and by following
my collection development plan
so I can offer my patrons
a fantastic collection with enthusiastic
and professional service.
- (inaudible)?
- (inaudible).
(background chatter)
- But we don't, we don't find
our food and just like...
(background chatter)
- The three little pig wolf thing?
(inaudible).
- (inaudible).
- She counted all the way up.
And she wants to know
the lines or something.
- We're going to, now that you guys have
most of your categories filled in,
I would like for you to
flip over the lab sheet
that's in front of you.
There are two reviews for this book.
Compare what you have on
your graphic organizer
to what you find in the review.
If you had mentioned that
Bridge was a protagonist,
or basically mention Bridge and give some
description of Bridge, then
that would be something
that is in common with one of the reviews.
If you find something in common,
circle it on your graphic organizer.
I would like for you to
circle everything on your
graphic organizer that you
also see in the reviews.
And again, you can work with
your partner on this one.
(background chatter)
- (inaudible).
- (inaudible) it talks
about what they deserve
and (inaudible).
(background chatter)
- 30 more seconds.
That's okay, (inaudible).
Did you find that there were
several things in common
between the elements you looked
for and found in the story?
and what you find in the review?
- [Students] Yes.
-  The review has some additional
items in it, doesn't it?
There are a lot of people
with the same basic items.
Anyway, I wanted to do a
quick Venn-diagram up here,
and compare and contrast.
I want for each group, this group,
I want each of the two of you to find one
thing that you found that
wasn't in the review.
Or, one thing that was
in the review that was
not on your paper.
Okay, (inaudible).
Okay, you guys, I want you to find,
one for each of those groups, I want
you to find one thing that
was in common (inaudible).
So this is compare, this is contrast.
Contrast, compare.
Find one thing that was in common,
and one thing that's different.
Oh, okay, here's a sticky in the
middle of the table,
I want you to write it on the sticky.
You guys (inaudible) hard.
(background chatter)
(inaudible)
Awesome, step up here and tell
us what it is and where does it go(inaudible).
?
- (inaudible).
Awesome, perfect.
So all you guys came up with a (inaudible).
(inaudible)
- We did like don't count your chickens
before they hatch (inaudible) and it
was in our graphic organizer (inaudible).
- Oh, okay, (inaudible).
- (inaudible).
- Perfect, and that was (inaudible).
- (inaudible).,
- Good, perfect.
Okay, so everybody here found
something that they had that
wasn't in the review, it was
in their graphic organizer.
(inaudible).
You guys, come on up.
This table, everyone at this
table is looking for something
that was found in both
their graphic organizer
and in the review.
- We found (inaudible).
- Super, (inaudible).
- (inaudible).
- Super, so that goes in the middle
because it's in common with both of them.
This group?
- (inaudible).
- Perfect, they found both
in the review and in their
organizer that (inaudible).
- (inaudible).
- So that was a?
What category (inaudible)?
- (inaudible).
- Oh, was that in common?
Did you find it in the
review also or was it...?
- (inaudible).
- Just you guys found it?
So where would it go?
Excellent, excellent.
That would go in the graphic
organizer because it was
something that wasn't in the review,
so it would go over here, perfect.
Okay, next?
- We found that the (inaudible).
- Okay, so you found something
that was only in the review
that the, how the pigs
disguised themselves.
Where do we put that on that?
Excellent, something that
was only found in the review.
Save the best for last.
What'd you guys find?
- We found that the graphic
organizer and the review,
they both talked about
(inaudible) that related to
(inaudible) like the (inaudible).
- The allusions in there,
Wizard of Oz, Three Little Pigs,
Excellent, that was (inaudible).
So we see an awful lot
is in common with these.
Sometimes, you guys find
something that aren't in
the reviews, the reviews sometimes had
something you didn't find.
They are a little bit different.
Not necessarily in your review cover every
literary element there is.
You won't necessarily tell them
the five different types of
literary devices that are used
there, and that's okay.
What you want to do with your review is
tell some about the book, and give a
substantiated opinion of the book.
Why do (inaudible)?
What are the good features of this book?
What are the weaknesses
in the book that you read?
Now there are other things
that you may need in there,
and I'll show where you can get
some additional information.
Let's bring this on down here.
In the online catalog.
Both of those computers
are logged in over there.
(inaudible).
Okay, look up.
So far (inaudible).
So if you want to make a note of
how many pages as a reminder to yourself,
"Oh yeah, that was a really long book",
or "Oh, that was a quick read."
That would be something to
kind of jog your memory there.
Things like, "Oh yeah,
this was about Korea."