- [Instructor] All right. So, I showed you
all that video for three reasons. Number
one, I want you to see that volleyball is
not a girl's sport. Here in the South a lot of
people think of volleyball as a girl sport
because we don't have a lot of male high school
volleyball teams. I don't know why, we just
don't. That's a common misconception, that
volleyball is a girl's sport. Everybody in
that video was a male. Everybody in that
video was over 50 years of age. That means
volleyball is a lifetime activity. Raise
your hand if you can take a guess at what
a lifetime activity is. Yes ma'am.
- [Girl] A lifetime activity is something
you can do when you're older.
- [Instructor] A lifetime activity is
something you can do basically for the
rest of your life. Would golf be a
lifetime activity?
- [Students together] No.
- [Instructor] Golf?
- [Students together] Yes.
- [Instructor] Golf would be a lifetime
activity. There's people 70, 80, 90 years
old that are playing golf. As a matter of
fact, playing golf is an accomplishment,
to be able to go out and shoot your age.
So, I'm if I'm 70 and I go out and shoot a
70 on a golf course, I've done pretty
good. Golf is a lifetime activity.
How about bowling?
- [Student together] Yes.
- [Instructor] How about tackle football?
- [Students together] No.
- [Instructor] No. Tackle football would
not be a lifetime activity. If I was to go
to the YMCA, do you think I would be able
to find a league to sign up for tackle
football at my age?
- [Students together] No.
- [Instructor] No. Can I go out to the
YMCA and find a
volleyball league for somebody my age?
- [Students together] Yeah.
- [Instructor] Yes. So, volleyball is what
we consider a lifetime activity. Something
you can do the rest of your life. Okay, the
third thing, those guys were pretty good.
- [Students together] Mmhmm.
- [Instructor] And they were pretty
athletic. So by playing volleyball and
staying active, you're going to be more
athletic than a lot of people that are
your age. So, not only is volleyball a
lifetime activity, it's going to help you
stay in shape, help you stay active, okay?
First thing we're going to do is the serve.
With the serve there are a few things we need
to remember, okay? First thing I want us to
remember with the serve is that the ball
must stay at the waist. When we hit it out
of our hand, we want it to stay at our
waist. If I hold the ball up here and I
hit, the ball is going to go up. It's all
about the angles, okay? If I hit the ball right
here it's going to go up and out like I want
it to go, all right? So, then I want to hit it
at my waist. Second thing that we're going
to remember is that my opposite foot needs
to be forward. If I hit it with my right
hand, I want my left leg to be up front,
like this. What other activities have we
done that your opposite foot is forward?
Yes?
- [Boy] Catching.
- [Instructor] Throwing, right? With the
overhand throw we step with our opposite
foot. What else? Yes, ma'am?
- [Girl] The underhand toss.
- [Instructor] The underhand toss, that is
exactly right. I think Ms. Beldo
taught y'all the underhand toss. Step,
tick-tock point.
Which foot do we step with?
- [Students together] The opposite.
- [Instructor] The opposite foot. Do you
see a trend? Can you make a little
connection there? Opposite foot forwards, okay?
Now, the next things that I want you to
remember kind of go hand in hand. They are
tick-tock. Tick-tock looks like this.
Tick. Tock. Pretty easy, right? Tick.
Tock. Tick, I want to pull it back. Back
here. Tock, our arm is coming forward.
Now, we are going to add a little
something to the tock part. All the tock,
when we do tock, I want you standing like
this and do tock. When we do tock, we are
actually going to transfer our weight from
our back foot going forward into the front
foot. What do you think that's going to
do? If we transfer that weight forward.
Yes?
- [Boy] If we transfer our weight forward
it's going to put more pressure.
- [Instructor] It's going to put more
pressure on the ball. Am I plugging it
harder or softer?
- [Students together] Harder.
- [Instructor] Harder. It's going to
produce more force. Right? I'm going to
hit the ball harder if I do this than if I
do this. Does that make sense? Because
you're getting that momentum going
forward. It's just like in baseball. If
I'm playing baseball and I'm standing in
the outfield, am I going to throw it
harder if I do this or if I do this?
- [Student] The one with more force.
- [Instructor] The second one, right?
Because my momentum is going forward. Does
that make sense? So, my momentum is going
forward. Just like in four square. If I'm
playing four square and I want to hit the
ball and I'm trying to get somebody out in
four square am I going to hit it harder if
I do this or if I do this?
- [Student] That.
- [Instructor] The second one. I get my
force from the momentum going forward.
That's right, and the last thing I want
you to remember with the serve is the
follow through. Follow the ball, John will
you stand up please? If I want the ball to
go to John, my follow through should be
towards John, right? If I want the ball
going towards the flag, my follow
through...
- [Students together] The flag.
- [Instructor] ...towards the flag. If I
want the ball going to the cougar,
my follow through...
- [Students together] The cougar.
- [Instructor] ...going to the cougar. But
right now we're working on hitting it
straight so my follow through goes to my
target. Watch, see me take everything out.
Ball's at my waist, my opposite foot is
forward, tick...
- [Student] Tock.
- [Instructor] Tock, just like that. Okay?
We'll do it a little bit farther. Ready,
John? Opposite foot forward, ball at the
waist, tick, tock. All right. Did you see
everything that we had just talked about?
Opposite foot forward, ball at the waist,
tick, transfer my weight into tock.
All right.
- [Instructor] You're kind of hitting it
like that.
- [Student] I hit it.
- [Instructor] Good. That's great.
[Background noises of students practicing volleyball]
Tony, you ready? ...Tony? You ready?
Tossin' it up and hittin' it...
- And stop just a second, put
the ball on the ground. Ball on the
ground. A lot of people are doing a good
job getting that opposite food forward,
but they're not transferring their weight
to that foot, they're getting that
opposite foot forward and they're standing
like this. Am I going to generate much
force by doing this?
- [Students together] No.
- [Instructor] Think about baseball. I
could step with that opposite foot, but if
I step and then throw is that helping me
generate any force?
- [Students together] No.
- [Instructor] No. I want to step into it.
Same way in baseball. When I throw a
baseball, I want to step and throw at the
same time to get my momentum going
forward. We're generating force. So,
instead of... Tony, are you ready? Instead
of this, opposite foot forward and...like
that. I want to generate more force, so
I'm going to start with my weight back
here and go into it. You see the
difference? Ball on the ground please.
- [Students together] Yes.
So, work on generating that
force going forward. Okay? Continue. Go.
[Background noises of students practicing volleyball]
And... stop just a second. Ball on the ground.
All right. One more way that
we're going to try to generate force is by
following through after we hit the ball.
So, instead of... Alex, are you ready? I'm
going to serve this to you. Instead of
doing this, kind of almost like you're
punching the ball and stopping, I'm going
to follow through to my target. If Alex is
my target, my arm should finish up here at
my target. Watch. Do you see the
difference in the force between punching
it and following through to your target?
So, that's another thing to work on. Remember,
if you are doing a good job with the ball
that you've got, you can switch to another
ball. If you've got one of these big
yellow ones and you're doing perfect every
time I would recommend switching to either
this or one of the yellow and blue ones.
Challenge yourself a little bit. Let's go
ahead and switch stations so that if you
were here, one person walk up here and get
a clipboard and paper so you can leave
notes for your partner. If you were over
there, come over here.
- If you weren't over here just put your
clipboard on the steps there.
[Background noises of students practicing volleyball]
- And everybody stop. Put the
ball on the ground just a second. No balls
in the air. Everybody stand up. Everybody
stand up. Alright, put everything on the
ground. Everybody should have to free
hands. Together, let's work on tick,
transfer your weight through to your
target. Ryan, go in his place. Tick, arm
back, transfer weight, follow through to
your target. I still see some people doing
this. Where's that ball going to go?
- [Students together] That way.
- [Instructor] That way. If I'm aiming at
the... Ball on the ground. If I'm aiming
at the white poster, my follow through is
to the white poster. Everybody pick out a
target. Tick, step, follow through. Go.
Pick out a target, tick,
step, follow through.
[Background noises of students practicing volleyball]
- Go get that ball.
We'll get you another ball.
Who can raise their hand
and tell me the first thing we need to
remember for the volleyball serve.
Yes, sir?
- [Boy] [Inaudible]
- [Instructor] The first thing we talked
about. Yes, ma'am?
- [Girl] [Inaudible]
- [Instructor] The ball should be at your-
- [Students together] Waist.
- [Instructor] The ball's at your waist.
And what is that going to impact? And
what's it going to influence?
- [Boy] How far the ball goes.
- [Instructor] It's going to influence how
far the ball goes. All right? So, if the
ball is up here, it's going to go where?
- [Students together] Up.
- [Instructor] Up. If I'm down here, the
ball's going to go...
Go out, so I want to add my
weight in order to get that angle so the
ball will go over the net and drop. What's
the second thing to remember? Yes, sir?
-[Boy] [Inaudible]
- Remember, it's what we talked about with
the underhand throw, four square, and the
overhand throw. Our opposite foot is...
- [Students together] Forward.
- [Instructor] Forward, right. Our
opposite foot is forward. Like this.
What's the third thing.
- [Boy] Shift your weight.
- [Instructor] I want to shift my weight.
We actually did tick-tock when I talk
about shifting my weight, but shifting our
weight is one of the most important
things, because that is how we produce--