(all students speaking at once)
(coughing)
(laughing)
(consistent murmuring throughout room)
- Negative x minus it?
(muffled speaking)
- It's one over, oh wait,
oh wait wait wait wait.
- [Voiceover] How do we solve for X?
- [Voiceover] X is the value of R anyway.
X is the value of R.
- What would you do for the one over X?
Wouldn't that be the first term?
- [Voiceover] X is the value
of R (speech drowned out).
- What I would suggest you do is,
is that you could rewrite
this as an expression.
- Oh, as the power (inaudible)?
Oh. Oh, okay okay.
- I used (inaudible).
- [Voiceover] Oh, yeah yeah.
All right, yeah I got it.
So it's gonna be negative
X minus one, okay.
Okay, no I got it.
So the first,
it's gonna be, so what--
(coughing over talking)
- [Voiceover] Whatever.
(multiple students talking at once)
- [Voiceover] Oh, come on.
- [Voiceover] I just wanted
to find where it talks about--
- [Voiceover] It would be
one minus one (inaudible).
- [Voiceover] Oh we have one (inaudible).
- [Voiceover] Is one over x the sum?
- [Voiceover] Do you
see, see what I'm saying?
Yeah.
- [Voiceover] I'm gonna put it in there,
so negative X minus one,
'cause later it's gonna change
- [Voiceover] Wait, you don't
really have to do it out
since it's gonna change the
(inaudible) so it's higher.
You'll have to, you gotta
(speech drowned out by talking).
Yeah.
(laughing)
- No no no no no, don't,
don't don't don't.
Don't even do that.
Do you know why?
Because it's part of a (inaudible).
Well--
(speech drowned out)
- [Voiceover] Yeah yeah yeah.
'Cause the whole thing is
negative, and then that's the
(speech drowned out by
other students talking)
- Remember the (inaudible).
(laughing)
(conversations going throughout the room)
- [Voiceover] He's a natural.
(laughs)
(muffled conversing throughout the room)
- [Teacher] But now here's the question.
You guys kind of already
answered this question.
(speaker drowned out by background noise)
Could you have found it?
- They give you, basically R is two X.
- Uh huh.
- And, since it converges,
it has to be less than
the absolute value of (speech
drowned out by others).
- You got it.
Okay.
(all students speaking at once)
- [Voiceover] That makes sense.
- [Teacher] Go back for a second.
- Yeah, you multiply
both sides by a third.
So it'd be one third times
every single one of 'em.
And the interval (speech
drowned out by others talking).
- [Teacher] Um--
- [Voiceover] Oh.
Maybe someone's (speech drowned
out by consistent chatter).
It means it's gonna get
shifted, and then (inaudible).
- [Teacher] You were just
scaling the (speech drowned out).
Because it's like, (speech
drowned out by others talking).
- I'd never, I never considered
(speech drowned out).
Oh, okay.
- [Teacher] Yeah.
(students chattering)
- [Voiceover] It's not gonna
change the domain of the--
- [Voiceover] Oh, no, no,
I'm putting plus negative--
(speaker drowned out by background noise)
- [Voiceover] The answer.
- [Teacher] Yeah.
So, the only thing I'm thinking is
it might be easier for you
to just (speech drowned out).
It might make sense somehow.
- Oh, how do you read (inaudible)?
- Yeah, how do you--
- [Teacher] No no no, no no no no no.
It doesn't reduce the
time it takes for it to--
- No man, right?
(speech drowned out)
- Oh, okay yeah.
- [Voiceover] One third.
Oh, I get it, I get it.
- [Voiceover] It only converges
as you, (muffled speech).
No matter what, well no matter what.
(students chattering)
- [Voiceover] One over X.
Three X, five X, two in, two over X.
- [Teacher] I think it does.
(students conversing around the room)
- [Voiceover] Thank you.
- [Voiceover] You're welcome.
- [Voiceover] That's what I'm,
yeah, that's what I'm saying.
- [Teacher] One over X.
Because what they want you to do now,
(speaker drowned out by background noise)
So, you'd say power series
is gonna be written as
a form of, say, geometric series.
Because now you've got, what?
What's the first term?
(speech drowned out)
- [Teacher] Yeah? Right.
Okay, what's the ratio?
- Negative (speech drowned
out by others talking).
- And when you write that out,
put (inaudible) around it.
(laughing)
Let him once, show him.
- Okay.
(laughs)
(muffled conversations)
- [Voiceover] Is it saying three X?
(speech drowned out by others talking)
- I would be, I would take
the (speech drowned out).
- [Teacher] Are you sure
you're working together?
- Yes.
(inaudible speech drowned
out by others talking)
- [Voiceover] And I'll turn it, one.
We got one, minus X squared.
- One over one plus X squared.
- That's X to the fourth, right?
Minus X to the sixth,
plus X to the eighth.
- This is, if you are indexing this.
This is your first term,
this is your second term,
this is your third term, right?
Think about the first one, okay?
We have left that, in
order to get that a two X.
Like the first R, okay,
the first side of it.
And say, it's the second term that
(speech drowned out) the first time.
So it's probably gonna,
probably gonna be it.
Probably.
- Okay.
- [Teacher] At least on these simple ones.
- [Teacher] Okay, leave that
for (speech drowned out).
- Okay.
- [Voiceover] N minus
one over one minus one,
x minus one would be zero,
which would be (inaudible).
- [Voiceover] Originally we
have negative one (inaudible).
- [Voiceover] X minus one.
(muffled conversing)
- [Voiceover] The right
one, so it's either gonna be
(speech drowned out by
other students talking).
- [Voiceover] Now you're
expanding by three
instead of zero six.
- [Voiceover] So, it's like
negative X squared switched.
So the negative that goes over here,
is negative X squared, too.
So the negative is which
Y (speech drowned out).
- [Voiceover] I don't, uh!
(laughing)
I don't know what I'm doing!
(students all talking at once)
- [Voiceover] All right look, hold on.
Isn't it the same as the third one?
- [Voiceover] That means that
the Y, like the same one,
Y is the common one.
- [Voiceover] Right?
(students consistently conversing)
- To the one, so this
would be X minus one.
And negative (speech drowned
out by others speaking).
(students consistently conversing)
Just put in one here, four, all right?
What's the ratio here?
(speech drowned out by others talking)
(laughing)
- [Voiceover] One, you're
multiplying the outside of two X.
Another one you're doing it as the two X.
That means you're moving
the X to the inside.
If you take a function and you
just scale it by a multiple,
if you take arcsine of
x, any function you want,
and you multiply it by scale,
like one third, one fourth,
(speech drowned out by others talking).
(consistently conversing
throughout the room)
- [Voiceover] Ah, but then there we said--
- [Voiceover] No! Oh my
God, what arc, what are you,
wait wait, hold on, hold on,
hold on, hold on, hold on.
- There's gonna be another
one I haven't, there,
and one third after that
is what we're doing here.
Our R remains the same.
It's the whole series multiplied
by the factor of one third.
- [Voiceover] Okay yeah,
I'm agreeing to that.
- [Voiceover] I'm pretty
sure that's right.
- You multiply this out,
it's gonna be one over three,
plus three x minus one.
- Why are you multiplying it out?
Just think of it as a scale.
It's not anything to do, it's
not gonna affect our domain
outside the function.
It's only gonna affect the range.
And therefore you're not
gonna have any remains
'cause the remains only
matter if you didn't have
but like one third of it, so
we're not doing it like that.
One third after it, we're
doing like a stretched version.
So it's not gonna affect the equation.
(consistent chatter throughout the room)
- [Voiceover] (inaudible),
so it's negative X.
- [Voiceover] What? No no no no no no.
(all students speaking at once)
- [Voiceover] That's the series
for (speech drowned out).
- [Voiceover] Uh, all right.
- [Voiceover] I'm just
(inaudible) negative X squared.
Right?
(consistent chatter among students)
- [Voiceover] No, no, no, I'm
putting negative x squared.
It's easier, 'cause then
later on when you do plus--
- [Voiceover] No, no, no, no, no, I--
(speech drowned out by others talking).
- [Voiceover] The sine's been switching.
No, no.
- [Voiceover] Yeah, but you
can represent that by saying--
- [Voiceover] Yeah, it's gonna be smaller.
(consistent conversing among students)
Well, it'll be switching, but like
would you represent,
how would you represent
X in the whole thing?
- [Voiceover] To the
negative, see the n minus one
is put, that's how I'm doing it.
(consistent chatter among students)
- [Voiceover] Wait, how would you find the
(speech drowned out by others talking)?
- [Voiceover] If it's the
absolute value of x minus one,
it would be less than one.
- [Voiceover] Mrs. Dockin?
- [Teacher] Yes.
(consistent speaking among students)
- [Voiceover] Is this, is this, is this X?
- We're not sure where we are because
of these coefficients that change.
(speech drowned out by others talking)
- What is X over R?
- Take this series right
here, which is that.
So, then integrate it.
We just though you integrate
every term to get it.
- Now you're looking for
a general expression.
- Right.
- You have a general expression.
It didn't tell you to come up with.
no, they didn't tell you to do that.
- Oh, okay okay.
Okay, because, in fact,
that's not a power series.
- [Voiceover] That's not a power series?
- It is, okay, but it's a
different form of a power series.
(speaker drowned out by background noise)
So you don't have to write
'em like this because
you would also need to have, what?
You also have to have (inaudible).
- [Voiceover] Right, yeah okay.
- Got it? Okay.
(consistent conversing among students)
- [Voiceover] You flip it around.
- One, good, yeah good, what's R?
The negative of, yeah you're
the negative x plus one,
but it needs to be in parentheses.
So now you need your R, okay?
Now, you're gonna do
them when you get to--
- [Voiceover] It needs
to be a form of K over R.
- Oh, I thought we just solve for R?
You said the third nominated was R.
(speech drowned out by others talking)
- [Voiceover] All right guys,
she said 1/3 times one,
whatever that is.
How do you multiply these?
- Does it need to be on the
(speech drowned out by talking).
(students chattering)
- Yeah, so you do it again.
- Yeah, multiply the whole interval, yeah.
Multiply the interval.
- [Voiceover] And this is
not in the form of a series.
(consistent chatter among students)
- That one third, does that
impact the greatness of one?
That's the question you want to answer.
I'm not answering it for you right now,
you need to figure it out.
- [Voiceover] So, when it's asking for,
does the function of the
(speech drowned out)?
(consistent talking among students)
- This, it's like that.
- [Voiceover] You didn't
divide it by seven.