- Take a look at that goal just to remind
yourself whatever it is you're going to be
working on. And this, we want to remind
you that it's kind of dinner party
conversation-ish. You agree with people at
dinner parties. You disagree with people
at dinner parties, but it's civil, because
it's friends that you invited over to your
house. You don't raise your, you don't
raise your hand at dinner parties. You
wait until, you wait until
[inaudible].
You wait until someone else is finished
speaking before you start speaking, of
course, because that's polite dinner
conversation. You add on to what one
another says. But like I said, we don't
necessarily have to agree. And then when
the topic starts to die down at a dinner
party, somebody else brings something else
up. So you can raise your own questions as
well. So the seminar is open, and my
question to you guys is who you think is
most to blame for the deaths that occurred
at the end of "The Veldt."
- What did it mean, like, George having,
like, I think that, I know a lot of times,
where he, especially in the, towards the
back, he... it goes back a little ways.
He's, like, talking a lot of things, like,
comments turning, comment, commen-, I
can't say that word. He says they're going
to turn the house down possibly for a
month, and how he pick out the picture
painter. And he was telling his, he was,
like, talking to his son a lot and, like,
about not, about doing what his son would
not want to have happen, and how he
spoiled his children so much. So he takes
out, there's a lot of things that his son,
his son and daughter, it just doesn't say
as much, wouldn't like, because... yeah.
But he wasn't, like, he wasn't, like...
- I agree that...
- "Oh yeah, I'm gonna go die today!"
- I agree that it was...
- He didn't want to die.
- Of course he didn't want to die. Who
wants to die? Except for if you're suici-,
you know, suicidal.
- I agree that
[inaudible],
and on Page 15, where it says, um, it's
mostly on 16, but starts on Page 15.
"Won't this house and this room replace
you and your wife and your children's
affections?" It assumes their mother and
father grow more important in their lives
than their real parents, and now you want
to come along and shut it off? Kind of
shows why that they hate them. And because
it, because it's, since the nursery is
their parents, it's like some guy who
thinks he can tell you, coming along and
can tell you to kill your parents, you
know?
- It's the same thing as they're doing,
though. They're killing their parents.
- Well...
- But they think the nursery is their
parents.
-...they don't think their parents are
their parents. They don't matter as much
as parents.
- If they'd been nice to them, and now
they're going to turn everything off, then
isn't it imbalanced? So now they're
relying on the house, because that's what
they've learned to do, as...
- Yeah.
- It'd be like, take an example, people
are killing their parents.
- And on Page 15, it says, like... I
also think that it's, the dad says, "I
sen-..." The psychologist says, "I
sensed only that you had spoiled your
children more than most, and now you're
letting them die in some way." So if
they, like, they don't really know, like,
when someone says no to them, they've been
spoiled so much they don't even, like...
well, they just can't take it. It makes
them go all crazy and stuff. So they
wanted to kill them, because they, like,
couldn't fly to New York, so...
- Yeah. Because I think
[inaudible]
- And if their parents, and if their
parents, and if they felt that their
parents were actually their parents, then
maybe not. But since their parents don't
really take care of them, it's the house
that takes care of them.
- Yeah.
- And then the...
- The house and the room replaced their
parents.
- Yeah. Their parents and friends.
- It's not like the parents could...
- They don't have friends, because
they're, the room, they get all these
adventures because of the room.
- Yeah.
- They don't have friends.
- And they kind of, like, rely on the
house to give them stuff all the time.
- If the house refused them, if it could,
then I don't think that they would want to
kill it. I think that it's just because
they don't feel like their parents are
actually their, they don't, they feel,
their parents aren't important to them. So
when they say no...
- On page, on page 13, the mom's saying,
"That sounds stressful. Would I have to
tie my own shoes instead of letting the
shoe tier do it? And brush my own teeth,
and comb my hair, and give myself a bath?"
The kid's, like, now relying on
everything. He's never had to do something
for himself. So he doesn't really, like,
know.
- Yeah.
- He's gotten so, like, stuck on having
everyone do things for him, he thinks,
like, doing your own thing would be, like...
- A challenge.
- Yeah. Like, and I guess you can use an
example as "Wall-E," a show. People get,
like, so fat, and they rely on everything
so much that, like, they have to move in
chairs, and they, when you golf, it's
virtual golf, there's a robot for you. So
they just, they take robotics and machines
to the next level, and they, it's all they
rely on. And so many people don't have to
work.
- Yeah, and weren't the ones that, like,
bought the house, that they were actually
the cause, because they were the ones ...
like, on Page 5 and 11, they even said
that, "We were the ones who bought the
house. We were the ones who got us into
this mess." So, but then all of a sudden
they just took it away from their
children, which made them mad. So again,
they were the one who was causing all this
madness in the house.
- I think it...
- Like, don't you think that people would
be sort of obese, like Elliot said?
- Yeah. They would be.
- They would be.
- Yeah, but then they'd be like everyone
else in the world.
- But then they also...
- Yeah, and...
- Getting exercise?
- But they're obese...
- And also, I think that it's George
Hadley's fault, not necessarily both the
parents, because the mom didn't really do
as much. Because, like, well, the quote
over there it said that, like, she's the
one who let them in for a minute. But. . .
- She just wanted to be nice.
- She just wanted to be nice. But I think
... like on Page two, it says, "But
nothing's too good for our children,"
George said. So I don't think it's as much
Lydia's fault, because she also tries to
get them out of the house instead of just
staying there. She just wanted to be nice
to the kids because George had shut it off
so abruptly. But I think it's more
George's fault that they spoiled them, and
that therefore gets himself killed.
- Does anyone know when this story was
written? Because I'm guessing it was...
- 1950.
- All right. Because I was, I'm guessing
it was wri- I was, guessing it was written
when women weren't, like, thought of that
highly. Because Wendy only actually speaks
once, and is a sniveling idiot most of the
time. And Lydia's, and Lydia Hadley is
pretty passive. And it's the guys that
are, have all the action, and have
anything really going on.
- Except in the final scene.
- Well, yeah. But that... she on-...
- She says one line. One line in the whole
book, basically.
- I know, but Lydia sort of has a bit of
action.
- Yeah, but...
- She doesn't do much. She doesn't, like...
. .
- She's pretty passive.
- She doesn't, like, um, disagree with her
husband or her kids. She doesn't do
anything like that. She just follows
whatever her husband says. Maybe she has a
few opinions, but not really.
- And Wendy says four words alone in the
whole thing, so...
- Well, I mean, you hear her screaming,
but other than that...
- Is that a word?
- Well, that was
[inaudible]
- Unless she's saying it...
- Close enough.
-...at the same time as Peter, like,
when they both come in and say, "Hello,
mom and dad"...
- Doesn't really count.
-...or when they both say, "Mommy,
daddy, come quick." But she's saying it
at the same time. She only says four words
by herself in the entire story.
- The screams are actually their parents,
when the kids were pretending in the
nursery that their parents were being...
- Yeah, they realized that at the end, but
they didn't really make that very clear.
They're like, suddenly they realized why
those screams sounded familiar. I thought
the whole book, or the whole story, that
it was, like, the kids' screams.
But it's actually the parents.
- What are...
- Yeah, because it's really not clear on
that. I figured that it's actually so they
all
[inaudible].
- Well, I'm, it's more, it's nicer to
have, like, a mystery, kind of.
- Mm-hmm. Yeah. I figured that it's the
author's fault.
- The what?
- The author's.
- But...
- How is it the author's fault?
- Because it's his story.
- Well, the author wrote it.
- That doesn't make any sense.
- But Carl, the author
[inaudible].
- Yeah, that doesn't make much sense. It's
not his fault. It's the... it's totally
off topic.
- Yeah, I agree with Elise. When I didn't
really get who the screams were until the
very end, where they said, yeah, that...
I think it's on Page... um, 19. But,
yeah, that they were... it says on Page
20 that, "Suddenly, Mr.and Mrs. Hadley
screamed, and suddenly they realized why
those screams had sounded so familiar."
So I thought it was the kids the whole
time, I thought...
- Aaron was saying something before, but
then everyone...
- What I was going to say is the, a little
while ago, when I was going to ask you,
why do people think it's, like, Peter
Hadley or other... because, I mean...
- The other is both of them.
- Because more or less the majority did
George Hadley. So why, just those people
who did that, why did they do that?
- I understand with Peter Hadley, because
it is his, he seems to have the main role
of actually murdering the parents. But
it's not his fault he got spoiled. He
can't help it if his parents spoiled him.
- Yeah, because...
- Actually, even if the parents had been,
played more of a parent role, they would
still probably have preferred the nursery,
because...
- You don't need to
[inaudible].
-...the parents could still say no, and
the nursery does, they can, like, do
whatever they want with it.
- I agree with the both parents part of
it, even though the mom wasn't as involved
as George was, the mother was not do-,
posing a part in the kids' life as being
the mom, and the house was. So that caused
them to think the house was their parents,
and the house was their family.
- This is...
[inaudible]
- Indirectly... directly, I think...
- You can go.
- Directly, the, Peter was probably most
responsible for the parents dying.
- Directly.
- Directly. But indirect... well,
directly the lions were.
- Oh my God.
- Indirectly... but directly it was
mostly Peter, but indirectly, it was, it
was kind of everybody's fault.
- I kind of agree with, like, both the
parents, and then the dad. Because in the
beginning, the parents are, like, slowly
taking away some things, like the painter,
and not letting them go to New York. And
that kind of builds up their anger. But in
the end, the dad just wants to shut it all
off. And then the son starts getting
really mad and, like, threatening them,
finally they, like, get really mad, and
then they start imagining the parents
dying, and then...
- They've been imagining the parents dying
through the whole thing.
- I think it was the parents' fault, and
the inventor. Because, I mean, none of it
would have happened if they wouldn't have
had the, just, like, the super technology
house, and the nursery.
- So it's technology's fault.
- It's not the inventor's fault, because
he didn't know.
- But it's not the, it's not the
inventor's fault that they thought,
though.
- If he wouldn't have made it, it would
have never happened.
- And also, if the dad wouldn't have
bought it, it would never happened, too.
So that's my two opinions.
- They couldn't...
- But they bought it, but they made it and
bought it to be a good thing, not a bad
one.
- No one invented it so that you would, so
that it'd be used as a murder machine.
They didn't just make it, like, on the
advertisement, "Greatest Murder Machine
Ever."
- Perfect for murdering your parents.
- We don't know, like, why he built it.
Maybe it was because of that, but you
don't know, like, exactly what his point
of the invention was.
- It was to, like, study the children's
thoughts.
- It was to study their minds.
- Because the children...
- He said that, but what if it's not?
- He's a liar.
- The children were mentally impaired, and
they needed to be looked up on, and they
wanted to know what they were thinking, so
...
- So a psychologist
[inaudible].
- Another good quote to show that it was,
to show that it might have, that it could
have been the parents' fault, was that, on
Page 11, it said... yeah, George said,
"Who was it that... who was it said,
'Children are carpets. They should be
stepped on occasionally.'" Because the
parents didn't, they didn't do anything to
the kids. They...
- They didn't really step on them that
much until the end.
- They just did what they want.
- They just all of a sudden just, like,
flattened them.
- Yeah, they just did it so abruptly.
- Yeah, they just started and let it go.
- It was just like, bam, you're dead.
- No wonder they wanted them dead.
- Guys, let's try and talk one person at a
time, or else we can't hear.
- My turn. Okay. On Page 15, it says that
the dad went from Santa, Santa to Scrooge.
And, like, if he would have taken away,
like, one thing at a time over a period of
time, I don't think the kids would be,
like, like, killing them. But it says he
just took all the good stuff away at once,
and they got, like, really mad.
- That's also kind of dangerous, though.
Because they started getting mad at him as
soon as they took away the picture
painter. So it was, they still could've
gotten mad. It's also more dangerous for
the parents to actually slowly take them
away, because they get more and more mad.
- All the anger...
- I have another opinion that I was trying
to say, but then I let Fiona go first.
That's not fair.
- No, that's not, it's my fault.
[inaudible]
- All the anger built up because...
- Anyway, um...