- Tell them what you wrote.
Describe your three
pictures, and then they're
going to share what they
saw, and the three pictures
they picked.
- (background chatter)
- The cat.
- I picked the roller coaster.
- Man.
- What did you get for what (inaudible)?
- I only did two.
- (background chatter)
- I think the Earth (inaudible).
- Y'all did the roller coaster?
- [Instructor] Max, is that possible?
Why not, what did you write?
- [Max] There's no gravity.
- [Instructor] So, in that
picture he's weightless,
but where is he?
- [Max] In front of a building.
- [Instructor] So, he's on a planet, right?
- [Max] Yeah.
- [Instructor] So, what should happen,
if this was a video and we
saw the next two seconds
of that video?
- [Max] He's falling?
- [Instructor] He should fall, right?
All right, write that down
next to that picture.
- (background chatter)
- I don't mean to do that.
- [Instructor] All right, so let's
look at the roller coaster.
- He couldn't even fall like that because
you got the gravity pushing down,
so that's why why he
wouldn't fall like that.
And that's either like, strange stuff.
But I don't think he could fall like that.
- Unless he... (inaudible).
- He can't fall like that.
That's impossible. Get his weight,
and (inaudible).
Yeah, exactly, 'cause he can't do that.
Yeah, 'cause you can see
his shadow under that.
And don't think he, I think he
got like a hoop or something.
So, like a little string or something.
- Or like, he fall?
- Yeah, 'cause he can't do that.
They must have took that while he was.
'Cause that's impossible.
Earth's gravity pulling him like that.
Unless he in space or something.
- (background chatter)
- [Instructor] All right,
so why would he fall?
- Because the force of gravity pushing down.
- [Instructor] So, why
would he fall that way
and not fall that way?
- The gravity would push him down,
and not up, so (inaudible).
There's like, there's gravity on Earth,
so like if you consider, like how Newton
found the apple when it fell
to the ground.
- [Instructor] Okay, so
you know there's something
going on that's pulling you down.
And you say, "What if you were on the
"other side of the Earth?"
Would it be pulling you up then?
If you were on the other side?
Or, would it still pull
you down to the ground?
- It would still pull you down
to the ground.
- [Instructor] All right, so
on the planet, what can we say
about gravity?
Where is it trying to pull you?
- To the center.
- Ah, to the center, so
it doesn't matter where
you stand, it's not pulling you down,
it's just trying to pull you where?
- To the center.
- To the center, okay.
All right, one more minute for sharing.
Make sure you have
three pictures described
on your T-chart.
If you need to borrow an
idea from your neighbor,
do that now.
- (background chatter)
And you got the Solar System?
Okay so, it says planets can move
because of gravity.
Where are they moving?
- (background chatter)
- [Instructor] (inaudible) around the sun.
And what has them go in a circle and not
flying away?
All right, who would like to share
what they wrote with their group?
Their favorite one,
their favorite picture?
All right, Arquel, which one
was your favorite picture?
- [Arquel] The roller coaster.
- Roller coaster, who
picked roller coaster?
All right, so let's all look
at the roller coaster.
And Arquel, tell us what
your team wrote down
and Sarah will add it to our list.
- [Arquel] We had put that
the gravity brings the speed to the...
to the roller coaster.
So, if you wanted to
make the speed increase,
you would want to bring your hill higher.
So, therefore the...
the speed will increase
and it'll go faster.
- [Instructor] All right, so
Arquel says that gravity
makes roller coasters go faster?
So, if you want a faster roller coaster,
you need to build a higher roller coaster.
Did anybody write anything different
for roller coaster?
Carlos, what did you write?
- [Carlos] Oh, the same thing,
but the steepness of the
hill when it's going down
it increases its velocity,
and it's more G's.
- [Instructor] All right, so
he says the steeper the hill,
more velocity, more G's.
What's a G?
Let's have Carlos try
first, then we can help
him out if he needs help.
What's a G?
You said G.
- [Carlos] Yeah.
A G is a pull.
- Okay, so it's a pull.
Adriana, you want to add to it?
- It's a force pushing against you.
- All right, pushing against you.
Anybody else want to add to that?
It's a pull, its a force,
it's pushing against you.
How do we get a G force?
What do you think, Austin?
- [Austin] You have a push or pull,
you have excess friction, air accelerates.
- Push or pull, excess friction.
Arquel?
- All the forces together.
- All the forces put
together on you? Okay.
So, let's write "G force"
down and put a question.
'Cause we're still not sure what that is,
maybe we can get there.
So, we're not sure quite what a G is.
But we know it has something
to do with gravity.
All right, let's pick another picture.
Who had a favorite picture that we haven't
talked about that wasn't a roller coaster?
What was your favorite picture, Greg?
- [Greg] The dude.
- The dude, who is the dude?
- (laughing)
- He has a name.
We know who that is.
Who is that, Enrique?
- [Enrique] Johnson.
- [Instructor] It was Newton, right?
What was Newton's first name?
Not John.
- [Students] Isaac?
- [Instructor] Issac, there we go.
Issac Newton, all right.
And what does the dude say?
Isaac Newton?
What's he saying?
What's his quote?
- [Greg] Not that dude, this one.
- Oh, the floating dude.
Okay, the floating dude.
He'd rather talk about the floating dude
above Isaac Newton.
Okay, so let's look at the guy floating
in the middle of the air.
He looks like he's planking.
Is this a possible picture
if you just saw the picture?
- [Students] No.
- Greg, why do you say this is impossible?
Because the Earth's
gravitational pull, right?
- Okay, so he says the Earth's
gravitational pull, what?
- Like, this wouldn't work because
when you pull... (inaudible).
- Okay, he should be being pulled down to
the center of the Earth.
Why do you say the center?
- 'Cause that's where
the gravitational pull's
coming from.
- 'Cause that's where
all the gravity wants
to take you and that's
where all the gravity's
coming from, I like that answer.
Anybody want to add to it?
Vanessa.
- [Vanessa] But if you
have pressure against both forces,
you could possibly stay up longer?
- Okay, so how could you get pressure
to make you stay up longer? Chloe?
- [Chloe] Force?
- [Instructor] Where would
that force come from?
- Your body?
- [Instructor] So, how
could he, if he's not
touching the ground, make himself float?
What's underneath you that you don't see?
- [Chloe] Gravity?
- Well, we don't see gravity, but what's
underneath him?
It's around us right now.
- [Students] Air?
- The air, right?
So, let's think about the air.
If we could make the air thicker,
what would we also increase?
- [Student] The gravity?
- [Instructor] Not the gravity, we're trying
to go against the force of gravity.
- [Student] The weight?
The force against our weight.
What's that called,
let's think about a boat.
Floating in the water.
- [Student] Bouyance?
Bouyant force, right?
So, if you could increase the
bouyant force of the air,
and Vanessa said if you could
make that strong enough,
you should be able to float.
Does anyone know a planet where there's
more thick clouds than we have here?
It's our neighbor.
- [Students] Mars.
- He has clouds?
Who has clouds, who has thick clouds?
Jarissa?
- Venus?
- Venus.
Yeah, is that what you were going to say?
Venus has super thick clouds, right?
And if we could go there,
maybe there'd be
enough air underneath you,
that you could float in the air.
If they was pushing enough bouyant force
on your body, okay?
All right, anymore for the floating guy?
Did anybody write anything different
for the guy who looked like
he was floating in the air?
I know that Karima and
Anthony had a good answer.
What did you guys write down Anthony?
- Put that...
I put that the gravity
will pull you to the center
of the Earth, and it will like...
Like it would...
- [Instructor] It pulls you
to the center of the Earth,
and what did we decide about where you
stand on Earth?
- Like on the other side?
- [Instructor] So, what would happen if you
went to the other side of the Earth?
Would it still pull you the same way?
Or is it going to pull
you an opposite way?
- The same way.
- [Instructor] The same way,
where is it always going
to pull you?
- Down.
- [Student] Towards the center?
- [Instructor] To the
center, to the middle, okay?
It doesn't matter what
planet you stand on,
doesn't matter where
you are, it's trying to
take you to the center
of the object, okay?
So, why do we get stuck to the Earth,
and that the Earth's stuck
to us in this picture?
- 'Cause the Earth's solid and
it doesn't let us go out into the (inaudible).
- Okay, so he said the Earth is solid.
Are we solid?
- [Students] Yes.
Hmm, okay, so maybe it's
not that we're solid,
'cause maybe there's
something else going on.
What do you think, Carlos?
- [Carlos] The Earth
has more mass than us.
- [Instructor] The Earth
Jenny, what's mass?
- [Jenny] Mass is, well, all of us then?
- [Instructor] We all have it.
How would you give a definition of mass,
what is it about us?
- [Jenny] The type of weight?
- [Instructor] It's the type of weight.
Okay, we're on the right track.
Who wants to help her out?
What's mass?
- [Student] The amount of density?
- [Instructor] Amount of density.
Okay, we're getting better.
Jarissa?
- The amount of space that it takes.
- [Instructor] Well, what would
that be, what's your space?
Volume, okay?
So, space is volume. We're
still trying to figure out
what's mass?
We've heard some density
words, we've heard
volume words, what do you think, Ky?
- The amount of electrons?
- [Instructor] Oh, we're getting closer.
So, it's your electrons, your...?
- [Student] Atoms?
- [Instructor] Ah, your atoms.
So, it's how many atoms
you have inside your body.
That's your mass.
So, now someone else said weight,
so let's go back to that.
How do you get weight?
So, you stand on the scale.
How do you know your weight?
What is going on?
What do you think Hakeem?
- [Hakeem] Pounds?
- [Instructor] We measure it in pounds?
Okay, so how do me measure it?
How do you get pounds?
What's happening to your mass?
What happens when you stand on the scale?
What is it measuring?
- [Students] Your weight.
- [Instructor] Your weight.
So, then how do we figure that out?
What's going on?
What's going on on a scale?
Carlos.
- [Carlos] The gravity
is pushing you down?
- [Instructor] Gravity
is pushing you down.
So, what happens to your
weight, if you have more mass?
- [Student] You're heavier?
- You're heavier.
So, your weight, how would
we give a description
of weight now?
We know mass is how many atoms you have.
We know volume is how
much space you take up.
So, now what's weight?
Carlos has kind of said it for us.
How would we put it as a definition?
It's the pull of what on your mass?
- [Students] Gravity?
- Pull of gravity.
So, let's look at the guy
in the picture again.
If this was going to be true,
what would we have to say about his mass
to be able to float?
Would he be allowed to
have a mass on Earth?
Hakeem says "no," Vanessa says "yes."
If you're going to float,
and there's gravity,
always trying to pull you down,
in order to float, what do we have to do?
With our mass?
Decrease our mass, okay?
So, let's think about if
we go to another planet
with our weight.
Does your mass change if
you go to another planet?
- [Students] Yes, no.
- Do all of a sudden, you have more atoms in you?
- [Students] No.
- [Student] Depending on the gravity.
- What did you say?
- [Student] You have the same atoms, but
your weight and mass changes.
- You said the same
amount of atoms, so your
weight and mass changes.
But if you have the same amount of atoms,
isn't your mass the same?
- [Student] Yeah.
- Okay, so what's the only
thing that would change, Jarissa?
- [Jarissa] The gravity.
- The gravity, so then
what would that change
about your weight?
Would it change, or
would it stay the same?
- [Student] It would change.
- [Instructor] It will change.
So, what can we say if we
went to a smaller planet?
- [Student] You'll become lighter.
Why?
- [Student] Because it has less gravity.
- Has less gravity, so less pull.
You weight less, okay?
So, let's put "weightless"
next to "G force" as
another word we should look up.
Ready?
All right, so, what I want you to do now,
using all your notes that we just took
and what we just talked about,
I want you to flip your paper over.
And in the circle, I would like you to try
with your partner, to write a definition
for what you think gravity is.
I'll give you one minute.
You and your partner try to figure out
what you think the
definition of gravity is,
and write that in your circle back.
- (background chatter)
Make sure you guys share that, okay?
A lot of weight, or...
What's the other word of
how many atoms you have?
What's it pulling on?
Very good, so it pulls on your mass.
And think about where it's trying to pull.
Oh, that's a good definition.
- (background chatter)
30 seconds, start putting in your description
of gravity, try to write your definition
on your paper.
Make sure your neighbor
also has a definition
on their paper.
- (background chatter)
Pulls what?
Pulls the...
- [Student] Weight?
- [Instructor] You almost said it.
- [Student] Mass?
- [Instructor] Mass.
Make sure you guys share that, okay?
You guys done?
Okay, so what is gravity?
It's a force, so that means it's a what?
- [Student] A...
- [Instructor] A short pull?
Gravity's pulling us, right?
Okay, so what's,
so what do you think, is
it pushing or pulling?
- [Student] Pushing.
- [Student] Pulling.
- [Instructor] Ooh, we have a disagreement.
Better figure out which ones right.
- (background chatter)
Okay, so it's a pull.
So, where is it trying to take you to?
- (background chatter)
And what is it trying to take about?
Your...
Your definition.
All right, what are you having?
- I wrote that gravity
is an invisible force
that pushes or pulls
you towards the center.
- [Instructor] Okay, so
the word I want you to
make sure we say is "invisible."
'Cause we'll talk about that, okay?
All right, so let's share our definitions.
Who would like to share
their definition first?
All right, Ky.
- [Ky] We put gravity is a force
that always brings you
to the middle.
- [Instructor] All right,
Gravity is a force that
always brings you to the middle.
So Sarah, can you add that to the circle?
Arquel, what did you guys write?
- [Arquel] Gravity is a pulling force that
brings you to the center of the Earth,
and it wants to (inaudible) the mass.
- [Instructor] Okay, so
you added "mass" to that.
Okay, so it's pulling on mass.
What do you want to add Angel?
- I want to add to Kyle's
answer that it's invisible.
- [Instructor] Invisible.
So, let's think about what
we learned about forces.
If it's invisible, you can't see it.
Is it touching you?
- [Students] Yes.
- Or is it everywhere?
- [Students] It's everywhere.
- Everywhere.
So, is it a contact force,
or a non-contact force?
- [Students] Non-contact.
- Why do you say that, Israel?
- [Israel] Because it's not touching you.
- It's not touching you.
So, even if you're floating in outer space,
will gravity still be there?
- [Student] Yes.
- What do you think, Carlos?
- [Carlos] Yes.
You say "yes."
So, those astronauts, will
they still feel some gravity?
Even though they're out
at the space station?
What do you think, Angel?
- Outer space has some
gravity, but greater
than, that's why they wouldn't feel it.
- What do you think it depends on?
We have mass so far.
But the strength of
gravity also depends on
something else.
We have mass, but what could it also
depend on, Vanessa?
- [Vanessa] Force?
- Okay, gravity is a force.
Angel was getting there,
he was saying that
it's still pulling on you,
it's just not as strong.
- [Student] The weight?
- That's mass.
We talked about mass and weight.
Trying to get the other thing that's
going to control gravity.
- [Student] How big the planet is?
- Okay, so that's mass.
Let's think about the astronauts who are
not as close to the Earth.
Are they weightless?
They have the same amount of mass,
their mass didn't change.
But they went farther away from the Earth.
So, why are they weightless?
Why do they float?
What's the other factor
going on with gravity?
Moving away from the center of the Earth.
So, what do we call that?
Has to do with how the gravitational pull
depends on...
We have mass, and we're
looking for the other factor
we could change to change gravity.
What do you guys think?
If I'm really far away
from Jarissa, am I able to
grab her
as much as if I was closer?
- [Students] No.
- If I go real close to
her, is it easier for me
to pull on her?
- [Students] Yes.
- But what happens if I go far away?
I have the same mass,
my mass doesn't change,
can I reach her as easily now?
- [Students] No.
- So, what's the other thing
going on with gravity?
- [Student] Distance?
- Distance.
So, if you're far away from the Earth,
can gravity pull on you as hard?
- [Students] No.
- No.
But the closer you get,
the little bit stronger,
little bit stronger.
So, then why do we feel the pull
of gravity here on Earth, but I don't feel
the Sun?
- (background chatter)
We're closer to the Earth
than we are the Sun.
So, we're going to feel the Earth before
we would feel the Sun.
But now if we left the planet, we started
going somewhere else,
say I was going to Mars.
What would happen the
closer I got to Mars?
Who would start pulling me now?
- [Students] Mars.
- The Mars center of its
planet would start to pull me.
Okay?
So let's look at the
picture of the planets.
Thinking about pulling to the center,
why in the picture of
the planets is the Sun
in the middle of all the planets?
- [Student] Because it's the biggest.
- [Student] Oh, it's the biggest one.
- We got a couple of different answers, so
let's share with our neighbor first.
See if you know why the
sun is in the center.
You got 30 seconds.
- It's got the biggest mass.
- It got the biggest mass,
and it's the biggest.
So like, it got the
most gravitational pull.
That's why it's in the middle.
- (background chatter)
- [Instructor] All right, Marco.
Why do you think the Sun is in the center
of our solar system?
- Because... I don't know.
- [Instructor] You don't know.
Okay, Javier, what do you think?
You're his partner, what
did you guys talk about?
Based on what we just talked about,
why would the Sun go in the center?
- It has more mass?
- [Instructor] It has more mass.
So, what does it also have more?
- [Student] Gravity.
So, he's always going to
be in the middle, right?
What if we had a bigger star come our way?
Like what about a black hole?
Say one of our neighbors blew up.
One of our...