- Has more light around him and it goes
off into this huge dark hole through the
trees.
- Why do you think it's more light around
him?
- I don't know. Just to show that, to
bring him more into the main point that
you should see when you look at the
picture.
- What is the dark force symbolizing? Why
is it a dark force? Why isn't it, like, a
bright light? Yeah.
- I don't know. It kind of reminds me of
what Jack said. Dante started going
through the forest. It kind of reminds me
of his travel of starting to go to the
layers of hell and stuff. Hell's not a
very bright place so it reminds me of
that.
- One thing, the light and religious
paintings. Jesus has a light around his
head so it might symbolize how he's pure
or more religious. But--
- What'd you say?
- I said but Dante isn't pure so why would
they highlight someone who wasn't as pure
as like Jesus?
- Okay, so I want to come your statement
in a moment, because Kailyn had something
to offer. Why do you say he's not pure? Is
there any indication that he's not pure?
- Well it's kind of an inference because
he's man. We all assume that the purity is
in God or Jesus or Buddha or whatever.
He's not because he's man and men have
faults. Women have faults. A human being
is just not divine, I guess.
- But it says in the text that he gets
angry with people who are not true to
their religion and their beliefs
politically and religiously. So he kind of
is the most pure one. Not like Godlike but
he is more pure than the rest, I believe.
- So do you think that's why Dante went to
hell in the first place? To go see all the
bad people? Do you think he was going
there to learn a lesson? Or going there to
prove that he was right?
- Because remember this is a fictional.
This is fictional. So can a character...
'cause you're right we infer that man is
sinful. But can
a fictional character be perfect? Can be
flawless? Can be sinless? And if so, is
Dante trying to go a different way of
inference. Is he trying to infer that he
is, from what you've said, that he wants
to find out more of what sins are so he
can make himself pure if he's not already.
So can a fictional character be pure?
- One of the questions I think was the
three beasts he encounters and what do
they represent. I kind of thought that
they represented what he does or what he
did and everything. Like a wake up call.
You're going to go see all of these people
who have done things similar to that so
you kind of want to change your ways. They
were reminding him what he has done and
what he did because he was violent because
he was in that guild kind of thing. He was
considered a fraud by the other team I
guess side. So I think it's more of a like
he's going to there to see what happens
when you don't be the best you could be, I
guess.
- Who judges where you go? Is it the devil
or is it a higher power?
- I thought it was the gods that judged
that.
- Are there gods in this story? Do we ever
hear much about the gods?
- We aren't sure about the gods.
- Yeah, really.
- Who judges where all these people go?
Cause they're talking about all the famous
people and the places they are but who
decides that?
- We didn't really read the hell part
as opposed to the...
- Yeah, yeah.
- So maybe in the other books it would
explain.
- Where the gods are.
- And you said who judges where they go
and everything? Technically we don't know
what supreme being judges that because all
we know is the devil is on the bottom
eating Brutus, Cassius and Judas. But in
the book, on page 41, lines 8-9, Minos
is the one who discover the crimes and
dictates where they go. So he's kind of
like boss of hell sort of. Forty-one
lines eight and nine.
- I have a question. Are their crimes so
bad to the point that they go to hell or
is it just because they made like sins or something?
Because everybody makes them so would that make
everybody go to hell?
- That's what I find too
[Background Chatter]
- Meaningful. But in their own perspective
they are different
- Individual, yeah. So do you think that
the layers of hell are how bad of the
thing that the person did like how far?
What do you think depends on how far you
go down--
- Like, the pain increases?
- One of my questions are, are the
punishments of different people different
based on who they are or what they do?
- I think it's what they do but through
their actions they can kind of be defined
as who they are. I think the layers of
hell go down as the pain and suffering
increases related to their crimes
- Couldn't it be like their pain and
suffering for all of eternity is based off
of all the pain and suffering that they
had caused others in life? For instance,
in Limbo. All these babies that had died
and weren't baptized are now there but
they hadn't really hurt anybody so they're
not being quite as punished as, let's say, Judas
who's in the center of hell having his
head gnawed on.
He caused a lot of pain and suffering
therefore we was given a greater
punishment for what he had done
- So it depends on who they
put it on.
- Yeah.
- So if they just keep it to themselves?
Like, gouging out the eyes. That's not
really hurting anyone else.
- Right. Where's the gouging of the eyes?
Where did you just pull that from? What
piece did we read where the eyes were
gouged out?
- Oh, I'm sorry I got confused. Oedipus?
- Oedipus.
- He punished himself for it in a weird
way. But, do you think that his punishment
would not go as far because he didn't
torture other people?
- Think before you respond. Think about it
because I want you to respond to this.
This is huge. I want you to write your
question down on a piece of paper and then
their responses to it because you have
probably just now created a thesis for an
essay we're going to do for the end of the
year.
- Okay.
- So write down your question. Mainly she
has brought up, just like I heard you guys
doing with these pictures, a different
text. Didn't you bring up the Odyssey with
this?
- Yeah.
- Do you want me to write Oedipus
specifically?
- Yep, write down the gouging of Oedipus'
eyes. Where would Oedipus have ended up in
Dante's Inferno?
- Okay, so pretty much--
- Yep. And I want you guys to answer and
then I'll move on and come back. I love
how you bring in another text. That's one
reason I brought this picture in, so you
guys hit on that. I love that you brought
this up. This is real higher order
thinking because at the end of this year
our essay for you guys for the final is to
bring in the texts that we've read and you
have to develop a theme so right there's a
good start. Okay, you ready for them to
answer it?
- Yeah.
- Okay.
- The pain that Oedipus caused wasn't
intentional. So I don't really think he'd
be punished as harshly. I do believe that
he'd be punished due to the fact that he
did kill his father and I believe a couple
other people during that fight. So, he would
be punished but I don't believe that the
gouging of his eyes would lessen any of
the punishment. 'Cause, really, he didn't
knowingly go into the incest and do that
intentionally. So really, he shouldn't be
punished for something that he didn't know
he was doing.
- But he still killed somebody.
- He did kill somebody. And the gouging of
his eyes, I don't think would lessen that.
I think it was more of a pain in life
lesson for him. Although, It did cause him
a lot of pain, I believe the guilt that he
faced caused him greater pain than his
actual gouging of his eyes.
- May I clarify something really quick here?
So you're saying basically, because she
asked where in hell would he be? So f+irst
of all, what level do you think he'd be?
Gouging eyes or not, where would he be in
hell? Where would Dante run into him?
- He would be with the murderers.
- With the murderers, okay. So you're
saying that he wouldn't be any more in
depth than that simply because of his
gouging.
- No.
- That is just his own--
- Retribution.
- Yeah.
- He did that to lessen the guilt in his
life--
- In himself.
- 'Cause the guilt was much more painful
than him gouging out his eyes.
- And also, even delivering pain to yourself
can get you in hell with, like, suicides.
- Right.
- 'Cause there's the whole ring where like
people kill themselves and they go to
hell. Or they destroy their possessions. I
didn't quite understand it completely but
it seemed to say destroying items that they
had, I don't know, maybe a couch or something. If you
destroyed that, you'd go to hell because
they destroyed their own items.
- Right, right. In Circle Nine, and that's what important
about this, in Circle Nine, those people that destroyed or
take from.
You know, you have Canna after Cain. Everything is
allegorical. Every part of Circle Nine,
there's an allegory. There's Ptolemy,
there's Cain. Everybody is compared or
made allegorical in there for their sins.
Because of what they did to humanity. Like
Ptolemy murdered people in his--
In his--
He was a ruler. He just murdered people.
Mass murders. So, he was put in there as a
comparison to that kind of sin. That
Hitler type of sin. So everybody in that
level, too. Which would be interesting to
see. Talk about some of our other
literature. Talk about The Odyssey a
little more.
- I have one more question about sin. Do
you think, is everyone's definition of
sinning the same?
- Actually, I don't believe so.
[Background Chatter]
- We were just talking how everybody lies
but how are some still in Limbo.
- Goes along with what he said was,
"no, I didn't steal" so you stole and then
you lied.
- Yeah.
- So you double dipped.
- So you half and did different things.
- Oh interesting, so what'd you come to?
- We came to they'd go to the serious one.
- Yeah.
- Whichever one's more serious
- Why?
Basically the one thing that impacted
the world more, like in a bad way, is going to take
the worse punishment. So if I stole a
penny, or I lied to the king, I'd probably
get punished for lying to the king. That's
what we kind of came up with.
- Yeah.
- So I want to ask you a question. If
you're saying you lied and then you lie
about lying, or you steal and you lie
about lying.
- I don't steal, sorry.
- Yeah, they're two crimes and this person
has chosen to commit two crimes. Okay, so
does that play into that?
- Would you suffer twice the punishment
then?
- No, it doesn't bring up any of that in
Dante's. Basically everybody's got the
same punishment.
- But still wouldn't you get like
harsher--
- Well, depending on the circle.
- Yeah, but some people in the circles do
have worse punishments than other people.
- Will you give me an example?
- Well, let's see. Ulysses, and I forget
the other guy's name, they are in the same
flame and I think he said the flame was
burning brighter. I would assume that'd be
a worse punishment than other people if
they're burning --
- If they're burning, yeah.
- Some of the less worse... um... lesser punishments.
It's like magicians get their heads turned
backwards. You could see where you've been
but you wouldn't cry over it. Unless
getting stabbed to death and then healing
and then getting stabbed to death again
- Yeah
- Then your flesh getting eaten off over
and over and over again.
- Yeah.
- I want to ask you guys a question
because we've studied pictures all year
long and there was one when we were
studying Oedipus. And I don't know who in
this group had this one when you were
doing those folders together, but there
is, what is her name, Antigone's brother's
name that was dead...
- Polynices.
- Yeah, Polynices.
- Was it the one where she was like
leaning over his body?
- Yeah, by the rock.
- Yeah.
- Okay, now that you've read The Inferno,
do some of those photos from some of these
other stories and poems tie together or
relate or reoccur?
- I can relate.
- Okay talk to me about that.
- Because it reminds me of Dante being lost in the forest
in the beginning and then it reminds me of how
Oedipus gouged his eyes out and couldn't
see anything and so he didn't know which path
to take. He had to rely on somebody else.
He had to rely on Virgil to get him
through what was to come. Then Oedipus, he
had to rely on Antigone to tell him where
to go and trust her with his life
basically.
- Nice. Nice.
- That's what I got.
- Well as I walk away I want you guys,
'cause I'm going to leave this here. I want
you guys to talk about other literature.
'Cause you said yes, I can relate some. You
just did. I would like for you to relate.
- All right.
- Okay.