- [Teacher] So just leave your
clicker on your table guys.
I mean you can put one in front of you,
just don't turn it on yet,
they're not activated.
Please don't play with them because
then the batteries can stay
charged through the day.
Thank you for the help.
Excellent, thanks.
All right guys, so let's get started
with our discussion here.
Set the clicker down
please don't play with it,
just leave it on the table, thank you.
I asked you today to
get our thinking going
to answer this question.
Danny DeVito is between
4'9" and 5'1" tall.
So, i'm 5'10" so Danny DeVito
is either between this tall
or about this tall.
We're not sure on his height.
His wife, Rhea Perlman is 5'0 tall.
How tall do you think their
sons and daughters will be and why?
All right, so please raise
your hand to share your answer,
and I'm going to ask you
why you think like you do.
So, I'm going to start
back there with Alex.
So, turn this way so that I can hear you,
okay?
- [Alex] Okay. I think their
kids would be around 5'
because their mom is 5' tall and their dad
his middle height is 5'?
- [Teacher] Okay, so you're
looking at the middle
estimated height of Danny DeVito
and his wife's height is 5',
so you think together then
all their children will
be 5', boys and girls?
- [Alex] Mm-hm.
- Okay. Great, thank you.
What else do you think? J.R.?
- I said 5' too. I said 5' as well
because that's about
how tall they are,
so their kid would be around that.
- [Teacher] Okay, so you're looking at
kind of his average height and her height,
so you think the kids will be around that?
Okay, anything different or you
want to explain it further?
Michael?
- [Michael] I just said that you get
your height from your parents, so
whatever the parents were right around 5'
the kids will be about 5'.
- [Teacher] Okay, you get your
height from your parents.
So, since the parents are
about 5' the kids will be 5'.
Boys and girls?
- [Michael] Yeah.
- Okay, great. What do you think?
- [Student] Well, I think
the daughter could be 4'9"
and the sons would be around 5'2",
because both of the parents are shorter,
and so they could be a little bit taller
or even a little bit shorter
than one of their parents?
- Okay, so even though
the parents are shorter
they could be taller or
shorter than the parents,
and you said that the
daughters could be about 4'9"
and the sons might be about 5'2"?
- Yes.
- Is there a reason why you think
the boys would end up being
taller than the girls?
- It's just kind of a normal thing.
Normally boys are taller than girls.
- Okay, so a normal thing, boys
are usually taller than girls.
Okay, great.
Any other ideas on the
height of their children?
Adam, what do you think?
Well, what do you think about...
- I think that they'll be around,
I think boys and girls,
will both be around
5' because it's right inbetween the parents.
- [Teacher] Okay, good.
What about me and my family?
I'm 5'10".
So, I'm tall.
What do you think about my family members?
How tall do you think they are?
I'm 5'10", how tall do
you think my mom is?
How tall do you think my dad is?
What's your estimation? What do you think?
Raise your hands everybody,
let's participate.
Mackenzie what do you think?
- I think your dad would be around 6'2"
and I think your mom would
be around 5'11" or 5'9"?
- [Teacher] Okay, so my mom
is between 5'9" and 5'11",
so close to my height, and my dad
would be taller, about 6'2".
Brian, what do you think?
- [Brian] I said that I think
your dad would be taller
than you, but then your mom would be
around the same height.
- [Teacher] So, my mom
is about the same height
and my dad is taller?
- [Brian] Yeah.
- Anybody think anything. . .
Pardon me?
- [Brian] Or like around 6'.
- [Teacher] My dad would be around 6'?
- [Brian] Yeah.
- [Teacher] What if I tell you
my little brother...
my little baby brother, is 6'4"?
And he is. This is true, he is 6'4".
So, he's a tall guy.
Does that change your ideas about
the heights of my parents?
You guys are nodding "yes."
What do you think now? Travis?
- [Travis] Maybe your dad is like 6'4"
and your mom is like 5'8"
or 5'9" or something?
- [Teacher] Okay, so Mom is about here,
Dad is taller or 6'4"
like my little brother?
Michael, what do you think?
- Both of them are about 6'.
Okay, great, what do you think?
- Well, I know that a lot of people
get their traits from their dad, from dads.
So, that your dad is taller around 6'5"
and then your mom is shorter, like 5'8".
- So, you see my height,
and my mom is about 5'8"
and my dad is 6'5",
so for my brother and I,
you're figuring about our traits?
What do you mean?
- That you get your traits from your dad.
- So, my dad's genes are coming through.
Why do you think that?
Why do you think I have
only traits from my dad.
- Because I know a lot of
people who get their traits
from their dad and more than their mom.
- So, more traits from dad than from mom?
Do you think that's pretty much general?
- [Student] Yeah.
Okay, great.
Do you guys have anything
to comment on that?
What do you think?
- I think your dad's probably like 6'2",
because my brothers are both
taller than my dad already
and they're still in high school?
- [Teacher] Oh, interesting.
Well, I'll tell you my mom
was 5'11" at her tallest.
Now she's shrinking, she's like 5'9".
You know how that happens as you get older
and my dad, he's only 6' tall.
So, my little brother is
the tallest in the family
and my other brother, he's 6'1".
So, height does come from both sides,
but my dad's not as tall
you guy's might've thought.
Let's talk about Danny DeVito again.
Here he is, our favorite actor, right?
Notice his lack of hair, he's bald.
The question on here says
"Danny DeVito is bald.
What do you think his son's
hair or lack of will look like
when he's older, and why?"
His son, Danny DeVitto has a son.
What do you think about his hair?
Nice and loud so I can hear you.
Matthew.
- It said that their son would
have bald hair on the top,
but some on the sides?
- [Teacher] Some will be bald on the top,
but he'll have some hair around the sides.
Why do you think that?
- Because usually if somebody's dad's bald
they're not always bald.
- [Teacher] If somebody's dad is bald
they are not always bald?
- [Student] I've seen that.
- You've seen that?
That's a good observation, Matt.
What do you think?
- [Student] Well, the mom has a lot of hair
and the dad is bald, so I thought,
he will still have
a lot more hair than his dad.
He wouldn't be completely
bald, but bald on top.
- Okay, so mom has a lot
of hair, dad's bald.
So, you think the son will have
hair, but just bald on top?
- Yeah.
- So, when you see the
traits being passed down,
how do you see it?
- I'm not really sure what
you mean by that question.
- You're kind of saying that
he'll have this trait,
but he'll also have this trait.
So, how do you see that happening?
Did he get all of his traits
from one or all his traits
from another, the son,
or do you think . . .
- I think they were combined.
- They were combined. The
traits are combined.
Good, Sean?
- I thought he would have
like a blackish-brown hair,
because that's what the
mom's hair color is.
- [Teacher] Okay?
- He probably wouldn't be bald,
but he'd have a receding hairline.
- [Teacher] Okay, so he would
have a receding hairline,
and for those of us that
don't know what that means,
that means when a person
starts to lose their hair,
and it kind of inches back and
they're losing their hair.
That's what a receding hairline is.
So, the hair falls out as it moves back.
Are you ready to see what
Danny Devito's kids look like?
Here they are for our predictions.
We have his son in the
middle standing taller
than everyone else in the
family. He's about 5'5".
So, he's taller than both mom and dad.
This is Danny Devito's
wife, Danny Devito and his son.
Here's his daughters.
This daughter is about the height of the mom,
but she has big shoes on.
The other daughter is taller.
But notice their hair, what do
you notice about their hair?
Ryan, tell me what you
notice about all three kids.
- Well, they all have
hair, they're not bald.
- [Teacher] They all have
How would you describe their hair?
- Curly?
- [Teacher] Curly hair. What color?
- Black.
- [Teacher] Black or dark
brown, yes very good.
All right, so we see that.
Now, when we think about these bunnies,
another question I asked you
is this, look at the picture.
If they had ten offspring,
what do you think
the coats for each bunny would look like?
The fur in what respect,
that was the question.
Nathan, what do you think?
- [Nathan] 25% would be
white, 25% would be black,
the remainder would be gray with a little white?
So, part of them will be black
and part of them will be white...(inaudible)
So, half of them will be gray... (inaudible)?
- [Teacher] Okay, so here's what we have.
I'm going to use abbreviations.
25% is white, 25% is black
and 50% will be gray.
Nathan says that because one
parent is white, one's black
they'll combine to form a gray color,
just like mixing paint in art class.
Any other predictions?
What else are you thinking?
Let's hear from somebody new.
What else do you think? Omar.
- [Omar] I think 40% of the
bunnies are going to be black,
40% are white, and 20%
are going to be half black
and half white, like a
black bunny with white dots,
or a white bunny with black dots.
- [Teacher] All right. So, you're
saying 40% black, 40% white,
20% is going to be black and white.
You will see both colors.
We'll see black and we'll see white.
Why did you choose 40%, 40% and 20%?
- [Omar] Because I think that it's rare
for bunnies to have dots . . .
It might be rare for them to have dots.
- [Teacher] Okay, so you see
that a solid colored bunny
more likely, the probability
is higher for a solid color.
So, that's why you chose 20%?
Great, great thinking. Great explanation.
Sean, what do you think?
- I had 20% white,
20% black,
and the rest are gray.
I would have said 25%, but
you can't have two and a half
babies being white.
- Okay.
All right, so you would've said 25%.
So, you were thinking similarly.
- [Sean] Yeah.
- Why do you say 20%, 20% and 60%?
- Because most of them would be
a mixture of the two,
but a few of them would have to have more
of one of the parent rabbit's traits.
- [Teacher] Okay, so because
they have offspring,
the majority will be a mixture
of both of their traits?
So, mom and dad will blend
together to create gray,
but some of them will
look just like the father,
some will look just like the mother,
so some will be black, some will be white.
Great. One more idea.
Kasey what do you think?
- [Kasey] I know in health
that everyone has a dominant feature.
I think white is, so that the majority,
so like 40% would be white,
and 20% would be black,
and then the rest would be gray.
- 40% white, 20% black
and 20% gray.
And you said, because in
health you were learning
about dominant features and you believe...
- [Kasey] That's only 80%.
Oh, what did you say for the last one?
- I said the rest.
- Wow, well thanks for paying attention
Good check there guys.
- [Kasey] It would be 40%.
- ...60%, we need 40...
Did you say 40?
- [Kasey] I said the rest.
- I was just making up too
many different numbers.
Well, I'm so happy that you
guys are paying attention.
I'm going to tell your
math teacher, good job.
Okay, 40% white, but here's what Kasey said
that was really good.
She said that 40% will be white,
because white is dominant.
You used that word.
You talked about that
in health a little bit.
So, let's talk about dominant
and what that means.
What does it mean? What do
you think dominant means?
And be nice and loud for us. John.
- Most of?
- [Teacher] Most of. Good.
What do you think Sam?
- Main?
- [Teacher] Main... Sean?
- The majority?
- [Teacher] The majority...Alex?
- Beat out all others?
- [Teacher] Beat out all others. Nice.
What do you think, Sean?
- [Sean] Strongest?
- [Teacher] Okay. Let me show
you a little example here.
So, where do we get our traits, first of all?
Where do we get traits?
- [Students] From parents.
- From where?
- [Students] Parents.
- Your parents. Okay, it's passed down.
Traits are passed down and some
come from each parent, right?
Dominant, recessive, some
come from both mom and dad.
If you received a dominant trait . . .
See I labeled this cup
dominant and colored it pink
and you received a recessive trait.
So, half and half, mom and dad.
They come together,
which trait do you see?
The dominant one or the recessive one?
- [Students] The dominant one.
- The dominant one. What if I put it this way.
Which trait do you see?
The dominant one.
What if I put two
recessive traits together?
- [Students] The recessive.
- The recessive, okay. Either way I pair them,
mom or dad, dad or mom.
If I have two dominant
traits that go together,
what do I see?
- [Students] Dominant.
- Dominant, okay. So, if the dominant trait
is present, then...
finish the sentence.
If the dominant trait is present
in your genes, then what?
- [Kasey] It will show.
- It will show, Kasey says.
That's right, if the dominant
trait is present it will show.
Are you guys remembering this
from yesterdays little intro?
Okay, let's check this then real quick.
Yesterday you filled out this concept map.
Let's make sure that
your answers are correct.
Jsut take a look. So, read this with me.
- [All] "Genetics is the study of heredity,
the passing of traits
from parent to offspring"
and if the offspring has the
same alleles, we call that?
- [Students] Purebred.
- And if they have different alleles?
- [Students] Hybrid.
- What that means, allele, that word
say that, allele.
- [ Students] Allele.
- It's the fun word to say
during our genetics unit.
That's the form of the
gene, so is it a dominant
or is it a recessive.
Okay, so let's go back here.
Genetics is the study of . . .
- [Students] Heredity.
- The passing of...
- [Students] Traits.
- I don't hear everybody.
Controlled by...
- [Students] Genes.
- Made of...
- [Students] Alleles.
- Say it again. Alleles.
- So genes made of...
- [Students] Alleles.
- Shows when present. We call that...
- [Students] Dominant.
- And can be masked...
- [Students] Recessive.
- Recessive, all right, very good.
Any questions on the concept map?
Any corrections if you need
to make them, please do so.
All right! Well, let's get going with our lab.
Are you guys ready?
Okay, please take out your lab paper?
We're going to go back to some
of those reflection questions later on.
Notice the top of the paper.
It says "Problem". This is
what we're trying to solve.
This is the point of our
scientific investigation.
"Are traits controlled by
dominant alleles more common
than traits controlled
by recessive alleles."
I'd like you, on the lines, to
create your own hypothesis,
or your prediction for this.
"Are traits controlled by
dominant alleles more common"
that's the question "are they more common
than traits controlled
by recessive alleles?"
So, write down what you think,
write down your prediction.
If you can write it in the if-then format
of how we do hypotheses, that's preferred,
but if that confuses you at this point,
just write what you
think is going to happen.
Are dominant alleles more common
than traits controlled
by recessive alleles.
Whatever you think, it's your thinking.
We will talk about our
hypotheses in just a moment.
So, once you've written
down your hypothesis,
reread it and make sure that
it answers the question.
Then we're going to get
to work using our clickers,
which i'll explain in just a moment.
I'd like to hear you share some
hypotheses before we begin.
The question again, "Are traits controlled
by dominant alleles
more common than traits
controlled by recessive alleles?"
Please share your
prediction, your hypothesis.
Ronnie.
- I said yes, because dominant alleles,
it shows over recessive alleles?
- So, you believe
dominant will be more common
because they show over recessive alleles.
Okay, great.
Girls, one of you share
your hypothesis for me.
Who would like to share?
Everyones looking at you Kate.
What do you have on your paper?
- [Kate] I said that I thought the dominant
alleles were more common?
- You believe the dominant
alleles will be more common.
Okay, great, thank you.
Another one. Alex?
- [Alex] I agreed with it.
I said that I believe that
dominant traits were more
common than recessive,
because there's more combinations to get
dominant one's over recessive.
- You believe dominant
traits are more common
than the recessive, because
there's more combinations...
- [Alex] To get that?
- To get to that. To get
the dominant traits to show.
Good. One more. Matthew?
- I said that the dominant
traits are less common,
because in the picture with Danny DeVito?
His son and daughters
didn't look much like him?
- Okay, so you believe
that the dominant traits
are less common, because in
the example of Danny DeVito,
his kids didn't look much like him.
- [Alex] Yeah, and how your younger brother
is 6'4"...
- And how my younger brother is 6'4",
but he's taller than
the rest of my family.
Okay, so you're making connections to
our earlier conversation, good.
We're going to revisit our
hypotheses after we do this lab.