(whispering)
- We gotta work quiet.
(mumbles)
- It's three and a half inches long,
and is it?
Seven centimeters.
- Keep going, gotta keep going.
- Wait, wait, wait, wait, wait.
- It's probably about one pound.
(whispering)
- Okay, yeah let's go.
- I don't know how...
- You measure it with this,
inches then centimeters.
- One inch.
- That's one inch.
- Yeah, then do it across.
- We need one inch, one and a half.
- One and a half.
- Three and a half.
- You got it.
- It's a bone, got a bone.
- Pick it up.
- It'd be easier if we could pick it up.
- Here's a bone.
- There's one yeah.
- You all, let's put it in the middle.
- We gotta tear it apart now.
- We don't have to tear
it apart even more.
- It's a bone. It's part of that.
- Wait, hold on, hold on.
- (mumbles) and feathers.
- You all start pulling those ones.
- It's on my finger!
- There's a ball.
- It's a bird, it's a bird.
- No, look at this claw.
- It's a birdy bird.
- Look, there's its, wait where's its?
- There's its teeth and there's its--
- It's a skull.
- You all be careful with those little ones.
- Just broke it.
- Oh my god, I found something.
(laughter)
- You guys are being mean.
(whispering)
- A skull.
- I found a skull right there.
(whispering)
- How many skulls did you all predict
would be in your owl pellet?
- I put one.
- One? How many have you found so far?
Was it right?
- We found a couple bones.
- What about skulls, how many skulls?
- It's tiny.
Alright, how can you determine
what kind of animal it is?
How much did it weigh?
- Ten grams.
Do you think,
do you think its weight
has anything to do with
how many skulls inside?
Why would that have anything to do with...
- Because the skull might weigh
about two grams maybe.
- I think here's another skull.
It's got a lot of bones in it.
- Okay, see if you can determine
what animal it is.
- Looks kind of like a teacup.
- This is a rat skull
because I can see its teeth right here.
- I know, Jake found
another skull I think.
- This is a skull.
- This is so cool.
- Let's get playing boys and girls.
- You all, I think this is what we got.
- No, that is a bone.
- No look, look.
Where's the claw?
And look at this claw.
I think it's the same.
- And then look.
- Look, let's see.
- Oh, that's a skeleton.
- Oh, that is a skeleton.
- Ooh, my touching it.
- A whale,.
- Ooh yay, we found a skeleton.
Look at the skeleton Chloe.
- It's a skull. It's a skull.
- Ew, ew, ew, ew, ew.
- Put the feathers and stuff over here.
- Or whatever it is.
- Yeah, we need to (mumbles) the feathers.
- Look, this is soft.
- It's not soft, it has something.
- There's a little baby bone.
- It looks like a squirrel.
- Look, I got a baby bone.
- No, seriously.
- What animal did you
predict you would find
in your owl pellet?
- A bird. A bird, a gopher and a rat.
- So what have you,
have you decided what it is?
- A bird.
- How did you determine it was a bird?
- We found like big claws like this.
- How can you be sure that it's a bird claw?
- Because these are usually as hard
and like sharper.
- We put this.
- Oh, we got the skull and we got a skull.
- How many animals,
how many skulls have you found?
- We only found like two.
This is what I was thinking. You
know how it has sharp stuff up there?
- What's a way that you
can determine what it is?
- I think we got a bird,
we got some more claws.
- However much bones you find...
- Compare the bones that you found
to the bones on the chart?
- I found another skeleton.
- Keep working.
- It has to be a bone, this might be something right there.
- Let me get that out,
because I haven't got anything out yet.
- We got two skulls.
- I found something, I found this.
- Another skull.
- Yeah, I think.
- Found another bone.
- You did?
- Yep.
- We found all sorts of, here's another, this
is a claw.
- It's a bird.
- Is this a bird claw or, I don't know.
- I think that's a...
- Where's the bird skull?
- Found something.
- What is it?
- Wait, hold on, wait.
- I think we'll find another skull.
- What do you think this is Daniel?
What do you think this is?
- I don't know.
- Know what that is?
- I bet that's probably something.
- I think this bone might be something found in its arm.
- You all, look what I found.
- I think this is a skull right here because...
- We got them two, don't worry.
- We got a bone, we got a bone.
- We got the same skeleton.
- Have you determined
what your animal is?
- No, we don't know.
- I think this is an eyeball.
- We got a bunch of eyeballs.
- Here, let me see that.
- Look, look, look.
- It's a tooth.
- Eyeball.
- Let me see.
- Look, I found this.
- This is the (mumbles) part of the eyeball.
- Look, look, I found the--
- Ew!
- I found the pelvis! I found the pelvis.
(children talking over each other)
- The owls are on this chart.
- I think that might be something, wait.
(children talking over each other)
- With the tweezers.
- Here's an eye socket.
- Over there somewhere.
- This is this I think.
- We need to get the hair out of it.
- Oh my word. I think we got...
- Look, I got the head.
- See how sharp these are?
(children talking over each other)