- Winter is colder.
- Okay, alright.
Okay, okay.
So, that's his position.
He's going to stick with it for a minute,
but then he might have to go around,
he might change his mind, alright?
Okay.
This group agreed with Fernando, okay?
That it's because the Earth
orbits closer to the sun
in the summer than in the winter.
Who would like to share
they're thinking?
I'll call on you if you don't (laughs).
So, what do you think?
- Well, I think it's
because since the Earth
like orbits around the
sun, like in an oval,
when it gets here it would be warmer
because it's closer to the sun.
- Okay.
- And it's winter when it's
away from the sun (mumbles).
- Okay.
So, can you go and draw that
on the board, what you mean?
Because I heard you say that
the Earth orbits around the sun
in the shape of an oval.
Raise your hand if you agree with that.
Okay.
So, that's the Earth and
it's orbiting around the sun
and he said that the shape
of the path that it travels
as it orbits is an oval, okay?
Anybody else in this
group has something to add
to help him defend Fernando?
Okay, I see.
Can I read what you wrote?
- Sure.
- He said that the orbit
is not a perfect circle.
So, that's sort of what he's saying there.
Is that right?
- Yeah.
- And how would it not being
a perfect circle affect
the difference in summer,
winter temperature or heat?
- Well, we know that the Earth,
if it was a perfect circle
the seasons wouldn't change.
- Okay.
- It would be the same.
- Alright.
Okay.
- Depending where the Earth is--
- Alright, okay.
Anybody else have something
they want to add in this group?
Okay.
Now anybody based on these two groups?
Anybody want to move from their
group to these two groups?
Not yet.
Okay, that's alright.
Okay.
Now let's go to Raul, okay.
This group agrees with Raul and he says
it's because the Earth's
tilt changes the angle
of the sunlight hitting the Earth.
Defend yourselves.
- So, I remember learning
that the tilt of the axis
is the reason for the seasons.
But I read the question again,
it says the Earth still changes
and if it doesn't change
it stays the same.
- Okay.
Let's read it again.
Read it really simple.
- It says it's because the
Earth's tilt changes the angle
of sunlight hitting Earth.
- Okay.
So, it says the Earth's tilt
changes the angle of sunlight.
- Yeah.
- Does it say it changes
the tilt of the Earth?
- No.
- Okay.
So you going to stick with what you
said or you want to change?
Can you show me?
If I give you something can
you show me what you mean?
- Alright.
- Okay.
So, I'm going to give you
an apple and I want you
to pretend it's the Earth, okay?
And I'm going to stick this
bamboo skewer through it,
well it didn't go exactly
right, but just pretend.
So, what does this represent
based on what you just said?
- This is the axis of the Earth.
- So, this is the axis and
what does the axis do?
- (mumbles).
- Okay.
So, the Earth rotates around the axis
which is what Ryan said, right?
Okay.
And be careful because
I just poked myself.
I want you to be careful (laughs).
Okay.
So, can you stand up and
show me what you mean
and let's have someone else in your group
that agrees with you be the sun
and stand kind of in the middle
of the room right here, okay?
Alright.
So she's the sun, you're the Earth,
show us what you mean, okay?
- Okay.
Well, the Earth orbits the sun--
- Alright.
What's the word you were
just about to say though?
Revolves?
I think that might be okay, too.
What do you guys think?
Do you think revolve and
orbit might be the same?
- Yeah.
- Okay, alright.
- It doesn't matter.
- Okay, so you're going
to have to make the--
Go around the outside of the
desk for your orbit, okay?
- Well, it orbits the sun in a tilt.
- Okay.
Which one is tilt?
- I forgot how many degrees.
- Okay.
Alright, okay.
So keep going.
- It orbits in an angle.
- Alright.
Hold it the way you think
it's supposed to be.
Okay.
- I think it's this one.
I'm pretty sure.
- Alright.
So she's tilting it, but
now, and it's tilted.
Right now it's away from
the sun, is that right?
- Yeah.
- Okay.
Now keep coming around (laughs).
Of course does it make a
little job to play that?
- No.
- But we're just imagining
those who were in this room
(mumbles).
Okay.
Now stop there for a minute.
Is your axis pointing
where you want it to?
- Yes.
- Okay, alright.
Keep going.
You guys need to make space
for her to come through
on her orbit.
Okay, alright.
So, does that help some of you?
How many people think that she's right?
That the Earth tilts as
it's going around its orbit?
It's actually kind of spinning on its axis
while it's going around, right?
Is that right?
- Yeah.
- It's spinning the whole time, right?
What does that spinning give us?
- Day and night.
- The spinning gives
us day and night, okay?
Right?
Okay.
Because one side of the Earth
is facing the sun it's what?
- Day.
- And the other side is in?
- Night.
- Okay, alright.
Okay, alright.
This group over here.
You guys agree with--
- Susan.
- Susan, okay?
And Susan said that
she thinks it's because
the northern hemisphere
is closer to the sun
in summer than in winter.
So, what do you think?
- So, like she said that
its axis is tilting,
but as it moves around the sun the
northern and southern hemisphere
are closer and farther away.
- Okay.
- But on this side the
southern hemisphere is closer.
(mumbles)
- Alright.
- And when it comes over
here, the northern hemisphere
is closer in the sun and--
- Alright.
Anybody else in this big
room have something to add?
- Well, I agree with her, Natalie.
Because as it is tilted, I believe, that,
23.7 degrees
and so when it goes around
the sun shines bright and as it's turning
and so as it goes around it will change
where the light is hitting it.
- Okay.
Can someone add to that
or give us more detail?
- I'm also pretty sure that
like the state of Texas
it's more closer towards the equator
and so it doesn't have all of the seasons.
- Okay.
So, you think that places
on the equator, right here,
they don't have four seasons?
Summer, fall, winter, right?
- I think they do have seasons,
they're just not as different as like --
- Okay.
So, there's not much, that
difference in the heat
from the sun and the
winter versus the summer?
- Yeah.
- I think they're always
getting the same amount
depending on--
- The same amount of what?
- The same amount of sunlight and heat.
Because they're getting it directly almost.
- Okay.
Alright.
- (mumbles)
- Why do you think that?
What makes you say that?
So, you think the orbit is
elliptical like this group,
Fernando's group agreed.
But it's not enough to change
the difference in temperature.
- I don't think heat
really varies depending on,
I mean it varies, but not
in that small of a scale,
depending on where it is.
And so just that little, teeny movement,
ellipse or something, will not change--
- Okay, alright.
Okay.
I think we have another group over here.
How about the Shakira agree-ers.
Do you want to move now?
Okay.
Everybody if you want to
move to a different table
go for it now, okay?
Nobody agreed with Warner, huh?
Okay.
So Eva's out, alright?
People don't think that it
gives off more heat, right,
in the summer than the winter
in Warner's group, right?
So we're down to--
And Shakira's out, right?
Alright.
Who said to me that they didn't
agree with any of them?
- I changed my mind.
- You changed your mind?
Okay.
Alright.
So, here's what I want you to do now, okay?
I want to do another
little demonstration, okay?
Would you be the sun?
Okay.
And would you be the Earth?
Now here's what I want you to do for me.
I want you to orbit around the sun.
I want you to pick a spot.
Like let's say that yellow bucket, okay?
And as you're going around
I want you to keep the axis
pointed at that yellow bucket
no matter where you are.
Can you do that?
- Yes.
- Alright.
Give it a try.
Alright.
Now stop for a second right there.
Okay.
He's still pointed at
that yellow bucket, right?
Keep going.
Alright, stop right there.
He's still pointed pretty
much at the yellow bucket
and you're tilted over
a little bit, right?
Like she said.
Because we all kind of agree pretty much.
These two groups agreed with that.
What season is it right now?
In the northern hemisphere?
What season is it right now
in the northern hemisphere?
- Winter.
Why is it winter in the
northern hemisphere?
- Because it's farther away from the sun--
- Okay.
So, it's pointing away from the sun, right?
Do you think it's because
the northern hemisphere
is farther away?
- No, because it's tilted away.
- Tilted away?
- Yeah.
- Okay.
Alright, keep coming around here now.
Keep pointing at the yellow bucket.
It's a little bit hard to do, huh?
Okay, stop right there.
What season is it right now?
- Would it be spring?
Perhaps.
- It would be spring in
the northern hemisphere.
What is it in the southern hemisphere?
- Fall.
- Okay.
So it's the opposite, right?
Okay, keep coming around here.
Alright, keep pointing
at the yellow bucket.
Now what season is it in
the northern hemisphere?
What season is it in the
northern hemisphere now?
This group over here?
Somebody in this group.
(mumbles) the table.
What is it?
- Summer.
Why is it summer in the
northern hemisphere?
- Because it's closer to the sun.
- Closer to the sun?
- And it's like, kind of like--
- Are we like a few hundred
or thousand miles away
from the sun?
A few hundred or a few thousand?
Or like a few million?
- Yeah.
Okay.
So, in the scope of that,
it's hard to picture,
do you think that the
distance between this spot
and this spot is that much
compared to the sunlight
coming over?
- Yeah.
- To make it that different?
Okay.
So, you think it's more the tilt.
- Exactly.
- Okay.
I'm not sure in your past science classes,
what is it about heat
energy and light energy
pointed on something that
makes something warmer
or colder?
Anybody have an idea?
- Depending on how direct it is
because what I was thinking
is like if this is the sun
and, can I come up?
- Come show us.
- So, if my pencil's the heat and the light
it would be coming from here
and it would be coming
and it would hit with him, this one more.
- Right.
- And this one will be direct.
- Okay.
- So, I think what he's saying
is that both the northern
and southern hemisphere are
still getting sun, aren't they?
- Yes.
- Because we're so far away that the only,
which side of the Earth is not getting sun
right this minute?
- This side.
- When it's rotating it's night time.
But during the day is it
still pretty much light
in the northern and southern hemisphere?
- Yeah.
So, what he's saying is
that it's more direct
to the hemisphere that's
tilted, right, toward the sun.
It's still getting sun and
somebody over here said
something about the equator,
the places on the equator.
- Those over there.
- Who said that?
Say that again.
- Like states or, I'm not sure--
- Any locations, right?
- So like for Texas, as an example,
I'm not sure if it's
exactly on the equator,
but I know it's really
close to the equator.
- Okay.
Closer than we are.
- Yeah.
(laughter)
- Okay.
- I just read somewhere
that it doesn't have
all of the seasons.
- Okay.
- Yeah.
- Somebody else said I think
as much difference
or variation.
- Yeah.
- Okay.
So, this is summer in
the northern hemisphere.
Now we're going to cut across our orbit
and save time,
go back over to that side
and what season was that again?
- Winter.
- What season was that again?
What season is it now in
the northern hemisphere?
Winter, okay.
So, which hemisphere is getting
more direct sunlight now?
The southern hemisphere.
And what season is it now
in the southern hemisphere?
- Summer.
- Summer, okay.
Alright.
- Because the heat's having to go around--
- Okay.
So, let's go back for a second.
Raul's group said it's because
the tilt doesn't change,
but the tilt, as you're going around,
changes the angle of the sunlight
that's hitting the Earth, okay?
That's Raul's group.
You guys still agree with that?
- Yeah.
- Okay.
And Susan's group said it's
because the northern hemisphere
is closer to the sun in the
summer than it is in the winter.
Anybody want to move groups now?
- Wait.
Does that mean more direct or--
- Well--
- Or literally closer?
- Literally closer.
Okay.
Anybody want to move groups?
(laughter)
Okay.
That's okay.  You don't have to change, alright?
And this group (mumbles) with Fernando
that is because the Earth
orbits closer to the sun
in the summer than in the winter.
Alright.
I'm going to show you something
and I'm going to see if it
changes your mind, okay?
- Do we get to eat the apples afterwards?
(laughter)
- Well, we'll see, okay?
Alright.
Okay.
So, take a look up here.
Alright.
This is a simulation.
What do I mean by a simulation?
You can come back and
sit down with your group.
What do I mean by a simulation?
- It's a photo or a
video of what actually--
- Right.
It's not out in the universe
looking back at our Earth.
It's not from the space station
or anything like that, okay?
So take a look.
Alright.
And look at what's
happening with the axis.
It's a little bit hard
to see on the screen.
Okay.
Did you notice how like
what we tried to do,
It stayed pointing the
same direction, right?
Let's do it one more time.
Okay, alright.
Okay.
Now does this look kind of like what
he drew on the board at the beginning?
Does it look like an ellipse?
- Yeah.
- Or an oval?
- Okay.
So, I wish I had a glass, a clear glass.
- We do right over there.
- We have a clear glass?
- That's alright.
We can use this.
Okay.
- There is one over there.
- We can use this.
Okay.
I want you, and you're looking at this,
kind of from the side.
Does it look like that?
When you're looking at the rim of this cup
or the rim of this glass
from the, sort of the side
does it look like an oval?
- Yes.
- Yeah.
- Okay.
Let me make sure you can see that.
It does, doesn't it?
When you're looking at it from that angle.
But look at it straight down now.
What does it look like?
- A circle.
- It looks like a perfect circle.
Let's let a couple people experience that.
Look at it from the side,
now look at it straight down.
- With this one you're almost looking,
you're looking like right here.
- Okay.
- So, the glass it was right there--
- I want you guys to try it too, okay?
Alright.
It might.
But what I want you to think about here
is this is sort of what
you guys probably saw
in your fifth grade science books,
maybe even in your middle
school science books.
We'll have to take a look at
the pictures in our books.
You know, publishers, the
people who print the books,
they don't always do things
the right way for us to work.
And do you know that there are many,
hundreds and thousands of
adults, maybe millions of adults,
who think that the orbit of
the Earth looks like this
because this is what they
saw in their science books
when they were kids growing up.
But just like the glass, what happens?
I'm going to do it again, but
I'm going to flip it over.
We're looking at it from up above.
So, look what's happening now.
- It's a circle.
- Yeah.
And did you know that the Earth's orbit,
it is slightly an oval, but
so slightly that it's
really close to a perfect--