- [Instructor] Okay. Look at your music.
We are doing four parts, obviously. With
them, take just a general idea for the
whole thing. Raise your hand if you see or
have any eighth notes in the whole song.
Raise your hand if you ever sing eighth
notes. Sopranos, where do you have eighth
notes? Shelby, tell me.
- [Shelby] Measure nine.
- [Instructor] Say it really loud so they
all hear you.
- [Shelby] Measure nine.
- [Instructor] Measure nine, very good.
Audrey, where do you have eighth notes?
- [Audrey] Measure thirteen.
- [Instructor] Thirteen, good. Reese,
where do you have eighth notes?
- [Reese] Measure nine and measure...
- [Instructor] Measure nine and thirteen.
Hey, what do you notice about the soprano part and
the bass part, then? Same rhythm. Almost
the same rhythm all the way through.
Tenors, where do you have eighth notes?
Braden.
- [Braden] Twenty-one and twenty-two.
- [Instructor] Twenty-one and twenty-two.
So, getting toward the very, very end. Altos,
tell us something about your part
rhythmically. Raise your hand. Give me a
summation of what you do. Jamie.
- [Jamie] We don't have any.
- [Instructor] You don't have any at all?
You only have quarter notes, half notes
and some whole notes. So, how many beats does
a half note take up, everybody?
- [Together] Two.
- [Instructor] Two, make sure you last
long enough through that and then look up
at the whole notes. Solfège, what key are
we in? Where is Do? Brady.
- [Brady] F.
- [Instructor] F major. So, the first
pitch that the altos have is...
- [Together] Do.
- [Instructor] Do. Sopranos, what's your
starting pitch?
- [Together] Mi.
- [Instructor] Basses, what's your
starting pitch?
- [Together] Do.
- [Instructor] Tenors?
- [Together] Sol.
- [Instructor] Very good. Look at it for a
second, there are some jumps in the very
beginning. They don't mess around, right
away we've got some eighths and some
intervals. Chant on solfège, your part. One
and two and three and four and...
♪ [Chanting together] ♪
Very good. Go on.
Two, three, four. On the second to last
measure on the first page, bassists and
altos will move. Stepwise, motions, so you'll--
they both go up one step. Be aware of
that. Notice that we have some repetition.
Do you see some patterns that are coming
back? So, if you miss it the first time,
you get a second shot. Where if you get it
right the first time, remember what it
sounds like so you can do it again.
Continuing, second page. One, two, three
and chant.
♪ [Chanting together] ♪
Freeze. Let's go back and join the basses
with us at measure nine. Do, re, mi.
Everyone, measure nine, and...
♪ [Chanting together] ♪
Okay. Sopranos, careful, it might screw up
your voice. Why did you have an issue
there? Why did you miss it?
- [Student] It's a skip.
- [Instructor] Because it's a skip in the
melody? And why else? A practical reason.
- [Student] Here to here.
- [Instructor] Because it's hard for you
to look from the edge of the page down to
the next one. Top of the next page,
measure seventeen. A little faster, and go.
Sorry, seventeen. Sopranos, fa; altos, la;
tenors, fa; basses, fa. Ready? Hey,
everybody has fa, that might be a good
place to find the measure.
- [Student] La.
- [Instructor] This will help. You're
right, sorry, except the altos. Listen
right there when you're actually singing,
for that, and go.
♪ [Chanting together] ♪
You'll have to hold this for a very long
time. Go back to the beginning. The rule
is number six. Jesse, repeat the last
step. The last step.
- [Jesse] Oh, never quit singing.
- [Instructor] Never quit singing. Look
up, find your keys points. Okay. Second
key.
♪ Do mi so mi do so do ♪
♪ [Singing together] ♪
Sing your starting note.
One, two, three, four.
♪ [Singing together] ♪
Good. Now, I have two minutes to try to
fix and try to correct, to do as much as
we can to do a little bit better with
this. Take a second and look through the
piece and hear it go by in your heads. Do a
quick run-through, because it's hard to
know. I cant remember what I missed, I'm
still freaking out about the whole thing.
Take a minute, replay it in your head.
Find areas where there were problems for
you. Overall, you did extremely well. You
listened to each other. You could hear
that it sounded like music. If you weren't
sure about an interval, you would sing it
and then you would go, "Oh, this is right
yes," and you were affirmed. And I think
you got more confident as you went along.
Problem areas. Raise your hands if you had
one. Chelsea.
- [Chelsea] My problem I had was with
measure seventeen.
- [Instructor] Seventeen. Sopranos, do to
fa, that's a like a little bit of a tricky
leap and some of you hesitated a little
bit there. So, then you heard it, and you
were able to go on, and then I liked when you
got it again when you got back to nineteen.
Finding fa, that's a strange function in
the music. Yes, Patrick.
- [Patrick] Measure nineteen, fa to la.
- [Instructor] Okay. nineteen, fa to la. Just
making sure that you know where you're
moving. Fa to la? Where? Oh, nineteen. Yes,
sorry. My eyes were at seventeen. Good. Bass
hands. Excellent, thank you. Grant, where?
- [Grant] Twenty.
- [Instructor] Twenty? Yes, and what did
you do?
- [Grant] I couldn't figure out the notes, I
mean I couldn't figure out the [inaudible].
- [Instructor] I think it surprises you
because you move up by a step. You were
fine, so, la, and the ti, you weren't
willing to actually sing ti, because it's
not very often that you sing it. Stepwise
motion, so, la, ti, do. You did an
excellent job, basses, throughout, then
returning to so and do when you had it.
You had some issues with fa and la.
Colin.
- [Colin] Six and seven. Where we were
going from la to fa, and then back to do,
and then we had an eighth notes. Because
of that...
- [Instructor] Okay. So, being aware of
when you have eighth notes. And, chances
are there isn't ever a point where you
have eighth notes that other people don't.
So, when you hear it, then you can move with
them, and it's always by step when you
have eighth notes. And it's always
ascending. So, you don't have to worry
about going down anywhere, but, yes, fa
and la continue to be icky. I didn't time
it. We have to sing it again. I'm so
sorry. Okay, so we fixed the things that
we missed. We're going a little faster, so
it sounds like music, and not just this exercise.
Listen across the room to each other.
♪ Do, mi ♪
You stayed very well in tune.
♪ Do, mi, so, mi, do, so, do ♪
Set your key.
♪ [Singing together] ♪
Remember, you always sing
with the very best tone that you possibly
can. If you look up, basses, I'm trying to help
you out some with my hand signs every so often.
Sing your first note please.
♪ [Singing together] ♪
One, two, three, four.
Have a seat. And now evaluate yourselves
comparing the first reading to the second.
That means you need to think about how
well you did the first time versus how
well you did the second time, and if you
haven't had any thoughts or wanted to
share anything yet, it's time, because
this is opinion time, and there's no wrong.
The room is going to tip over from the
hands on this side. There are four sections.
Jamie.
- [Jamie] Well, sometimes they're like a step away from
each other, but something, like, I know
they're like one long [inaudible]
and sometimes I [inaudible].
- [Instructor] Okay. So, there are a
couple little slips with stepwise motion
that time. Okay, Hannah.
- [Hannah] I thought the sopranos the first time
did a lot better than the second time.
- [Instructor] I would agree. The first
time you did better than the second. There
are a couple of reasons for this. Raise
your hand if you feel like, when you think
back on how well you've done both times
you did better the first time. Why? Why?
Emily.
- [Emily] Because you were so focused and
trying to get it right, so the second time
we've already gone through it, so we relaxed
a little and little things slip up.
- [Instructor] Okay. Some of you may have
relaxed just a little bit too much. What
else possibly? Colin.
- [Colin] I think some of us got a little
too over-confident.
- [Instructor] Ohhh, that's an excellent
thing to check. Just making sure some of
you don't get a little over-confident.
Although, basses, the fa's and la's were
much better this time as an overall
section. Amanda.
- [Amanda] If the first time usually
there's a few problem areas for me then I
try to focus on them way too much and then
I see the spots where it might have been
tricky for me, like that jump from la to
do. So, I freak myself out about that even
though I got it right both times.
- [Instructor] You get stuck in your head
a little bit.
- [Amanda] Yeah.
- [Instructor] Okay. So, doubting yourself
and then not being sure. What else can
happen? Ariella.
- [Ariella] Along with what Emily said about
how we sometimes get over-confident
because we've already seen it and we just
fly by it because we're not really trying
to pay attention to it too much.
- [Instructor] Okay. Ryan.
- [Ryan] Measure nine. It's the so, so,
mi. I went back to the so because that's
what we did on the first page.
- [Instructor] Oh, okay, because you're
remembering, now, the patterns that you
had. You get the patterns mixed up when
you actually start to sing it the second
time. That's a good thought, too.
Michaella.
- [Michaella] Between the [inaudible] and
because we to sing notes over and over again.
over and over again. I didn't like it.
It's kind of hard. I didn't get the first
two notes right and finally on like, the third
note. I think I just figured out what we were doing.
- [Instructor] Patrick.
- [Patrick] I think that sometimes [inaudible]
because we've already sung the music and now I think
that we kind of know what's going on.