- Why do they keep getting colder? Why do
they keep getting warmer?
- They add water to it.
- Maybe they add water to it. Okay, what
else?
- The thermometer?
- What about the thermometer?
- They could have lights.
- Lights, well did they turn off the
lights afterwards? Okay, at this point, at
that point?
- Maybe after they took their first
temperature they took out the thermometer.
- Maybe they took out the thermometer and
that has something to do with it. The
thing is, ultimately are we gonna know
what they did? Unless I was video taping
you during that whole process. There are a
couple things I wanna point out here in a
second. I think several of the ideas are
possibilities. What happens if you put
your thermometer into the water initially.
What do you need to do? As soon as you put
it in there what do you need to do? Do you
immediately start taking readings?
- Yes.
- Everybody agrees? We immediately start
taking readings. As soon as we put it down
in there, like the first second we start
taking readings? We take a thermometer,
put it in hot water and immediately start
taking readings?
[Background Chatter]
- Like, what's the starting point and the
next temperature would be whether it
increased or decreased from that point.
- Okay, so we need a starting point. What
were you going to say?
- If you put it in there, like if you had
it at a certain temperature and you put it
in cold water it would still be reading
room temperature. It wouldn't change
immediately...
- Yes, so it goes 22, 21, 19, 18...
It's going down [inaudible]
- So, what could have been the issue here?
- They took it at the very beginning.
- Good, good. They just didn't wait long
enough. Look at this one. I saw this in
one particular group. Because, by the way,
you guys realize you were doing some very,
very different things, right? As we were
doing, and collecting this data there were
some major differences. What could have
happened? What was going on here? Just the
obvious stuff. Observation, what's the
difference in the pattern? Yes, Ma'am?
- The hot water is like consistent like
it's just gonna stay at the current temp.
- Hot water stays hot? Right? Cold water
is doing what?
- Increasing in temperature.
- It's increasing in temperature. The room
temperature water is doing what?
- It stays the same.
- With this same group
I just happened to catch this.
Cold water. Luke warm water. The person
was doing this. This is the warm water.
- Oh *laughs* body heat.
- Keeping it warm.
- Insulating it.
- What was happening?
[Background Chatter]
-Transfer of heat.
- We're gonna be doing a lot of labs over
the next several weeks. This doesn't seem
like a big deal, right? I mean, would you
have noticed somebody just sitting there
going like this? You've gotta start
thinking like scientists, though.
Because that could be a huge deal if we're doing
something with temperature, right?
Okay, good.
Well, the obvious - or the observation.
What's going on with the cold water?
- It's increasing.
- It's increasing, okay. Luke warm water?
- Staying the same. The hot water?
- It's getting cold.
- It's getting cold. Okay. What's
different from the first slide?
- Yes?
- The hot water went past the room
temperature of the cold water.
- Did it actually happen to somebody?
- Did it actually happen? Yeah. Let's do
this first. Let's go back to here, what
word would you use to describe what's
going on here? What's all this heading
towards?
- Room temperature.
- It's all headed towards room
temperature. There's a fancy word that
starts with an E.
- We may have talked about this last year.
- The fancy word - The idea, there's a word
I want you to walk away with.
The word is?
- [together] Equilibrium.
- Okay, how does this show equilibrium?
Rebecca, how does this show equilibrium?
With the hot water, how does this show
equilibrium?
- Rebecca.
- It's Sierra. It all goes toward the
same, it's kind of like the hot is
increasing and it's temperature-
- The hot is what?
- I'm sorry I meant the cold. The cold is
increasing in it's temperature and then
it's going towards the room temperature.
- It's going towards room temperature. The
hot is?
- Decreasing in temperature and it's going
towards the room temperature also.-
- Is this what we would expect? All right,
so what happened? Because I don't have any
idea. What happened here? Yes?
- In some places of the room there are
places where there is a lot of air coming
out? So maybe that one cup was under a lot
of air.
- We do have some powerful air vents. What
do you guys think? Is that-- that's a huge
amount. Any other ideas? Yeah?
- I think they accidentally read one of
the cold cups and marked the temperature
down for a hot cup.
- Is it possible there's human error here?
And they just... they looked at the wrong thing?
- Maybe when they were pouring the water
into the cups maybe they accidentally
mixed the cold up with the hot.
- So there's mixing the water,
thermometers--maybe just read them wrong.
So you guys think some kind of human
error, then? Yes? Yes?
- Let's go back to this and let's go to the
next step. Kind of like what we've done in
the past. I want you to think of this at
an atomic level, a molecular level what's
happening here. In order to do that, we're
gonna play with BBs. I've got enough sets
of BBs here, each group is gonna have a
set of BBs. All right. So group up a
little closer together.
Alright, so you two maybe go around... you guys.
Here's what I want you to do. Within your group one half
have one set [Background Chatter]
Actually, the two of you can... [Backround Chatter]
Marcus...
Good, here's what I want you to do. The
BBs will be what?
- [together] Atoms.
- Atoms and molecules. Okay, are atoms and
molecules just sitting?
- No.
- When we add energy are they gonna go
faster or slower?
- [together] Faster.
- When we take away energy they're going
to?
- [together] Go slower.
- Or, rather than take away, when they
release it. I'm gonna give you a couple
minutes. I want you to talk within your
groups. I want you to be able to do three
things.
I'm gonna call people up here in a second.
I'm gonna stick you on the overhead so
everybody can see your BBs. I want you to
be able to simulate the top line, the
middle line and the bottom line. So,
getting cooler, room temperature, staying
the same and getting warmer. I also
want... kind of a bonus would be to use both
how would you show something going into
equilibrium? All right, talk to each other
real quick. Some are getting cooler. Some
are getting hotter. Some are staying the
same temperature, and how would you show
equilibrium? I'll give you about a minute
or two.
[Background Chatter]
- All right everybody. Take a look at your
BBs. Hands off BBs. [Inaudible] I got a volunteer.
What were the BBs again?
- [together] Atoms.
- Atoms. And we're trying to show what?
- Movement towards equilibrium.
- Movement towards equilibrium. What?
Energy-- energy and movement how those go
together. Energy transfer is kind of a
fancy way of saying it. Okay, everyone
take a look at the chart. Here's the
graph. Show me the top line.
And tell me what you're doing.
- Make it faster, because it's hotter. It
decreased because it's going down and
getting less heat.
- Okay, so it's gonna start-- the BBs are
going to start going fast and then...
- Slowing down.
- Slowing down. Could you show us...
Yeah, we're in an awkward spot.
Getting warmer, the bottom part of that chart.
- At first it goes slower and as it gets
warmer the molecules move faster because
it's getting warmer.
- Thank you. I'm gonna do room
temperature. I think room temperature
would be this, and it stays the same.
Kenny what? Well, it's gotta be moving,
right? Room temperature would just be this
and I have to do what?
[Background Chatter]
- Oh, I probably should have picked the
same group. The two of you working
together, how could you show us
equilibrium? Of going towards equilibrium.
- She's going to do cold.
- Okay, and you're going to do hot.
Okay good now, time out. What did you do?
Or were you not done?
- I started out fast and she started out
slow.
- Why did you start out fast?
- Because I was hot.
- And you were?
- Cold.
- Cold. And Lauren, what did you do?
- [inaudible]
- The same speed, which was getting close to equilibrium.
- Show us one more time. Good. Who
disagrees? Nobody? Good. Thank you. Here
we go, keep going. A couple more things
real fast. Most of you guys had this going
about six, seven, eight, nine... anywhere
from six, seven to 15 minutes of data. If
we did this for an hour, what would this
look like?
- They would eventually all be on the same
line for a while.
- And it would be pretty boring. So this
would keep going-- well, what would be the
lowest point?
- Room temperature.
- This would be the highest point? Then
this would still continue the same. What's
the word?
- [together] Equilibrium.
- Here's how all this started. This whole
lab that you guys put together and created.
It's a demo. Here's how it all started. I
asked you a question yesterday-- a couple
days ago. Jar, bag with some water in it,
scarf, although I told you gloves, and then
aluminum foil. We came up, we felt all
four of these things. And you made a predic...
Well, the question was,
"If we put these outside, left them there
overnight, you look outside your window--"