- It's big.
- [Voiceover] Okay.
- And that's all, and
the little blood cells,
and I drew one on there,
in kinda like a magnified,
and there's little blood strands,
they're blood strands, DNA strands.
- [Voiceover] Now, those DNA
strands are only in the blood?
Are they anywhere else in your body?
- They're in your hair
and in your fingernails,
in your skin, they're everywhere.
- [Voiceover] Okay, so it's
not just in the blood?
- But you usually get it from the blood.
Blood. (laughs)
- Okay, alright.
It looks like you've got
a couple questions.
You can call on whoever you want.
- Me?
- Are these questions?
You guys, are these questions for Ryan?
Okay.
- [Voiceover] How do you know
Chuck was right? (laughs)
- [Voiceover] What?
- Well, he's a pretty smart guy.
- [Voiceover] Who?
- Chuck, my uncle.
- [Voiceover] Oh, okay. (laughs)
- Maybe.
- Even though there's a
bunch of DNA on the strand,
what does that have to,
how do you know that a piece of that DNA
came from either the mom or the dad?
- That's why (mumbles) because
DNA comes from both of them.
The dad gives the DNA and
the mom provides the DNA.
Okay, David?
- It was in the blood, right?
You said it was in the blood, right?
- [Ryan] Yeah.
- Yes, but couldn't blood be transmitted
to another person because they had the,
yeah, it could be transmitted
to another person,
so that's not really a trait.
- [Voiceover] Sure, when someone
gets a blood transfusion?
- Yeah.
- [Voiceover] Right?
Like if you're in the hospital
and you're injured and you
get blood transfusions?
If your eyes are blue and
you get a blood transfusion
from a brown-eyed person, does
that turn your eyes brown?
- [All] No.
- [Voiceover] It could, if (mumbles).
- [Voiceover] Okay.
Does it give you a widow's peak
when you have a straight hairline?
- [All] No.
- Okay.
If I get a blood transfusion tomorrow,
hopefully that doesn't happen,
but if I get a blood transfusion tomorrow,
is that going to give me a cleft chin?
- [All] No.
- If the person had a cleft chin?
- [Voiceover] But how do
people die when they get,
when they get blood transfusions?
- Carlos, can we talk
about that later maybe?
Let's stick with how we get our traits.
Do we get it through the blood?
Okay, not really?
Girls, what do you think over there?
- I was sure it had something to do
with the blood (mumbles),
but that's between your parents,
and it has nothing to do with the traits,
so I don't know.
- [Voiceover] Do you want
to come over here too?
- I want to come over there with the boys.
- Yes, I (mumbles).
(laughs)
- [Voiceover] You guys are,
you guys haven't even said anything yet,
and already they're,
they're joining your group.
Okay, should we hear from
the people who think,
I've got a large (mumbles).
Lorenzo, do you want,
should we hear from you?
Or are you thinking about
coming over to this group too?
You're set, okay.
Let's hear from Lorenzo.
Okay, Lorenzo, what do you think?
- I think that it was (mumbles)
that brown-eyed people
have more traits than blue-eyed people,
because I know more people
that are brown-eyed than blue-eyed,
and I think I read somewhere
that usually brown eye
is a dominant trait
over the blue eyes.
So for most of the times,
brown-eyed people,
if you have brown-eyed parents,
you will get brown eyes,
but how is--
- [Voiceover] So you heard
something about a dominant trait?
Okay, any questions about
that dominant trait?
Brown eyes being dominant trait?
- Because a lot of people
have brown eyes like that,
and not many people have blue eyes.
- [Voiceover] True?
Blue eyes are more rare?
Okay.
Lorenzo, whoever you want to call on,
you've got two people.
- So like, what you were saying right now,
(mumbles) something about your parents,
then you would get it from your parents?
- [Voiceover] Hmm.
- [Voiceover] What?
- Because when he was,
when he was saying that,
about the traits,
he said you,
if your parents have
brown eyes or blue eyes,
that you're gonna get
that trait from them.
So, from your parents, so--
- [Voiceover] Interesting.
Do you get what she's saying?
- What?
- [Voiceover] She's,
she's saying she's
sticking with this group
because it's coming from your parents.
Okay.
- That's why they say it's half and half.
- [Voiceover] Okay.
- Also, I'm in your group too,
but what's it called?
- [Voiceover] (mumbles)
- Yeah, I see more brown eyes,
but still, they always get
their traits from the parents,
not only--
- [Voiceover] But a lot of people have,
some people still get blue eyes,
and then others, it's because of,
they still get the
traits from the parents,
and some of them don't look alike, so--
- What about, what about,
some people have,
both of the parents have brown eyes,
and some of the kids turn,
they have their blue eyes, though.
- [Voiceover] Yeah, that's great,
because that's a great,
how many of you guys have
seen something like that?
- I have seen it.
- [Voiceover] Where two
parents have one trait
and then their kid has the opposite trait?
Like brown-eyed parents, blue-eyed kid?
You guys have seen that?
Why does that happen?
What do you think?
- I'm not really sure.
I know my parents have
brown eyes, and me--
- And you have green eyes.
- Yeah.
- [Voiceover] Your parents
both have brown eyes, right?
And your eyes are blue?
- Yeah.
- [Voiceover] Okay, so why does that happen?
Lorenzo, since it was your idea let's
hear from you.
- If I'm correct,
there's more brown-eyed traits,
so you get,
if you have a brown-eyed
parent and a blue-eyed parent,
you get a brown-eyed trait
and a blue-eyed trait,
but because brown-eyed is dominant,
most of the time, you get brown-eyed.
But you still have blue-eyed traits,
so even if you have two
parents with brown-eyed trait,
if they both also have
the blue-eyed trait,
you could get blue eyes.
- [Voiceover] I have a
question for you, Lorenzo.
You keep using this word, dominant trait.
Does, in your mind,
does dominant mean more?
- [Lorenzo] More?
- [Voiceover] When you're
saying more traits,
in your mind, does dominant
mean there's more of it?
- Yeah.
- [Voiceover] Okay, what do you guys,
how many of you guys have
heard this word, dominant?
- [Voiceover] There's
recessive, too, which is--
- Recessive?
Okay, does dominant mean more?
Anyone know that?
- It means power over the others.
- Like an overpowering
trait, he's trying to say.
- Are you trying to say more?
Are you trying to say more
or are you trying to say stronger?
- [Lorenzo] Stronger.
- [Voiceover] Okay, so this group,
the group you're sitting in,
the group one, right now,
is someone who thinks
that there's more traits,
come from the brown.
Do you think that?
You're not sure?
- Say yes.
- [Voiceover] But you know
something about dominant?
Okay.
- [Voiceover] I'll stay with my group.
- [Voiceover] Yes?
- [Voiceover] Can I make my own
group where it's like--
- [Voiceover] Yeah! (laughs)
Good, yes.
What are you thinking?
- I'm moving.
- Maybe it's just maybe that
nature decides what
something will look like,
because I don't know,
my parents have brown
eyes and I have blue eyes,
and we don't really have
anyone else who has blue eyes.
- [Voiceover] You're picking the--
- [Voiceover] Wait a minute.
- [Voiceover] Fiona, no.
Olivia?
- Yeah, nature.
- Okay, nature makes,
so you've got blue eyes,
nature had something to do with that,
not your parents?
- [Voiceover] Yeah.
- Okay.
Anyone want to respond to that?
- [Voiceover] Ryan?
- How does nature do that?
How does nature choose your eye color?
- [Voiceover] Doesn't it have something
to do with your parents?
- Of course (mumbles),
how could you just (mumbles),
a slot machine
where it's like 'ching'
and then the eye colors
roll around and stuff?
"Oh, you got blue eyes!"
- [Voiceover] I don't know (mumbles).
- Let him respond. You're not sure?
- [Lorenzo] No, I'm not sure.
I'm still (mumbles).
- Any other questions? (laughter)
- [Voiceover] Oh, yeah?
- [Voiceover] And like, you know how,
I was gonna ask this,
what if you get it from your
grandparents or your (mumble)?
- [Voiceover] Grandparents have black eyes.
- [Voiceover] Or from
your aunts or something.
- [Voiceover] I really don't know.
- [Voiceover] If your aunts
and sisters (mumbles).
- [Voiceover] Yeah, what if his aunt
and sister has blue eyes?
- That's right.
What if somewhere way back,
someone in your family had blue eyes?
- [Voiceover] You guys better (mumbles).
- [Voiceover] I don't
see how that (mumbles).
- How does that happen?
Does anyone know people who look like
their grandparents?
- [Lorenzo] Yeah, my cousin does.
- Lorenzo?
- My mom said that I
look like my grandparent
because I have a mole or something
that's in the same spot as my grandpa.
- If that's the case for you,
does that support what he's saying?
Nature decides?
Or does that keep you
in what you're thinking?
- [Lorenzo] It keeps me in.
- [Voiceover] But I have a question.
- Okay.
- How do people,
one eye is blue and
the other one is green?
- [Voiceover] Oh, I know that one.
- [Voiceover] That's a mutation.
- [Voiceover] No, no,
some people have really--
- [Voiceover] Yeah, like--
- All right, let's refocus.
Let's refocus.
We haven't heard from this group.
We haven't heard from the few groups
that have the most
amount of people in them.
Okay, so let's give them a chance to talk.
Ladies, can you start us off?
- You guys read it.
I have to read it? (laughs)
- [Voiceover] We agree that people
get half their traits from their parents.
We think this is a (mumbles)
trait from both of their parents.
Also, (mumbles) for example,
(mumbles) that--
- What? (laughs)
- For example, if one person has,
one parent has--
- [Voiceover] Because for example,
for me, I have my dad's eyes
and I have my mom's,
my mom's (mumbles).
- She has traits from,
some from your mom and
some from your dad, okay?
- [Voiceover] Yeah.
- It looks like you've got someone
who wants to say something about that.
- [Voiceover] But if,
what if you get more,
if you get some traits
from your ancestors too
and not just your parents?
What about your--
- That would just go back
a generation, though.
- Does that still
support what you're thinking?
- Yeah.
- No, because we're
talking about the parents.
How they have half.
- [Voiceover] Yeah, but you then
also get from your parents,
some of them,
so some people don't look
like their parents at all,
but they look like someone
else in their family.
- I'm seeing this issue come up again.
What about grandparents?
Kids who look like their grandparents.
How does that happen?
Does anyone here wanna, any of you guys?
Go ahead.
- You still get it from your parents
because your parents, if your
grandma has it, then that
trait is somewhere
in your mom or your dad.
It just doesn't show up as much,
so it can transfer back to you.
- [Voiceover] What can we call that?
That there's a trait in you
and you just don't see it?
Does anyone know a word for that?
- Invisible? (laughs)
- [Voiceover] I heard it over here.
- [Voiceover] Recessive.
- [Voiceover] Yes, recessive, okay.
Who else has heard recessive?
Raise your hands.
Scientists call a recessive gene
a gene that does not express itself.
It doesn't mean it's a
little gene that's quiet.
It just means that it's a
gene that's not showing.
Or a trait, sorry, a
trait that's not showing.
That's called recessive.
You also want to talk about this more,
a little bit more, let's
stay on this topic.
I think it will help us figure it out.
Yes, Ryan?
- Like he was saying, it's
probably about the DNA strands,
when they, when two people (mumbles)
combine in different parts
or put in different pieces of it,
like maybe one, like maybe the blue eyes is out
and brown eyes goes in there.
Or maybe when they have one
of those recessive genes,
the recessive genes get,
it goes into the strand too.
Maybe when Tyler said that none of,
neither of his parents have blue eyes,
maybe his grandpa or his
grandma or their grandparents,
maybe one of them had blue eyes,
and it was in his mom or his dad,
and it went into the strand
that he was created from.
- It didn't show up in the mom,
but then it popped up in the kid?
- [Ryan] Yeah.
- Okay.
David?
- [David] I don't know, I think,
I don't know if I agree with him,
but I think I kind of do because,
like he said, it was dominant,
but he still has,
he still has a little bit in him,
so it's kind of like a,
well, because you still have,
some of your traits,
or your parents still
kind of have a little bit.
- How are,
okay, how are,
how is this idea
that brown-eyed kids have,
I'm sorry, brown-eyed,
there's more traits in brown eyes, right?
Is that what this idea is about?
All you guys right here?
How is that like this one?
That we get half from
mom and half from dad?
Or how can we use some of this thinking
and layer it onto some of this thinking,
so they're both right?
- [Ryan] The question is
how are those two the same?
- [Voiceover] Right.
- How are that one and this one the same?
- [Voiceover] How are pieces from this,
how do we use pieces from this idea
that Lorenzo is bringing
up, dominant and recessive,
how do we use pieces from this
and combine it with pieces
from this group over here?
Let me get you to talk
about that with your group.
Let me ask, I'll ask that
question one more time.
What's right about what
these guys are saying
and how can we add it to
stuff this group is thinking?
- [Voiceover] What if the
kid is born blind, right?
(all students talk at once)
Or what if the kid comes
out deaf and blind?
- (mumbles) some express
themselves and some don't.
- Woo!
That, you just gave me a brain scan
because you read my mind. (laughs)
Say there's two DNA strands.
One in this hand, one in this hand.
They combine.
The dominant ones from each of these
take over and make one
of all the dominant ones
that were in them.
- Can you give me an
example (mumbles)?
- With Tyler, maybe there
was a dominant gene.
The blue eyes was dominant.
Maybe it was passive before it started,
whatever it's called, recessive,
and then it became dominant,
but over time,
and then it (mumbles)
went in Tyler.
- How can a dominant gene
become a recessive gene
and become dominant again?
- [Voiceover] Maybe (mumbles)
every time it gets passed down.
- [Voiceover] Hmm.
- [Ryan] Like with us, we get bigger.
- What if your,
if your mom had
two blue-eyed parents,
but Ryan here, today (mumbles)?
- And they combine.
I found it.
(all students talk at once)
- [Voiceover] All right,
are we ready to pull back?
All right.
I didn't get to hear from
all, these two groups,
but I did get to hear from them.
I think what this group
has is something good,
and I think you guys want to hear it.
(mumbles), you're gonna be the
spokesperson for that group?
Great.
- We agree that people get
50% of their genes from their
mom and 50% from their dad.
We think this because
if there's two people who made the baby,
then it's, logically,
should be split in half.
But
all,
every time someone has a baby,
all of their genes of both
parents go into the baby.
Only some of them decide to
express themselves and show.
- [Voiceover] Go ahead.
- Say I have two DNA strands
from two different people.
Say, Mary and Joe.
Mary and Joe both had grandparents
that both have blue eyes,
and that gene got passed down to them.
Now, they combined to make one gene.
Say Mary had blue eyes,
had a blue-eyed gene,
and Joe had a blue-eyed gene.
Those two genes combined
to make one dominant blue-eyed gene
and it goes in,
like what Tyler,
like with Tyler.
- [Voiceover] Right, so we,
Tyler, he used you as an example.
Your parents both have brown eyes, right?
- [Tyler] Mm-hmm.
- [Voiceover] And what
were you guys saying about,
his parents both have
brown eyes, but something,
they had something else too?
- Yeah.
- Because everyone kind of has
a little bit of everything in them,
it's just some,
some color or some trait just decides
to show because it's more dominant.
- [Voiceover] You know the movie,
you know the movie,
(mumbles), that movie?
They went to some place
and they went to go get,
(mumbles) found out,
they got the book from some person
and they matched it up to ours,
and it was different colors,
so they had different kind of genes
for like, for things.
So if you compare a baby who has blue eyes
and one who has brown eyes,
it's gonna have,
it's gonna have different
things with the eyes.
The DNA thing will be different.
- [Voiceover] Maybe those DNA genes that,
in a DNA, maybe they would look different
for a blue-eyed person
than a brown-eyed person?
- Yeah.
- [Voiceover] Did you wanna say something?
- Maybe the DNA of Tyler's parents,
for example, if their grandparents
had blue-eyed DNA accumulating in them,
it might have been
passed down through them.
And then when they got to where
they were forming Tyler inside their,
his mom's stomach (laughs),
it might have, the blue
DNA might have overpowered,
combining those two blue DNAs by getting,
it might have overpowered the brown eyes,
which made Tyler get the blue eyes.
- [Voiceover] (mumbles) 50%?
It could be like 50%.
- [Voiceover] That happened in my family.
- They're saying,
what color eyes are your parent's, Tyler?
What's your mom's eye color?
- [Tyler] Brown.
- Oh.
- [Voiceover] Yeah, what
you got on your mom's side?
- From my brown-eyed mom? (laughs)
Brown.
- [Voiceover] So what
about your mom's mom?
What about your dad's?
- [Voiceover] What about your dad?
- All right, you guys, let's talk.
Let's talk for a second.
If we've got an example of one person,
in science, you never hang
everything on one person.
Let's be careful about that.
And we don't want to have
him be the reason for all.
But this is a good example.
Do we think that people can have
genes in them that aren't showing,
but then they can have a kid,
and then those genes pop up?
- [Voiceover] Yeah,
because if the two genes--
- Did you want to say
something about it, Lorenzo?
- [Lorenzo] Yeah, because I think that
if a parent had brown eyes
and one had blue eyes,
but the brown-eyed parent
also had some blue-eyed genes,
then the baby would
probably come out blue,
because it has the blue-eyed gene
and then half of the blue-eyed gene
from the other parent.
- How could we figure out how
we get our traits for sure?
Because we have a lot of ideas, but what,
in science class, what will we do?
What kind of activity could we do?
What kind of research could we do?
How would we find out?
- We could go on AskJeeves.com and we--
(all students laugh)
- So we could look it up on the Internet.
Okay, guys, one resource we could look at.
How else could we figure this out?
- We could take a survey.
- [Voiceover] Didn't we do that?
(mumbles) the class?
- [Voiceover] We did?
- [Voiceover] No.
(all students talk)
- But we could (mumbles) whole school
so we have more to research,
or more, I don't know.
- [Voiceover] Make a larger sample size.
Then, we get information
and we find out that
X percent of our students have brown eyes
and X percent of our
students have blue eyes.
How does that help us find out
where those traits came from?
- [Voiceover] It gives
us more of an idea--
- [Voiceover] Their parents
and their grandparents too.
And their great-grandparents.
- [Voiceover] We'd have to ask people to,
we'd have to ask people to do
some research on their families?
Okay, so we could do some family research.
Sonja?
- We could make up an
assignment (mumbles).
- [Voiceover] Sure.
- [Sonja] (mumbles)
- [Voiceover] Okay.