- [Male student] Dakota didn't want to
bring his... because it's all
broken.
- [Teacher] Well we can still look at it.
Go get it, honey. Actually, Hannah, bring
Dakota's petroglyph over, please. Yeah,
that's the thing with clay. It breaks very
easily. Okay. All right. Will you still be
able to tell us about it?
- He said that it exploded.
- Please don't break it any more. Are you
going to be able to talk about it still?
You can tell us what was on it. Okay, put
it down, Addy, or it's going to break.
Okay. So you guys, you did... Your small
group was Washoe, and you're going to
present to the whole group next week or
the next week after.
- The whole group?
- The whole classroom.
- Okay.
- Okay. So what I need you to do for a
little bit is talk between yourselves
about what you found. And the four things
that I want you to make sure somebody
knows something about: food, shelter,
clothing, and location. But if you found
something else you want to talk about, go
ahead. So anybody, chime in.
- Okay. I think I know where they're
located.
- Can you tell us?
- South Lake Tahoe.
- [Female student] I know what they ate.
- In your strong voice though.
- They ate onions. They ate wild potatoes,
wild carrots...
- I think a little bit...
- Wild mustard, sunflower seeds, wild
carrots, wild potatoes, wild strawberries,
raspberries, wild gooseberries, wild
rosehips, wild rhubarb, pine nuts, and
they used...
- Sweet potatoes, wild turnips, wild
spinach... seeds...
- Okay. Do you think we're good on food?
- [Together] Yeah.
- Okay.
- I think Olivia got the part.
- Well, we'll talk about that after. So we
have location...
- Shelter.
- Go ahead. Okay. Who's going to go next?
- [Coleman] I have they used sticks and
leaves to build their homes.
- Okay. What do you have your
information on?
- I have clothing. They used rabbit
skins, buckskins, and plants.
- Okay. And I'm sorry, Coleman.
What did you say?
- They used sticks and leaves to build
their homes.
- Okay. So you got those four covered. Any
fun facts you guys found? Dakota, what did
you find out? Give us one fun fact.
- [Dakota] In 1859 the Washoe... Wait.
- Let Dakota, guys. Remember, we're trying
to be good listeners.
- In 18...
- Go ahead, sweetie.
- In 1859 the Washoe had about 90 people
[inaudible] times.
- Aw.
- No, no, not 90, 900.
- Can I see what you wrote?
They had 90,000, or?
- Nine hundred.
- Nine hundred, and now
they only have 300?
- No, let's see. The population. Well I
got it off the computer.
- Yeah, I got 1500.
- In 1855 the Washoe numbered about 900.
But are now reduced to about a third of
that number.
- What that the same fact you had, Dakota?
- Yeah.
- Yeah, very good. Thank you, Dakota.
- I got in 2007, there was 1500. But I got
it off the computer too and it said that.
- Well, you know the computer
is not always...
- I got the latest.
- What kind of data did you get? Like
demographic? Or where did you get yours
from?
- I got it from Google.
- Well guys, 300 was what yours said,
Dakota? And yours said 1500?
- Yeah.
- Are you sure yours wasn't 1500 from
before? And now it's 300?
- Well it said in 2007.
- Okay.
- On here, on my brain copy.
- Okay. We might need to look at that some
more, you guys. We'll look into that
before we report on that. But that would
be a fun fact anyway. Joe, did you tell us
anything?
- [Joe] Yeah. I have another fun fact.
- Okay.
- A fun fact. Their houses are called
Gadus.
- Gadus, okay. Okay. Now
who hasn't had a turn, guys? All of you
got your hands up. Let's include our
little friend, Addy. Okay.
- [Addy] They made baskets.
- Any good baskets?
- Mostly Dot So La Lee.
- Most famous one.
- She was famous for making baskets.
- What was she famous for, Olivia?
- [Olivia] She was the... She made the
most baskets than other Washoe people, the
other Indians.
- And why was she more famous
than all the other Indians?
- I don't know that, but I think she was
like a really good basket-maker.
- You think she was a good... Can you
scoot over?
- I can, yeah.
- Okay. Did you guys get to see any of the
samples of the baskets?
- [Together] Yes.
- Did you know that they're in very... Oh,
you have a picture? Awesome. These are
actually Dot So La Lee's baskets?
- Mm-hmm.
- Okay. So the thing, if you every get to
see one of Dot So La Lee's baskets,
they're woven so tight, you could carry
water in them. And we talked about
symmetry today in math. They're perfectly
symmetrical. Yes, they're woven so tight
that you can put water in them.
- And even Dot So La Lee had like 2000.
- You what?
- She had made that many baskets.
- She made how many?
- A lot.
- Two thousand.
- Two hundred and something.
- Wow. It would be nice to have one of
those now, huh?
- Yeah. But they're like... You can't even
buy them.
- You cannot buy them, huh?
- They're like in a museum.
- They're in museums, but I think some
people do have a private collection of
them.
- Really?
- Maybe one or two, yeah. They're not like
our petroglyphs that we're going to talk
about. Can you have a petroglyph in your
private collection?
- [Together] No.
- Those you can't have. Okay. So you guys,
let's see, who wants to be the writer? Do
you have a pencil? Grab that pencil. Would
you write your tribal name up here? You
guys are Washoe. And then go around, Addy,
and find out. Write the name of the person
next to the food, the shelter, and that's
what you're going to kind of be
responsible for. Let's get Addy... And you
can go around and ask each person, or you
can say, "Who wants to do food?"
W-A-S-H-O-E.
- I'll do fun facts.
- I'll do shelter.
- No, I'll do shelter.
- Okay. How are we going to decide?
- Joe should do the clothing.
- Joe should do
clothing.
- Is that okay with you?
- Do you think I should tell you the name of the...
- Hold on. We're not doing these. We'll do
that later. Thank you, Olivia. Olivia
volunteered for food. Joe, do you really
want to do clothing?
- [Joe] I was either going to do clothing
or language, because I found a whole thing for...
- Everybody can do a fun fact too.
- But I was going to do a fun facts.
- We need somebody to do food and
location.
- Okay. I'll do location.
- Shelter.
- Shelter and location.
- I got... I'll get shelter.
- Good. Thank you, Coleman. And then, I
know you guys want to do fun facts too, so
everybody can do a fun fact.
- L-E, and then M-A-N.
- C-O-L-E-M-A-N.
- L-E.
- L-E-M-A-N. Okay. Now we just have
location left.
- But what's Dakota doing?
- What do you want to do?
- How about me and Dakota will do location
together?
- Does that work? Okay.
- That's who's going to do the fun fact.
- Everyone can do a fun fact. So write,
"Thomas/Dakota" for location. No, don't
worry about fun facts. Everybody has got a
fun fact right there. So if both of you are
doing it, it's got to be super duper.
[Background Chatter]
- Okay, so, we're going to look up if they
lived in Washoe. They probably did.
[Background Chatter]
- Did you have their names down, Addy?
- It's like, Washoe people...
[Background Chatter]
- Where are you guys going to find the
information, Dakota?
- And Dakota.
- D-A-K-O-T-A.
- Better... You guys, what did we find
out about Google? Maybe you want to find
two. If you have two things and they don't
say the same thing, you might want to
check another one.
- There's a lot of maps on Google.
- There's a lot of maps on Google?
- Yeah.
- We're going to go... We're going to go
on maps and look where...
- Okay. Thanks. I'm going to take that so
when you... Okay. So next week or the week
after, you guys are going to do a whole
group, class presentation on your tribe.
And you're welcome to bring pictures, or
artifacts, or like pieces of whatever, if
you want to do that. You can bring a
basket. Obviously, it's not going to be a
Dot So La Lee.
- Can I bring a arrowhead?
- Did your tribe have arrowheads?
- Yeah.
- Okay. Now, looking in front of you, you
guys, for our art project we did something.
What is this called. Who knows? Olivia? I
like how you raised your hand.
- The petrograph.
- Louder. Petro...
- Petroglyphs. And what is a petroglyph?
You're going to break yours, Thomas. Addy,
what's a petroglyph?
- It's a carving in a rock.
- A carving in a rock. Did your tribe make
petroglyphs?
- We don't know.
- Why don't you know?
- 'Cuz they put things like right down.
They made it. They just moved. They just
carved it in and nobody really knows,
unless there's someone from that tribe who
made it and passed it down,
generation to generation.
- Yes. Very good. What were
you going to say?
- You know when we were looking on that
website? We were looking on that website
...and one said,
"Washoe."
- Okay. Yes. So some of them they attri...
They say that they did it, but we don't
know who did what petroglyphs. But in our
state, can we narrow it down to one of
four tribes probably? And maybe, if they
found petroglyphs where your location was,
you could say those were Shoshone
petroglyphs? Would that work?
- We're Washoe.
- Washoe. I'm sorry. All right. So who
wants to share theirs first? So what
you're going to do is you're going to
share it, and show the whole group, and
tell us what yours meant to you. Okay?
- Okay.
- Addy, you want to call on somebody?
Since everybody is dying to talk. Who's
going first?
- Coleman.
- Coleman, can we see yours? Okay. I want
to zoom in on it. Hold it up a little bit,
because I got it up. Okay. What does yours
mean to you?
- It means that it's night, and there's
some stars, and there's a duck. And then
there's a canoe on the water.
And there is a lot of meat and camping.
- Camping. Okay. Anybody else want to go?
- Pass it around.
- Joseph. Oh, don't pass it around. We
don't want to break it. We're going to
stick them on wood or something. Oh, let
me get a picture. Oh, I'm zooming in. Up
higher, Joe, because I've got this on a
tripod. Okay. All right.
- Mine is we're going to
drink some water from a river with fish in
it and a duck on top. And there's a snake
trying to eat the duck. There's an eagle.
It's daytime and the skies are clear.
- Oh Addy, you're calling on people. Thank
you. Okay. Addy, sit back a little bit so
we can see Miss Olivia.
- ...random things, but
I think I know what it is. It means
they're hunting buffalo at night. And then
the daytime came and it's all
rainbow. And we caught
some fish. That's it.
- Okay. Good. Who wants to
go now? Thomas. Nice.
- So there's a camp and there's a little
hill behind the camp. And there's people
in war, and there's a snake. And then, one
person is not in war. He's just trying to
shoot a duck. But then the other guy shot
him, and then there's... And this has been
happening for three days.
- Okay. Dakota.
- Mine kind of blew up here.
Mine kind of blew...
- What happened to yours, honey?
- It like kind of didn't turn out so well.
It like blew up in pieces.
- Can you tell us what it was before it
blew up in pieces?
- Well it was like, I don't know.
- Did you have like hunting
symbols, or anything?
- No.
- He just did like squares.
- I drew lines because I...
I remember I didn't really know
what to write.
- You didn't know what to write? Okay.
That's all right. But if you could do it
again, what would you do?
What would it mean to you?
- I'd probably make up a war thing.
- A war thing? Okay.
- It's more war, except hunt.
- Hunting? Oh, okay. Did you go, Miss
Addy? Okay.
- Humans were hunting for humans. That's
what's on mine.
- Okay. Addy, I would wait until everybody
was listening. Thank you.
- I can't show your...
- Okay. Just show the other children.
- It's a sunny day. A snake is trying to
eat the fish. The fish are in the river.
- Cool. What's the little zigzag?
- Mountains.
- Oh, those are mountains? Oh, cool.
- Sun. Snake. River. Just fishing.
- Just fishing.
- So, what other kind of art things could
we have done to show your tribe? What
would have been your tribe only?
- Baskets.
- We could have maybe tried to weave
something. What else?
- Basket, but [inaudible]...
- That wouldn't be too fun. In our
project, like we could pretend that we
were real...