- [Male student] So our question was:
What are the reasons
why Holden has a sudden
acceptance of letting Phoebe grow up.
And I got this question because,
I feel like the carousel
represents growing up
because (drowned out by
other voices) you have
to let people grab towards
something they want
or else if you're not letting
them experience the world
to its full extent then
you're just sheltering them
and they're just going
to live a sheltered life.
So they can't really do all the things
that they have the
possibility of experiencing.
- Yeah, I agree with him,
with Damon because I think
the carousel symbolizes
the ride through life.
Because it never really
stops, just continuously
goes around and around.
And the goal is to grab the golden hoop.
And I think that symbolizes,
I don't know, happiness
because everybody tries
for it and they keep trying
even though they fall,
they keep getting back up
on that carousel and trying to grab it.
And if you hold a kid back from trying
to grab what he wants, it's just like no,
I'm not going to let you go out there
and try to get what you want.
They're sheltering them from
their own happiness, kind of.
Because (inaudible)
- I also agree with Brandon,
but I also think that,
let's just say Phoebe was on
the carousel and she fell off.
I don't know if Holden would go to her,
but I think based on
his character he would.
But then I think that
would be bad just because,
like Brandon was saying, if
you don't let them fall,
if you don't let them
make their own mistakes
then they're not gonna learn from life.
So like my dad, he's so overprotective.
I think pretty much all parents
are really overprotective
of their kids, but you should
just let them go out there
and experience the world
and learn from themselves.
Not necessarily, because
I think that's their fear,
learning from their mistakes.
So I just think it's better
if you just let them go
like a little bit at a time just so
they can just figure out things in life.
- I think people have a hard
time letting go of any child,
whether it's their brother,
their sister, their actual child
because it means that they're leaving soon
and they're actually going
to experience their own lives
and then when it comes to a parent
or an older brother or
sister, they don't want you
to experience the same
thing that they did too,
so they're like telling you what to do
and it seems like they're telling
you how to live your life,
but they're giving you advice.
- I think parents, the reason
that they're so protective
is because they know that
saying ignorance is bliss,
because it really is,
and innocence is in a way, you
know, because you don't know.
And so they just want
their child to be happy
but inadvertently they're
actually making them sad
if they just won't relax
so they can (inaudible)
- And also, I think a lot of
kids don't understand this
but part of the reason why our parents
have such a hard time letting go
is because you were part of their lives
for as many years as you've been born.
They preciously try to take care of you
and they may seem like they're trying
to shield you from everything,
but they're just trying to look
out for what's best for you.
But you can't think of it like,
oh, once this one chance goes
by, I'll never have it again.
Because it really is like a carousel.
You're gonna keep going on
and you will have another chance.
- Going back to the
carousel I also thought
that the carousel, it may just seem
that there are a bunch of
different people on it.
So I think Holden kind of realized
that even though the carousel,
he knows have different people on it,
you kind of have to
allow the kids to grow up
because you can't always
keep them the same
like the carousel, it's not
a real machine or something.
We all have to grow up eventually.
- Just listening to you guys,
what do you think about,
when I was home in Los Angeles,
my nephew at that time
was about six months old.
And at that point in
time he was just crawling
and putting everything in his mouth
and stuff like that, like leaves.
You'd show him an apple
and he's like, "Ahh."
And then he puts a leaf in his mouth.
And you're just like, "Holy!"
You have to dig it out kind of a thing.
So in one respect, I mean, it's just like
there's this idea of let
people figure out things
on their own, but in that respect,
he'll die if you let him figure
out oh, you can't eat that.
So I'm just trying to think
as far as a parent goes,
how does a parent know when
to let them figure it out
versus how does a parent
when to protect them?
And I think that's part of
the conflict Holden is having,
he's trying to figure out
how he can protect people
and what he should protect them against.
- Me and my grandpa talk
to me and he was like,
"I know that I have to let you go."
And I think that they
know when to let you go
by how responsible you are.
Like if you do what you're supposed to do
and you show them that you're working
or doing what you said then
they want to let you go
because they know that you
(inaudible)
- That's true, and I also think that
it's not really based on yourself mostly.
It's based on your parents
and how they've grown
and how with having kids
you grow up as a parent
and you know and it's just nature,
you just know when they're ready.
That's what I think.
I don't think really it's just based
on all of their mistakes.
I just think it's pretty
much based on (inaudible)
- [Teacher] Interesting.
- I think when people
start changing and stuff,
like their attitude, because
I've noticed my little brother,
he's starting to change
and he has an attitude now.
He's starting to get a
little rebellious and stuff,
and I think that's when parents
have to start letting loose
on their kids cause we have to
experience things on our own,
and it's not just being
told what to do and stuff.
You have to have that
experience to learn from.
- Every person has their own free will.
Like the saying you can
take a horse to the water
but you can't make it drink.
You can enforce your rules on your child
as much as you want but you
can't force them to do anything,
you can just have an influence on them.
And that's something that
parents have to understand.
You can't force your kids
to do their homework,
but you can ground them if they don't.
- All right guys, I want
you guys to keep going.
You guys are doing a great job.
I can see your notes are
also looking pretty good.
I'm gonna move on to another group, okay?
But keep this going
because I think you guys
can come up with a lot more, okay?
Thank you guys.
You guys are doing an
awesome job with your volume,
we're gonna come over to
this group over here.
- All right, can you fill me in
on what you guys talked about
making sure we have the volume up.
- We have a couple of
questions, we have like -
(voices talking over each other)
- Oh, okay. Let's just come up with,
tell me about the one that you guys
are the most excited about.
- The first question is my question,
which was what are the reasons why
people live their lives
through other people.
And I kind of came up with that question
because Holden, he kind of
was denied of his childhood
because Allie died and so
that really impacted him.
And since that he's kind of been trying
to preserve the innocence of Phoebe.
Like making her go back to the carousel
even though she says she's too big for it.
He's like, "No, you're not."
He's trying to help to
her keep that innocence,
or just children in
general keep that innocence
that he was denied.
- It kind of was a parent
versus child kind of thing.
It goes against like parent versus child.
So a parent when they have a child,
they kind of want to live
their life through their child.
And they make them do all these chores
to get into (inaudible)
because they never got to
do it when they were little
because they were
deprived and their parents
probably didn't want them to do it.
So they kind of (inaudible).
- [Teacher] Interesting.
- I said that I just think
this whole concept of
the identity is not yet established,
and you have the father
and have somebody else
create their footsteps (inaudible)
I had these two other questions
because I was reading the book where
I was wondering why, I was
trying to get more in depth
with why Holden wanted his job
to be catching children in the rye.
- Okay, so I kind of answered it
and I said it's very in tune because
when you fall off the cliff
you can't get back up.
Just like when you lose your innocence,
you can't get it back because
this experience happened.
If you get exposed to it, you
can't magically forget it.
It just stays with you
and that's a part of you
that's just lost.
- [Teacher] Interesting.
- That kind of relates
back to the question about
(inaudible)
It seems like Holden is kind
of holding onto his past,
and so he's still living
in that innocent stage,
and when he's living an innocent stage
he can't make a wrong decision,
which is very hard from
his now because he's 16,
he keeps transferring
to all these schools,
and he can't really
grow up because he still
has that memory and so
that's why he's confused
about his identity.
- [Teacher] Good point.
- Going back to the first question
about why people live their
lives through other people,
it kind of goes through influences too.
Like he was talking about James Castle,
and when he died he said
that James liked to digress
on a topic and have speeches
and it kind of made him
think about, oh yeah,
that's a pretty great idea.
It's not bad, but why would
people be waiting for that?
It was actually like
a digression off topic
makes you think of new ideas.
- And I think going back
to that question again,
that sometimes parents want
the best for their child,
so they convince their, what
they want their child to be.
(inaudible)
If that makes sense.
And at the end, sometimes
you can't force the child
to do what they don't want to do.
- So in a way it's kind
of like you guys said,
the parent versus the child.
They wanna form their
own identity as a teen,
but at the same time
the parents are so busy
trying to protect them.
Is that what we're kind of
getting at through everything?
They're so busy trying to protect them
that they just gotta learn to let go.
Is that what we're saying?
- Yeah, kind of.
Like Holden says he's trying
to protect that innocence,
because he's always referring
to (inaudible)
There's a part where he's
walking down the sidewalk
and he called Allie to help
him cross to the other side.
And that's kind of interesting
because usually you don't
think an adult would say that.
A child would say that.
And it's because he's mad at his parents
because they won't talk about it,
so he's kind of just living with this.
- [Teacher] Interesting.
So he's just trying to
find a way of coping?
Is that possible?
- Yes.
And then there was
another kind of question
about where Holden comes to (inaudible)
Kiana said-
- Why do people feel the
need to forget the deaths
and move on?
And I thought of this question because
when Holden was inside just his room,
Phoebe was getting all frustrated
with him because she was
like, "You don't like anything!
You don't like anything!"
And he was trying to make
up stuff that he did like.
Like he did say he liked
Allie, and she'll say he's dead
so pick something else.
And he was arguing with her saying that
just because he's dead
you don't forget him,
and you can still like someone who's dead.
And he thinks that Allie is
thousand times better than,
nicer than, people who
are alive today, now.
So that just proves how
he's holding on to that
and he's not planning on forgetting that,
and he holds that near
and dear to his heart.
And so that's probably why he
doesn't like a lot of people,
because he compares them to how Allie was
and his innocence, his maturity
level, how it was then,
and how he sees how people today,
because kids don't
understand he's holding on,
so he doesn't really
understand what's going on.
- [Teacher] Anything
else to add on to this?
- No.
- [Teacher] I like what
you guys are doing.
I like how you're tying
in the death of Allie
with the catcher in the
rye type of a thing.
What about the carousel, first of all?
- I don't know, it sounds like it goes
with the whole keeping the
innocence going and all.
'Cause I know he would
probably ride it too.
Did he ride it?
- I was thinking of repetition,
because how the parents feel,
it rotates around and round.
And whenever Phoebe passed by,
he would tell her how pretty she looked.
She was never changing.
That's kind of what he wanted,
he wanted her to stay in that
stage, and nothing to change.
- [Teacher] Nice. All right, guys.
I'm gonna check on another group.
I want you guys to keep going with this,
you guys are tearing it apart.
Good job looking at the symbolism
and tying everything together.
All right, and your notes
look good as well too.
I like it.
I think you guys could
explore the carousel
and tie that in a little more.
Okay, hi guys!
You guys, the volume is doing really well.
(background chatter)
So you guys fill me in.
- Okay.
- [Teacher] Tell me what
you guys talked about.
- Just mostly like (inaudible)
and symbolism in the book.
- [Teacher] Start getting louder.