- [Voiceover] Today is Wednesday.
- Yes, I would clone myself.
- Good, why? Why would you clone yourself?
- Because everybody deserves a second me.
(several laughs)
- So you would just...
- And I would clone a woolly mammoth
for my clone to ride on.
(several laughs) Honestly...
- What would some of the negatives
to cloning something like that?
- (straightens throat) Well,
it's another me (mumbles).
But it's still good,
because, you know, I'm me,
and I'm good and bad.
- Do you know your clone
is not going to be, like,
set, right? You're gonna have
to wait for it to grow up.
- So, I have to raise a
little baby clone of me?
(several laughs)
- Yes.
- And it'll look just
like me when I was a baby?
- Pretty much.
- Oh, that's wrong!
(several laughs)
Oh, my God.
There are so many possibilities.
- Alright. So, let's start off with...
- I'll get it a baby (mumbles).
- Raise your hand if
you can remind us, like,
what is cloning?
There's only one of you?
- Like taking the DNA, or,
like, I don't know, like,
whatever, out of one person,
like, trying to, like
duplicate it into another one?
- Okay,great. We're all...
well, was there only,
like, one type of cloning?
What were some of the different types?
- Well, one type of cloning
is only tissues and organs only,
and another one is,
let's see, animal and livestock cloning.
- Anything else you want
to add to that? Gady?
So, what's one way they do
the cloning? So, they take
the DNA from one animal, what do they do?
- [Gady] (mumbles)
- Do you remember what parts they used?
Like what kind of cell they used?
- [Gady] Nucleus?
- They did take the
nucleus. And they used?
- [Another Student] (mumbles)
- The eggs of the other animal.
Okay, it's kind of interesting.
You can take the egg
from one animal and
completely change its DNA.
So, now when that turns into
a new organism, it's an
identical copy of the
animal that it came from.
- And if you take... you can bring back
endangered species, too.
Because remember that (mumbles)
or whatever, then they put in the cow?
- Yeah.
- But they were, like,
related in some kind of way,
so it wasn't, like, weird.
- That's true. It was
probably a decendent.
Do you guys remember that from the video?
They had tried to take an animal
that was almost extinct,
in fact, they couldn't actually
do the tests on the animal.
Remember, they were saying
that there were so few of them
that they couldn't even
do the tests on them?
Right? How long did (mumbles)
last? Does anyone remember?
- [Several people] Three days.
- Yeah, it was about three days, right.
But it was the first time.
- So, when they couldn't open up that cow,
the cow died, right?
- I don't know that for sure,
but I'm guessing that they were
not that interested in the cow medically.
They were...
- Oh, no, I was just wondering
because there's a cow sitting there
with a giant gaping hole in its womb.
- That's true. That does happen.
- I mean, I don't care if
the cow died, honestly.
That's another hamburger for me.
But that Goward? That
Goward? That's swole.
You can't get any other animal like that.
- Anybody else in here
agree that it's okay to do
that testing to save endangered species?
- Well yeah, because if
there's like a hundred million
cows and one... whatever
that thing was called...
(several laughs)
- So, we should probably
try and get more of them?
- Yeah, why not?
- Okay.
- We should clone pandas.
- Let's hear somebody else, though.
Is there anybody else that has....
- (mumbles)
- I said, (mumbles) alligator.
(mumbles) try and bring it back.
- That's true. What happens
when there's so many?
I mean, how many of you have ever watched
the movie Jurassic Park?
- Oh, my God, I've seen all
of them at least twice.
- So, that's a good question.
So, if we can bring back
something that looks like a cow,
fabulous. What happens when you
want to bring something
that looks just as cool,
but has bigger teeth?
- Well, you see, it breaks
out of the cage, like in
Jurassic Park the Lost World,
and it starts attacking
all the...
- Great.
- Well, yeah, it kind of
started eating people.
- That was wrong.
- Fabulous, but what could be
some of the downfalls on that?
Like, any negatives to cloning animals
that are endangered or almost extinct?
- Well, hardly any of the (mumbles)
- You need to...
- The DNA might get messed up
(mumbles)
- Yeah, but remember
that when we're messing
around with the DNA, yeah,
maybe there could be a
mistake. What happens then?
- (several mumbles)
- It could die.
- It could die, yes.
- I would say. One good thing
about bringing dinosaurs
back is that you finally
get to study them the way we want to.
- That's probably what
scientists are thinking.
"Wouldn't that be great
if I could study something
and actually be able to touch
it and see what it does?"
Because a lot of things they
tell you about, you know,
dinosaurs, is what they think
they do. "Well, we think
they eat this," and, "We
think this is how they lived."
Wouldn't it be great if we
could actually study those?
- What if dinosaurs were never real?
- Well, they found skeleton remains,
so they're pretty much
sure they were around.
- They also found (mumbles).
(another student coughs)
Because you can't just stick
an animal in an environment
and maybe it will survive, because it will
mess up the chain of life.
- Anthony has a really good
point, because what's going
to happen if we have dinosaurs?
We can't just stick them
somewhere for them to roam
around. Because they don't
have anything they can
naturally eat anymore.
And they don't have any
natural predators anymore.
- That's why you just bring
back T-rexes and velociraptors.
And what not. Then, you
just feed them cows.
(several laughs)
- You don't know if they
necessarily eat cows, though.
You don't know that.
- Well, it's meat.
- It is meat, but that's
also your food source.
- Well, that's not going to be (mumbles).
Maybe eight or nine. Maybe 25 for a T-Rex.
(several laughs)
- You're underestimating
the size of some of these animals.
But the same thing
applies to actual animals,
instead of just dinosaurs.
What happens if we have animals
that are going extinct because
we are building new houses,
and we're expanding our
cities? So, we're moving into
some areas where there are
some animals, and they start
to die off because we are
taking over their land?
So yeah, we could make a
hundred copies of these animals,
or whether it's plants, or
birds, or certain insects.
But that is a good question -
where are they going to live
if we just bring them back?
- Wildlife park.
- So, that is a good thing.
And again, remember that
you all add (mumbles) because
if you put them somewhere
that (mumbles) a park, they
won't necessarily survive.
So, you might need to think
about all the other stuff
that goes with that. So, yeah, the food chain.
Interesting, how everything's connected.
Raise your hand if you'd like to share
one of your questions from yesterday.
We'll start with Anthony.
- Okay, so like say me
and this lady get married.
We both can't have kids, so
they take my DNA and they make a
clone of me. I'm married to this person.
Would that be only my child,
or would that be our child?
- (several mumbles)
- And if, why?
- Maybe, yeah.
- But what if you're married?
- (several mumbles)
- Well, does it require two
people that has your DNA?
I'm sorry I didn't hear you.
- (mumbles)
- Maybe, it is. Maybe it's
totally the environment.
Who's to say? Maybe if you
raise it, and you're like,
"This is our kid..."
- Well, because of that case,
then, there can't be any more
like if we depended on cloning,
there woudn't be any...
(mumbles) well, there'd be
less drama in the world,
because we wouldn't be...
doing stuff the natural way.
And, like, people being
knocked up in bars and stuff,
(several laughs)
and random places, and stuff,
and, like, not knowing their
father in life, you know.
But you know what I'm saying, right?
- Do you think it would be hard?
- Like, what if people
were 100% dependent on this?
There would be a lot less problems.
- Eventually, if you
keep cloning yourself,
and then your clone cloned itself,
and your clone clones itself...
- You'd have the same group of people.
- You'd have the best group ever.
- Yeah, but how would you know
because you wouldn't be here.
- That's dumb, that's what that is.
- That's interesting.
- We can't have just a
bunch of the same people.
That'd be one stupid...
That'd be dumb, man.
(background chatter)
- I don't know.
Walking around seeing all the same people?
- That's stupid! You're
not going be like (mumbles)
- Like the Matrix, everything repeating?
- Other questions. Let's get
one from a female this time.
We got the guys' questions.
Let's get a girl.
Don't all shout out all at once.
Mayra, what's one of your questions?
- I said, like, if they clone
a sheep, and it's like, sick,
wouldn't it... or let's say there's
a regular sheep,
and they clone that, wouldn't
the clone be sick, too?
- What did she say?
- Not necessarily.
- No, because it's like you said,
it's two entire different bodies of life.
A lot of things can go
wrong in one person.
So, how could it just be the same thing,
two different (mumbles)?
Unless it's like a problem
with an organ that the one had,
and then (mumbles).
- Well, I want to say that,
like, a disesased kid (mumbles)
- Maybe. What about, remember, you
just did genetics, right?
If it's in your DNA, what would happen?
- If it was in your DNA...
- (background crosstalk)
- It probably would get
it. If it was something
that it caught, it
probably wouldn't get it.
- That's true. So it depends,
I guess, maybe what it is.
Right? So you have this sheep,
just cloned it, and because
it has something very serious
with it, and if it's genetic,
then yeah, there's probably
a chance that that clone
would probably have the
exact same disorder later on.
I think they were showing...
Remember when they were doing Dolly
and they showed some of the
animals they had cloned?
I think they were talking
about the sheep, Dolly,
and then they had some mice
that they had cloned.
They had said that the animals
they had cloned...
does anyone remember what
any of the side effects...
what they've noticed?
- [Student] (mumbles)
- Sometimes they can't
breathe right. What else?
- [Student] (mumbles)
- Sometimes they died really young.
So, just because it's a clone...
maybe we haven't quite figured it out yet.
Because it seems like
maybe there are some issues
with the animals actually
coming out healthy or normal,
if they're dying younger or
having problems growing.
Other questions? Hector, what
is one of your questions?
Or, if you don't have your
questions ready, or you feel like
your
questions were answered,
maybe you just have a comment.
(mumbles)
- You have none? What do
you think about cloning?
(fire engine siren)
Do you agree with it? Or are
there are certain places or
times you would agree with it?
- Um, I agree with it.
Like, the pros I would agree with it,
like, for food?
- For what?
- Like cloning for more food?
- Oh, like the chickens?
Right? Cloning to make more
chickens. Wouldn't it be great
if I have a perfect chicken,
and I could make a hundred
copies of the same perfect chicken?
(several background voices)
- I've had all types of chickens.
They all taste the same.
(several laughs)
- That's true.
- Everything tastes like chicken.
- But have you ever gotten
like a really tiny drumstick,
and then you got like
the nice meaty drumstick?
- Well, like a tiny little
drumstick. They still taste good.
(several laughs)
- True, but what one gives you more food?
- You got a point there.
- Okay, so maybe, right...
- But still, you could
put them together...
- In the case of KFC, the reason
why their chicken's so big
is because they put hormones
in them to make them big.
- Yes. That's the way they approach that.
- That's the best way
to do that right there.
- Not really. People get cancer from that.
- So, would this be a good solution?
So instead of making... eating... our cows
and feeding pigs, and
feeding chickens these extra
vitamins and extra hormones,
to make them larger
and grow faster, would it better
to just take the large, big cows
and just clone them? Or make
chicken and make copies of it?
Yes? No?
- Does anyone see any... maybe.
This sounds really great,
like we're going to make
these big meaty chickens
so that everybody has a lot
of chicken that they can eat,
but is there any downside to that?
- No. Honestly, no, I don't think so.
- Not for you. Great.
Is there anybody else?
- Money.
- Money how?
- They could cost more to (mumbles),
but they could cost less
and be more affordable,
which is what we want.
- Good. Money is a good issue, right?
People won't have to
think about money issues?
- I don't think there'd be a money issue
if you were cloning chickens,
because you can always
just get, you know, take
a syringe and, like...
- But that's what he was saying,
that maybe it'd be cheaper
if they could make it
without using as much stuff.
- Yeah.
- Mm-hmm.
- It would take longer.
- What do you guys think about
the cloning for body parts?
- Can I go back to the chickens
for a second?
- Sure, go for it.
- Wouldn't there be a lot less
farmers, so then there'd be
a lot less jobs because,
you know, like the whole...
- That is true.
- Like a lot of companies
will go out of business
because, I don't know,
I feel like there's like a monopoly on it,
- More private
industries are going to go
out of business, and that's
going to destroy livelihoods.
Because all the big livestock companies
like KFC and McDonald's...
well, they're not
a livestock company, they're fast food.
- But they're going to be selling it
to those (mumbles), right?
They're going to let it go off of...
- Just by show of hands, who
in here might have a problem
eating food if they knew that it had been
genetically messed around with?
- That's just because you
guys are okay with dying.
(several laughs)
- Chris, not sure, or
does it just kind of...
- I don't care, really.
(several voices)
- What was the question?
- Oh, I said would you
be bothered if you ate
genetically modified food?
- No, before that. The one
before Anthony started talking.
- We were trying to see
if there was any downside
of cloning chickens.
- We'll get there.
I know the question. We'll get there.
- I want to say something.
- We'll get there.
Alright. Erica.
Medical, the cloning the body parts, like
if people are sick and they
need a new heart, or new lungs,
or a new kidney.
- Ms. Scott, I wrote the name
of it. It's called Therapeutic Cloning.
They refer to it that way.
So, that's what it's called
when you do that.
- So when we're using it,
for cloning for the organs
for individuals who have
issues, whether it's,
like just a few cells, or
like nervous cells for people
who had spinal cord injuries...
what do you think about that?
- I think it's a good idea.
- It's a good idea?
Do you have any reasons
to be worried about that?
- (mumbles)
- It would be better than nothing?
Any concerns. Anybody else?
- Have you heard of of
a book called (mumbles)?
What was it called?
- (mumbles)
- I don't think I have. What's it about?
- That's okay.
(several laughs)
Levon is going to have to read it now,
because he'll be like, "What?"
- It's about, like, in
the future, will people,
if parents don't want their
kids any more, they can, like,
they can give them a
(mumbles), like they can take
their other body parts off
and... they can take their
other body parts off of them
and stuff, so they (mumbles)
like your body parts are
still alive, (mumbles)
so one arm could
be like your real arm,
and your other arm could be like (mumbles).
- Interesting. I'll have
to read that book sometime.
Now, when they're doing
the therapeutic cloning,
they're not actually creating,
like, a whole new human,
and then (mumbles, video
disruption) the body parts up.
There's a couple of different
ways they were doing it.
- (mumbles)
- Do you remember what
they were using to...
how they were growing the organs?
- (mumbles)
- That is true. But what
were they trying to do
with the cloning? How are
they trying to avoid that?
Do you remember? Does anybody remember?
How is cloning supposed to help your body
to keep from rejecting?
Because...
- Do you guys remember what happened
to the woman...
- Close. Very close to that.
(indistinct voices)
So, remember when you get a body organ,
like the lady with the kidney, right?
Who'd she get the kidney from?
- [Several Students] Her aunt.
- Yeah, so she got it from her aunt.
Somebody she was not even related to
that just happens to
be part of the family.
Like, they were a match.
She had to take... remember
all of those pills she had
to take? To make sure
her body doesn't, like,
get rid of the kidney.
And then, unfortunately, it still did?
So, they're looking at
getting, making kidneys,
and I think that they were
growing them inside of a cow.
I think it was a cow. Might have
been a pig. It was a big animal.
- So, you're going to grow human
kidneys that are functional?
- Mm hmm.
- On a cow?
They were using another
animal, and they were actually
growing it, like, not in
the animal. It wasn't part
of the animal. They were
using the animal as a place
to keep it growing and functioning.
- So on the outside of a
cow, there'd be kidneys.
- Underneath the skin. Yep.
And then they would take
take them out, and
transplant them into humans.
- This is like that episode
of South Park where...
it's a little bit
inappropriate, but not too much.
- Then let's not go there.
It's a little too inappropriate,
then let's not.
- Nevermind. Nevermind.
You're going to watch it for yourself.
- Fabulous. But they are
also trying, by cloning,
because remember a lot of
times they're trying to find
animal parts that might match.
Like for example, did you
know a pig heart is about
the same size as a human heart?
- So, you could have a pig heart?
- They were thinking
about taking pig hearts
and transplanting them into
people that needed new hearts.
The problem is, of course,
is it's a pig's heart,
which means the outside of the
heart looks like, pig cells.
So, your body would know
that it's not a human heart.
It would know that it's a pig heart.
And your body probably
won't want that in its body.
So, they were trying,
remember they had, trying
to grow new pigs?
I think they had little
piglets running around?
The pigs had human DNA in
there to make the outside
of their hearts and the outside
of their lungs, and kidneys
all kind of copy what a
human cell would look like
on the outside? So, that when
they keep those body parts,
if they put them in a human,
your body wouldn't recognize
it as being something different.
- (mumbles)
- Did you know they've
actually done that?
- My dad's friend's
daughter has pig intestines.