- All right. We've been talking about
listening and viewing. I have our chart to
help us out, and I wanna see if you can
tell me what effective and respectful
listening and viewing looks like. Matthew.
- Um, looking.
- Looking. Okay, so our eyes need to be...?
- [Together] Watching.
- Watching. Christopher.
- Hands.
- Oh, what do our hands need to be doing?
- Still.
- They need to be still. Matthew Pelkey.
- Mouth shut.
- Our mouth shut. Our lips are...
- Closed.
- Closed. Collin.
- Don't lay on the carpet. Don't be silly.
- That's right. So tell me. Help her out,
Jacob. Our feet what?
- Be quiet.
- Our feet need to be quiet. Maddie, can
you help me out with one more? We've done
eyes watching, lips closed, feet are
quiet. What do we need to do? Who can help
her out? Alice, I see your hand raised.
- Ears.
- Listening.
- Ears listening. And one more. Let me see
if-
- Hands to yourself.
- Adam.
- Keep your hands to yourself.
- Hands are still. Okay, so let's do our
checklist. We said eyes watching. Let me
see those beautiful eyes. I don't see
Layla's. I need you to turn your body.
Very good. Next, ears listening. Does
everyone have their ears listening? Next,
lips are...
- Closed.
- Unless I call on you, just like I did
with all of our helpers, hands are...
- Still.
- Still. So Catherine, I'll tie that shoe
in just a minute. You put your hands still
in your lap. Perfect.
And our feet are...
- Quiet.
- Oh, I love it. Are we ready to view our
video?
- Yes.
- Perfect. Okay. I want to be sure you can
see before we begin, because we're going
to turn out our lights. All right, what do
we want to find out? I want you to watch
for what type of weather you see. What are
we watching for?
- What type of weather.
- Weather. And what tools are the children
using to observe that weather? So the
second thing we need to watch for? Tools.
Listen and watch for the tools. And have
we had an experience like that? So let me
see those beautiful eyes. Let me see them.
Face forward. Lights helper. Where's my
lights helper?
- Claire.
- Claire, would you mind turning out our
lights? Okay. Do we know what we're
listening-
- Yeah.
- ...and watching for? Okay. Eyes
forward. I'm going to be seeing who's
doing their job. Ready.
- The wind is blowing my hair, but then
it's very strong today. We decided to blow
bubbles. They're blowing away. That's
Oliver blowing bubbles, too. Oh, Amy's
bubble just blew away. It was so windy,
the wind is making the bubbles.
- The wind's pushing out the bubbles, and
then the bubble comes out.
- We didn't even do anything. All we did
is hold up the bubble wand.
- Whoa.
- You can't see the wind, but you can see
what it's doing.
- That looks like fun.
- What are they doing?
- My dad gave us some old sheets to tear
up so we could make some streamers.
- Is he having fun?
- That's Oliver, and the streamer just
went in his face.
- What are they doing?
- Let's see what they're doing. Let's
watch.
- I was pretending the streamers were the
hair of this pig, because the little knot
is really shaped like a head, and the rest
of the stick is their body. And if they
have branches growing on them, that's to
me their hands and their legs, or
something.
- All right. It was very short. Well, did
you enjoy that?
- Yeah.
- I want to see that again.
- Good.
Go turn on our lights.
- Again.
- Now. Oh, we might watch it again later.
So let me see if you were listening and
viewing our video. I'm going to check by
answering these questions. Now, if you
know the answer, what are you going to do?
- Raise your hand.
- What weather did you see? Let me see
someone I haven't heard from. Emily, what
type of weather did we see?
- Blowing.
- It was blowing what?
- Bubbles.
- Wind.
- Wind. Blowing wind.
- What tools were the children using to
observe the weather?
- Bubbles!
- Bubbles. And what did they do?
- They ripped the paper.
- They ripped them, and they put them on
the stick. Have we had a similar
experience?
- Yeah.
- Yeah, for the bubbles.
- Yeah, let me see who's... let me see
who I haven't heard from. Clara, what did
we do?
- We blowed bubbles.
- We blew bubbles. Did we have to go like
this?
- No.
- Did we have to do that?
- What happened when we put it in the
bubble solution and put it up? What
happened?
- The wind blew it.
- The bubbles blowed out.
- All right. So now we're going to do a
think-
- [Together] Pair share.
- I want you to turn to your partner that
you talked to yesterday.
- Okay.
- I want you to share how you observed the
wind. We had a lot of windy weather
yesterday. Talk to your partner about
where you observed the wind.
Emily, she'll be right back. You be
thinking. Jacob, what did you see
yesterday?
- [inaudible]
- Wind. How did you see it?
- What did it blow?
- [inaudible]
- The trees? It blew the bubbles the other
day. Collin, what did you see?
- [inaudible]
- Perfect. I like that. You used the tools
we made in school. Marcus? Are you back?
All right, we just got through watching
our video, talking about our wind
observations. Now I want you to tell me
what effective speakers do. I'm going to
call on some people I haven't heard from
yet. Marshall, tell me one thing an
effective speaker does.
- Speaks slowly.
- Speaks slowly. All right, let's see what
else effective speakers do.
- They keep their eyes on the audience.
- Eyes on the audience, just like mine are
on you right now. Bronwen, show that
you're listening. Raven?
- [inaudible]
- Show your work. I want to see that
beautiful work. Who else has read? Who can
tell me another one? Who have I not heard
from today? Who have I not heard from
today?
- You haven't...
- Wesley. Wesley, what else should a good
speaker do?
- Volume up.
- Huh?
- Volume up. We want to hear what you have
to say. All right. Clara, tell me
something else.
- Be still.
- All right. Oh, you need to stand still.
Should you sway back and forth when you're
presenting your work?
- No.
- No. Okay.
- Have we covered it all?
- Yes.
- Let's see. Let's remind ourselves. Look
at your-
- [Together] Audience.
- Speak-
- [Together] Slowly.
- Stand-
- [Together] Still.
- Volume-
- [Together] Up.
- Show your-
- [Together] Work.
- Okay. Now remember, don't hold up your
thumbs up sign until I ask if that person
did these jobs. My first speaker is
Holland. Holland, will you please come up?
Okay. Okay, go ahead.
- I can see the wind blow a horse's..
- Huh? Horse's what?
- Tail.
- Okay.
Did Holland look at the audience when
she presented her work?
- Yes.
- What do you think?
- Good.
- Hold up those thumbs up signs. We want
to give her good feedback. Put your thumbs
up sign down. Thank you, Holland. My next
speaker is Alice. Alice. Thank you for
choosing a safe path. Come on. Good.
All right. Let's watch our speaker.
Remember.
- I can see the wind blow grass.
- All right. Did Alice speak slowly?
- Yes.
- Thumbs up sign. Awesome. Put your thumbs
up sign down. My next speaker. Yes, Fran.
What do you want?
- [inaudible]
- Wesley, please come up. Cathy, just look
through your window. I know we're close
today.
- I can see the wind blow the roofs.
- Did Wesley stand still?
- Yes.
Good job. All right. Thumbs up sign if
he, yeah, if he stood still. Good. Our
next speaker, Sofia. Sofia, come up.
Okay, let's start out like this. Loudly.
- I can see the wind blow
[inaudible].
- Did Sofia have her volume up?
- Yeah.
- She did a much better job. Let's give
her those thumbs up signs. Good job. Oh, I
don't see everyone's. Thank you, Adam.
Good. Thumbs up sign down. Matthew Bashir.
- I can...
- Oh, hold on. Are your friends listening
to you? Let me see if you're remembering,
if your eyes are watching and your ears
are listening. Christopher, we want to see
you look at the speaker. Turn your body
this way, please. Thank you.
- I can see the wind blow kites.
- Very good. Show your work. Oh, they've
already got those thumbs up signs.
Friends, do you believe that he showed his
work? Is he showing everyone? Good. Why,
thank you, Matthew.
- What does that say?
- Hmm?
- Why is the
[inaudible]?
- What is that? His kite is in the shape
of a...
- Star.
- Star. Isn't that beautiful? I love those
details. Catherine, your turn.
- I can...
- Oh, hold on one second. I'm sorry to
interrupt. Eyes forward. Eyes forward.
Good job.
- I can see the wind blow my star. I can
see the wind blow leaves.
- She wrote two sentences. Show your work.
Very good. Did Catherine look at her
audience when she presented her work?
- Yes.
- Good. Thumbs up signs. Christopher,
Romley, Emily, we want to see your eyes up
here. Thank you. Aiden. Aiden. All right,
Aiden, we're going to do a quick check.
May I please have this? It's okay.
Accidents do happen. I just didn't want
you to get hurt.
- What get hurt?
- Because you're holding it... we want
to be safe with our materials.
Criss-cross. Very good. Aiden, I love the
details in your picture.
- I can see the wind blow...
- Down.
- ...down the tree.
- Show your work. Nice. Oh, thumbs up
signs. He spoke very slowly.