- Let's go.
- Okay.
- (Teacher) Continue.
- Yes. All right scholars,
here's my question.
What do you think...actually, let me start
by quoting the passage.
So it says, they can
either trust or predict
what Chacko's attitude
would be, and they were
trying to hide that, get rid of it all,
before Chacko returned.
So, what do you think Chacko's opinion
of all of this chaos would be?
- Could you just be particular with...
the chaos you were talking
about? What's that?
- The entire situation,
the steamy love affair,
and the reaction on Baby Kochamma's part.
And Mammachi's part.
- Got it.
- I don't think he'd be happy
about the love affair,
cause as it says, it's like,
she had defiled generations of breeding
like the little blessed
one, blessed personally by
the Patriarch of...
- [Teacher] Antioch.
- Antioch, an imperial
entomologist, and Rhodes Scholar
from Oxford, so it's like
she had taken what their family
had worked for for so long, and just...
thrown it out the window.
- I'm gonna have to
disagree with that Becca,
I mean, I think that
Chacko is a liberal type.
He is very progressive, he's a Marxist,
he didn't allow his father
to beat his mother as
most Indians...Traditionalists,
probably would be OK with.
I think that Chacko would be
no more angry about the whole
affair than anybody would be if,
some guy was having an
affair with his sister.
As a social ideal, I think he
would be fine with everything.
- I agree because I feel
like, oh God I had this
whole plan of something to
say and I can't remember.
Sorry.
- No, it's not your fault.
- (Teacher) Well, what is the
only thing that made Chacko
upset at Mammachi?
- Was it that she abandoned her children?
Oh, I got it.
Yeah, I feel like the
most of this passage,
though it's third person narration,
it really feels like it's coming out of
Baby Kochamma's mouth, and it's like
her diction throughout all
of the italicized stuff.
The whole central paragraph
where it uses a lot of
dirty diction like mud and
filthy and coarse and black.
To quote the passage once again.
So, I feel like that all
really Baby Kochamma's words
and not necessarily Baba's beliefs,
and I feel like they have
really contrasted beliefs.
- (Teacher) Yeah, I mean I
feel like all the diction
you were talking about,
for instance, when it says,
"Mammachi's rage at the old
one-eyed Paravan standing
in the rain, drunk, dribbling
and covered in mud..."
And it repeats mud a
lot, and I think it's...
that's just kind of dirty and
the action is really impure
and they're trying... and almost
like mud covers things up.
So it's almost like it
should be covered up.
And they were trying to cover it up.
- But don't you feel like they
used Chacko not being there
and coming back as an excuse
to do everything they do.
Oh, he's coming back
so we have to do this.
They kind of use him
as the excuse to do it.
- Well, it's sort of like
Chacko could intervene,
and so we have to do it now
so we can't miss our
chance to do it again.
- I think that's important, actually.
I think that a theme of
unintended consequences
like it says here, "It wasn't
their fault when the whole
"thing spun like a deranged top."
I think the theme of
unintended consequences is
really crucial to both
the book and the movie.
In the movie, for example,
when Mahuditi says
she thinks she knows what
the consequences will be
if Kayani gets married, but
the unintended consequences
confound the defilement that she commits by
him being around.
- I think that's... this
book and movie is really
trying to say, is this is
what happens when you set
up rules and don't adapt
to social conditions
which are inevitably bound to change.
(laughter)
- I'll just go. (laughter)
In the fourth paragraph, they
talk about having a plan.
It's very orderly, and
they said that Kochu Maria
was a midget lieutenant.
They had this very
organized and planned out,
even though in the second paragraph,
"she shuddered with a
school-girl shudder."
It's like her childish
emotions are being turned into
or coming out through her adult form where
she has the power to do stuff.
- Yeah, on that I really
want to say cause it says,
"school-girl shudder" at the beginning.
And then it back in the fourth paragraph,
when it's talking about their plan,
they're referred to as,
"the two old ladies".
So that's contrasting in
a way to be described,
which obviously it's important.
- Yeah, I think that's one
of the themes of the passage.
Conflicts between age and
which one is ultimately...
I don't want to say better,
but a better advantage.
I guess.
- Like in authority?
- Between age and youth, you mean?
- Between old and young.
- Yeah, age and youth.
Which one
can have a better life according to them.
- They also play with age.
When they locked Ammu
up, it's kind of like
putting her in time out,
like they tricked her in to her room,
which is also a parallel
I saw in the movie
when they locked Kalyani up
so she couldn't get married.
It was to keep them from doing stuff.
- I just want to bring up
another theme of the passage.
Where it's the very
beginning where it's before
we are completely ruined
by the (inaudible).
It kind of presents this idea that
society is not built
on the basis of individual
needs, what you do.
In this society, at least,
affects everybody around you.
And it kind of contrasts
Ammu's individualism with
what societal hierarchy,
and how these two women
are higher on the hierarchy,
so they have authority over her,
and so they're telling her not to do this.
And they're presenting
their authority over her.
And Chacko's even higher than them,
just cause he's a guy.
- When the passage lists
the life cycle events,
the weddings, the funerals, baptisms,
and birthday parties, it
says for generations to come,
so I feel like what Peter was saying,
it affects all of society.
That also ties in with the
age because the weddings
are for younger people.
The funerals are when you die.
The baptisms are when you are just born.
So it's saying it will affect everybody
at all parts of their life,
that's how profound it is.
- And even
that sentence that Peter
was talking about, before
it goes any further.
Before we are completely ruined,
I think that's also
just family selfishness
because they're just
projecting what her...
the consequences of her
actions will be for them.
Not necessarily for her.
And in the movie, where
the leader of that house
of she's just really
concerned about herself.
She'll sacrifice all of the other women
just so she's comfortable.
- But does she also use a we.
I think both Baby Kochamma and Diti
say the same thing.
We're gonna be ruined by this.
We we we.
(laughter)
- In regards to that, I think...
In water, you know how all the widows
they sorta put them together, and they
sort of create this unity.
It's all out of despair because
they all lost something.
In a sense, Mammachi lost her former love,
and so did Ammu.
Ammu had babies without...
It wasn't a formal tradition.
The way she had her babies.
And so in a sense, she has...
She's in grievance,
and so those two aspects
unites these women.
- Yeah, they're all widows.
and that really...
- But does that give them right to be...
- Oh understand, that's why
I feel like it says, "we".
Not "we", like our
family, but more of like,
"we" women who are widowed.
- (Teacher) Austin, what do you think?
Do you think that gives
them the right to...
because they've also lost and because
Baby Kochamma and Mammachi
has also experienced
trauma, so that also means Diti, as well.
Her husband died when she was young.
Does that give them the
right to take that...?
- I don't think so,
cause that was actually
one of my questions.
Especially when it says,
"Her tolerance immense
needs, as far as her son
"was concerned became the fuel for
"unimaginable fury at her daughter".
And then just my question was,
is Baby Kochamma's actions motivated by
Indian society or her own emotions?
So I don't think that
they should be able to
from their past experience...
take it out on everybody else.
- I think that what we're
talking about right now,
maybe be reason that Ghandi
appears at the end of the film.
Because Ghandi, as he is
portrayed in water is a symbol
of rationalism.
And it's... when he shows up,
nice Diti sees that (inaudible)
may have a refuge from
cycles of hatred and
of tradition conceived
for the purpose of
basically personal gain.
Ghandi's existence in the movie is
indictments of almost every
action taken in this passage
by the scheming old women.
- I think that Ghandi, in
the movie, represents more
of rebirth because they talk about how
much society will change
once Ghandi takes power.
The widows will gain power.
The untouchables won't
be untouchable anymore.
They'll gain more rights.
So I think they look at him
as, not really rationalism,
because some people think
that he's just crazy.
The Brahmin caste
don't see him as rational,
so I think it's more of a
hope in an idealized society.
- Building off of what she said,
how Ghandi represents re-birth,
I think coincides with
the movie's title, "Water".
For me, at least, the way I saw it.
I felt like water was
rebirth throughout the movie.
They washed themselves... it
was washing away their sins.
Being reborn. I thought who's the girl?
The one who killed herself.
- Kalyani
- I thought that it was
symbolic when she drown herself.
Because the way she was killing herself,
she was submersing herself in water,
and I thought since
water was clearing away
your sins and stuff, she in a sense,
she was clearing away her sins.
And so she would go to
the next life sinless.
- I think that the drowning
of Kalyani parallels to how
Sophie Mol drowned.
How it's like the innocent life
was taken by the water.
Which isn't really... innocence, too.
- But was Kalyani innocent?
- I think that if she hadn't
been forced to do things
she would have been...
she didn't feel right
about what she had done.
- I'm gonna take the
opposite view point to
the water that symbols of
inescapability in the movie
because of the way... in
both the movie and the book.
It says the fisherman had
already found Sophie Mol.
She...
They drowned trying to cross the river,
and Kalyani loses everything
when she crosses the river
and realizes who Norian really is.
The river is important in both works.
It's an inescapable wall.
So I don't think water is
portrayed as a good image.
- I mean, it could possibly be both.
I think Peter made a
pretty good point about it.
Sam did with Kalyani's death
and Sophie Mol's death.
But I think it could be both.
- I think it's a duality thing.
And then going on combining
what both ya'll said,
where you said it's an inescapably,
and the way they view it
as washing away their sins.
View it as a cleansing
thing also, for example,
emphasizes the irrationality
of all their beliefs.
And they're cleaning themself in this...
if water is just viewed a symbol,
they're cleaning themselves
with something that's bad.
I also don't think that...
- They depend on the water, too,
to get their food from it.
They wash themselves in it.
Yet, it's also... it creates
this... it's something that
the Paravans are trying to overcome.
A lot of people are trying
to overcome this barrier,
but they depend on it.
They still need it.
So it's contrasting what they believe...
- Just like a duality thing.
- Yeah.
- It's the family and God's talkings.
Their immediate family.
They depend on each other
because when you're a child,
you have to have an older
figure to help you grow up.
But, they are also...
They cause the turmoil with each other.
They create their own
problems, pretty much.
- It's like you can't live with them,
but you can't live without them.
- (Teacher) Susan, did
you have a question?
- (Susan) Yes, I did.
Well, a lot of them are about similarities
between characters.
But one thing that I thought about was how
Norian dealt with his lover's loss,
and how Velutha was able to
deal with being separated from...
Ammu.
And do you think that
their status influenced
how they were able to
deal with the situations?
- Sorry, I missed all this.
(laughter)
- So she
- (boy student) I heard
- Well, Norian, because he was a Brahmin,
the highest caste,
I think he said we'll either
going to Calcutta or India,
?
to start his life.
- You mean Kolkata?
- Or, I'm sorry, or England.
To become a lawyer.
So he had the option of completely
starting his life over
wherever he wanted to go
because he had education,
and he could provide for himself.
Velutha was an untouchable,
so he had no opportunity.