- ...confusing for people to understand,
but we're looking at density today.
We're looking at how much stuff
is packed in a certain area.
So, if you flip over to
the back of your paper,
you've got that little box at the top.
And it tells you one of the reasons
some of the objects float
while the other objects sank
is because of their density.
If you could write down
the definition of density
in your box, I would appreciate that.
The amount of matter, when I say stuff,
like when we were learning about
solids, liquids and gases at
the beginning of the year,
stuff is matter.
So the amount of matter
that's in a certain area
is an object's density.
It's not its mass, it's its density.
So the marble is more dense
than the Styrofoam ball.
Okay?
So now that we know the word 'density,'
we're going to start using the word 'density'
for the next part.
(Classroom chatter)
The amount of stuff
packed in a certain area,
or the amount of matter.
The marble had more
matter in that small area
than the Styrofoam ball.
The Styrofoam ball is spread out
and have all those air holes,
making that matter more
spread out, less dense.
Krayla?
(Student asking question)
Yes, right now.
Okay? All right.
So that was simple.