- I have a dream that my four children
will one day live in a nation where they
will not be judged by the color of their
skin, but by the content of their
character. I have a dream that one day the
state of Alabama will--
- Will be.
- Will be transformed into a situation
where little black boys and black girls
will be able to join hands with little
white boys and white girls
as sisters and brothers.
- My dad and I have that dream too.
- When we let freedom ring, we will let it
rumble. We will let it ring from every
village and every hamlet and every state
in every city. We will be able to see that
day when all of God's children, black men
and white men, Jews and Gentiles,
Protestants and Catholics will join hands
and sing the words of the old Negro
spirit, "Free at last. Free at last. Thank
God almighty. We are free at last."
- Dad, when I listen to Reverend King, I
know that he's right.
I know that things are going to change.
- I think you're right.
- Act IV--It is now spring of 1963. The
speech of Reverend King has continued to
lead people and speak out their
[inaudible].
He has met with another president, Lyndon
B. Johnson,
and has seen changes sweep
across the country.
- May, Billy, please come in here.
I have some news.
- What is it Mom?
- Reverend King is dead. He was shot in
Memphis, Tennessee.
- No, Mom. That's not fair. He was
helping all of us.
- I agree, Billy. It isn't fair. But
remember, Reverend King lives on in us.
Every time we remember the words, every
time we speak out against things that are
unfair, we are giving remembrance.
- Okay? So, go find the people that had
your card and have your conversations, get
your feedback about how you did.
- Miss Walters, I got all three too.
- Great. Great.
- Did you see me? I had nine points.
- You were a good listener.
- Very good. Great feedback.