- (student) ...so you can't
count it out completely.
- (Teacher) Hmm. So we have
three things going on here.
I hear exponential decay,
I hear an upside-down parabola,
and I hear a negative-sloping line.
Red, why don't you chime in?
I haven't heard from you.
Are you going with decay?
Are you going with decreasing line?
You going with upside-down parabola?
What had you guys decided?
- We were going to go with decay but...
- (Teacher) You were going
to go with decay, okay
- But, I changed my mind because
decay, it keeps decreasing all the way.
But MySpace, it got to a point
where it stopped decreasing...
and it was (inaudible) like what Rosetta said.
- (Teacher) So it stopped decreasing,
which is what you're
saying, and you're saying
that's in agreement with Rosetta.
I have a serious issue
with a line stopping.
Can somebody talk to me about that?
I have a serious issue
with a line stopping
or having some kind of decrease
that then slows itself.
- It's the end of the line.
Slows itself. Colin, I
haven't heard from you.
- I don't think it's linear
because the linear is going to
signify that at one point
there are going to be
no users or people on MySpace.
I agree with Elsie that it
might be decay because
it decreased, but
decay doesn't ever touch the X-axis,
which would signify there are no users.
- (Teacher) Ah!
- And there will always be users.
- (Teacher) Oooh, what's
somebody thing about that?
Really, really, really
significant comment that
was just made by Colin. What do we think?
The fact that it's never going
to... how did you say it?
- I said that the linear
was going to, at one point,
to hit zero, and
with decay it's never going to hit zero.
It's going to get really
close but not touch it.
- (Teacher) Jeffrey.
- I agree with Colin.
Because if it was a negative line, like
a negative line, right?
You're going to go past
zero, and you can't have
a negative amount of users,
'cause a line keeps on going forever.
- (Teacher) Ok, does
exponential keep going forever?
- No. I mean yes! Yes, it does, but
because it's so small that
it never touches the X-axis,
but it keeps on going so
it just never hits zero.
- (Teacher) So, if we all agree,
are we getting closer
to agreeing that it's
exponential decay?
- (female student) Yes.
- (Teacher) If we are agreeing
it's exponential decay,
then what Jeffrey just said...
what does that mean for
MySpace the company?
Will it go out of business?
- (several students) no...
- (Teacher) Based on what
Jeffrey just said about
an exponential decay, at the end.
What does that mean for
MySpace the company?
What do you know about MySpace
the company at this moment?
- It's still low.
- It's still low, but is it in existence?
- (several students) Yes
- It is. Do you know what's keeping it
You know?
- I think because you're
always going to have
that one user account
(laughter)
- (Teacher) Ok, you might, you
might always have that one user.
There's something, though,
that MySpace provides
that other websites don't,
that's very easy to do
that other sites don't have.
And this is what's keeping it
from touching that X-axis.
Do you know what it is?
Alicia? Talk to us, I can't hear you.
- Music?
- (Teacher) Yes, Alicia,
who is in the band,
would obviously know this, right?
Tell them what you do on MySpace, Alicia.
- Bands can make pages and they can
upload their songs and
you can listen to them.
- (Teacher) Yeah, you
can upload your music
on MySpace easier than
any of the other sites.
Very good, thank you for chiming in.
Alright, let's shift gears from MySpace,
now let's talk Twitter.
Twitter, Twitter, Twitter.
What do you think about
the growth of Twitter?
(background chatter)
- Alright, keywords. Red,
start me off with keywords
and then we'll bounce to
Pink and around the room.
(clears throat)
Give them your attention,
ladies and gentlemen.
Are you guys prepared
and ready for Twitter?
- Rush
- (Teacher) I'm sorry, rush?
(inaudible)
Where, show me?
- It's missing...something there
- (Teacher) What's your keyword?
- Rush
- It's in the middle of the sentence.
- (Teacher) In the third sentence.
Oh, rush, is that what you said?
Ok, just speak up, I'm
getting old, I can't hear.
- Growth continues steadily.
- (Teacher) Okay... anything else?
- Yeah, but it's at the tweets.
- (Teacher) This, the tweeted?
- Yeah.
- (Teacher) It goes with this. Okay.
So what do you guys pick for the growth?
What function models Twitter's growth?
- Exponential growth.
- (Teacher) You think it's
exponential growth, as well?
Alright, is there a team? Pink, you're up.
- I disagree with that.
I think it's linear because it says that
another keyword that they've given
is with 40 million in May, that
whole sentence right there.
- (Teacher) Got it.
- That's like a slope,
if you think about it.
With 40 million in May, 2009,
6 months later 60 million,
and then 80 million in May 2010.
The slope, it would be 20 million.
So it's linear. It's going positive slope.
(inaudible)
- (Teacher) Hmm...
filling out those listening labs?
Pink just gave some hard core evidence.
Red, do you have a comeback?
Or have they won you over?
You have a comeback.
Let's hear it, Lenny,
what's your comeback?
- This can not be because
(laughter)
because it's going to get to a
point where it's going to stop.
It's not like we're going to take it like
100, 100, 200, and so on
- (pink) Do you have a time machine?
(laughter)
- (Teacher) Ok, so let's leave...
Lenny, I think exponential
growth isn't going to stop
and I think a line isn't
going to stop, right?
And I think that, if we
think about the future...
I think that's what Star is maybe
trying to do, is predict the future.
We don't really know. But
from the language here
in your text, the information you do know,
I think 40 million then
60 million then 80 million
is pretty concrete evidence of slope.
Do you agree?
- yes
- (Teacher) Yes? Anybody else
want to chime in on this one
that I haven't heard from?
Maybe from...
Elianna on Blue?
Bleaker, I haven't heard from you.
Carlia yet? What do you guys think?
How 'bout anything you
want to add about Twitter?
Anything you want to add?
Greg, go ahead.
- Well what Lenny was
saying, I cannot beat
and I agree with them. That's it.
- (Teacher) Ok, thank you!
Any...?
- I agree with Star because
as you mentioned (inaudible) what this does
or hope is that they'll be able
to Tweet via text messages.
And that's something that
Facebook didn't offer.
So the more things that...
the more things that
Twitter puts out there
the other social networks
is going to increase.
- Ok, so as Twitter grows, you're saying
the other networks might be slowed?
Who though, is going to outperform it
if it's a different type of graph?
Who is going to outperform
Twitter for sure,
if Twitter is linear and the other one is
a certain other graph we mentioned?
(inaudible)
Facebook, right? Because Facebook is what?
- Exponential
- (Teacher) Exponential. Very good.
Ok! So let's go now to AIM.
We're doing very well on time here.
AIM. Who's going to start us off with AIM?
Alright, Pink, you can start us off.
(background chatter)
Keywords and reasoning, talk to me.
- Some key words we worked was
AOL lost their dominance.
- (Teacher) Lost their dominance. Okay?
Yep?
- And then we put continuous
fielding is growth today.
- (Teacher) Okay.
- And we said that it was
quadratic equations, because
at one point it was really high,
but then as time went by,
it started decreasing,
but then it started
getting more popular again.
Lately, teenagers liked using it,
so it started going up again.
- (Teacher) Ok. Is there
another keyword up here
that would help anybody?
I think there's at least one more keyword
that I haven't seen pointed up. Elianna?
- Is it comeback?
- Comeback? Where's comeback?
(inaudible)
Beautiful. Made a comeback and maybe even
one more thing a little
earlier. Jermaine? Thank you.
Sorry, say that again?
- Dominated
- (Teacher) Dominated,
very nice, Jermaine.
So it started out dominating,
then had to make a comeback.
Does anybody want to
add on to what Pink said
about this being quadratic?
- Which way?
- (Teacher) Which way?
- Would make it positive from earlier?
- (Teacher) Positive what? Talk
to me about the equation now.
- Quadratic is always going to...
- (Teacher) Do quadratics always go up?
- (student chatter) no,
go down too, parabolic
- (Teacher) This parabola?
They always look like this?
- no
- (Teacher) Think about inverses
we learned through this year.
Raise your hand and let me
know what you want to say.
Talk to me. Do parabolas
always open upwards?
Go ahead.
- (male student) I just
want to agree with them
- (Teacher) You agree
that it's a parabola?
- Yeah, because in a parabola...
it says that it started
off dominating, but
you're on top if you're dominating.
Then it said that it made a comeback.
That means at one point it
would have to be decreasing
and then to make a
comeback they come back,
they come back up.
- (Teacher) Beautiful. Wanna add to that?
Go ahead.
- I was just going to say
the other end (inaudible)
- Alright, so I just want
to make sure I answered
Purple's question in the back.
You asked which way? Take a look at this.
This is what you're talking about.
Could the parabola be like this?
(background chatter)
What would this mean if
the parabola were down
for the company?
- If it was down, then that
means it's imaginary. Right?
- (Teacher) You're thinking
of something about imaginary
and it's not if it's down.
That has to do with a negative.
Right, if there's a
negative A coefficient.
Something else, though.
What would this mean
for the company's trend?
DeShawn?
Go ahead, DeShawn
- They would have had
a spiral at the bottom
and then they would lift up
- (Teacher) And come back down.
Purple, are you alright with that now?
You understand? This would not have worked
based on what DeShawn just said.
Here's my question for you on AOL.
Why isn't AOL an absolute value graph?
What starts high, comes
down, and goes back up?
We did do absolute value functions, right?
Turn and talk first, and
then you're going to tell me.
Write that question down somewhere.
I want to know why it's not
an absolute value graph.
(background chatter)
- Oh, yeah, we did talk
about these today (inaudible)
(background chatter)
- if every five minutes
they add ten members
but every five minutes
you're getting ten members
then every five minutes
you're gonna lose ten members
so parabola is not possible
(inaudible)
(background chatter)
- (Teacher) Ok, guys...
Bring it back.
I want to know why isn't...
Why didn't anybody say absolute value?
I'm going to maybe put one over here,
and then I have one more
really important question
about these graphs for you,
and then we're in good shape.
Absolute value... the reason
I asked that is because
that also starts high, comes down low
and goes back up. I need some reasoning.
Let's change it around, start
with Gold and go around. Go.
- I don't think it's
an absolute value graph
even though it kind of follows
the same kind of trend.
Because in the absolute value, it's
Y is equal to absolute
value of X, meaning that
as time passed, they would
be losing and gaining
a constant amount of people.
So like, if you gained ten
members every five minutes,
every five minutes you
would be gaining ten members
no matter what. Every five minutes, or
when it goes down, every five minutes
you'd be losing ten members.
Whereas a parabola that
changes is not constant,
you can lose and gain
power then they'd be equal
to join or don't join
and you can't guarantee
that you're going to gain
that amount of members
every time that amount of time passed.
- (Teacher) So would it be
fair to say it's too con-