- [Instructor] And then with Carl's
example was down to MSB, marginal social
benefit. So how can we put that into
words? Marginal social benefit. Andrew?
- [Andrew] Isn't it something that can't
really be measured?
- Okay. Yes, and it's harder to measure,
but how would you explain it? What is it?
Think about what we did in the example and
say like, everybody is benefiting from
washing cars. Right?
- [Student] So, what is... It is a social
benefit and it's what he gets from the
society.
- It's what society gets from you.
- Yeah, you're on the track, but it's what
we get from his interaction. Right? Okay.
So, it's the benefit to society for
whatever market that is. Okay? So, social
benefit, this is going to be the
additional benefit, okay? The additional
benefit that society... those that are not
involved in the transaction, but from
society get from one more unit. Okay? Now,
I'm going to put next to this slash costs.
Oh, just kidding. That's... that's the
other document. So, down here is just
something is a negative thing. So what
this leads to... Do you think these two
definitions lead to positive externality
or negative externality?
- [Students together] Positive
Positive, they're things that market itself does
not take care of. Okay? Market, obviously, in this
example, does not take Carl and offer YTB
for all of our benefits, considering it
doesn't pay him at all. Right? There are
things in society that, when you look at
the actual amount someone is paid, they're
maybe not paid to the extent of the
benefit they get. Okay? So, right now if
you flip over to the back, we'll come back
to definitions later, flip over to the
back. Oh, I'm sorry, on the other sheet,
because I didn't put it on the back, on
the other sheet you have two columns. I
want you first, by yourselves, without
talking to someone else, think of, try to
think of at least two examples where there
are things in society where there are
markets for these and it makes everyone
better off because they're there, and we
all benefit from them. Okay? Go ahead,
write them down. Think about it. You
really think, you're going to have to
defend it. So, think about, on your own,
what markets are out there, things that
happen, that benefit everybody, not just
the people participating in the market.
So, benefits more people than are just
paying for the service, not just the
buyers or the sellers of that service, but
outside of it, people are benefiting from
it. Write and think and then we'll talk
about them. Write and think, write and
think.
- [Student] Wait, do we need negative
ones, too?
- Just positive right now, we're going to
go back to the negative ones. So, just
think of the positive ones right now.
Okay, benefit people, again, let's cover
the definition again. Benefit people
outside of the buyers and sellers in that
transaction. Okay? So, we're not talking
about just the buyer of someone who goes
to a store and buys something and the
benefit they get from it, that's marginal
benefit, but that person buying this gives
other people benefit outside of that
person.
- [Student] But, like if they built a
hospital in the neighborhood, and it has a
reputation of being not like, they don't
have a lot of equipment, it's not very
good. Then, could you like, the property
values of the of the town go down.
- So, you could talk about... Okay. So,
you're on absolutely the right track, so
then that would be a negative.
- [Student] Like, so what could always be
a positive benefit?
- Okay. Well, let's talk about some of the
negatives. Some of you wrote some stuff
down. I saw Matt right away think of
something, what'd you write down?
- [Matt] I said flu shots.
- Okay. Why?
- Because the more healthy people there
are around the less you'll... I don't
know. The less sick people there are, the
more healthy people there are.
- Overall, right? Because, if one
of you... Think about this. If one of
us... If half of the class gets flu shots
and the other half doesn't that mentality
shows us that now that other half is more
likely to get the flu, right? So, that is
an absolutely... Flu shots. What could you
make that into a broader explanation.
- [Students together] Vaccinations.
- Vaccinations. Okay? Vaccinations. So, go
ahead and write those two down because
those two are textbook examples.
- [Student] Is medicine good?
- Medicine... It depends if it's
contagious, but go ahead and be more
specific, so you want to put flu vaccine
or any kind of vaccine. It's a perfect
example because that is a big issue right
now. A lot of parents are talking about
not vaccinating their children because
they're worried about issues of autism
that have been indirectly, slightly
connected to it, but, for the most part,
that has not been proven yet, so now we're
seeing other ramifications of that
decision. Over here, go ahead
- Pro sports.
- Pro sports, tell me why.
- People who play get paid for doing it
and the fans enjoy watching them.
- Okay, good. So, pro sports, and we're
not even talking about people that
necessarily pay for the ticket to go. You
might just get to watch on TV. A lot of
times on the main stations, you don't even
have to pay cable lines. So, you would go
ahead and benefit from those.
- [Student] If you pay, aren't you
technically then part of that?
- If you paid for it then you're part of
that market.
- [Student] So, like vaccinations. You pay
for vaccine.
- Okay. But that person that pays for the
vaccination doesn't get it, but all of us
benefit because that one student got the
vaccine. Okay? So, that's the key. It
benefits people outside of the one paying
for it. So, that's why it's social. Okay?
Sam?
- [Sam] YouTube.
- Okay. Tell me why.
- Because people can freely put up any
type of videos they want. That uses
creativity and people that want to hear
music from anywhere can do it wherever
they want.
- Absolutely. So, YouTube is a great
modern example, because we all benefit
from that kind of laughter, that
enjoyment. It doesn't cost us anything.
People do it for their own interest and we
all benefit. Cody.
- [Cody] Education.
- Education. Tell me why.
- Students learn and they get to do well
in the world and then the world gets some
technology.
- Okay. Good. Like, you brought up tax
payers. So, your parents pay for your
education in school. Right? But, by the
fact that you're becoming educated, even
if they pay for your college tuition. Now,
you don't give back just to your parents
with that education, you give back to
society overall. Right? To everyone,
hopefully, in the world, one way or
another, you end up giving back to
society. For more people than are paying
for your education. Okay. Yeah?
- [Student] Clean energy, like electric
cars or something, because even if you
yourself don't drive one, that makes like,
it improves.
- Okay. Anything green. Absolutely.
Anything green like that. You can put
green technologies benefit the world,
which kind of brings us to one that we're
going to talk about with a negative. Okay.
Yeah.
- [Student] I just had a question. Could
you put stock, like since if someone buys
a stock it raises the price for everyone
else?
- Yeah, I've never heard that example, but
you could argue that. It's still
benefiting a select group, though. I guess
in some stocks though, that's millions and
millions of people, so, I mean, you might
be able to argue.
- [Student] I didn't know, because they're
still involved in the transaction.
- They're only involved if it's their
initial one. So, that's why I think it's
worth some argument there. You might be
able to prove that. I think some of the
other ones across the board are a little
bit more general but that's definitely
something to think about. Andrew?
- [Andrew] Well see, I agree with him,
because when the stock prices go up people
see that as "Oh, the public is spending
more," so that would bring the economy
up, which would bring--
- That's a really good point because
that's an indicator of the health of the
economy.
- Right.
- So, by the stock market being high, it
makes everyone employ people. Yeah, that's
a good extra point to add in. Yeah.
- [Student] What about something like... sorry
[Background Chatter]
- [Instructor] You were thinking of the same
thing at the same time? Alright, go ahead.
- [Student] So, like, taxpayers, and the
government pays them and even if you don't
pay taxes you still benefit from it.
- You could actually put public works down
in your column, because now that we've
kind of opened that can, we can think
about parks, right? And I get the example
all the time. There's a really nice park I
live right by Glenn Ellen, and I am not
technically in Glenn Ellen but right by
there, then I go down there, I run by the
park, I take advantage of that public
area, and I add to my benefit. So, just by
having that park, it kind of benefits more
people than just the people that pay for
it. So, any public works. Police, you
could talk about firemen, they benefit
many more people than the people that pay
for them.
- [Student] The people that clear the snow
off the roads. Delightful.
- [Instructor] Can I get some negative
externalities then? Flip it back over.
Let's go right on. Flip it to the other
sheet and let's go to the other thing here
and then we'll start graphing it. Marginal
costs. Let's put that in our own words
here. What is the marginal cost of these?
Everyone think about it for a second.
Think about it, write down your own
definition. This is something you should
know like the back of your hand at this
point. In your own words, write down the
definition of marginal costs.  Write it down,
you already did? ...Marginal cost...
You got it Andrew?
What is marginal cost?
- [Student] The extra cost of hiring one
additional worker.
- Okay. One more whatever it is. It
doesn't have to be a worker. We're all
thinking about workers because we just got
out of inputs, we just got out of inputs
and factor markets and resource markets,
but, remember those units one, two and
three, they had marginal cost, too. If you
picture a monopoly graph, what does
marginal cost look like on a monopoly
graph?
- [Student] Upward sloping.
- Upward sloping, right? So, we can think
of the system in every unit. So, what does
it need? One, the additional cost of what?
- [Students together] One more unit.
- One more unit. Let's just keep it like
that, because input is just factors. One
more unit, because in a monopoly, it's
marginal cost of making one more unit. In
a labor market, it's the additional cost
of one more worker. Keep in mind again,
these are both people that are
participating in that market. So, I'm
going to put... This is the same thing,
except for it's the cost. So, you wrote it
ready in your own words but make sure
you've got that basic idea. Additional
cost of one more unit. So, now we're
applying it to this new idea. What's the
marginal social cost of something? The
marginal social cost. Andrew?
- [Andrew] How much society loses for one
more unit.
- Okay. How much society loses for one
more unit or how much it takes away, or
cost us when we make one more unit. So,
we're going to think, and I'm going to add
thoughts here. It's for all of society.
So, flip it over, what are some examples,
or go to the other sheet. What are some
examples of negative externalities now
that we've got this down in your mind.
What are some negatives? Zach.
- [Zach] Breathing in pollution.
- Pollution. That again, he is on it, this
is the textbook definition. Pollution is
the most common example. So, what has
government implemented to try to curtail
pollution? What kind of things have they
done?
- [Student] Smoking ban laws.
- Okay, good, smoking bans. So, you could
say pollution, you could also say
cigarette smoke is a negative externality.
So, government stepped in, which is the
type of pollution. The government stepped
in and said "No, you cannot smoke in
places of employment, you cannot smoke in
any public area in Illinois, " it's
obviously done by state, but the state has
stepped in to curtail this type of
externality. Betty?
- [Betty] Don't they have pollution rights
that they can buy in the market?
- Okay. Very good. Who do they buy them
from?
- The government.
- Good. So, federal government actually
sells pollution rights. So, that's another
way that they deal with it. What agency
was created to deal with pollution?
- [Student] The EPA.
- EPA. So, the EPA is out there trying to
make sure that only so much pollution
happens. Yeah.
- [Student] This is kind of more local,
but like banks in Elmhurst, like they make
a lot of banks, a ton of banks, but every
single time they make a new one it seems
like less use of all the banks like
there's no point to them and it's like a
lot of--
- So, you're saying that's a negative
externality because there's too much?
- [Student] Not just that there's just
like... Say you replace a store that maybe
some people use and make a bank and then
there's less to do in Elmhurst.
- Okay. Try to think of the best way... I
mean, I see what you're saying because
that transaction takes away from your
enjoyment of living in a town.
- [Student] You could put something else
there like a new house or a restaurant or
something, just don't put a bank.
[Background Chatter]
- Okay. So, how would the government fix
that?
- [Student] ...They could be like "We're not
going to let you buy it." The bank buy
that lot, they could have said no.
- So, they might limit, they might say how
many of these business could be. That's a
new one. I've never heard of that, but
obviously there's something there to that
because you're saying it's taking away
from the enjoyment of people in the
community. It is maybe adding to the
wealth of the community with the
employment and the income that's being
raised, but overall... True, no. I think
you've got something there but it's a
different lens. Andrew?
- I think that a better example for that
would be parking lots because then it's
just there and not doing anything, whereas
for a bank it increases the competition
and it increases the rate of...
[Background Chatter].
- [Student] The parking garage closer to
the Y encourages people to go down to the
retail area of Elmhurst and it kind of
does encourage people to...
[Background Chatter]
- All right. I like what you guys are
going with this, either one of you could
make an argument with it. That kind of
brings up another point, though. This is
somewhat of, Alex, are you with me? This
is somewhat of a, this is somewhat of an
opinion, right? Because, now you're saying
that there's certain things, that there's
definite, and those are going to be our
perfect examples like pollution. No one in
their right mind can argue that pollution
gives a benefit to society. They can argue
that what they produce that produces
pollution is helping industrialize, I
mean, talk to China. One example. Their
massive pollution, few regulations at all
because they're trying to compete with
other countries and step up, but they're
not, they definitely would say it's worth
it. But pollution itself, no one can say
that it's good. Andrew mentioned something
about the beauty of something. What are
some things that people buy or do--