- Look at your station
one information.
And the question we
posed in station one
was does temperature affect the rate
of chemical weather.
And yesterday, you guys
constructed a graph
to show that data.
Why is it useful to construct
a graph in science class?
Sky?
- Because it's a visual way
to show you information.
- It's a visual way to show
you information.
I have a case up here as an example.
Based on that graph, what does
that pattern reveal
about our question?
Gabrielle.
- The cooler the temperature
the more the, I mean,
more increases in time.
- The more what increases in time?
- The more uh
weather.
- Okay, anybody want to restate
that, Rebecca?
- The colder it is,
the more time it
takes to weather.
- Very good.
The colder it is, the more
time it takes to weather.
If we're talking about
dissolving a tablet,
is that chemical weathering
or mechanical weathering?
Logan?
- Chemical weathering.
So the colder it is,
the longer it takes
for the chemical weathering to occur.
Would you agree?
Thumbs up or thumbs down.
Thumbs up, I would agree.
Now I want to talk about, so what?
Why does it matter to us.
Why does it matter
in our daily lives.
Talk about it for one minute,
record your thoughts
on your wipe board,
and be ready to share back.
[Background Chatter]
- We could consider
where to build our stuff...
- In what types of areas
would you have to
be specifically and particularly hot?
What about up north?
You've got 30 seconds to
finish writing your thoughts.
[Background Chatter]
- Okay, it might dissolve
faster in a warmer place.
Or, what type of rock
would I want to avoid?
Limestone, why?
[Background Chatter]
- Okay, very good, very good.
Alright, let's share some of
our ideas with the class.
Info managers, table three,
what did you find?
- If you live in a cold environment,
there will be less chemical weathering,
than there is in a warm place.
- Good point, if you live in a
cooler environment,
there will be less
chemical weathering
than in a warm climate.
Who's gonna be particularly
concerned with this?
What, for instance,
job field is gonna be
concerned with this idea?
Forrest?
- Construction?
- That would be one area, what else?
- Statue building?
- Yeah, any kind of artist
who's designing statues.
What type of rock would
you want to avoid
if you're living in a warm area?
And you know that chemical weathering
could be a problem.
What rock would you avoid?
Patrick?
- Limestone.
Do you guys have some proof for me?
Somewhere in your data as to why we
should avoid limestone?
Which station, Alex?
- Station three.
- Flip to station three for me.
At station three, who can explain to me
what the lab was that you did?
Someone I haven't heard from, Colin?
- We put one small piece of chalk into
a bottle of vinegar and
a small piece of chalk
into water, and we saw
if the acid from the vinegar
dissolved the chalk and if
the water dissolved the chalk.
And the chalk didn't
dissolve in the water,
but the acid made it fizz, bubble,
and it was just dissolving.
- And why did we use chalk?
What is chalk a type of?
What is chalk a type of, Jeremy?
- It's a type of limestone.
So your evidence showed that yes,
limestone weathers quickly with acid.
Why is acid a part of our environment?
How does it become part
of our environment?
Andrea?
- Acid rain.
- Acid rain, acid rain.
Now, as we grow up it's important that
you're environmental advocates.
That you fight for
protecting our environment.
What types of things can you do
in your lives to cut down on acid rain?
Give me two ideas on your wipe boards.
Two ideas.
[Background Chatter]
- Is that polluting our water, our air?
- Polluting the air, and it's getting
into our clouds...
- Very nice, very good.
So air pollution particularly because
the air pollution contributes
to that formation.
- You are making worst case scenarios.
You don't have to consider the unthinkable.
- It can happen, alright?
- You don't have to consider the impossible.
- So we can unplug outlets when we're
not using them.
- We can turn off the water when
we brush our teeth.
[Background Chatter]
- What about things in your house?
Electricity.
Cut down on your electric bills.
Remember you burn fossil fuels,
to make electricity.
So right now as middle schoolers,
the easiest thing to do would be to cut
down on your electric use.
Alright, I want every
table to share one idea.
Info manager from table one, give me
one idea.
- One idea is we can help the
environment by taking a
bus to school, instead of
like everybody having
their own individual cars.
- Good point.
- Or even better you can walk.
- Instead of having that carpool line
going on, let's take busses.
Table two give me one idea.
- Save power by changing
your lightbulbs
to CFLs.
- Yeah, use those light bulbs that
are like the twirly
light bulbs, they use
a lot less electricity, good idea.
Table three give me one.
- Conserve water by turning off
the water when we brush our teeth.
- Now conserving water.
Think about what the question was.
How can we be environmental
advocates to cut down on acid rain?
- We can cut down on electricity
by unplugging outlets.
- Very good.
Unplug items from the
outlets, that's good.
Table four.
- We could use hybrid cars.
- Hybrid cars, that's good.
They burn less fossil fuels, good idea.
Table five.
- Recycle.
- Recycle.  How would that help acid rain?
Okay, so it's cutting down on factory
use, that would be a good one.
Table six.
- Cutting down on electricity.
- Alright, cutting down on electricity,
because to make electricity
you have to burn
fossil fuels.
Table seven, is there any that haven't
been said?
- Carpool to work and school.
- Carpool to work and school,
I love it.
You got something to add?
- I was going to say
instead of the bottles
end up in landfills, so
you can keep bottles out
of landfills if you reuse them.
- Yeah, very good.
A lot of times we focus
only on the idea of
recycling, but it's good to reuse, too.
That's a good idea as well.
So we talked about
how the temperature
will affect our chemical weathering.
We haven't yet talked
about how temperature
affects mechanical weathering.
Which lab would
answer that question?
How temperature affects mechanical
weathering.
- Station four.
- Alright, look at station four.
Take one minute, you don't have to
write this one down, discuss it.
What does station four
tell you and how is
that important in daily life.
Take one minute.
[Background Chatter]
- And it like ice wedges,
and then it'll make
bigger cracks and then
it will do bad stuff
for sidewalks.
[Background Chatter]
- What were you supposed
to be measuring?
In centimeters.
You measured in milimeters,
but you meant
to measure in centimeters.
- So how much was it in centimeters?
Well if you said it was at 79, which
would be right there.
What centimeters is that at?
- Around 15.
- Write down 15.
Oh wait wait!
I had it going the wrong way, and no one
even noticed.
So if it was at 79, where would it be.
At 79, the tick mark right below the 80.
- About 16.
- About 16, and if it was at 76
where would it be at?
- About 14 and a half.
- Very good
Alright, let's pick someone at random,
who's the lucky person, Andrew P.
What did you notice was the difference
between the same amount of water
when it was frozen
and when it was left
as a liquid.
- When it was frozen it was taller.
What does that mean
that it was taller?
Lucy?
- Well the water was
frozen to ice.
So it expands a little.
- It expands.
I like the use of that word.
Water expands as it freezes.
Here in Louisville
how is that a problem?
And it's been a particularly
big problem this winter.
Ethan?
- Because like, the water
can get in the cracks
in the roads and then
when it freezes it will
expand and it will crack
roads and buildings.
Soon the people will have
the construction people will
have to rebuild the roads.
- Right, very good point.
Now that affects us here
in Kentucky because we
have those cold winters.
What types of areas
would it not affect?
Forrest?
- Florida.
- Florida, areas that
don't have freezing
that's a good point.
Now we've talked
about climate as far
as temperature goes.
We've talked about
the warm temperatures
and the cold temperatures
and how it affects the
chemical and mechanical weathering.
What is the other
aspect of climate, other
than temperatures?
Other than temperature,
what is another
aspect of climate?
Patrick?
- How humid it is?
- How humid it is.
Which lab do you think would tell us
how humidity affects weather?
Flip through,
Sky?
- Seven
Let's look at station seven.
Now, during our labs, the materials
managers were always in charge of
getting the materials ready.
A material manager.
Can someone explain to me, what's
the difference between the steel wool
that was covered with a cup versus the
steel wool that was not covered
with a cup.
What would that difference be?
Lucy?
- Well the steel wool
that was covered,
well the steel wool
that wasn't covered
with the cup, it was all like
stuck together and it wasn't rusting
and the one that was
covered with the cup it had
like stuff popping out, like
it wasn't all stuck together and
it was rusting.
- Okay, so the one that was
covered with a cup and moistened,
had a lot of rust.
And the one that was moistened, but
was just left sitting out dried
and did not have a lot of rust.
Would you agree?
Okay, what is the purpose
of covering it?
Why do I cover that?
Otis?
- Keeping the water from evaporating.
Yeah, it's keeping that water in.
So is the covered cup a dry environment,
or a humid environment?
- Humid environment.
- A very humid environment.
I have a great map here that tells you
a little bit about different areas, and
tells you what their humidity is like.
I'm gonna flip off both lights
to help you see it.
This is a tropical wet area,
tropical dry area,
semi-arid which means dry, arid,
then, marine, west coast,
Mediterranean, and humid sub-tropical.
These areas that are marked as humid,
sub-tropical, such as down in Florida,
those areas that are marked as humid,
what do they have to be cautious about?
If it's a humid area,
what do they have to be
cautious about?
Don't see a lot of hands,
talk about it for one minute.
What do humid areas have to be
cautious about?
[Background Chatter]
- Now think about this,
an area like Kentucky.
And our summers aren't just
hot, they're humid.
So we have to deal with cold winters
which are gonna affect
mechanical weathering,
and we have to deal with,
Yeah, so we're kind of getting the worst
end of both scenarios.
Yes, we definitely are.
Good point.
Alright, I need someone
I haven't heard from
to share, let's see who
the random card
is, Lucy.
What do you think?
- They have to be careful
about rusting
like their cars and stuff.
- They have to be careful of rusting.
Good point.  Because the more humid
the air is, the more
likely you are to have what?
Oxidation.
Now there was another lab where
we used steel wool.
What was the purpose of
the other steel wool lab?
What were you trying to answer,
what were you trying to determine?
Jamiel, what do you think?
[Background Chatter]
- There was the key word,
the what kind of water?
Salt water.
You look to see if salt water
affected the oxidation rate.
You look to see if salt water did.
Silently, look at your data,
and tell me did salt water affect
the rate of oxidation.
Jeremy, did salt water affect the
rate of oxidation?
- Yeah