- Right here.
Okay, so is that gonna tell us
what one of our asymptotes is?
- Yeah.
- Yes, because your asymptote is where
this would be undefined, right?
So, it's gonna be X equals what?
- Positive two?
- Positive, but, okay, if
we put positive two there,
we have two plus two.
- So, it'd be negative two?
- Negative two, that's why
we have an asymptote that
X equals negative two, okay?
Now is there another number out here?
- No.
No, so what would that other number be?
See there is one here,
but there's not one here.
- So it'd just be zero.
- So, it'd just be zero.
So, does that tell you what
your other asymptote is?
Y equals zero, 'cause f of x stands for...
that's your y isn't it? Okay.
So, you can tell by looking
at the function itself,
what your asymptotes are gonna be.
Okay, tell me what this
asymptote's gonna be,
your x, your vertical asymptote.
- [Student] Zero?
- [Teacher] Zero, X equals zero,
so you're gonna be drawing
your asymptote right there.
What about your y?
Remember how we covered this up, and you
would have y equals what?
- Negative one?
- Negative one, y plus negative one.
So, the function itself tells
you your asymptotes, doesn't it?
Okay, does that help?
- Yeah.
- [Teacher] Okay.
(background chatter)
- [Student] All right, so...
- [Student] No, but it's like
that right here though.
- [Student] But see she has negative two.
- [Student] Right here.
- [Student] Then how did she get the,
did we write the first one wrong then?
- [Student] 'Cause x equals zero.
- [Student] No, because she
got zero and negative two,
and that's what I got.
You wrote it down wrong.
- [Student] Where?
- [Student] Right here, 'cause
zero is supposed to be on top.
Oh, so, no, never mind, you got it right.
- [Student] It's the same. I
just switched these around.
No, but you're right because
you know how x is vertical,
okay, so, for this one it's going to be,
the x is going to be negative 2, right?
- Mm-hmm.
- Okay I got it.
- [Student] So wait, the
asymptote isn't the same thing
as the parent function, right?
- No.
- Did you have the graph? Did it turn out?
- And how do you know, up here?
- Check this thing out.
- Huh?
- [Student] So, what would
the parent function be?
- That's what I was trying
to work out for you.
- [Student] Did you find the parent function?
- For what?
- It's not x squared, is it?
- One over x.
- [Student] All of them is
going to be one over x.
- 'Cause you can't just put x.
She said put a one divided by x.
That'd be the parent function.
- [Student] All right.
- How do you know which
is the parent function?
- It's the one that's consistent.
- That first one that you put.
- It's the one that's exactly in between
the first and third quadrant.
This is your parent function.
- This one and this one, right?
So blue right there and right there.
- But you totally ruined it.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, the colors I
used are kind of weird.
- Do you have a red?
Are you using it?
- This is the graph, right?
So, if it's the first one
and the third one, right?
- Hey wait, that first thingy comes out at
negative three, not negative two.
- Hm?
- [Student] This first little line
right here comes out
negative three, not negative two.
Is the parent function still,
I mean, is the asymptote
still negative two?
- I think
- [Student] (gasps)
- So, how is one negative two?
- [Student] You gotta switch it,
because the one x plus two
when you use the calculator
you go into a negative, so
the y would be zero because
it's not going to negative.
- How would the y be
zero, the y is a negative?
- You got em' switched, all
you gotta do is switch em'.
- I'm not understanding.
She busy.
- Okay.
Oh, I know why.
It's because we don't
have no y in the equation.
Like this one, it'd have a y.
The y would be negative one.
And on this one, we don't have it,
so, automatically the y would be zero
and the x would be negative two.
- That makes more sense.
- [Student] All right you got it.
- Yeah I had to think about that.
- (laughter)
- [Student] So, that's how you do it.
- So, then the asymptote is the...
(inaudible) right here?
- [Student] Uh-huh.
- Which one?
- So, then the translation is the down one.
- Wait, what?
- The translation is the down one.
- So, what is this down?
- [Student] Let me plug it in.
Divide by x parentheses...
One over, divided by x minus one.
- Okay, so we don't need no parenthesis?
- [Student] No.
- [Student] I'm almost done.
- You're crossing it, that's
the y, yeah. But that's the x.
This is x and this is y.
- Yes.
- [Student] Well, look on the
sheet. It will show you that, um...
- I basically used this one as an example.
It's like the same type of
format that the problem is.
- Okay.
- Okay, yeah that makes sense.
- So, the asymptote is zero.
- It says h equals x .
- Yeah.
- Yeah, so zero,
yeah wait... Yeah.
- [Student] This is the graph you start with?
- Yeah, that makes more sense
'cause that's how the graph is.
Okay, we got the asymptote.
X equals, is it zero?
Yeah, and then y equals negative one.
And the translation is one unit down.
Do you have a value?
- Yeah.
- Uh-oh.
- So, it'd be three units down.
We would put this on negative
three cause that's y.
So, since it's y, we
would have to put it on
negative three and zero.
- Right?
- [Student] 'Cause it's the same as this.
- Yeah.
- And then y equals negative three.
- Yeah, x equals zero and
y equals negative three.
Translation, three units down.
- Wherever the lines,
like, go the furthest
but don't touch.
- Okay.
- Oh, you're just marking
down the asymptotes?
- Yeah. She said she forgot, yeah,
so I guess you can just
put up there yellow.
- Okay. Are you on number four?
- Yes.
- So, on number four it would
be five units to the left.
- Number four, yeah, yeah, you're good.
- Okay.
- She just told me, she just told,
- I just wrote it wrong I guess, then.
- How do you know how to
graph it with... (inaudible)?
- Like in the calculator?
- In here. And it's really
not good to graph it here.
- Yeah.
- Okay.
- This seems to be not that
hard, now that I get it.
- Really.
- Like, remember how Grayson
thought that it was three
I knew she was wrong... (inaudible).
- I mean, I didn't think it was wrong.
- You just instinctively
knew that it was wrong.
- (laughter)
- [Teacher] Is it going to have
a vertical shift also?
- Yep, up, down, down.
- Okay, up or down?"
Down how many?
- Two.
- On number five?
- Oh, three. It would be three.
- Three. Okay, so you're
going to have two shifts
on number five, right? Okay?
- Uh huh. I haven't plugged it in yet.
- We're going to have a shift here, right?
What would make that undefined?
If x equals...?
How about positive two?
Because two minus two is zero.
I mean, the zero is
where you needed to be.
So, x equals two, right?
Okay, now, what are we going to do
with this thing out here?
That's a vertical shift of y equals...
negative three.
Y equals negative three.
- (bell rings)
- So, we have two translations, okay?
Two units right and...