- What note are we going to start
the question with for bell?
Marilyn?
(inaudible)
Doe, it's going to end that note is?
F, thank you.
What are we going to end
the question with?
What are we going to
end the question with?
Josh?
- Anything but doe.
What are we going to
start the answer with?
Start the answer with.
Paige?
(inaudible)
Yeah, you can actually
start with doe, okay?
So this is really anything, okay?
And then anything else
for anything in between.
Got it?
(inaudible)
What part?
We have 15 R's.
And we have a five note scale.
Abby?
(inaudible)
The C's and the E?
(singing notes)
(inaudible)
Big it.
There we go.
(inaudible)
Eggs and bacon are coming off.
Two eggs, whoops, one bacon.
Here we go.
John, before you go to your instrument
boys and girls-- (inaudible)
Yeah, well, my shoe fell off.
Can I have these two rows
speak the question and these two rows
speak the answer?
Just so we solidify the rhythm.
Ready?
Speak in pack, speak in pack.
Ready, set, speaking first.
Valentines, valentines.
Pink, red and blue.
Now you.
I made a pretty one,
just for you.
Switch please.
Question answer.
Ready, begin.
Valentines, valentines.
Pink, red and blue.
I made a pretty one just for you.
Okay, two jobs when you
get to your instrument.
Remove eggs and bacon by drawing
your fingernails down the nail
and pulling towards you.
Job number one always in this classroom
is not to talk while I'm talking,
thank you.
Job number two,
make your X.
One, take off bars.
Two, make your X.
Ben J.
(inaudible)
That's my instrument.
Thank you.
I'm going to move it now.
Yeah there's (inaudible).
Okay, I've already set my instrument,
anybody not get a turn on the basses yet
this year?
Not had a turn on the basses yet.
- Everybody had a turn.
- I haven't.
- Yeah, you have.
(background chatter)
- Okay, let's have Josh and Britney go
to the back row and start their jobs.
(background chatter)
Oh my gosh, we do not have time.
Go!
That row may go.
Okay, you're about two
seconds too late on that.
Your row may go now.
Draw your finger to the top
of the nail and pull it towards you.
Sabrina?
Egg, oh they're wrong?
Okay, eggs and bacon.
Agata's row may go.
And the last row may go.
(background chatter)
- How come on this (inaudible)
it says H equals B?
- 'Cause in Germany they don't have
B, they have H.
We have instruments made in Germany.
(background chatter)
Josh is ready, Britney's ready.
Ben is ready.
Abby's ready.
All right, boys and girls.
You have two does on
your instrument, two F's.
Would you locate one, yes?
(background chatter)
You have two F's, locate one and hover
both mallets above one?
Hold question on F.
Speaking and playing alternating bounce C.
Ready, set and here we go.
(xylophone music)
Stop, we gotta do it again because
Josh remembered half way through
that he was supposed to speak while
he played.
Let's try it again, Josh.
Ready, set, and here we go.
(xylophone music)
Excellent.
Answer on the other F.
Hold answer on the other F.
Ready, set and here we go.
(xylophone music)
Yeah, we're going to try the answer again
just some of you might have messed up
the rhythm.
Ready, set, and here we answer.
(xylophone music)
Make your X.
This time you're to do the question again,
but you may use two bars this time.
But we have to start beating the question
on what mill?
- [Children] F.
- F, so one of your bars must be F.
The other bar has to be next door
to F in either direction.
Here we go.
Question only.
Starting on F, only using two bars.
Ready, set, and here we go.
(xylophone music)
Uh oh, what are we not supposed to
end the question over?
Dawn?
- F?
- F, this time you may use your whole
instrument for the question, you have
to start on F but don't end on F.
Ready, set and get question
here we go.
(xylophone music)
Good, didn't hear anybody end on F.
I did, make your X for a second.
I heard some people's questions
that maybe sounded like this.
(xylophone music)
I don't really remember
what notes I played,
I was just kinda doing
whatever I wanted to
up and down up and down.
Could I sing that?
- No?
♫ Valentine, valentine ♫
- [Teacher] Probably not.
But if my question sounded like this--
(xylophone music)
Could I sing that?
Probably.
Did I use some patterns in that
like a good musician?
I did.
♫ Valentines, valentines
♫ Pink, red and blue ♫
Okay?
Try it.
You don't have to do the same thing I did,
but let's do some
repeated notes, let's use
some patterns and let's
not be all up and down
our instrument.
Ready, set and here you go.
(xylophone music)
Not bad.
Let's try the answer, boys and girls.
Start at any note you want but end on N.
And let's make it memorable and singable.
Something you can remember,
something you can sing.
I made a pretty one just for you.
Ready, set and here you go.
(xylophone music)
Not bad, not bad.
Here's what I would like to have happened.
I'm going to ask the question,
Tyler's going to give the answer.
Amanda's going give an answer.
I'm gonna ask the question,
answer, question, answer, question,
answer, question, answer.
And then the next row
we're going to switch.
Paige question, me answer.
Kia question, me answer, you get it?
Okay?
- Yay!
- [Teacher] Shh.
Paige, would you mind before we begin,
arrowing over to the last slide.
I want to show you what I am looking for.
Yeah, go for it.
When you are doing, yeah keep going.
When you are doing your question,
or when you are, keep going.
Sorry, keep going.
That's it, okay!
Here's what I'm looking for.
Are you alternating your mallets?
Are you bouncing your mallets?
Are you doing the correct rhythm?
Did your question start on doe
if you're the question?
Did your answer end on
doe if you're the answer?
Was your melody memorable and singable?
Here we go.
My turn first, so we'll go question answer
down the batch feels, and you get it.
Todd.
(xylophone music)
- I forget the--
- I made this pretty one just for you.
(xylophone music)
Paige, question is ready, here you go.
- Do I start this time?
- [Teacher] Yeah, you start this time.
Yeah, you're going to do the question
now I'm giving you the answer.
(xylophone music)
Now, question, answer, question, answer.
Let's actually do this.
Question, answer, question, answer.
Question, answer.
Ready, Britney?
Josh you get ready to do the answer.
Ready, Britney, here she goes.
(xylophone music)
Oh, you know what Ben, it sounded
like the end was ended on a doe.
- Oh, yeah.
- [Teacher] All right,
you want to try it again?
That's why Eli was like--
- Oh.
- [Teacher] Yeah, okay?
(xylophone music)
Ready, go.
Good, Sabrina, go.
- It's, um--
- [Teacher] Question.
- Okay.
(xylophone music)
Nice job.
Now, some of you didn't get a chance
to do the question or didn't get a chance
to do the answer.
Right?
So here's what I'm going to have you do.
And we have 30 seconds to do this.
With the person next to you,
one of you do the question, one of you
do the answer, okay?
(background chatter)
(xylophone music)
Let's try it together!
Ready, set and here we go.
(xylophone music)
Answer.
Nice.
Here's the beauty of the pentatonic scale,
boys and girls.
No matter if we're doing a million
different things at the same time,
if we're all on different bars,
the notes of the pentatonic
scale sound so good
together that you can
could be playing something
else and it still sounds musical.