(background chatter)
- Think out loud, what are we doing?
- OK, you know the area
of the square is 196
so you want to
(background chatter)
- How do we do that?
- Take 196, divide it by four.
(background chatter)
- Hold on, let me hear from somebody
that I haven't heard from.
- Need to find the square root of 196.
- OK, why are we taking the square root
instead of dividing by four?
- Because all sides are equal?
- Well, if all sides were equal,
that's why we would divide by four.
(background chatter)
- Because to find the area of the square
you have to square it.
- So the opposite of
squaring is square root.
- So, we would divide by
four if we were given the...
perimeter.
If we were given the
perimeter of the square
we would divide by four.
But we were given the area,
so we need to square root.
- [Several] 14.
- OK, so the side lengths are 14.
- Multiply times 4.
- It's 56.
- Anybody see a problem with this?
(background chatter)
OK, so this side is on
the inside of the figure.
So it doesn't count, so
instead of doing 14 times 4,
- [Several] We do 14 times 3.
(background chatter)
- How do we find the
perimeter of a semi-circle?
(background chatter)
- 2 pi R divided by 2 .
- 2 pi R divided by 2?
(background chatter)
- How do you find the
perimeter of a semi-circle?
- 2 pi R divided by 2.
- So the radius, that means 7, 7 is 14.
2 times pi times 7.
So that should be 2 times 3.14...
(background chatter)
So the whole thing is 53.38.
- So then, 2 pi R divided by 2?
- I got 2 times pi times 7 divided by two
cause the radius is only 7
cause that line was supposed to be 14.
So 14 divided by 2 is 7.
(background chatter)
- Here, Skye, can you take this?
Thank you.
Put the final answer on there
and then quick to the next problem.
(background chatter)
- C squared.
- OK, all of the line
segments in the diagram
of the bathroom floor shown below
are either vertical or horizontal.
How many one inch square
tiles would it take
to cover the figure?
(background chatter)
- Don't you got to work
it into two rectangles?
- I think it'd be easier
of you did it the long way.
(background chatter)
- Does it matter which way you split it?
Either way you're going to
have to split something, right?
(background chatter)
You can determine either
of the missing sides.
- In order to find the area of a rectangle
you must apply (inaudible).
7 times 6 is 42.
- Where is...I don't
see a 7 in my problem.
(background chatter)
OK, but what does 7 represent?
I don't see a 7, what is...?
- It represents the length of this.
- What length?
- From the line on down to 6.
- OK.
Could you label that with a 7?
Cause I still don't see 7.
(background chatter)
- It said, how many one
inch squares (inaudible).
- OK, so you want to multiply what by 12?
- 87.
- 87 times 12?
- [Several] Why?
- But you made the 12 into a 7.
- OK, so you want to do
85 and divide it by 12?
- Where are you all getting 12 from?
- A foot is 12 inches.
- There's one inch, not twelve.
- Oh, because I found the 87 feet squared.
I found the area of it,
but then you've got to find
how many 1 inch, so you
multiply it times 12
because there's 12 inches in a foot.
- So what are we multiplying with?
- [Several] 12.
- So we're doing 87 times 12?
(background chatter)
- Shouldn't you divide though?
- Try dividing.
What do you get when you divide?
(background chatter)
- Say that again.
- In one square foot,
there are 144 inches.
Instead of going by 12
which I said originally,
shouldn't we be doing it by 144?
Since one square foot is
how many inches it is?
- But I've got 87 square foot.
- But I'm saying in each
foot, there's 144 inches.
So instead of 12, there
are 144 square inches.
So instead of multiplying by
12 cause that would be wrong
now that I think about it,
we should multiply it by 144.
(background chatter)
- OK, let me ask you guys this:
what if we converted all
of the feet to inches
before we found our area?
- Could we do it that way?
- [Several] Yeah.
OK, let's try it that way.
What would 9 be in inches?
9 feet in inches?
- [Several] 108.
- 108? What would 5 be in inches?
60, thank you LaDarius.
7 in inches, 7 feet?
- 84.
- 84, thank you Kashmir.
And 6?
- 72.
- 72, thank you Sierra.
OK, we know what all
our units are in inches.
Now when we find the area,
we're going to be finding square inches.
Somebody want to take over from here?
Skye, do you mind if you continue writing?
- Uhm yeah. No, I don't mind.
- Thank you.
You can erase all of it.
My eraser got stolen.
- So, do we do this the same way
but multiply the length
and the width, right?
- Yeah.
(background chatter)
- It's what?
- 6,480.
(background chatter)
- It's multiplying.
- But that's wrong though.
Don't you still have to subtract...
I mean, like 84 minus 60
because they're part of the...
- No, we didn't convert the 12.
We converted the 7.
- Oh, OK.
- So it's still already changed.
Good question though.
(background chatter)
What's the total?
- 12,528.
I just checked it originally
with the 87 times 144
and that was correct.
You are supposed to multiply by 144.
- Good job.
- What did you say it was?
- 12,528.
- How'd you get that?
(background chatter)
- OK. Next problem.
No? You have a question?
Yes.
(inaudible)
- When you get 1000?
When did you have 1,044?
(background chatter)
Oh, and then you multiply by 12 again.
Because guess what 12 times 12 is.
- [Several] 144.
- So that's what you're doing.
You're multiplying by
144, you just broke 144 up
into 12 and 12, right?
(background chatter)
- They way you get 15 from
when the outside is 10
before the 15....(inaudible).
- From the very, very
top to the very bottom.
- Thank you, because now
we know that that's 1 inch.
- Can't you break it up?
- Now that we know the
basic triangle in the back.
- That means you're breaking it up into...
a triangle and a square?
- Yes.
The square on the bottom.
- I'm sorry, Jacob?
The base of what?
- The base of the triangle in the back.
(background chatter)
- But what's the base?
- 5.
- The height is 5 and the base is 15.
(background chatter)
- Well yeah, but I was
asking Jacob what the base
of the triangle was.
Can you explain why the
base of the triangle is 18?
- Because the width of the rectangle is 10
and I have to add the
sides of the triangle.