- Our is, like, Crown-- Crown Royal, and, like,
it shows, like, a helmet, and, like, an ad
for it, and it says, "He who wears the
crown, " I think that's, like, if you wear
the helmet, you will seem cool.
- Mm-hmm, and the helmet is for what, do
you think? Motorcycles or cars, kind of
racing kind of stuff? And Crown Royal,
tobacco or alcohol? Alcohol, and racing a
car. Thoughts?
- Drinking and driving. Huh.
- Well, that's bad.
- But they appeal to your-- your, uh, love
of racecars and motorcycles and cool
stuff, but those two don't really mix, do
they? Next group.
- Ours is tobacco, and it has a picture of
a firefighter, and it says, A bit braver,
so it's trying to hook you by you
wanting to be braver, and trying tobacco.
- So the inference there would be that
tobacco makes you braver? What do you
think? Could it really work? If I chew
tobacco? Am I gonna be able to fight a
fire?
- No.
- But firefighting appeals to a lot of
young children, right? That bravery, that
toughness, that rugged fireman thing. It's
like, if I do chewing tobacco, I'm a
rugged fireman type. Um, what are my teeth
gonna look like, though?
- [together] Yellow.
- Not gonna look like the rugged fireman
type, am I?
[Background Chatter]
- Fireman sounds like he smiles, is that
what you said? All right, um, ladies?
- Um, ours was alcohol, and, um, they got
our attention by, like, the grandma and
the daughter playing patty-cake and
telling stories about her.
- So grandma and daughter-- and
granddaughter playing patty-cake, lovely
little sunny porch, sponsored by... ?
- Budweiser.
- Oh, my.
- Oh, that's so popular.
- So drink? You're appealing to the family
nature? And the message is, drink our
drink.
- Yeah, it says that, like, all stories
weren't about family, they also had some
other stuff.
- Family and Budweiser.
- Yeah.
- No.
- Yeah, you're getting it now. All right.
Ladies?
- Um, ours is, um--
- There's isn't really an ad. There's is a
display at a grocery store.
- Yeah, like, there is, um, a whole bunch
of, like, alcohol in the background, and
up closer, there's tobacco, and then
there's a bunch a candy bars that should
appeal to the little kids.
- Right next to the... ?
- The tobacco.
- Tobacco, okay. Candy bars.
- Like right there, and then, um, also you
have pretty much the candy.
- Alcohol behind the booth, tobacco right
up front, and candy bars right at hand
level.
- Kids would probably think that tobacco's
candy.
- They might.
- Or as good as candy.
- Does tobacco come in flavors like candy
does?
- [together] Yeah.
- No.
- Yes, it does.
- Oh.
- Mint, berry, apple.
- Ew, really?
- Really. Hey, I think I missed a group.
Did I miss a group? This one up front?
Nope. Did I get you guys already? Did you
guys share? Oh, you did share, just with
me. Share with the rest of the group. It's
- Ours is alcohol and, like, if you're a
rockstar, you'll drink, like, if you drink
this, then you will become a rockstar.
- What hook did they use?
- The girls in bikinis.
- So how many guys are in that picture?
- One.
- One guy, and he's the one who's drinking
the alcohol, and... ?
- Fifteen girls.
- Fifteen girls in bikinis. So if-- the
message is, if you drink this... ?
- You'll get hot girls.
- You'll get hot girls, yeah.
[Background Chatter]
- All right, you've had a chance to let--
Oh, sorry. Eyes. Ears. Mouth. Thanks.
You've had a chance to look at these ads.
Um, you've got a chance to see how they're
trying to hook you in. You're knowing that
the messages that they're sending are
slightly warped. It's their trick to pull
you in, but it's your job to think and
process through using your critical
thinking skills. Weigh it out. Consider,
but then choose something else that's
healthier. So we've looked at negative
influences. It's time to talk about
positive influences in your life, things
that can help you say no to all of that,
no matter how appealing it is, no matter
how many girls in bikinis show up. Leave
your cards right where they are in the
center. It's time to take a look at the
charts that are around the room. There are
five of them. These are activities you can
do instead of things like using drugs,
alcohol, tobacco, like a social activity,
um, something you can do with someone
else. Ideas?
- Have a sleepover.
- Sleepover, good. All right, so in just a
few minutes, we're gonna be rotating
around the charts with different
groupings. We're gonna be writing down our
ideas of other positive things instead of
this. Can anyone name one physical
activity, something you can do that would
be instead of using drugs, a positive
thing? Football? Yeah. Did you want to
share too? Go ahead.
- Um, riding your bike around the block.
- Good. You're on the right track, guys.
Keep those ideas in your head. When you
get to the chart, you'll have to write it
down. What's something you can do with
your brain, a mental activity that would
be positive?
- Chess.
- I like chess.
- Math. Not for everybody, I understand.
Um, this chart over here says "Emotional."
What's something you can do, um, that
can make your emotions feel better, your
passions, or whatever? How can you support
yourself emotionally, so you can say no to
this?
- Trying to think happy.
- Yep. Positive thoughts.
- Watching emotional movies.
- Definitely gets your mind off those. I
know you got great ideas, and I'm gonna be
willing to see those on those papers in
just a few minutes, so save them in your head.
- Okay.
- The last one is spiritual. Spiritual.
Somehow you can nurture your spirit, so
you have the ability to say no to negative
influences.
- Go to church.
- Church. All right. Save it. You'll get a
chance. Time to look at your pencils
again. Leave your papers right where they
are, okay? Face-up. This time, we're gonna
go by color, and you might notice that
there are markers at each station, for the
right color. So when you get to the
station, if you are-- patience. I promise
I'll explain it. No worries. When you get
to your station, we're gonna start with
your bag of colors. You will take your bag of
colors and your marker, and you will only
use your color marker. So if you are a
green guy, you would grab a green marker
and you will be writing at this station
first. You'll write down however many
ideas you want. You'll talk it out with
your group. You might notice, Mitchell,
that I also put group work, uh, reminders
up here, about how to work with others in
your group. One, everybody has the right
to speak, so make sure you give everybody
a chance to talk it out if they need to,
and to write it down, the topic. Don't
interrupt. Give everybody a chance to
share their side. Two, everybody has the
right to be respected. We're not looking
for put downs. We're looking for ones that
can encourage us, positive things, so when
you're getting ready to write positive
things, speak positively to each other as
well. And three, everyone has to agree to
work together to solve a conflict. So if
you're having a difficulty in your group,
talk it out. Work together to solve that
problem. If it's not working, and you
can't solve the problem, who can you turn
to for help?
- You?
- Me. And others in your group. So if
you're a green person, you're gonna get
one green marker, and there are multiple
in here, in case your marker doesn't work.
Get a different one. Write down whatever
ideas you want. When you hear me say,
"Switch," or, "Rotate," you move to the
next chart around like the face of a
clock. Take your marker with you. So
there'll be multiple colors on here.
You'll get a chance to write on every one.
Yes?
- How does this work? Are you supposed to
write it down like a list?
- You can write all over that paper. Yeah.
Anywhere, as long as we're on the front.
Everywhere, all over that paper, so you
can all be on there at the same time as
you want, you can take turns, you can
arrange however you and your group want
to. You each can have a marker, though.
There's plenty of them for everyone.
Yellow's are over here at "Emotional,"
um, I believe blue's are "Social,"
purple's are "Physical," and oranges are
"Mental." Questions before we begin?
Think about something to do besides.
You'll have approximately 30 seconds to a
minute, so listen for me to say, "Switch."
Keep writing until I say it. Go!
[Background Chatter]
- Here. How about we take this and put it
on the floor. Does that work better? I
know, it's going everywhere, isn't it?
Here you go. You guys want to take that
one down, too, put it on the floor, so
it's a little easier to write on?
- Yeah.
- Good.
- I know, isn't it cool?
- Yeah.
- So I see you got chess on there. Anyone
think of some other ones? Other mental,
ways to use your brain, things you can
think about it?
[Background Chatter]
- Think of school kind of activities,
things related to learning, using the
brain. Spelling. You can practice your
spelling. You can do your math. I think
you guys are in right place. You have a
lot of good ideas. Tell me your favorite
one so far.
[Background Chatter]
- Give him a spot.
- Good.
- How do you spell "baseball"?
[Background Chatter]
- Oh, online. The Playstation, yeah, that
is definitely a social event.
- I've got XBox Live.
- So social means involving what? Talking
to other people, human beings, a
relationship with them? All right. Ready
in 10, nine, finish what you're writing,
eight, seven, six, taking your marker with
you in five...
- Oh, our marker?
- Four. Yep. Your writing in your color.
Three, two, one, rotate.
[Background Chatter]
- Spiritual. All things that are
spiritual. What does that really mean?
- Your spirit?
- Your spirit, yeah. It could be feelings.
I think we did emotions, though, right?
- Yeah.
- So this one would be more nurturing your
soul, yourself.
- We've got meditation.
- We've got mediation, right.
- Yoga!
- Oh, yeah! Why don't you write that one
down?
- How do you spell "yoga"?
- Yes, perfect. The Bible, poems. How much
do you connect with your spirit or your
soul? Any other resources or people?
Pastor from a church. Friends you know
from the church, or wherever you attend
services. Who else besides a pastor can
lead, um, a group?
- You can pray.
- Pray, good. You guys are on the right
track. Emotional support. Where can we
find emotional support? Family, friends,
good. Who are some other resources for
emotional support? Culture? How can we
nurture your own good feelings? What do
you do to feel better?
- Cuddle your pets.
- Cuddle your pets. You know that one's my
favorite, too.
- It's okay, you don't have to spell
things. All right, capping markers. Ready
to move? 10, nine, eight, seven, six,
ready gentlemen in five,
taking your marker in four, three, two,
one. Rotate.
[Background Chatter]