[background chatter]
- I'm not too sure if I like this screen
print with the acrylic on top of it. I'm
not too sure about that.
- It makes it less
[inaudible].
- It's different, in an awkward way. I
don't know how to explain it. It doesn't
have any depth to it. It has no dimension.
Like, she's standing there, he has to take
the paint and try to add dimension to it
and then. . .
- It looks like she's laying down.
- Actually, yeah it does. I mean, he has
to take the paint and try and add
dimension to it, and then add the cool and
warm colors to make it pop. And I'm just
not feeling it. I like the Mick Jagger
one, but I'm not feeling this Taylor Swift
one.
[cross talk]
- See, I like pop art. I just, I don't
know.
- Did you notice that?
- What?
- I thought it was a green that goes in
to, this. That's on them, it's more like a
quiet, like she's sleeping softness. But I
didn't notice it that it goes into purple,
periwinkle, and this dark violet color
that comes out of this red on the bottom
half side. Did you see that? Then it goes
in to two, and he breaks off the colors
And it's like
[inaudible].
- All right, let's take a couple of
minutes and try to just wrap up some of
our questions. And then we'll talk about a
whole group discussion, and see what we
all have and what we want to write.
[background chatter]
- In a sense, it would be a good picture
for the stance that she's in. You know,
the title of the album is called
"Fearless," and we decided that it is a
powerful stance she does look kinda
fearless. In the way she's standing. The
way he did it, it just doesn't look like
her.
- [inaudible]
- It's like the wind's coming back and it
pushes her hair. . .
- Yeah, but you would think that she would
want to be looking directly at the camera.
- But then her hair wouldn't have been
like that.
- Yeah, but they just need some big ole
fans, it's Hollywood. You can get some big
ole fans to blow your hair back. You would
wanna be looking at the camera if you want
to be looking fearless.
[cross talk]
- You have to think. . .
- It's more of country music. I mean, I
could see if you were saying like,
hip-hop, pop. And you get like all
forceful, "What's Up, I'm here."
- But they're saying, you know, she's a
pop icon. If she's a country artist, then
why are they putting her on pop billboards
and pop charts?
- Because she's mainstreaming into the
different areas, she's creating kind of a
new version of country for the younger
generations like you guys. You wouldn't
compare her to Kenny Chesney. Those who
want newer generation of country.
- Right.
- All right, let's just try and get to our
last question and then we'll talk about
whole group and get you back in here.
Let's go ahead and start, you guys can
chime in when you guys have an answer, if
you want your input put in. So let's just
talk about the describe section. What we
really need to talk about is describing
the scene in your own words. What kind of
words would you use to describe this
piece? Let's start with Mick Jagger.
- Bold.
- Proud.
- Electric.
- Electric. Okay, those are good ones.
What about Taylor Swift?
- It's more feminine. More soft
- It's pale, it's delicate and
[inaudible].
- Delicate.
- Soft.
- You said soft.
- It's like he's almost scared when he's
doing Taylor Swift, compared to Mick
Jagger. Because Mick Jagger is all rough
and boxes everywhere.
- I think he almost makes Taylor look
almost intimidated. She's kind of pushing
away--
- The position.
- . . .and you have all these colors
around her. With the selection and. . .
- Innocence. Yeah, I think we talked about
that with Taylor a little bit. You kind of
have to look at the personality of each
artist as well.
- Plus really you have to listen to her
lyrics then it, like, paints a picture.
- She has an innocent expression.
- I'd say innocent, yeah. Okay.
- Fierce.
- You say fierce? Okay.
- It's like her personality, she just
breaks it out with this bold pose.
- All right good. So those are some good
words, key words to describe it. So,
analyzing. Let's figure out and pinpoint
specific elements and principles of design
that we see in the piece that we want to
discuss.
- Colors.
- Colors? Color's a big one. In both of
them actually.
- Paint strips?
- The paint strips, it looks like it's a
lot of paint. It kind of creates a lot of
movement, with the way that it's flowing
through the pieces. All right, so our big
ones are color. . .
- He said in the video color is
everything.
- And that's his main focus is color.
- The different colors make the value in
the picture, the dark colors make the
darker shades, and light colors.
- He uses more bold colors in Mick Jagger
than he did in Taylor. And like the
contrasting colors of Mick Jagger are more
loud.
- I'd definitely say it's louder. Okay,
good. Let's discuss the movement a little
bit. So if you look at it, I see a lot of
movement personally in the touch with the
hair. I like how the hair is like that and
I like her position from the side, because
I think it adds interest. Like I was
saying a second ago, if she was looking
straight forward, I don't think the hair
would have the same effect as it does from
the side. And that's just my personal
opinion, but I like how the hair is kind
of flowing through and it's creating the
movement through the piece. And then with
the Mick Jagger one, the movement in this
piece right here is really interesting to
me. How he chose the green and the red to
contrast each other. I think that's big
bold move in this area. Good.
Now what are our focal points?
- Faces.
- Faces? And what are the big things that
factor in for that? Why is that? What did
he do?
- The colors around her make her pop.
- The colors surrounding. If you look, the
face is white right here, and then her
skin tone is pale as well. So that kind of
pops out against the bold colors. What do
you guys think about the materials?
The silk screen and the acrylic paint? You
guys got to see a little bit of him
working in the video, where he gets those
huge rows of the acrylic paints from the
jars, and just dipped in a couple
different ones. And just started coloring.
So what do you guys think about his
process, and the materials he uses?
- He doesn't really choose what direction,
he just kind of goes with the flow.
- It's very free, if you watch him.
- [inaudible].
- Mindless. Mindless creativity. He does
what comes to him, which is interesting.
Any other comments about the actual
process or materials?
- I think It would have been more amazing
if he didn't use the silk screens.
- So you'd rather him just paint it than
add the silk screen?
- I think it would be more like a wow
factor.
- And some of his pieces are just
paintings. More of the people though, like
the Rollins he painted. . .
And the ones he did for President Obama.
President Reagan, some of the Statue of
Liberty. And also some of the other people
like Aerosmith, and the Beatles as well.
And he's usually famous for painting
his faces. And he would go into the color.