(alarm beeps)
[Background chatter]
- Okay, would the person
who is currently writing,
please stand up?
(students groan)
(laughter)
- Alright, nice and loud.
What did you guys put?
And why?
- Nicholas Carnatkey
created the perfect tangent
of calculating all the key
transient effects on the core
to predict, to create the
perfect amount of work.
- Okay, very good. John, nice and loud.
- Marie Curie.
- Okay.
- Discovered that radiation...
- Okay. What about you guys?
(student murmurs answer)
- Alright. Two claps
for these neighbors.
(students clap)
- Sit down. Pass the board one person.
- What would be, this
is an opinion question,
what do you think would be the result,
if scientists didn't
communicate their findings
to the community at large?
Go!
(students mumble)
- Do we need to write
this down on the board?
- Just give a bullet sentence.
(students mumble)
- Do we have to pick a scientist
for this one? To prove it?
- Nope.
This is just an opinion.
Just give me, like, a one
word bullet, would be fine.
(alarm beeps)
Okay. Pass the board one person.
And would that person please stand up?
Troy, what did you guys have?
- There would be multiple
theories on how things worked.
Society would be stagnant
and Newton's hypothesis...
- Newton was actually asked
by a college of scientists
about the thoughts of gravity and stuff,
and he didn't think it was important.
So when he found out, a
few months before that,
he didn't publish it, until
they asked him about it,
and then he republished to
them, so they could hang out
with everybody else.
- Okay. Excellent. What do you guys have?
- There would be no uniform
units, therefore there would
be no real way to judge one's discovery,
and you couldn't really
bounce one idea off another.
- Okay. What'd you guys have?
- We said that we wouldn't
have the technology
that we have today
because scientists tend to
go off of what other scientists have done.
Because I know that Celsius
went off of Newton's ideas
of how the poles were flat,
and so he went on an expedition
and found out that they were.
- Okay. Very good. Alright.
Two claps for all our neighbors.
(students clap)
Pass the board one person.
Okay. I like this one.
If you could interview
any of the scientists
that we've looked at today,
who would it be
and what one question,
would you be sure to ask?
Okay. Go!
(students murmur)
(alarm beeps)
Okay. Stop right there.
Pass the board one person.
Please stand up. Please stand up.
Who's going from this group?
- Andy.
- Super.
Okay. Nice and loud. Let's
use active listening. John,
who would you guys pick and
what question would you ask?
- Marie Curie.
(student laughs)
I said it right.
- And what question would you ask, dear?
- If she got any oppression
from the male scientists.
- Okay. The oppression from
the male scientists. I like it.
What about you guys?
- We would ask Thomas Edison,
"What inspired you to
create the phonograph?"
- Excellent. Okay. Back there.
Who would you pick and what?
- We were also going to ask Thomas Edison
to see how other people felt
about his invention of light bulbs.
- Of the light bulb,
specifically. Okay. Brandon?
- We had Albert Einstein
and our question would be,
how did he come up with all his theories,
if he couldn't pass high school math?
- Okay. What'd you guys put?
- We picked Oppenheimer and we would ask
why he went into this?
If he realized what he actually made?
- You probably can't see
it, but they have written
on the board, "The Manhattan Project."
Okay. Very good. And you guys?
- Oppenheimer. What his
thoughts were of the morality
of the atomic bomb.
- Okay. This is a really great segway
to what we're going to do next.
Big claps for all these guys.
(students clap)
Please move into your catwalk formation.
Find a partner. Go!
In ten. Without the
boards! Just yourself.
Just your bodies!
Nine.
Eight.
Seven.
Six.
Five.
Oh, we have a partner whose hand is up.
Four. Looks like, there we go.
Three.
Two.
One. Be sure to,
oh, we need a real quick
hands up, don't we?
Hand ripple! Establish
who your partner is.
(students laugh)
Wow! That was emphatic! Okay!
Be sure you're using active listening,
because I will quiz you.
Here's your question:
"How are scientists
affected by social issues?"
Social issues going on in our culture.
How does that affect what
scientists can and can't do,
or what they think? The person who
woke up the earliest
will answer this question
and then stand back to back. Go!
(animated conversation)
When you're done, stand back to back!
Okay. Face me.
Since this one is kind
of a shifting gears one,
I want to let you
volunteer. Did anybody have
a really good answer that
their partner gave? Yeah?
- Interference from the church.
- Okay. Definitely a social issue.
- If they don't have
their research believed,
they could not receive funding,
or just get shunned, basically.
If it disagrees with what the
society basically believes in.
- Okay. So, you could be shunned,
you could risk your political or your
religious beliefs. Em?
- Problems with morality,
like testing on animals.
- Okay. Did you guys want
to add something down there?
- No.
- No? You're good?
- They said what we said, basically.
- Okay. This question is
for the other partner.
"Why do you think scientists
try to understand the natural world?"
Think for a few seconds.
"Why do scientists try to understand
the natural world?"
(students murmur)
Okay. Give your answer,
then stand back to back. Go!
(animated conversation)
Okay. Face me.
I'm going to let you guys
volunteer on this one, too.
Who had a partner with
a really good answer?
Yeah?
- It's just human nature
to question things.
- Okay. Very good. Since
we got the bigger brain
with all the cool parts to
it. We just question. Okay.
What'd you guys have?
- Because they're extremely
curious on how things work
and why certain things do what they do.
- Okay. So we're very curious creatures.
- How to make things in
everyday life easier?
- Ooooh! That segways to my
next question. Split apart!
Brody, take the catwalk.
Logan, take the catwalk.
Hey, you guys were my
first ones last time, too.
Aw, such love!
- I was the first one last time.
- Were you?
- Yeah!
- Oh, I just remember those
two catwalking together.
Okay. Shift us down two!
Super. Shift down two. And
a real quick hand ripple
to establish your partner.
Hand. Hand. Hand. Hand. Hand. Hand. Hand.
Hand. Hand. Hand. Hand. Hand.
Super! Okay.
The person who has ordered
the most ID badges this year
is going to answer the following question.
Shh!!
Here's your question.
Five. Four. Three. Two. Thank you.
"What motivation is there
to develop technology
to meet human needs?"
What motivation do scientists
have to create technology
that meets human needs? Think about it.
Go!
(animated conversation)
Okay. Split apart.
I'm just going to randomly
popcorn on this one.
Brandon, what'd you guys say?
- We came up with, make life easier.
- Okay. To make life easier. Alright.
What's something you guys said?
- Money and power.
- Money and power. Interesting.
What's something you guys said?
- To decrease death.
Like, medical science.
- Okay. So, let people live longer?
Probably also live more quality lives?
Excellent! Okay. Take the
catwalk. Take the catwalk.
Shift down two partners
once she gets down there.
Shift down two. Super!
And a quick hands up!
Hands. Hands. Hands. Hands. Hands. Uh oh!
There we go.
Hands. Hands. Hands.
Hands. Hands. Hands. Hands.
Now, everybody, take three steps that way.
One.
Two.
Three.
Super! Okay. This time, the
person with the longest hair
is going to answer the question.
"What evidence can you cite
from today's scientists
that we've discussed, where
something microscopic,
something you can't see, was
being sensed or manipulated?"
What is an example of the
scientists we learned today,
hold on, just one sec.
What is an example of
something the scientists
we learned about today,
hold on, hold on, hold on.
I had a request to restate the question.
"What is an example from
the scientists we learned
about today, using, sensing or manipulating
something that is microscopic
or can't be seen?"
Okay? Now go.
(animated conversation)
We certainly cannot see that.
Except on the macroscopic level,
we can see the results of it.
(teacher laughs)
Brandon decided to use a
lifeline called phone a poster.
So, Brandon, what was your answer?
- I found on, Thomas
Edison found radio waves.
- Okay. Very good. Face me, please.
Emily, what's something
you guys talked about?
- Marie Curie found radiation from atoms.
- Okay. Very good. Erin,
what's something you guys talked about?
(student murmurs)
- Okay. Very good. Take the
catwalk. Take the catwalk.
On the catwalk. Alright.
PG! PG! PG! Thank you!
(students laugh)
Scooch down. And, hands up!
Hands. Hands. Hands. Hands. Hands. Hands.
Super! Okay. The person,
whose last digit, in their
address, is the lowest,
is going to answer this question.
(students murmur)
Okay. Here is your question.
We talked a second ago about the fact
that scientists are naturally curious
about our natural world,
but many scientists
have learned to manipulate
our natural world.
"What is your opinion of
scientists manipulating,
using for our benefit, our natural world?"
Okay. Go.
(animated conversation)
Okay. Face me! Nice and
loud so everyone can hear.
Brian, what did your group discuss?
- We thought it all depended on humanism.
How they thought the humanism
in relation to all the other
creatures of the world, that
they feel like they're higher
than all the other creatures,
then they can do what they want
to the natural world.
- Okay. So, as long as
it's being used for good.
- I guess.
- Okay. With the benefit of humans or
the world in general?
Kind of a socialist view?
- The world.
- In general. Okay. John,
what did you guys say?
- Yeah, what did we say?
- Pretty much the same thing.
- The same thing, pretty much.
- Okay. So, are you, specifically,
looking at human needs
or more, global?
- Human.
- Okay. What about you guys?
What did you partnership talk about?
- That it was okay to a
point. There was a point when
you should not manipulate
the natural world.
Like, taking a dolphin from one ocean
and moving it to another.
- Okay. So, who should decide
what those points are?
- I don't know.
- Okay. Alright. That segways
us to the next question.
"If you were..."
Let's see, let's do this. The person
with the most buttons on is
going to answer this question.
(students murmur)
Okay. "If you were the
scientific consultant
to President Barack Obama,
what percentage of our National Budget,
should be spent on science, and why?"
Justify that amount. Go!
It's a percentage. So, we're
not talking a dollar amount.
What percentage?
(animated conversation)
Well, it doesn't really
matter. Do you think half
of our budget? Do you think
a third of our budget?
You think a quarter of our budget?
(animated conversation)
I don't know. You could delineate that.
Okay. I could tell by looking at you guys,
that we've got a couple of folks that feel
kind of passionately about this,
so spread back apart and face me.
What did you guys say?
- Well, I said that 15% is a good amount
because then, it puts enough
money forward to get going
and leaves money for
other things that we need.
- Okay. Now you guys had a
very specific take on it.
What did you guys talk about?
- We talked about if medical,
if the percentage was
accounting for medical
sciences, as well, as it should
and, if it is, then the
percentage should be increased
to help.
- Like 50 to 60%, if medical is included.
- Okay. So, we have to
look at the different
kinds of research. Are
we just studying stuff
to study stuff? Are we
developing a technology
that will help human
need? Are we looking at
medical? Alright. Very
good. Take the catwalk.
Take the catwalk.
On the catwalk.
They do their little turns on the catwalk.
Okay. Of the science, of the person...
- We haven't scooted.
- Oh, scoot down. I'm
out of order. Thank you.
Scoot down. I got so
excited about the questions.
Scoot down. Scoot down. We will! Okay.
Here we go. We're creatures
of habit sometimes.
Hands up, real fast. Make sure
you've got the right partner.
Uh huh. Uh huh. Uh huh.
There we go.
Okay. The person,
whose third, no.
The person whose last digit in
their cell phone number is the highest.