- [Teacher] I teach in
a second and third grade
combination class.
The students are arranged
in grade-level specific
table groupings.
This allows students to
complete any grade-level
specific projects together
and receive instructions
in a manner that's clear to them.
I also have a guided reading area.
And a independent reading corner.
All of the resources the students may need
are located around the
perimeter of the classroom
leaving access to the
center of the classroom,
the large rug area for all
of our class discussions
to take place.
As well as collaborative group work.
Students also have available
to them the reading corner
area as an area for
collaborative group work.
They have a listening
center where they access
books on tape and CD.
We have three computer
stations where children
word process completed writing projects,
or they do research on the internet.
But complete sentence,
okay for that first part.
All right, and then
someone who's taking turns.
So we're clear on the rubric
what my expectation is
when we walk around.
Questions?
- If they make a mistake,
do you want us to correct
their English or (inaudible)?
- You know what, what I think
is a nice way to correct
someone when they misspeak,
and I do this a lot,
so you might notice that I
restate what someone has said.
And that's part of being a good listener.
So, being able to recall or restate.
Something like, oh, I heard you say,
and then you restate it
in the way that might be
more appropriate.
That's a respectful
way of being a listener
and also a speaker when
you're trying to teach
and be a role model.
- I have a different idea, I think that is.
- Okay, so there's another way,
"I think that is," excellent.
So we're going to just try
this out and see how it goes.
We're going to try this out again,
and practice those cues.
- Are we the
same number as usual?
- Yeah, okay so here we go.
We're going to practice.
When you get to your pictures,
this is what I want you to do.
Right now, I have put, I
have this image of a whale
on, okay can you have a seat?
I need everyone sitting next
to their partners right now.
So what I want you to do
is, looking at this picture,
I want you to practice
right now in your group
sharing one or two things that you notice
in this picture.
What do you see?
So I want you to share
exactly physical features,
and use descriptive language
to talk about what you see.
Question?
(inaudible)
Hold on a second, sweetie,
I just called on Jonathan.
Just a second.
Question?
(inaudible)
- We're going to describe
with our partner.
So you're going to need
to turn to your partner.
Adam what did you?
- I don't really understand what that thing
in black is.
- You know, it's just a shadow.
It's a shadow.
This one?
It's just a shadow on the picture.
It just doesn't look very
clear the way it came out.
It's the shadow on the image, okay?
All right, so turn to your partner.
When I ring the bell,
number ones share first.
When I ring the bell, number twos share.
When I ring the bell,
I'm going to take some of
your descriptive language.
Sharing what you see.
(bell ringing)
(background chatter)
- Number twos.
(bell ringing)
- Okay, excellent.
So I'm going to pick a stick.
I'm going to go fishing in my sticks.
And when I call your
name I want you to share
either what you saw, or
what your partner saw, okay?
What was the detail that was shared?
And I'm going to write
it up on this sticky note
because I'm modeling now
what you're going to do
when you get to your stations.
Everyone's going to get
a stack of sticky notes
and you're going to get an
opportunity after you share
to record some of your
ideas of what you see.
Number 10, Cesar.
(inaudible)
Sorry?
You want to ask a question?
For a clarifying question?
- No, I was just making a comment.
Just I don't like it when there's only
like one sticky note for everyone.
Because then the first
group who goes there
puts like every single
little thing that they see.
And it takes up like maybe three-quarters
of the whole paper.
And then the next group
has like (inaudible).
- Okay, so we're going
to solve that problem,
because each individual
gets a sticky note, okay?
And then you're going to choose
where you're going to put it.
All right, so number 10, Cesar.
- [Cesar] Madelaine said that she saw
white spots and one on the bottom.
And she said an Orca,
and she saw
a very long tongue and sharp teeth.
- [Teacher] She actually named the animal,
which was an Orca.
She saw white spots on the bottom.
And what was the part about the teeth?
- (inaudible) and a few sharp teeth.
(background chatter)
- Oh sorry, and then sharp teeth.
Okay, so I wrote more than
one idea on this sticky note.
But what you're going to do is after we do
the conversation, after we
walk through the stations
and see the images and talk about it,
then you're going to go
back and record one idea
on the sticky note.
And put it onto the picture.
So let's try one more.
I'm going to turn it over.
So look at the picture,
and then I'm going to
ring the bell, you're going to share,
and I'll pick somebody else
to share what they see.
(bell ringing)
(background chatter)
- [Teacher] Okay, so who's
next, number 21, Roberto.
- My partner says, oh what I said?
- [Teacher] It can be what you said
or what your partner
said, whatever you decide.
His was good?
- I said that I see a pod
of Orca whales and their
dorsal fins sticking up out of the water.
- [Teacher] That was great.
So he has two points, that he sees the pod
which is how we refer to,
- [Students] A group.
- [Teacher] A group, excellent
use of the vocabulary.
The Orca whale, so he's named
the actual type of whale.
And he starts looking at the dorsal fins,
which is one of the physical features.
Not only of the Orca, but of what?
- The humpback doesn't.
- The humpback, that's right
it doesn't have a dorsal fin.
So which ones have the dorsal fin?
- All the others
ones except for that one.
(background chatter)
- [Teacher] There's a couple
of other ones as well.
- Blue whales don't.
- [Teacher] Blue whales,
good, good, good, good, good.
Eyes up here.
Are there any questions
on what I want you to do
when you go around to
the different stations?
Yes, Sarah.
- So how many sticky
notes are we going to get?
Like a couple, four or five?
- So, first I'm going to give you a chance
to walk around.
And then I'm going to
come around and I'm going
to give you some sticky notes.
- [Sarah] So you're going
to let us look at them
and then we're going to
pick which one we want
and put a sticky note on?
- Yes, exactly, exactly.
(background chatter)
- What's this?
This one's cool.
I see, some baleen,
which means it's a baleen whale.
And it looks like it has a big mouth.
And the baleen looks like it is,
some sort of bendy thing.
And on the bottom of
the baleen it's scary.
And it looks like it has
a big mouth which probably
means it is a very big baleen whale.
- I see a baleen whale with
a lot of crushed thingies.
And a person's touching it.
I'm not sure if it's a
real whale that's alive.
It might just be an exhibit.
- No, Jake.
- And (inaudible), so I don't really think
this is something that's underwater.
(background chatter)
- It's part of baleen.
It's like a baleen whale,
there's baleen, but.
(background chatter)
- [Boy] It looks like a Blue
Whale, because it is very big.
It also doesn't have any throat looms.
and it has just a small bump
for it's dorsal (inaudible).
It also looks like it's
swimming very close to the top.
And that also looks like
it's coming up for air.
(background chatter)
- I see a whale
that a man is touching their teeth.
- I'm not exactly sure
what type of whale this is,
but it's a whale.
- I see someone touching part of a whale,
and it might be part
of a baleen (inaudible).
I see a whale and I think it's coming
to the surface for a
breath because they cannot
breathe under water.
- I think that that is
a baleen whale because
it is, it is white
and it's a little bit gray.
((background chatter)
- I see a whale that is going up
to the surface of the water, and I believe
that it's a beluga whale.
- I see the whale.
I think it's going to jump out the water,
and then dive (inaudible).
- I see a big, gigantic, beluga whale
with his skin has a couple
like dents and wrinkles.
- And it doesn't have a dorsal fin.