- [Girl 3] And the climax is when
(Background Chatter)
Andy he throw the rubber ball
and told Bouncer to go and fetch it
but he just sit there
(Background Chatter)
and then
yeah, Then Andy called
Toby to go and show him how
to pitch the ball
- [Girl 1] Okay
- [Girl 2] (mumbles)
(Background Chatter)
- [Girl 2] Oh, almost part of the end is when
the puppy
that is Bouncer becomes crying
and then Andy
took the puppy to Toby
- [Girl 1] Yeah, in the beginning
I was getting like selfish.
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] May I interrupt for
a second, so you guys
it looks like you've developed
the beginning pretty well
and you found examples, right?
Have you talked about the ending yet?,
and how he was at the end? I
see you're on the back page.
How does Toby change at the end?
Have you guys talked about that part yet?
What's his character trait
at the end of the story?
- [Girl 1] We talked about the--
- [Teacher] Okay, so who was working on that part?
Was somebody working on that part?
Yeah, was there a trait that
you picked for him, at the end?
- [Girl 2] When...
the little puppy Bouncer
started crying
and Andy took the little puppy
Bouncer when Toby (mumbles)
- [Teacher] How did Toby change then?
How do we describe Toby then?
- [Girl 2] Happy
- [Teacher] Happy?, yeah can you give an example
of now that he's happy?
He's happy why?
- [Girl 2] Because he just (mumbles)
thinks anymore that (mumbles)
- [Teacher] Ohhh.(nods in approval)
Can you come up with another
reason, maybe together
if you guys can look for
another example as to why
at the end of the story Toby is happy?
Can you look and see if you can find one?
- [Girl 3] I think that Toby,
in the ending is kind
- [Teacher] Is kind? Okay, can you
come up with an example
and share it with them in the scene?
And then maybe you guys can
come up with a consensus
on one that you agree? Or you
can write two different things,
right? You don't all have
to write the same thing.
One of you can write he's kind
and one of you can write he's happy
as long as you have what?
(Pauses for an answer)
- [Girl 2] Your reason.
- [Teacher] Your reason, absolutely.
So share that other example.
Share that other example, too.
- [Girl 3] I think I've got he's kind.
Maybe because he's going
to be kind to Bouncer because
he's still like a little puppy
and he doesn't know how
to do stuff. I think.
- [Girl 1] Yeah, in the end
when he said
(Background Chatter)
for me at the end
he was getting kind of happy
because...
Andy told Bouncer to--
Andy told Toby to
to get the yellow ball.
You know the yellow ball.
- [Girl 3] Yeah
- [Girl 1] And Bouncer was
kind of tired and everything.
because he's-- he's small
and Toby, he catched it and
they were playing, yeah,
and they were getting happy
and Toby in the end at that part
he was used to liking Bouncer now.
- [Girl 3] Mm-hm
- [Girl 1] At the climax--
- [Girl 2] At the climax, it was when
(Pauses)
(Background Chatter)
It was when Toby...
When Andy told Toby
to show Bouncer how to fetch the ball
and then started fetching the ball
(Mumbles)
(Background Chatter)
and then he started to play
and Bouncer and
Bouncer danced on his bed
Bouncer tried
- [Girl 3] Okay
(Background Chatter)