- We are entertaining using second person
stories. Last time we were together, we
started a story here today called Aliens
in the Library. You saw that I put my name
up here on the line, and it says Aliens in
the Library. The introduction page is the
part where I underlined those 'you's. Did you
notice how these 'you's are underlined over
and over again? The reason is because we
don't typically write like this.
This is kind of unfamiliar for us.
We had fun making the beginning of this
story. We only wrote half of the story
using this graphic organizer. Do we
remember why we only wrote half of the story?
Why did we only write this
side of the story?
- Because that was, like the one story
[Inaudible]
- Right. There are two main things that
you can choose from. If you look up here
at the board, everybody should be looking
up here, you can see that there are two
choices for each one. You have your
introduction and you have your two
choices. We only did this half of the
story, so right now we're going to hide
the other half because we're not even
thinking about it yet.
So the story was that you're in the
library, you hear a noise like, what did
we say, rats in a blender? And so you go
out to investigate what the story was.
Now, that's the coolest part about this
project guys. The reason we are making our
own stories rather than me grabbing the
book from a shelf and copying it on here
is because we want to use information in
our own way. What's that called when you
take someone else's information and put it
on a piece of paper? What's that called?
Who can remember what that's called?
What's that called?
- Copyright infringement.
- Copyright infringement, or there's
another big 'p' word, too, that we talked
about. That's a tough one, do you remember
what that one is?
- Plagiarism.
- Plagiarism. And if you take a story of
someone else's and stick it on there, it's
a problem. And so, when you have a story
in your mind you want to make sure that it
is your story and your story alone. The
best way for me to describe this is, right
now for reading team we designed our own
t-shirts for a t-shirt contest. Maybe your
t-shirt isn't the winning entry, and the
team doesn't make your shirt on their
shirt. But you go to the competition, and
another team from another school district
has your shirt design on the front of it.
How would you feel about that? How would
you feel if someone took your idea and
walked around with your shirt on? Your
idea, that you came up with your in your
own brain? How would that make you feel?
- Kind of angry.
- It would make me feel angry.
How about you?
- Sad.
- Sad is another really good word for it.
I would be furious, if we used our
exciting words for our writing. But I
would also be really disappointed. Maybe
kind of flattered that someone liked my
idea so much they put it on their own
shirt, but it's the same thing. Is it
wrong to steal someone's bicycle?
- Yes.
- You think it's wrong. Why is it wrong to
steal someone's bicycle?
- Because that was just like stealing. You
steal without even asking.
- Right. And that would hurt someone's
feelings and it's illegal. Is it wrong to
steal someone's pencil?
Is it wrong to steal someone's pencil? Is
it wrong to steal someone's pencil? Why is
wrong to steal someone's pencil?
- Because it's their property.
- Because it's their property and it's not
yours. So stealing someone's ideas is the
same idea. So when you go to write your
stories, boys and girls, and the reason
we're writing our own stories is because
we're making this our own. We're making
this our own design. And I think that's
really important for us to remember,
because the more that you use your own
ideas, the better it is for you. You have
all these ideas in your heads, and I know
you all have wonderful creativity, so
we're writing our own stories. We're not
taking the story of a TV show you saw last
night like SpongeBob and you're not making
a SpongeBob story.
I want this to be your own idea.
So we have Aliens in the Library, and we
have our half here. You're a librarian,
you hear a strange noise, it sounds like
screeching rats in a blender, what should
you do? We decided our two choices were
open the door or hide under your desk. If
you open the door, you see the cutest
little alien standing in the doorway. I
think we had a majority of people here, I
don't know if everyone here likes the
cutest little alien idea, but this is our
story and we're sticking with it. It has a
big pink bow in her hair, antennae, and a
pink polka dot dress. What do you do?
You could either invite her in or slam the
door in fright. You invite her in. She,
surprisingly, speaks your language. She
explains that her name is Lott and she
became stranded when her spacecraft
crashed. She asks if she can come home
with you. What do you do? You have two
choices here. You can either take her home
or find another place for her to stay.
Lott is a great house guest, she even
helps with the dishes. You're glad you
decided to take a chance on making a new
intergalactic friend. You guys have seen
this before. We made this story, and I'm
not going to go over this story again and
again, but I wanted to review with you
what we talked about because over here,
I'm going to show you what the final
product is going to look like.
This is what the story is going to be
made. We did PowerPoint together. You're
familiar with PowerPoint. We've done
dozens of PowerPoints by now, at least.
And so, on our screen here I'm going to
open up my document that I made while you
were gone, and it is what the PowerPoint
is going to look like when you're
finished. It is a choose your own
adventure PowerPoint. And this is showing
that you've mastered the skill of being
able to use PowerPoint. You need to show
me that you understand how to use this.
This is kind of like our, I would say our
final exam for PowerPoint so we know we
can move onto the next thing, or the next
project, the next exciting idea that we're
going to do.
So while this is loading, you're going to
see that there are hyperlinks, and we're
going to work on those as well, which will
take you to different parts of your
document. So up here we have Aliens in the
Library by Mrs. Albright. I chose pictures
that are graphics from PowerPoint, or from
Clipart. The reason I did that is because
we own those. I did not take them from the
internet and drag them here. What happens
if you take them from the internet and
drag them here? They're someone else's
ideas, remember? They're someone else's
pictures. Yes.[Inaudible]
- You have to put the date and you have
the put the website. We have to, what do
we call it? Cite those. But we're not even
going to do the citation because this is
more about the writing of the project. So
we're going to do that instead. My Aliens
in the Library. I'm going to show you the
start of this, and then you're going to go
start writing your own story. So here's my
Aliens in the Library story. Now, the best
one from this class, the one that we find,
or two, that we like the best, we're going
to put on my website so the younger
students can access these from home, which
I think is a really great idea.
These are not going to be graphic or
bloody. You can have some things happen,
but you can't have guts falling out and
eyeballs popping out of heads. Okay?
Because this is for a young... you have to
remember your audience. This is for first
and second graders to use in the library
when they come. So we are not going to
make a big, bloody, messy, gory story.
Okay? We're going to make cute little
alien stories, apparently. This is what we
made last time together...
All right. You are a librarian. You stay
late one night working on your computer
and you hear strange noises coming from
the hallway. It sounds like rats in a
blender. What should you do? We chose to
do open the door. So when I click on the
button that says open the door, it should
take me to that page. Ta-da. You open a
door and you see the cutest little alien
standing in the doorway. She has a big
pink bow in her hair and antennae, and a
purple polka dot dress. What do you do
next? We're going to invite her in.
If we invite her in, she actually speaks
your language. She explains that her name
is Lott and she became stranded on Earth
when her spaceship crashed. She asks if
she can come home with you. What do you
do? I want to see what you guys pick for
this one. Who wants to pick one? Who wants
to pick a direction? What are we going to
do, take her home or find her another
place to stay?
- Find her another place.
- Find her another place? Let's see what
we decided for that part of the story. You
hear her shuffle down the hallway. You may
have missed the chance of a lifetime to
meet an alien, but at least you are safe.
The end. Now notice my ends always go back
to the beginning. So this is PowerPoint,
that you're familiar with, used in a
different way. Are there any questions
about what we did here? Yes.
- How do you get the green buttons?
- That's what we're going to talk about,
and that's a new part of the skill that
we're working on, but right now, we're
going to just be making these. I'm handing
out these. You're going to be in your
groups and we're going to start writing
our stories. After you're checked and over
there, you'll make your
PowerPoints, and I'll help you with your
hyperlinks individually in your tables.
- Does it...
- I'm sorry, she's talking.
- Does it have to be Aliens
in the Library?
- No, no. No, no, no. That's a great
question. It can be anything you want.
Any kind of story that you're interested
in. As long as it is not ...
- Bloody or gory.
- Bloody or gory or ...
- Violent.
- Violent, or, what's the other thing that
we just talked about?
- Inappropriate.
- Inappropriate or guts, you guys are
really stuck on the guts.
- Copyright.
- Copyrighted by somebody else. I wanted
to show you a couple other ones that you
can choose when you come for book
exchange. One of them looks like this.
This is actually a non-fiction choose your
own adventure about George Washington
crossing the Delaware, and it's about you
changing history which I think is a really
neat idea. If you're not much of a reader,
but you still wanted to read some books,
this one is very similar to actually, what
we're making here in PowerPoint. It has
graphics, it's called a graphic novel, and
there are different pieces that look
almost like comic books. I have several of
these also. I have the newer versions of
the old ones that I showed you
and read out loud.
The ones from 1986, remember I told you
how I liked them when I was a kid, a few
years ago? This one just has new covers on
it, so if you're looking for those. And
then this last one, this is a brand new
series that I'm hoping to get more on,
it's called The Golden Path and it's the
same idea, just different characters and a
different set of authors that made those.
So if you're looking for a choose your own
adventure story, and you go to type it in
the library catalog, you can type in
choose your own adventure. The problem
with that is you need to
know how to spell adventure.
- A-D-V-E-N-T-U-R-E.
- That's exactly right. Thanks, I wasn't
even expecting that. The other thing to
remember when we're keeping in mind, I'm
going to be coming around to help you with
your PowerPoints. Remember, we have to use
that rubric, that rubric. Show me that you
know what I'm talking about. Which rubric
am I talking about? Show me. Show me your
papers. Yes. This is the one that you need
to do. Also, you can put that down. This
other one that I want you to remember, the
other thing to keep in mind, is we color
coded these and we numbered them. The
slides need to go in the order that you
need it to be. This is a review of
PowerPoint, so this shouldn't be anything
new that you haven't seen before.
This is kind of our graduation project for
PowerPoint so that we can move on to the
next project, next time. So we're working
with PowerPoint. Who remembers how to
insert a text box? What were the
directions? We went over this before, and
we went over it a couple different times.
How do we insert a text box?
- You go to insert, you go over under the
text box, click on it,
and then you'll drag it and there it is.
- There it is. And how do you make it
change color? Does anyone remember how we
make it change color? How do we make it
change color? We're on insert and text
box. And make sure you make one down here.
Yep. And then you can type in it, and then
you do what with it? That's not wanting to
cooperate is it? That's okay. Let's work
on this one together. If you click on text
box, you make the text box and you start
typing in it. Who remembers how we change
the color of the text box? That's what
we're going to need to be able to do for
our buttons and our hyperlinks that we
talked about. Who remembers?
- You double-click on the box and it will
show up...
- Right. You double click on the box, or
sometimes even triple click until you get
those three a's at the top, then you can
change your color. I'll be around to help
you. Are there any questions about this
right now? Anyone have anything that they
want to talk about before we get started.
Every slide has to have a picture. What
happens if you do not have a picture that
you like from Clipart? What do you do? I
want you, I'm encouraging you to use
Clipart because it's something that's
already there and we don't have to worry
about where the source came from. But what
do we do if you want to find a different
picture somewhere else? What do we do?
- Find your picture.
- You can find your picture under Google
images. Then what do we do?
- Then you copy it and then you put it
back, and then we copy the source.
- You have to have the source. Very good.
Very, very good. Okay. If you would like
to have a whole separate slide with
sources, you can do that.
And we've done that before.
- And the date.
- And the date is very important. I'm glad
that you remembered that. Okay, so I'll be
around to help you, go ahead and get
started back again on your project. Make
sure the slides are in order. Do you want
to format your designs? You go under
design, you two can agree on a color
scheme. Do you like that one? That's good.
Let's look back at your thing. Let me see
which one was number two. That was number
three. Click on number two. And it should
be, exactly, boys, look at how you did
that. You put the words at the top, now I
did check the word vial on yours and it's
spelled wrong. V-I-A-L. Maybe my writing
is hard to read. And then you have the two
text boxes here at the bottom. If
something gets stuck, can I have you guys
be the experts and go over and help them?
- Sure.
- Okay, great. Thanks. Yes.
- Can you help us?
- Sure. What's the problem?
- We can get
[Inaudible]
- Well this one we want to get rid of.
Remember, when you go to do the insert and
you insert a new slide, you want to make
sure that the layout is the title only.
Remember how we talked about that one? So
you want to insert the text box. You show
me, what do we do? Right. And then what do
we do? Okay, so you drag it. What are you
typing in there? Okay. So you need how
many text boxes then? Exactly. All right,
so you go ahead and type in there so you
can show me you know what to do with that.
Can you click on it and then, use
typing? Upstairs.
Okay, now you want to, how do we make sure
you pull that up? There you go,
Are you okay
with all the pink?
- I don't care.
- Good. Make sure everyone's input is
added, though. Maybe he can help with the
graphics. Everyone needs to be able to do
something. We have to make sure this is
fair for everybody. You're working the
mouse, you're working the keyboard and
he's holding the paper. Let's maybe switch
it up a little bit closer, okay?
So everyone has a turn.