- [Teacher] Trying to find
meaning for their lives,
or were they just trying to,
what were they questing for, do you think?
- [Blonde girl] Well,
Gilgamesh was questing
for like immortality,
and that was for him,
and not really his people,
but Theseus I think was,
I don't know.
- [Girl with short hair] I think Theseus
was just trying to help
the people of Athens.
I don't think either of them
were really looking to find that,
but they both ended up finding it.
- [Girl in green] I think both of them
were like looking to help their people,
and then I also think
like a small part of them
was looking for glory.
- [Girl in white] I think it's kind
of like looking for their destiny,
like they know they're
meant for something bigger,
but they don't know what it is yet,
so they're just looking
for what that is, so....
- [Haley] Then he goes to take the test,
and the test kills him. Or not.
Then, he goes back to his father,
and he realizes that he's just like,
you know, the father's really
disappointed in the son,
and then he's really
disappointed until the son,
I think it could happen
in today's society.
I don't know about Gilgamesh.
- [Girl in red shirt] Well yeah, it
was a really like--
- [Haley] Abstract, connecting--
- [Girl in red shirt] In the really broad
sense, it could happen,
but like --
- [Haley] Like the story line.
- [Girl in red shirt] But when you
look at details, then like, no.
- [Haley] But I mean, minotaurs don't exist.
So it probably couldn't happen.
- [Girl in red shirt] But like you
were saying, like metaphorically,
it could be something, that, you know.
- [Haley] Like the storyline could happen.
- [Boy in blue] But metaphorically, you
could compare anything.
- [Girl in white shirt] That's true.
- [Teacher] Can you explain
more of what you mean
by metaphorically?
- [Girl in red shirt] Like me.
- [Girl with bangs] No, the
only one was like (Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] You mean hypothetical.
- [Girl with bangs] Theseus, not like he
goes and fights a minotaur,
and when he comes back,
he's like not dead,
but his dad thinks he's
dead and kills himself.
But it's like Haley said, I guess.
- [Haley] Thanks!
- [Girl with bangs] If you have like a test,
and like you're bad--
- [Girl in red shirt] Like a difficult situation
in general.
- [Girl with bangs] Yeah, and like your dad or
parents or someone are like,
"You can get through this,"
like, "You can beat it,"
and they think that you,
or like they think that you fail it,
or like catastrophe fail it,
or they think you do,
then they're gonna be kind
of disappointed in you,
but like they're not gonna
necessarily kill themselves
because you failed a test.
- [Haley] But still.
- [Teacher] You can laugh
if it was someone else.
- [Haley] But maybe like on the inside, he's dying.
- [Girl with bangs] Yeah.
- [Haley] Your turn.
- [Girl in red shirt] Okay, I just said, what
factors have to be changed
to make this apply to modern times?
- [Haley] Well, the--
- [Girl in white shirt] Probably the
whole like
fantasy aspect of it
would have to be changed.
- [Girl in red shirt] At least like
in the...
to the culture, like the
gods and goddesses aren't
like a, you know--
- [Girl with bangs] Big deal?
- [Girl in red shirt] Yeah.
- [Haley] I think that the gods and goddesses
kind of like connect with like
the people that are, not like in charge,
but that are higher up in our society,
like the government people,
and like parents and--
- [Girl in red shirt] I just think
more like mentors, in general.
- [Haley] Yeah, like people
that are higher than us.
- [Girl in red shirt] Like anyone
technically could like, you know,
that you look up to, that
you rely on for help.
- [Haley] It's like a figure,
rather than like-- - Yeah.
- [Girl in red shirt] A physical--
- [Haley] Yeah, god.
- [Girl in red shirt] God. Yeah.
- [Haley] Well my question was,
show the similarities
and differences between
Theseus and his father.
- [Girl in white shirt] Ooh, okay.
So, I think
like they both kind of,
they're very different
in their terms of like
loss and like failure.
Because like when Theseus's dad
like thought that he was like dead,
then he jumped off a cliff
and committed suicide.
But when like Theseus like
was with Ariadne or whatever,
and she like helped him to
like defeat the minotaur,
then he just kind of, you
know, left her on an island.
- [Haley] I think that,
I don't really remember how he got
in the situation of having to give
the people on Crete
seven maidens and seven children,
but like, I just think
that because that happens,
and because he does that every year,
I think Theseus is a better leader,
he's just like better in charge of--
- [Girl with bangs] I think that they're
definitely like
different rulers, too.
Because like Theseus is more,
like including the people like when
he goes and like he led
his army against Thebes,
but doesn't try to like--
most people would like try to steal stuff
from the city,
but he's just going to like bury the dead,
and then he leaves.
So like that's more of
a nicer leader I guess,
whereas his dad wasn't really like
put in that situation,
but I'm guessing that he
would be one of those people
who would probably take
stuff from that city,
and not include people very often.
- [Haley] It says that (Background Chatter)
- [Girl in gray] Because he lived
with his mom,
so he didn't want to have a son.
So then when he could lift the rock,
then he could come over and meet his dad.
- [Boy on far right] Is this question number--
- [Girl in brown] No, we're still asking,
predict what would happen
if King Aegeus and Enkidu hadn't died.
- [Girl in dark jacket] If the king hadn't died,
I think the son would have come back
and they just would have
lived happily ever after,
and there would have been no like--
- [Girl in brown](Background Chatter)
--not formed,
you know what I'm talking about?
Because King Aegeus--
- [Girl in gray] No, but he
would have died sometime,
and then Theseus would have taken over.
- [Girl in brown] Yeah, that's true.
- [Teacher] Can you go, dig a little
deeper with what you said
about the democracy?
What did you mean by that?
- [Girl in brown] Oh, just like
right when King Aegeus died,
Theseus came over and said,
"We're going to have a democracy
"instead of me ruling over all of you."
So like, we don't know if
that would have happened,
or because if he just
would have stayed alive,
he could have like changed Theseus' mind
and made him think a
democracy was a bad idea.
- [Teacher] Mm-hmm.
- [Girl in brown] Yeah.
He would've wanted him to be--
he would have that as king.
He would've been more like his dad.
- [Girl in dark jacket] Yeah, that's true.
- [Girl in gray] But if Enkidu didn't die,
then Gilgamesh would
probably like be happy,
and then like, conquer
a bunch of other stuff,
and like they would
probably like die together.
- [Boy in crew cut] She
could have sent him to Athens
to claim him as his--
- [Girl in brown](Background Chatter)
- [Boy in crew cut] Oh, okay, nevermind.
- [Boy on far right] You're allowed to go on.
- [Boy in crew cut] All right.
- [Girl in dark jacket] No, if
Enkidu didn't die, though,
I just think that Gilgamesh
wouldn't have really known--
like you know how they said he was
really arrogant in the beginning?
I think he still was kind of arrogant,
until Enkidu died, so he--
- [Girl] He would have stayed like that.
- [Girl in brown] Yeah, he would have stayed that way.
- [Girl in brown] Mm-hmm. Because
he went through like
a stage of depression, so.
- [Girl in dark jacket] Yeah.
- [Teacher] Do you think that each
one reached humility
at the end, or no?
Do you think that Gilgamesh, you said,
was still arrogant, even at the end?
- [Girl in dark jacket] No.
- [Teacher] Oh, he wasn't?
- [Girl in dark jacket] Not after Enkidu
died, but once he died,
it stopped of course, but--
- [Boy with crew cut] I think Gilgamesh
was arrogant until he found out
that he wasn't going to be immortal.
- [Girl in brown jacket] Well yeah, that, too.
Because then he had to like
live his life to the fullest
because he couldn't live forever.
He couldn't do whatever he wanted.
- [Girl in dark jacket] Who's your favorite
character between each story?
Out of the stories?
- [Girl in brown] Theseus.
- [Girl in dark jacket] Yeah, I like Theseus, too.
- [Boy in crew cut] We all like Theseus.
- [Boy on far right] Yeah.
- [Boy in white] It also said that Theseus
was grieving.
- [Girl in maroon] Was grieving her loss,
or his father's loss?
- [Boy in white] It was both.
- [Girl in white] Debate which character
had more impact
on their society.
- [Teacher] Can you say that one more time?
- [Girl in white] Debate which character
had more impact
on their society.
- [Teacher] Oh, she has the "debate" word in there.
Okay, let's hear it.
- [Boy in yellow] I'd say Gilgamesh--
- [Girl in gray] I would say--
- [Boy in yellow] ...he wants to be king.
- [Teacher] Let's let him finish his reason.
What's your reason?
You think who?
- [Boy in yellow] I think Gilgamesh.
Actually, I think Theseus would,
because he changed the kind
of structure of government,
and made it democratic.
That's it.
- [Girl in maroon] Yeah, I would agree
with you there in the way that
he kind of completely changed
the government structure where he lived,
while kind of Gilgamesh would probably
be one of those leaders
that is better forgotten
than remembered, and memory lived on
is not probably a theme in that story.
While Theseus kind of left his ways
and his story behind.
That people remembered on high,
rather than as like a low
point of their society.
- [Teacher] Weren't you
going to say something?
- [Girl in gray] Oh, I was?
- [Teacher] I thought you were.
- [Girl in gray] I think Theseus was, had an impact.
- [Teacher] And the reason for that?
- [Girl in gray] Because he like survived more
than Gilgamesh did, and he
helped people out of the maze,
with Adrian's help, right? Yeah.
Predict what would happen if the King
and Enkidu didn't die.
- [Girl in maroon] Well--
- [Boy in blue] I don't think
Athens would be democratic.
I don't think the king would have done it.
- [Girl in maroon] Yeah, he probably
would have been poisoned.
- [Teacher] Why is that?
- [Boy in yellow] Gilgamesh--
- [Boy in blue] I don't know, because--
- [Boy in yellow] Gilgamesh probably
wouldn't have been searching
for immortality.
- [Girl in maroon] Yeah, he wouldn't have
gone on that Journey.
- [Boy in yellow] Yeah.
- [Girl in maroon] Okay, well my question is:
how would you have handled some of the
tough situations that
each of the characters
had to go through?
- [Girl in gray] Wait, what was the question?
- [Girl in maroon] How would you have
handled the situations?
- [Teacher] Wouldn't have done any of them?
- [Girl in gray] No, I get scared
really easily, and stressed,
so that would not be good.
- [Boy in yellow] (mumbles) the Labyrinth thing.
- [Teacher] Sorry, I didn't hear what you said.
- [Boy in yellow] I wouldn't go to
the Labyrinth thing.
- [Teacher] Why is that?
- [Boy in yellow] It kind of sounds like a bad idea.
- [Girl in maroon] I might go and
just not defeat the beast,
and in the first place, I probably would
have traveled by water,
and not just said, "I'm too
good for that, it's too easy."
Because, I--
- [Boy in yellow] Bandits have sharp swords.
- [Girl in maroon] Yeah.
- [Girl in gray] Okay, what's yours?
- [Boy in black] Choose your favorite
character and explain why.
From, because you like
Gilgamesh or Theseus.
- [Girl in gray] Okay.
Oh, not like our favorite
character, just in the story?
- [Boy in black] Yeah. Well either way,
it doesn't really matter.
- [Girl in gray] Well because my
favorite character from Gilgamesh
was Enkidu? Is that how you say it?
Because I think he like really changed
Gilgamesh for the better.
And helped him and humbled him.
- [Teacher] Do you agree with that?
- [Girl in green] Yeah, I agree with that,
because I feel like he was kind of--
like Gilgamesh was so awful,
and like Enkidu came in
and just changed all that.
Plus, I thought that it was kind of cool,
his journey from like a
savage to the civilized guy.
Yeah.
- [Girl with short hair] I don't think that Enkidu
really meant to change Gilgamesh, though,
I think that it was just the circumstances
surrounding his death
that made that happen.
- [Girl in green] Enkidu's mom kind of made
that happen, too, didn't he?
- [Teacher] Did you feel like Enkidu
was just kind of created,
that he, I mean we were
saying that we like him,
but did he seem real to you,
or was he just something created?
- [Girl white] See, when I read it, the entire time,
he just kind of seemed like this robot
that the gods had
created to fix Gilgamesh,
so he didn't really have that
much of a personality to me,
so that's my opinion, I don't know.
- [Girl in green] Yeah, he seemed
like his pretty much
sole purpose of existence was
to balance out Gilgamesh.
- [Girl with short hair] And he did.
- [Girl in green] Yeah, he did.
- [Boy in black] My favorite character
from these stories
was Ariadne.
- [Teacher] Oh.
- [Boy in black] Well, because I
didn't feel sorry for her,
because she helped Theseus,
and like without her, he
would have been trapped
in the Labyrinth.
But then to repay her, he
just ditched her on an island,
and just left her, so
that wasn't very nice.
So I feel sorry for her, that's why.
- [Girl in gray] Okay, mine is:
how would you have dealt
with these situations in (mumbles)
- [Teacher] Can you repeat it one more time?
- [Girl in gray] How would you have
handled these situa--
(audio cuts out)
- [Girl in green] I wouldn't run away from the--
- [Girl in green] I would not have gone
on this journey.
I probably just would have
stayed home, not gonna lie.
- [Teacher] Do you feel like, that
people, to be great,
have to go out in the world
and seek these amazing achievements,
that that's what greatness is?
- [Students] Not necessarily.
- [Girl in white] I don't think you
necessarily have to seek them.
It all really depends on what your
definition of greatness is.
- [Girl in green] I feel like to get that
like glory and all that,
I mean, I think you can do that,
if you have enough impact where you are,
you don't need to go off on a journey.
- [Teacher] What do you think, Dinesh?
- [Girl with short hair] I don't know, I feel like,
if we're going by the
definitons as you would see them
within these stories, that
obviously you don't have to,
I don't think you have to
seek greatness, necessarily,
I don't think you have
to seek it to find it,
but I think that you do have to go off,
if you're just going
to stay where you are,
you're not really going to
be able to achieve it.
- [Teacher] So if you just sit on your front porch
and watch your life go
by, that's not greatness.
That can't constitute--