- So, good morning everyone.
- Good morning.
- Good morning, today,
today, what we have is,
we're going to have a debate
based on a couple things
that we have recently experienced.
One was research that we have
conducted about the chemistry
in scientific measurement
that's required in order
to address a local issue that we have
with current regulations on water
and different lobbying
groups trying to change
those regulations for their own interests
and the groups they represent.
Okay.
And so we had a field trip
to Wastewater Treatment Plant
that allowed us to gain
information locally from scientists
to see what they're doing on their side
and what their opinions are
for either side of this debate
that is current in our city.
So, today I'm going to start
with our overarching question
which has really helped us in our research
and is now going to help us
to just devise our debates.
The overarching question
is up on the board
if you'd like to see it.
It says, how is scientific
measurement applied
in the creation
and the regulation of our local
environmental protection laws?
The environmental protection
side over here is proposing
new tighter regulations
that may have an impact
on local businesses and rate payers,
or the people who pay for the
water utilities in our city.
So, I'll discuss the format of our debate.
First, and that's, again, up on the board.
I will be finishing up
my introduction here,
and then we will have our lobbyist group
introduce themselves, who they represent,
and what their major goals
are for today's debate.
Okay.
Then we'll have a question
session where each group
will be able to probe into the reasoning
and the deeper understandings
to reveal your research
and each side of the story,
so that our City Council members
on our outer rows back here
will be able to reflect
upon what is being said.
So, city council members,
please be writing your notes.
When we get towards the end
of our debate time period
we will then have you folks make a debate.
It's going to be a vote on whether
or not we should agree with
the environmental side and
their decision to make
tighter regulations to
change current regulations
to allow lower levels into the water
of various different chemicals
that they will be discussing.
Okay.
At the end, each side will
have a one minute opportunity
to discuss a focus summary
statement in which they will
be able to summarize the
things that have been revealed
during today's debate.
(student coughs)
Good.
And then, as I said, at the
end we will have a vote.
City Council will vote on whether
we should
make the restrictions tighter
on the water quality
standards in our city.
Are there any questions before we begin?
Okay, excellent.
And so, I believe the,
this side had choice,
and so that means that
Corbin and his group,
for representing industry,
will be allowed to have that closing,
the last closing statement today.
And so we'll start with Tyler,
and then we'll try to go
back as fairly as possible,
back and forth.
So Tyler, if you'd like to
start with your opening comments
about who you represent
and why you're here today.
- Our side of the argument
focuses on the environmental side
of the debate.
We believe that new water
regulations via legislation
that would more effectively
treat our drinking water
should be enacted.
The hazardous and deleterious chemicals
that are in our water,
particularly the excesses amounts
of nitrogen and phosporous
need to be controlled.
While it may negatively affect the selfish
interests of industry our
group would like to promote
the idea that doing nothing
and leaving our water
the way it is is not an option.
- [Teacher] Excellent.
So Corbin, we're ready to hear your side
and who you represent.
- Our side focuses on the
business aspect of this debate.
We hope to persuade the
EPA and City Council
to agree that the waste
water that we put back
into creeks and streams meets the criteria
that is currently the
standard for cleanliness.
And that it does not need improvement
except for a few chemicals
which does not improve
nitrogen and phosphorous
or that we do not need to
severely increase taxes
to pay for all of that.
- Outstanding.
And so, and then we will
begin, I guess, then,
with Tyler who can go ahead now,
and you can ask your first question.
And we'll be looking for
City Council members.
If you have any questions
that need to be clarified,
statements that you
would like to determine
what the reasoning is behind it,
please raise your hand,
and we'll make sure that
you get in immediately.
Okay.
(teacher mumbles)
(students quietly talking)
(student laughing)
This is so funny.
- Okay, we figure that since
you say that our waters
don't really need to be,
it already meets the
standards of cleanliness,
but already in Colorado
we see fresh water species
that are becoming more
endangered, as the more chemicals,
because of the pollution
that is put into our waters
via industries like metals and dentistry.
21 out of 822 Native American fish species
have already become
endangered and extinct,
and we just would like to
know why you think that
that means that the water's clean enough.
- Okay, let me ask you this.
Do you have information on what
chemicals killed those fish?
- We have like the excess
amounts of nitrogen
and phosphorous that the EPA,
the standards that they're
trying to enforce now.
Like we saw on the video,
this creates the dead zones
because it removes oxygen
and the algae, algae
blooms start to produce.
So, it's mostly the nitrogen phosphate
that's preventing the
correct amount of oxygen
in the water for the fish
to breathe, technically.
- Okay.
I'd like to follow this
up with an article from,
I believe this is from the Gazette,
which is our Colorado Springs newspaper.
Since we're focusing
this debate on Colorado,
most likely our city,
we see that our city
does not have a problem
with algae blooms, says
the writer of this article.
So, therefore, when you
talk about algae blooms,
we don't have a problem with this.
So why should we be focusing on it?
- Because the water runs off the lakes.
That does cause a problem with us.
- Okay.
But even if we did have, I mean, a few...
(Damon mumbles)
Like I said again, our city does not
have problems with these.
So we can't, therefore,
we can't focus our debate on these things
because it doesn't apply to us.
- Well, that one article
in a local newspaper from one writer
said that we don't have
problems with algae blooms.
But I've been in the
mountains around our area,
and I've seen many lakes,
ponds, just completely covered
with algae and scum.
And that so many of our local creeks,
Monument Valley Park,
and stuff, are just
littered with gross algae,
and it creates these dead
zones that the fish swim into
and do not have any way to swim out of
because they have no nutrients in them
and just die on the spot.
- And the same thing happened
in the 1960s with Lake Erie,
and it later happened with Chesapeake Bay
like we saw in the video.
And the same thing was
happening where they said
we don't need to fix it everything's fine,
and then just as nothing,
nobody did anything.
The lake soon was dead,
and it was like, there's no fish in there.
And the water's just completely ruined
with all kinds of chemical wastes,
so doing nothing isn't really...
- Okay, so I'm gonna interject.
What I'm hearing is that
there's a debate in here
about whether or not our
local water is an issue,
so I'd like to hear from
somebody in the City Council area
who will be making a vote today.
How about your thoughts about
the current water quality?
What you have heard from your
constituents in the areas
where you are located
and to determine whether
or not you feel currently,
right now, what level of danger are we at?
Have you heard a lot about this?
Do you feel like we are
in need of serious change?
So, we can direct
the rest of the debate.
Okay.
Anybody who would like to contribute?
Okay, Stephan.
- Well, all I know is that where
we're located, we're at the,
we're pretty much the first
people that use our water,
and then it goes downstream
for other people to use it, so,
so when we were talking about
eliminating the pollution,
the pollutants that we put into the water,
it's not, it wouldn't be
really affecting our city,
but the cities that are
down the stream from us.
- Okay, but this article
says that our, excuse me,
I think I read this wrong,
our state does not have a
problem with algae blooms.
- Regardless of the algae problem,
it says without the
oxygen, the fish, bugs,
and other organisms that
live in the water will die,
and quoting from the same article it says
in the worst case scenario
you basically have water
devoid of all natural aquatic life.
- But that's a worst case scenario
that we don't have right now
and we haven't had,
and it's not an issue in Colorado.
Granted, it might be an
issue in like Chesapeake Bay,
or Lake Erie.
(Theo mumbles)
- But we don't have it here, it says so.
And multiple scientists have
backed that article as well.
- Now Corbin, do you
have any measurements,
or do you have some values
that you can back that up with?
- Not specifically on
nitrogen and phosphorous.
I tried to find some, but I found...
- So, does anybody have
any of that information
because we want to know
how close to danger are we.
(students talking quietly)
Do we know about current levels
or about where we want to go with this?
(female student mumbles)
- Okay I would like to comment on...
(Damon mumbles)
- I'm sorry, behind you,
I just called on her.
- Oh, excuse me.
- So, even if it's probable,
wouldn't you want to prevent it
from like happening here,
with the algae?
(Female student mumbles)
- Well, if it's not happening already then
what do you have to do to
keep it from happening?
(Female student mumbles)
Yeah, if it happened, but
it hasn't happened yet.
- Yeah, but what she's saying
is it might happen.
- Yeah.
- I mean just saying that
something might happen
is just like saying something awful might.
I mean I could say that, you know,
an earthquake might
kill everyone tomorrow.
It might happen.
We don't know if it's going to happen.
- But fish and other organisms are dying.
It is happening.
It's not necessarily just the algae,
but it's the future problem.
We've already seen issues with the...
- [Teacher] Yeah, let's
see what Nina has to say
as far as City Council.
- Well, I just have a question,
wouldn't it be better
to be safe than sorry?
_ You're right, it would be
better to be safe than sorry,
but like I said
the levels of toxins
in the water right now
do meet the EPA required standards.
So, therefore, it is a safe level
according to the scientists
who work for the EPA.
- But we're saying that the EPA standards
need to be improved.
- [Damon] Yes, yes, we realize that.
- Because they're not, they're too low,
and there are many chemicals that are new
because of new industry in metal companies
and many other things that
are dumping into streams.
And those chemicals are getting through.
- How would you go about doing this?
How would you go about
stopping the pollution?
Because something that's
important to remember here
is the fact that the
pollution is not only caused
by industry it's something
that's misconcepted,
is for example cars.
People think cars pollute the air,
and it exactly does pollute the air.
But when it goes up and
it becomes acid rain
and it falls back into our
creeks it's also a pollutant.
Therefore, industry's not the only people
who are polluting the lakes.
It's actually U.S. citizens
doing the same work too.
- [Teacher] Okay, I like that.
And so, can you be more specific?
Did anybody gain anything on the fieldtrip
about learning about which types of things
the citizens in our area are
putting down their drains?
- Yes.
- [Teacher] That may cause issues?
- [Teacher] Okay.
- I've got a whole bunch of them.
- [Teacher] Alright, Corbin,
why don't you share then
what it is?
- You want me to read all of them, or just?
- [Teacher] So, we're not
focusing just on one group.
There may be other groups as well,
but also maybe it could be addressed
as a result of this debate.
Go ahead, Corbin.
(male student mumbles)
- Well, the guy that we
had giving us the tour
of the wastewater facility
did make some funny comments
that he's found some
pretty ridiculous things
in the water treatment plants.
Some of those examples were
railroad ties, dentures,
and he found a live person
inside of them one time.
So, it's not like the waste
treatment plant is purposely
putting all this out there.
It's, you can't stop humans
from putting out waste,
and a lot of the stuff that
they're putting in there
that they're actually reducing the levels
to parts per a billion
or parts per a trillion,
which some of the machines there do do,
are poisonous things like fluoride.
Which actually, the highest
water treatment plant
that puts out the most
fluoride is actually Mason,
which is right up there,
and lead and mercury.
And it eliminates that
from parts to a billion
from parts to a trillion.
(Damon and Corbin laugh)
- Well, first of all,
I would like to answer
Mr. Dunmar's question,
or Mr. Waz' question.
I'm sorry...
(Amanda mumbles)
We do have information
on how much nitrogen is required
in the water,
and it's 10 parts per million.
So, that's just to answer that question,
and then to move on to yours.
Yes, of course, as you
said in your own words,
you can't stop people from the
pollution that they do cause.
However, it is the job of
the water treatment plants
to kind of remove that
pollution and to produce
a safe environment.
And when we don't have
strict enough regulations
this environment is endangered
for not only for people,
but for also the
wildlife, for the economy,
for, you know, natural systems
that occur within Colorado.
It's all, you're putting
it all on the line.
- Okay, let's talk about
what would happen if we did
restrict pollutants
that go into the water.
- [Amanda] Okay.
- Well, let's talk about
the costs that everybody's, the citizens
are going to be paying
that they said that all our
state is going to be paying.
- Before you talk about cost,
would you rather pay more
and be safe or pay less and risk dying?
- Okay. I would like to comment on that.
That's an asinine statement because
do you have a statistic on how many people
have died from water pollution?
- I do have a statement
from the
Secretary General of the
United Nations. Ban Ki-moon
says, "More people die from
unsafe water than from all
forms of violence including war."
- [Damon] You just said
from the United Nations.
- Yeah, this isn't,
yes, we're talking
about a local issue now,
but that is a statement that proves that.
- Okay, I would like to
comment on this once more,
when you said United Nations that's...
- [Teacher] Okay, I'm sorry.
We're going to have to go
to hand raising I believe
because we're getting
too fast of an answer
before someone gets a chance to finish.
So, Theo finish up,
and then Corbin will follow behind you.
(teacher mumbles)
- No, I made my point.
- Okay.
- Well, like you said, you do
realize that's a local issue,
but the U.N. is United
Nations of the world.
So, that's not a local issue.
You're bringing up a fact that's
from countries like Africa
that don't have clean water
at all, nonetheless water.
So, of course they're going to
die from water poisoning,
but here in the United States,
we have the cleanest water
in the world, no matter where it is.
And Colorado also has one of the cleanest
state populations of water, if you will,
out of all the states.
- Yeah, because of the
regulations we have in place,
and with the new chemicals
that are being put into our water,
we need to restrict our regulations.
- [Damon] What are the new chemicals?
- [Corbin] Yeah, they've
been there for awhile.
- We're having new problems though.
- [Damon] Can you explain it?
- Everything such as
nitrogen and phosphorous.
- [Corbin] It hasn't been an issue before.
Why is it an issue now?
- It has been an issue.
- It absolutely has.
- It has happened all
over the United States.
- [Damon] Okay, when
we talk about nitrogen,
we're talking about if we restrict that
we're talking about maybe
shutting down part of
what we do here.
As we all know that we
are, we do grow many crops
in our state.
And nitrogen, mostly where it comes from,
is fertilizers used in that industry.
So, to say that we're going to
restrict nitrogen would be,
we might have to restrict
or shut down some industries
that do produce food.
- [Amanda] Such as what? What industries?
- For fertilizers.
- Fertilizers.
- You can't use fertilizers on your lawn
because if you have...
- And not even lawn, crops.
- Crops, lawns, anything
because the fertilizer you use
goes down drains,
which go into creeks,
which is really polluting
it more than the wastewater
facility was.
- So, shouldn't the wastewater
facility pollute it less
since we already have natural pollution
coming from these facilities?
(Amanda mumbles)
- We're already doing so much to prevent
these chemicals from going into...
- Okay so Will, I hear you're
saying that we're doing a lot.
What was learned on the
field trip? Specifically
what role do the scientists play
who are employed by our city?
What role do they play at the
wastewater treatment plant?
And how does that affect
your group's goals
for today's debate?
What are the scientists
doing, specifically,
and how does it support your side?
(classroom mumbles)
- Like they said on the fieldtrip,
they use bacteria, E.coli,
to break down the wastewater
that's in the water.
It's not like they're
adding pollutions to it.
Their job is to take it out,
which they are trying to do.
By doing that, they add some
phosphorous and nitrates
that are just byproducts of it,
but they remove a lot of those afterwards.
It's not like to clean it 100%,
it's going to cost 25 billion dollars,
and that's just for the state of Colorado.
- [Teacher] Okay, let's see
a City Council members.
I'm trying to get to them quickly.
I'm sorry, Amanda, behind you, Stephan.
- Where did you get that information that
it would cost 25 billion dollars?
- [Damon] This is from the Gazettte.
- [Cole] The Gazette article.
- [Corbin] It's from the article.
- Science has proven that to
remove nitrogen and phosphorous
from the water,
which is you guys's goal to restrict it,
it's going to cost about 25 billion
dollars to remove it all.
If you just want to do parts of it,
it's still going to be 2.46 billion dollars.
- Which is four times
the amount of what it is
costing right now to remove
the things from the water.
- Wouldn't that be better tough than
having to
fix up a completely good
stream that destroys the economy.
- Well I actually, on the fieldtrip,
I asked several of the
chemists that work there
whether the pollutants that
we put into Fountain Creek
and what we're doing for the environment,
and they said the water they
put back into Fountain Creek
is the water they get out of it.
It's cleaner than that.
- Yeah.
- So, in my opinion,
that statement is totally absurd.
We're putting cleaner water for nature,
and nature seems to enjoy it more
as I asked the chemist as well.
And farmers down stream
also enjoy that water
to water their crops,
and it helps their crops grow more than
Fountain Creek's streams already.
- [Teacher] Excellent point, Corbin.
Why don't we try Alexis and
see what she has to say.
- I have a question as to
how the water pollutants
destroy the economy.
You can say a lot about the economy.
- [Damon] What do you
mean by water pollutants
destroying the economy?
- Well you say that...