- Scientist number two?
I want to know what your question is,
what is your variable
that you're isolating,
and what are you measuring?
You guys ready?
Okay, so, table two?
Or table one?
- Our central question is
how does different types
of oil stains clothes,
even after they've been rinsed.
And our independent variable
is going through the different oils
that we used, and the dependent
variable is how they changed
from before, when we first stained them
to after when we rinsed them.
- Cool, and you may be
able to use the light probe
to determine the intensity of that stain.
Tomorrow--
- We also were planning on taking pictures
from before and after,
so we could like, compare those.
- So, you may want to do a
scale, like Marley did
with the intensity of her
hair dye, as well, okay?
But get it set up today,
make it really controlled
with all your measurements, and
just change the type of oil.
Alright, scientists, do you have any?
- Our experiment is we're
going to mix oil and water
and then try and separate the oil using
positive and negative charges.
- Okay, using positively and
negatively charged particles
to separate oil from water?
I don't know, I read your
document, I don't know
what the positively-charged
particles you are,
but did you work it out?
Okay, so what's your question then?
- Our question is does charged particles
affect the oil scum?
- Okay, does charged
particles affect the shape
of oil balls, them coming
together, scum balls?
Okay, good.
Table three, what's your question?
- Um, how long does it take to make scum
on the surface of the water, like,
using what we're going to use,
mainly olive oil and toilet paper.
- Okay.
- Perfect.
- And testing, the independent
variable is testing how long
we're going to stir.
How long it takes to make scum,
and then our dependent
variable, we're going to take
the observations of time.
- Okay, so the question
is, how long does it take
to form scum balls?
Independent variable is the stir time,
and the dependent variable is the...
- How long it takes.
- How long it takes to do it?
- Uh-huh.
- What are you going to measure, though?
- We're going to actually try to measure
the surface area of the (mumbles).
- Cool, so you're going to say
how much is covered by scum
at that point in time?
Okay, that should be pretty
easy to do with a camera shot.
Okay, table four, what's your question?
- How does temperature
affect the oil and water?
Awesome.
- And we're trying to figure
out how it will separate.
- How can you separate it?
What are you changing in the experiment?
- We're changing, we're going
to use regular temperature
and put it on a Bunsen burner
and put it in the freezer.
- Cool, and you're more than welcome
to use the freezer in the back.
Good idea.
Alright, table five,
what's your question?
- Does heat affect the scum ball?
- And our independent's
going to be amount of scum
and the amount of water,
and the dependent's going to be
heat (words drowned out by ambient noise).
- Okay, so your independent, now you said heat
and then you said the
amount of water in whatever,
so your independent is
really going to be temperature.
So, I feel like you have
two independent variables.
Why don't you just spend
a minute and talking about
which one you want to isolate.
Is it the amount of water
and the amount of scum?
Or is it temperature?
Okay?
- We were going to change the temperature.
- Then keep the amount of
water and the scum constant.
Because you can't do different
amounts of water and scum
and different temperatures.
It means you're testing
for two different things.
While you could do that,
it's two experiments
and we don't have time today.
So, just one experiment.
Alright, table six?
- So, our central question is,
is it possible to create scum
balls in different shapes?
- Okay.
- And our independent variable
was the amount of oil.
And the dependent was the shape.
- Okay, so is it possible to make
scum balls of different shapes?
Independent variable is
the amount of oil or scum,
dependent variable is the shapes.
While I'm over here, I just
want to draw your attention
to the back of the room.
That is the waste beaker,
which has scum on top of it right now.
It's every kind of oil
that Copper used yesterday.
So if you want pre-made scum,
I encourage you to use
Copper's waste from yesterday.
So, the bottom portion of it is
a lot of soap and soap water.
But the top portion of it
is just that less dense, oily scum, okay?
Alright, table seven,
what's your question?
- It's can we filter
out oil from the water
using the gravel filter?
- Okay.
- So, we're trying two
different types of oil
and we're going to put it
through a bunch of gravel
in the container.
- Okay, and you may need to use
two of the same identical filters,
so just make sure you're really consistent
with your measurements
between those two filters.
Good.
Alright, I'm excited about their project
because Copper had one group
that did a filter yesterday
and their results were very interesting.
So, check back in with this group later on
if you want to see what's
going on with the filters.
And table eight, what's
your central question?
- Does oil collect some of the things
in the surrounding body of water?
- Does oil collect the most what?
- Does oil collect the most of each thing?
- Oh, the most of each thing
in the surrounding body of water?
Okay, so you're going to look
and see what it attracts?
And what are some of the
materials you're going to use?
- Dirt, sand, and pebbles.
- Dirt, sand, and pebbles, awesome.
So, your independent
variable is type of material
that it would possibly attract.
How are you going to measure those results?
- Mass.
- Mass? Okay, cool.
You may want to work on a microscope slide
just so you can have a little bit of an easier
time measuring the mass.
If you get too big, it won't
measure on our balances.
Which brings me to my next
topic, which is safety talk.
Conservation of materials.
(students chatter)
- [Teacher] Did you
guys get a lecture yet?
- [Student] No, because
Sam is too busy with her.
- [Teacher] Why don't you go over there
and see what they're doing.
Go, talk to her.
Thank you.
Alright, lady scientists.
What's going on?
- We're like, I thought that we
didn't need to do the middle one
because yesterday we
didn't have enough time,
so we just did the small
amount and then the larger...
- [Teacher] Amount? Okay.
- [Voiceover] Now that
we did the middle speed,
we're actually seeing
a lot different stuff,
because the balls are
actually coming together.
That underneath, and we noticed also
under here that everything
settled to the bottom
except the dirt and oil
that reached to the top.
- [Teacher] Okay.
- [Voiceover] And this
is thicker than that one.
- [Teacher] Okay, let me get
another group over here
because they're also
trying to form a scum ball,
and I'd like them to see your results.
Terrence and Catherine and
Maddy, can you guys pause
and come and check out
this group's experiment?
- [Voicover] I don't see scum.
It makes me mad.
- [Teacher] Ooh, this is so cool.
- [Voiceover] Why does it look like that?
I want it to look like that.
- [Teacher] Come on over.
These guys are also doing
an experiment on scum balls.
Can you guys talk about what's
your independent variable?
What are you changing?
- [Voiceover] We're just
changing the different speeds.
- [Teacher] Okay, and Yasmine,
what were some of the things
you added that were
controlled within all three?
- [Yasmine] The dirt, oil, and the water.
- [Teacher] Okay, and they used
the black potting soil dirt.
Is it the peat moss?
In the plastic bag?
That's peat moss.  Okay, good.
And Taylor, it looks like
you have some cloudy stuff
in the bottom, what's that?
Don't know?
Can you guys fill her in?
- [Voiceover] Toilet paper.
- [Teacher] Toilet
paper, which makes sense
because there's a lot of
toilet paper over there.
Okay, and so far, your results have been,
they've just done the high
speed and the low speed, right?
And they're like, oh it's
the same, nothing happened,
nothing happened, right?
They came back today, and
this is the medium speed,
and what's going on?
- [Voiceover] A lot of dirt, balls are
actually coming down and forming together.
Because they were all
little pieces of dirt,
and now they're making big globs of dirt.
And that's weird.
- [Teacher] So, does
time, sitting overnight,
have anything to do with it?
- [Voiceover] That's what we
talked about with these two.
Actually this one, because, and this one too,
because we didn't see
a lot of carbon bubbles
in the first one.
And then this one, I just noticed that
it's actually the toilet
paper is on the bottom
and actually attached to the
bottom layer of the oil.
- [Teacher] Okay, are the
highs and the lows working,
the speeds, yet?
Have you tried to re-run the
highs and the lows today?
- No.
- [Teacher] Re-run the highs and lows,
you have a good seven, six minutes.
See if they start to form clump balls.
Not sure if you can use this one.
- [Voiceover] Can I go get a funnel?
- [Teacher] Sure.
There's one on the table.
I am not sure if your choice of particles
simply is inhibiting the
formation of the scum balls
or not.
If you want to add another
part to your experiment
to make it more controlled,
maybe you could add some toilet paper
and see if that adds anything,
or you could leave it how it is.
It's your choice.
Got about seven minutes, okay?
- [Voiceover] Thank you.
- [Teacher] Yes, cool.
Hey, you guys have some
diesel fuel on your table?
Any information, research, observations
that could be made about
the shapes of the molecules
would be awesome.
The three of you all together.
Alright, so...
- [Voiceover] We got 97,
no, 47, 94 for all of them.
- [Teacher] Okay, let me
put the camera on you four.
Ready?
Let's talk about it.
Is that okay?
- Okay, so you isolated your variable,
different types of oil.
You made everything the same, same size,
same amount of water,
same amount of soap, time,
soaking, everything was
super-controlled, right?
Okay, and then you just did
a light prep on all of them
and the look was the
same across the board.
- Yeah, it was 47, 94, like it jumped
between them two numbers, constantly.
None of them, like...
- Consistent, so it was consistent.
Alright, so any initial conclusions?
Yes.
- I said that since all the
things were like a darker color,
and the oils were kind of close,
I guess, in like,
how they felt and what color they were,
I guess that maybe if we used a white shirt,
maybe there would've been a difference
because it would've soiled it more.
- Do you feel like there is
still oil in this fabric?
- Yes.
- Yes, okay, alright.
Let me hear your conclusions,
and then I'm going to--
- This one that had water
on it is different-looking
than this one, like the
material looks more like--
- Like dry or something, right?
So, there's some qualitative difference.
I know that this one needs to be flipped over.
Because then it's the
same side of the fabric.
Okay, so water--
- That one's whiter.
- Lighter, okay, so you feel like these
are a little bit darker looking.
And your control?
- This one is darker.
- Your control was the
same as all of them?
The 47, 94.  Okay.
And you?
Any conclusions yet?
- Um, I don't know.
I kind of think the sand thing is sand
because I know the one
we put on the paper,
like it went all the way
down to 40-something,
so maybe the fabric was too dark
to the point where it was
(student drowned out by class chatter).
- Okay, and Lauren, what
was your central question?
- My central question?
- The central question of your experiment.
- Oh, it was to see after we washed it
how much of it was still there.
- How much of it was still there?
Okay, or if it would affect
the fabrics differently?
(student drowned out by chatter)
Okay, but your light probe is saying,
no they're all the same,
so maybe your eyes are
off or maybe the probe
is a little bit off or whatever.
- Should I take that as data?
- I think you should
take it as data, yeah.
And it's okay, you
addressed your question,
which was, how does oil affect
it different among shirts?
In your case, with the soap,
maybe not at all differently.
I'd like you to try one more
thing involving paper towels.
And what you're going to
do, is you're going to see,
you're going to press down as hard as you can
with a paper towel and
see if there's any oil
that's absorbed on the paper towels, okay?
So, that can be one other way to take data.
To see if there's still any
oil still stuck in the shirts.
- Okay.
- Okay?
Goggles on.
Goggles on! Goggles on!
- [Voiceover] What's
the highest temperature
we could put it at?
- [Teacher] Are you guys boiling?
- [Teacher] You can put it all the way up,
you just have to be really cautious.
Get your Hot Hands out, the big glove.
Alright, Heather's group,
I'm coming over to you guys.
Ready?
Okay, what's going on over here?
- [Voiceover] We put 10
millileters of motor oil
in 150 mls of water and we
added five grams of salt.
- Okay, ooh.
Salt, when I was a waitress,
we used to put salt
on our oil stains to get the oil out.
- Maybe you could put a second...
Wait, that's kind of like clay.
I was going to say flour,
because that's what we do
if I spill.
- What do you notice?
- It's starting to kind of clump.
- When we had the clay, it
was really, really clumpy,
but then it...
- It, the, uh...
- Yeah, like the clay just clumped.
And then we had to get
before and that didn't really
make a difference, it
just sat at the bottom.
- My hands are sticky.
- Oh, thank you.
While you're here, do
you remember the charge
of the particles of clay?
Positive or negative?
- Negative.
- Okay, so, negatively-charged particles,
and now you've added sodium chloride,
which dissolves in water.
You've got an A plus,
positive, CL minus negative.
And you're clearly getting a scum ball.
No?
What happens when you turn it off?
- It just all settles at the top.
- When we put clay in
there for the first time,
it was all little clay balls
that slowly rose to the top.
But nothing of the magnitude...
- So, that motion really
helps it to stay together.
- Yeah, that's what we did.
We put it at 500 RPMs first,
and then we dialed it back down to 100.
- Let's apply this to the
water treatment plant.
Was there motion at the
water treatment plant?
- [All] Yes.
- Was there clay in the water?
- Probably.
- From where?
- From the sediment on the
bottom of the Schuylkill.
- From the sediment on the river?
Now remember, the stuff that's going
in the water treatment plant
is coming directly from
the home, so it hasn't
had a chance to go in
the Schuylkill River yet.
- Okay.
- Would there be any clay in the homes?
- Not in the homes, no.
- Not in the homes?
Not in anything flushed down the toilet?
- Yeah.
- So, yeah, there could be
some, like, clay-like sediment,
sand particles going through.
Or at the very least, we could
say that there's probably
some negatively-charged
particles going through,
some kind of silicates.
- [Voiceover] Shall we
throw away the fabric?
- Sure.
- Who knows what's in feces, right?
Alright so, what I think is cool
about your experiment
is the motion is really
important in getting those
scum balls to form.
Have you talked about
CeCe's experiment yet?
- [All] No.
- Go ahead and give that a whirl
because they actually
put peat moss in theirs,
and they started to get scum
balls to form on medium speed.
Also, Matt, Ian's,
sorry, Catherine's station
is using sand, specifically,
and I forget what the other material is.
It looks like peat moss, and
they're having no success.
So, go ahead and do a
little quick walk-around.
And clean up.
- Motion.
- Can you let them, give
them a 10 second overview?
- Yeah.
- And then go?
Taylor, pull it together, you'll be okay.
You're good? Okay.
(students chatter)
- [Teacher] Did you get any scum?
- No we didn't, we just got into lumps.
The fastest way we got a layer, and
then everything, the soil
settled on the bottom.
And then for the middle
speed, it actually formed
big clumps of balls with the oil mixed in.
(student is drowned out
by classroom chatter)
- [Teacher] Clean up, clean up.
(students chatter)