- Okay, so what we're doing,
is you guys are trying to
figure out which one of these
invisible tapes yeah, is the best.
So, the first thing you gotta
do is come up with a nice
question for your problem,
that you want to solve.
Sharonda you wanna share
what you've come up with?
- Which tape is the strongest?
- Which tape is the strongest, okay.
Now see that's good because
you don't like... We were
discussing earlier you don't wanna say
which tape is the best,
because you really don't know
what does the best mean?
Strongest, stickiest, longest
lasting but I like it,
which one's the strongest?
Do you ladies have any ideas?
- I said it was Scotch.
Well we were gonna hang
the same amount of tape
up the edge of the table and stick a
marble to the other side
and see how long it holds
the marble for and that's
how you can determine
which one is the strongest.
- [Voiceover] Okay so y'all have marbles?
- I have.
- You got some marbles, that sounds fine.
So you're gonna do a sort of a time test,
which one can last longest okay.
That might work.
You might wanna do a
little test run tomorrow
because if it's something
where their gonna sit there,
the tape's gonna sit there
with a marble on it for
45 minutes, you may not
be able to get that done.
So you might wanna think
about maybe adding marbles
to see which one can hold the most or
do something to the tape
to make it drop the marble.
I don't know what that might be.
We're gonna come up with
some more creative ideas.
- I was gonna maybe cut like,
like this tape is cut halfway into it,
to see how long it will
hold with the marble on it.
- [Voiceover] Oh, once it's been cut.
- Yeah.
- That would be good, okay.
But, and again you have
to make sure that you
cut each tape the same distance.
You gotta be fair.
So what about, give me a
passionate sample hypothesis
that y'all came up with.
- If the Scotch tape is the
strongest then the marble
will stay on it longer.
- [Voiceover] If the Scotch
tape is the strongest,
then the marble will stick to it longer.
So in your hypothesis you're
mentioning the type of tape,
and you're mentioning
what you're measuring.
Okay.
- I'm having trouble
finding the group control
experimental manipulator.
- Okay, remember think
about your variables
think about the,
especially for your manipulated
variable what you're
changing between the groups.
- [Voiceover] The tape.
- Yeah the types of tape.
- I understand.
- Okay, I'll come back and
we'll discuss the other ones.
(students talking)
- Alright guys, Josh,
- Sir?
- since y'all have already been
working a little bit give me a
sample question, what you're problem is,
the question that you guys came up with.
- Our problem it was, which paper towel
sucks up more water?
- [Voiceover] Okay so you ...
- Absorbs more water.
- Absorbs more water,
or sucks up that's fine.
We're just nice and simple,
it means the same thing.
So you guys are going
straight for absorbency?
- [Voiceover] Yes sir.
- What about a hypothesis, Darren?
- If Brawny, Bounty and a name
brand paper towel are tested
then Brawny will absorb the most water.
- Nice and simple, nice and simple.
See you mentioned all the different brands
right in the beginning and then
you picked one and said
exactly what it would do
better, absorb the most water.
Okay, perfect.
Now, have you got any idea how you're
gonna test the absorbency?
Any ideas about your
procedure, what kind of
method are you gonna follow,
to figure out which one
absorbs the most water?
- [Voiceover] (drowned
out by background chatter)
We're gonna use water.
- What do you need with water?
- Like water, we need water.
- We need water, yeah.  We need water, but
how are you gonna use
the water to test it?
- [Voiceover] First we'll
get a measurement of how much
water we have in a container.
And then we'll put the towel
in the container and see how
well it sucks up the water.
To see if the level drops and
we'll measure it from there.
- So you're saying put a
known amount of water in
some kind of container,
and we've got tons of
beakers we can use.
Then put the paper towel
in there, take it out.
How long you gonna let it sit in there?
- [Voiceover] Like a minute.
- Well, you gotta know.
You gotta come up with the time and it's
gotta be right on.
Cause you don't wanna leave
Bounty in there for 10 seconds
but Brawny for 40 seconds. That's not fair.
You've gotta keep it equal.
But that's the kind of stuff you've got to
think about. You've got to be detailed.
Alright, and then you're gonna measure what
liquid is left in the container?
- [Voiceover] Yes.
- You can do that.
Yeah, that'll work okay, nice and simple.
So whichever one leaves
the least amount of
water behind should be the
best as far as absorbency.
- [Voiceover] Yes.
- Okay.
- [Voiceover] For our procedure
we're trying to think and
like maybe you could put
like three of the same stains
on one sock and then test it without one.
- [Voiceover] You definitely
need to use the same stain.
You don't wanna have Zout
going against coffee and
Clorox fighting mud.
That's definitely a good idea so,
what kind of stains might you use?
- We'll use,
what kind of (inaudible) we got?
- We can use food coloring.
- [Voiceover] Yeah, food coloring.
- I actually have some food coloring.
- Or we could use,
- [Voiceover] I got some barbecue sauce.
- Barbecue sauce?
As long as you do not
eat it during the lab.
That's fine, I like that.
Because that's more natural, I mean.
- [Voiceover] Ketchup.
- And that's already measured for you,
like in packets that
may not be a bad idea.
- Or mustard.
- Maybe yeah, now if you're
gonna do those kind of liquids
we'll have to find a way to measure it.
- [Voiceover] We can use hot sauce.
- Or hot sauce.
Okay that works, that is more liquidy
that might actually work.
Because we can pour it out we
can use pipes or you can use
pipets or beakers or something
to measure it out so that
each sock gets the same amount.
You don't wanna, again don't
wanna put twice as much
hot sauce for this to fight
than this one, that's not fair.
- Yes sir.
Okay, what kind of hypothesis?
- Our hypothesis was if
we test all three samples,
- Test all three.
and then I believe that the
Clorox will remove the stain faster.
- So you're picking Clorox,
why'd you pick that?
- Because the Clorox is sponsored by more,
(laughs) by more varieties of
stain removers and they beat...
- So in other words you've
seen commercials about it?
- Yes sir.
- So you're taking what you
know, inferences like we talked about,
talking about what you know
and making a prediction.
This one seems familiar,
have you heard of Zout?
- No sir.
- Okay most people say they haven't.
I don't know why.
- [Voiceover] I picked
the same one because that's
the only one I'd heard of.
- And the reason why we said...
- Instead of using a marble which I
forgot at home and we used weights,
but they were way too heavy.
So we put a glue stick on a
piece of each tape that was
about 10 centimeters long, and we
made a cut in it that was
one centimeter because
one half centimeter
was too steep or thick.
And then we recorded it
and we found that the first one that
dropped was this one which was a second,
it didn't hold on at all.
And then this one was 17 seconds and then
Scotch proving to be the strongest
dropped at 79 seconds.
- [Voiceover] 79 seconds alright cool.
So what does that data
then tell you, Sharonda?
You said when you collected it,
what are you, looking at what
you found out with your data?
What does it prove?
- That the Scotch tape is better.
- And it's not even close.
So I like how you guys have
chosen to use a bar graph
because I can just look at it,
I can just look at it and go
wow look at that. The bar is up so huge
compared to the other two.
Okay so it's very easy to distinguish
which one did the best.
Okay.
Did you find maybe, ladies, that
you had any kind of error?
- [Voiceover] Well yeah, the
first time I cut into the tape
I cut too deep like twice.
- Cut too deep?
- Yea, and then we found out the weights
just tore right away.
They were way too heavy.
They wouldn't even hold on when I let go.
- [Voiceover] So you're very
careful about making it drop.
- Yeah.
- Alright, cool.
Okay so what kind of data
are you collecting Mark?
I mean what kind of data are
you guys trying to put together?
- We trying to figure our which one is stronger,
which one would last the longest.
- Right now we're seeing
which one lasts the longest for
how many times we rinse it.
This is the first time
we're rinsing it and then
we're trying to wipe it up again.
- [Voiceover] Okay and
this is still the...
- This is still corn syrup.
- Still the corn syrup. Okay
cool, alright that'll work.
So how are you gonna organize this?
- I'll chart a graph,
and we're gonna see how,
which one tears first on which rinse.
- [Voiceover] So you're just
going straight up by the
numbers, before it rips.
Kind of simple so that gives
you, that generates you some
numbers to use, okay.
Alright.
Michael,
did you guys, I know you're
still kind of in the middle of
collecting your data.
Anything you see that can be
done better, something maybe
you made an error with?
Something that seems to not
be working like you expected?
- Dropping this one.
- [Voiceover] Okay.
- That was one.
- [Voiceover] That was one
alright, anything else?
Maybe that you're noticing
with your, anything that you're
noticing with your procedure
that you could, to make it?
- This guy could help
out a little bit more.
- We could've put this stuff in a little
beaker thing, would've made it easier.
- [Voiceover] Put what in the beaker?
- Our solutions and stuff so
we could've put it in there.
That way we have an exact measurement.
- [Voiceover] That's true, okay so what,
what you're saying is that
your experiment may have some
errors because you don't
really know what's left?
- We got measurments but we
don't have exact measurements.
- [Voiceover] So you think
it would've been better to
do that, if you were to do it
again that's what you might do?
Okay, alright cool.
Carry on.
(background chatter)
Okay, hi Jeff and Keosha.
Alright so you're right in the middle of
collecting your data. Do
you have a, have you come up
with a data table yet?
Designed how you want it to look?
Not yet, how do you think you want to?
You gotta make it organized
when you put your data in.
How you gonna write it down?
Any ideas?
- What about a graph?
- Well, you're definitely
gonna have a graph too.
But you also need a
data table to record it,
now that you're starting
to get some results.
- I don't know to do that, like.
- [Voiceover] Okay well we'll
just think about it then,
make something up.
What do you think will be
the easiest way to organize?
Okay let's do this, what
results are you looking for?
- The best thing, stain cleaner.
- [Voiceover] Okay, based
on what, I mean what are you
using as your rule to say
that they clean the best?
Color change or?
- Yeah.
- Okay.
- How much it took off.
- How much it took off,
how are you gonna measure
how much it took off?
- By, by the color.
- [Voiceover] Or do we
need to use something?
- [Voiceover] I don't know,
this is up to you guys.
This is your experiment.
What do you mean by the color?
- Like, how dark it went to light.
From darkest to lightest.
- [Voiceover] Okay you do that,
I mean you could compare it
side by side. That's a good
way, like a scale, sure.
You got any other ideas?
You could do that.
Alright so let's just
say you went straight up,
we're gonna compare the
original color to the new color.
How can you organize
that into a data table?
What kind of information would
you need to put in there?
- The color.
- Yeah, the color change.
Okay, so the color changed.
You definitely have to have the brands,
you've gotta know which one did what.
So how are you gonna write
down the color change?
How could you organize that into a chart?
- [Voiceover] That's hard.
- [Voiceover] I know, I know.
I think you already told me the answer.
What would you say you were looking for,
what did you say you were
looking for? The color change?
How were you gonna compare it?
- [Voiceover] From darkest to lightest.
- [Voiceover] From
darkest to lightest okay.
So isn't this sorta like before,
and after.
So maybe you can have a,
somewhere in your data table
a column or a row where
you're talking about what the
color is before, describing it.
So it's gonna be what
kind of data since you're
describing it?
- What kind of graph
should we use?
- We'll get to that in a second.
So what kind of data is that
where you're just writing down
like descriptions and colors?
That's what we've been working on.
We're not using numbers.
(mumbling)
Well, we'll get to the graph in a second.
You know what kind of
data it was where we,
collect descriptions and colors and words?
(chuckles) It's right there.
Say it.
- It's (laughing).
You've got a (making letter sound).
- Quantitative?
- Well that's numbers,
- Qualitative.
- Qualitative, so that's
what you're doing.
Now how you gonna put that in a graph?
(background chatter)
- [Voiceover] From the darker shade to the
lighter shade, right?
- [Voiceover] Decide what goes where.
- Okay that sounds good to me.
- [Voiceover] What kind of graph?
- [Voiceover] I don't know.
If you're trying to
compare and contrast these...
- Double bar graph?
- Sure.
That would probably work.
Okay here so,
you guys have been working
on which paper towel
absorbs the most liquid.
I see y'all have a data table that,
nice and simple.
Record how much water they...
- [Voiceover] Absorb.
- Absorb, how much water they absorb.
And what kind of conclusion,
Ms. Goodwin could you
draw for your data?
- For my data I drew
that Southern Homes had
absorbed the most water.
And then Brawny absorbed
the next, (laughs)
absorbed the next most.
And then it was, Bounty was the last.
- Bounty came in last, but only barely.
- [Voiceover] Only by one.
- So, Josh.
- [Voiceover] Yes?
- Based on the results
that your group got,
how would you, how would
that change your thinking?
In other words, how might that
change your shopping habits,
if you had these to choose from?
Well, I would pick
Southern Homes more than
any of the other brands
because it absorbs more.
- [Voiceover] And isn't that
what it's supposed to do?
- Yeah.
- Okay.
So Darren,
looking back at y'all's
procedure looking back at
your entire lab, is
there anything that maybe
if your were to redo
this lab right, is there
something you might would
change about it to make it
better or more accurate?
- Yes I would use different
measurements of water,
like three of them.
- [Voiceover] Three?
- Yes.
- You mean like repeated?
Like maybe for each paper
towel do it three times?
- Yes.
- Okay, alright, that's actually
a pretty good idea because
when you do those extra trials
it helps to eliminate mistakes.
Because you could've found
out with these two being so
close, if you would've had
time to be able to do it
two more times you could
have found that maybe
on average Bounty ended up beating Brawny,
or vice versa you never know.
Okay, Mia.
What about,
what about your hypothesis, was it right?
Did you pick the correct one?
- No, I picked Brawny.
- Brawny, okay so what kind
of new hypothesis, based on this?
Let's say that you guys came
up with a whole new idea,
that was different from
what you did this test.
Like another whole procedure
like Darren was saying,
do it multiple times, maybe
it's completely different.
What kind of new
hypothesis would you make,
if you were gonna do a similar experiment
with a twist to it?
- I would pick Southern Home.
- Just because it won this one?
- Yeah.
- Okay, so based on your results
you might choose the same one.
Anybody think they would
choose a different one?
- [Voiceover] I'd still
stay with the same one.
- Which was which one?
- Brawny.
- Why would you still pick Brawny?
- Because it was close
it wasn't, it was like,
it wasn't that close, but if
we would've made like more, if
we had tested it more then
it would've probably stayed.
- And so do you think it's possible,
- It is possible.
- that if you did a
completely different test,
than just seeing which one
sucked up water, maybe if you
tested strength,
Brawny could have won that one?
- Yes.
I know it could.
- [Voiceover] Okay, cool.
I like how y'all did the
lab it was nice and simple.
And other then Darren's error
did you see anything that,
anything else you would do differently?
Anything else that you feel that you could
have done better other than
just maybe doing it extra times?
- [Voiceover] Test to see like how thick it is.
- [Voiceover] Test the
thickness of the paper towel?
- Yes.
(mumbling)
- [Voiceover] Are you straight?
So in other words have
a second type of test.
Okay, sure.
- I'll probably change the
temperature of the water.
- [Voiceover] Change
the temperature of it?
- Yeah.
- [Voiceover] Oh, that's true.
So you have to add in different
variables because maybe
one of them works better under
- Heat.
- [Voiceover] or lasts better
under higher heat, okay.
Cool, awesome.
- [Voiceover] Tim!
- It's okay Tim doesn't
have to be over here.
So let's see what kind of chart you have.
Now explain this chart to me Deontay,
because all I'm seeing is check marks.
- I did mine, I just did something simple.
- [Voiceover] Okay that's fine.
- I put my name right there
and I put if it left a light
stain I left a check mark
and if it left a dark stain,
I meant stain, I put a check mark.
- [Voiceover] Okay, so I
see some of y'all are still
working on your graphs and
how you wanna display them.  Alright.
So why did you choose a bar graph?
- So we can do like the
levels of the stains,
we got like medium.
- [Voiceover] Medium.
- Light and dark.
- Let me see.
So you saying you're doing,
you're going kind of like
a qualitative data, light, medium, dark and
you're just sort of shading up to the
level you think that it had. Okay,
how could you do that better?
What might be a more
reliable way to gather data?
I mean the color change is okay, I mean
the color change is fine
because that's what you're
looking for, right? When
you buy a stain remover
you wanna see that it takes the stain out.
What might be some more
reliable data you could gather,
if you were to do this
differently, for the future?
You need to come up with
a creative way to get
better data or more data maybe?
- The more data we can get
is by looking through the
sock up under the sock to see how dark
the color went through.
- Okay, so compare the levels
and how much stain
was pushed through the sock?
- Yes sir.
- Alright that'll work.
What else?
- Or we can tell by if it's
a light, if it's a ring
around a light spot then we can tell if it
cleared and if it clears
some color off of it.
- So you're talking about
maybe the shape of the stain or...
- Yes sir, the shape of the stain.
- Okay, possibly.
- And if it's a ring around
it like this one right here,
if it's a ring around it
it's a light spot and we can tell
it isn't't clean enough.
- [Voiceover] Alright, so how about this?
Whose opinions did you use
to get these scales?
- [Voiceover] I used my own for mine.
- [Voiceover] Okay.
Cause they think that one
was the best and I think
this one was the best.
- [Voiceover] So, what
might be, think about this
what might be a better
way, a more reliable way
to get more data,
than just your opinions?
- [Voiceover] Ask other people's opinions.
- [Voiceover] Ask other people.
Again, if you were to redo
it, do you think it would
be a better idea to maybe
ask some other people?
- [Voiceover] Yes,
Like going around the class
asking what they think?
- [Voiceover] Getting a vote.
- [Voiceover] Like a vote, like a survey?
- [Voiceover] Yeah a survey.
- [Voiceover] Or a vote, okay.
Alright, last thing.
Now that you've finished it, what kind of
problems did you see?
Is there something that
okay, if I did this again,
I know we could've had some
error during this point,
like we could've made a mistake here?
- We saw that, if we woulda
let the colors and the
stain remover sit a little longer, that
it wouldn't have come out.