- [Teacher] At the end of class, I want you to
be able to explain how
to swing the bat faster
so the ball will travel further.
Because the faster the bat goes,
the further the ball's gonna go.
And there's three things
that we're going to
do to make the bat swing faster.
Okay, we're going to hold the bat at the
end to make it longer.
We're gonna hold the
A longer bat means a faster bat.
We're gonna use more body
parts or muscle when we swing
and we're gonna apply
more time to our swing by
stepping into the swing.
And we're learning to
bat so that we can play
more and more fun games
in order to stay healthy.
Because there's lots of
fun batting games you can
play with your friends here at school
and outside of school
that will help you have
a healthy heart and muscles.
And we're gonna do four
different things today.
I'm gonna ask you to talk to a partner,
I'm gonna do a little
experiment, we're gonna play
spotlight tag, and then we're gonna
have some personal practice.
And I've created a little healthy
a little helping worksheet for you
that shows you what it looks like.
Now all these things will
help you know and help you
be able to explain how
to swing the bat faster.
I want you to turn to a
partner and tell them
as many things, of as many games
that you can that use
swinging a bat or an impement.
Go ahead.
(Students Chatting)
- [Teacher] Hey everybody, let me
get your attention.
If I pull your stick,
I want you to tell us
a game or an activity that
you can do that requires
using a bat or an implement
to hit a ball or something.
We're green?
No, we're red.
Jeremiah, where's Jeremiah?
Yes?
- [Jeremiah] Softball.
- [Teacher] Softball, very good.
Raquel, where's Raquel?
What, Raquel?
Game or something you can play.
- [Raquel] (Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Do we use a bat to play soccer?
- [Students] No.
- [Teacher] No.
How about...Stephanie?
Baseball?
Who said golf, what about golf?
What about ping pong?
Do you know what ping pong is?
[Students] Yeah!
So all of these activities
are things that we can
play once we learn how to swing a bat.
Now, we're gonna go around the blue house,
and you're gonna sit on
the red dot until I say go,
and I'm gonna do a little
experiment to show you
how these things can
make the ball go further.
I would like you to
walk, please be careful.
Go.
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Okay, thank you for sitting.
Now over there I said the longer the bat,
the faster it goes.
The faster the bat, the
further the ball goes.
So I'm gonna show you what I mean.
Is this a very long bat?
- [Students] No.
- [Teacher] No, so I'm gonna swing
and see how far it goes.
(Students Laugh)
- [Teacher] Did it go very far?
- [Students] No.
- [Teacher] Now I'm gonna make that longer.
Who thinks it's gonna go further?
Let's see if it goes further.
(Background Chatter)
(Students cheer)
- [Teacher] It went a little bit further, huh?
- [Students] Yes.
- [Teacher] Now, by holding the bat at the end
it'll make it longer and it'll go further.
Now another way we make the bat go faster
is by using more body parts and muscles.
So I'm only gonna use a couple muscles
here to swing the bat.
You think this will this go very far?
- [Students] Yeah.
- [Teacher] Yeah?
Okay, let's see.
- [Students] No.
- [Teacher] I didn't use a lot of muscle.
Now I'm gonna use lots
of muscles on this step,
and I'm gonna twist,
see how far it goes.
(Students cheer)
- [Student] Do it again, do a lot of muscle.
- [Teacher] Anyone know of any other way we can make
the bat go faster?
Hit from the bottom?
I had it written over there.
Does anyone else remember?
I want to make my bat longer,
I want to use lots of
muscles, and.... Alex?
- [Alex] (Background Chatter).
- [Teacher] That's how we use lots of muscles.
I want to swing the bat
for as long as I can
in order to generate speed.
Now, if I start my bat
right here and I swing it,
do I have lots of time to hit the ball?
- [Students] No.
- [Teacher] Do you think it'll go far?
Let's see what happens.
(Students chatting)
- [Teacher] Now, if I start way back
here, do you think I'll have more time?
- [Students] Yeah.
- [Teacher] You think it'll go further?
- [Teacher] All right, let's see.
(Students cheer)
- [Teacher] So, raise your hand if
you want to hit the ball far?
Hitting the ball far will help
you be successful, and if you're
successful, you're going to have
a good time.
But today we're going to learn different
ways to hit the ball further by
making our bat go fast.
- [Teacher] Don't swing; please tell me.
- [Student] (Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] It makes the bat go faster.
Why does the bat go faster?
- [Student] (Background Chatter).
- [Teacher] The bat goes faster,
the ball goes faster.
But what makes the bat go faster,
because it's short or long?
- [Student] (Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Long. Longer bat means faster.
Okay, rotate!
Rotate!
(Background Chatter)
-[Teacher] Dominant hand on top.
Step, twist.
We're practicing what
grip is the best.
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] How'd that one go?
Fernanda, what grip are you using?
- [Student] Mr. Holden, can I go to the bathroom?
- [Teacher] Hurry.
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Excellent twisting,
Derek, excellent twisting!
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] What number are you
going to read it?
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Try this one: hold
your bat with your hands apart.
Put your left hand on top.
I mean your right hand on the top.
Left hand at the bottom.
Spread your hands apart like this.
Now try it again.
How did that go?
Is that one good?
You think so? Now hold it at the end,
see what happens.
It's right here.
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Now hold your hands,
put your right hand on the top.
Right hand on the top,
your right hand on top.
(Background Chatter)
All right, Fernanda. Big step,
let's see it.
Big step, twist your whole body.
Get your bat back, there you go.
Try it again.
Did the ball go further that time?
(Background Chatter)
(Whistle blows)
-[Teacher] Okay, sit behind your
little cone and answer
the question on your card.
Alright, now read it out loud for me.
(Background Chatter)
[Teacher] Which grip do you think makes
the bat swing fastest?
Holding it at the end?
Remember when we talked about
how long the bat is?
A longer bat can travel faster or slower?
- [Students] (Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Faster, so when you hold it
at the end it makes it longer,
and then you can swing it faster,
and then the ball goes further.
Is that what happened?
- [Students and Teacher] Yeah.
- [Teacher] All right, rotate.
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Alright, are you going
to twist or not twist?
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Back foot, step.
Put your weight on your front foot.
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Alright, so pretend your feet
are stuck in mud, so you can't move them.
- [Teacher] So we've been learning
all the different ways we
can make the bat go faster so that we can
hit the ball far, because
when we hit the ball far,
our game and when we're
batting is more enjoyable.
We've practiced, we've talked about,
and we've discussed three
different ways to make the
bat go faster so that the ball will travel further.
When we're batting, okay?
I have a sentence frame for you, it says:
"I can blank to make the bat go faster
"so the ball will go further."
Okay, you're in your
batting team groups right now.
When I say go, I want you
to use this sentence frame
and discuss the three
different ways you can make the
bat go faster so the
ball will travel further.
And then I'm gonna pull our sticks,
and you'll get to share
with the entire class how
you think you can make the bat go faster.
So now is your time to use
all of the intelligence and
brains of your group to
figure out your three answers.
Are there any questions?
- [Students] No.
- [Teacher] Okay, I'm gonna give
you about two minutes.
Use the sentence frame,
discuss with your group.
Go ahead.
(Background Chatter)
Alright, how is your group doing?
Jesse, you getting to share?
I might pick your stick.
Talk with Alex.
What are we coming up with Jeremiah?
How are we gonna make the bat go faster?
Do you remember?
-[Teacher] Okay, how about Alex.
Why do we twist, Alex?
Alex, why do we twist?
Alex, sit up, please.
When we twist, we use more what?
- [Students] Muscles!
- [Teacher] What color were we?
Black or green?
- [Students] Red!
- [Teacher] Oh, we were red?
Okay second grade, eyes on me, please.
Sit down on a number.
You've had a nice opportunity
to talk with your group to
figure out the three ways we
can make the bat go faster.
If I pick your name, please stand up,
speak nice and loud and
use the sentence frame,
and tell us one way we can
make the bat go faster.
Let's see here...
Jonathan.
All right, Jonathan, stand up buddy.
Jonathan, use the sentence frame, "I can."
- [Jonathan] (Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] I can hold the bat at
the end to make the bat go
faster so the ball will go further.
Good answer, give him a round of applause.
(Students clapping)
When we have a longer bat,
it generates more speed,
and more speed with the bat
makes the ball go further.
Now there are two other ways
you can make the bat go faster.