(Background Chatter)
- [Boy in black shirt] I think that Igneous and Metamorphic,
they're the least (Backgroud Chatter), there are two books
that don't use 'em
'cause they're (Background Chatter).
- [Student] Well my Igneous (Background Chatter).
- [Boy in black shirt] Yeah, it (Background Chatter).
Igneous and Metamorphic
cool off and react.
And only a few particles came
off, but I was (Background Chatter).
- [Girl in yellow] Yeah, it's
just awkward because
mine was, boosting most of yours.
- [Boy in black] Well yeah.
- [Girl in yellow] When I did my alien, on my
first try, it was 42 grade.
Then now when I'm measuring
it again, it was 22 grade.
It (Background Chatter).
- [Girl in gray] Mine never changed, all it did was lost
a little bit of it's rice crispies.
- [Girl in yellow] That was mine.
But, I feel like Igneous
rock, (Background Chatter) like, 20.
- [Girl in gray] Well yeah.
'Cause the weathering does a lot of things
to the rock's outside.
And--
- [Girl in purple] Mine was the same as Igneous
and metamorphic (Background Chatter).
- [Girl in yellow] And so, if I'd shake it...
like through weathering, a
bunch of rock would fall off.
- [Girl in gray] I haven't done anything yet.
It was three.
I can't wait to--
- [Voiceover] Oh.
(Background Chatter)
- [Girl in gray] I have to say, the one
with the marshmallows
'cause it's (Background Chatter).
- [Voiceover] Well for my
Sedimentary, it was harder.
- [Voiceover] Yeah, mine too.
- [Voiceover] What (Background Chatter)
(Background Chatter)
- [Boy in black shirt] 'Cause when I
did mine, only one piece of my
Sedimentary broke apart, and--
- [Girl in purple] The Sedimentary--
- [Girl in yellow] My Igneous rock--
- [Girl in purple] It has, like almost (Background Chatter).
- [Boy in black shirt] It might be a
little inaccurate since these
are not real Sedimentary rocks.
You have to keep that in mind.
- [Girl in purple] Well yeah.
- [Girl in gray] So, but what if
they were real Sedimentary?
Would we be able to tell what they are?
- [Girl in yellow] Yeah.
- [Girl in purple] Obviously.
- [Boy in black shirt] Do you know
any Sedimentary rocks
that looks like a granola bar?
- [Girl in gray] Yes, I saw them in my yard.
They're called a granola ball.
- [Voiceover] No.
- [Boy in black shirt] That was probably granite,
which is an Igneous rock.
- [Girl in purple] For Jeanie, do
we write just how many lasts?
'Cause mine must've had (Background Chatter).
- [Girl in gray] Okay so when I, when
I did the blendering,
of my Sedimentary, I lost only three grams
off of my, Sedimentary rock.
So I'm not sure what would
happen if I add these two.
(Background Chatter)
- [Girl in gray] Because of the heat out of the,
'cause if you were to
put heat to a rock like
our little blue Metamorphic rocks,
what would happen was
the heat would melt it,
and it would give pressure
to stick down to the tinfoil.
- [Boy in black shirt] Yeah,
that's how that happens.
(Background chatter)
because this is probably
the farthest off we have
from a little while.
- [Voiceover] Yeah.
- [Boy in black shirt] Like last
we (Background Chatter), and like
have you ever heard of
a rock that's called
(Background Chatter) Metamorphic rock?
- [Girl in yellow] Yeah.
- [Girl in purple] It can be greasy.
- [Teacher] Let's talk about why we use the models.
Obviously, you're never gonna
be so lucky as come across a
rock that's like the taffy.
Why did we use the Laffy
Taffy for our model?
- (Girl in yellow) Because the heat and the pressure,
the heat and the pressure would like
stick together, but
like a Sedimentary rock,
(Background Chatter).
- [Teacher] We use our fingers to
add that heat pressure.
We had to simulate it somehow,
we couldn't do the actual
Earth process in the classroom.
Do you agree with that?
- [Students] Mm hmm.
- [Teacher] Okay, so you understand
why, you understand why
we use that material for our model?
Okay.
- [Boy in black shirt] (Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Right, it probably melts.
And why did we use the
microwave for the Igneous rock?
- [Boy in black] Because--
- [Teacher] What were we
trying to simulate there?
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] From?
- [Boby in black] Magma is a really hot substance,
and this is what Igneous
rocks can form from.
- [Teacher] Could we actually
manipulate and touch magma
in the classroom?
- [Boy in black shirt] No.
- [Teacher] No.
Could we work a marshmallow?
- [Boy in black shirt] Yep.
- [Teacher] So we understand
the connection there.
We're trying to use materials,
that we can bring into the classroom,
but that will still simulate
lava, magma, the processes.
Okay? So pressure--
- [Girl in purple] I think it has less
effect of all the (Background Chatter).
- [Teacher] It had a lesser effect going through
the processes of?
- [Girl in purple] Of both.
- [Teacher] Weathering?
- [Girl in gray] And erosion.
- [Teacher] And erosion, okay.
Now you guys can think about this,
if you didn't like the
samples and examples up here
that I used, you could
always do it different.
Food material.
To make up your own experiment later.
Okay?
(Background Chatter)
[Teacher] Let's talk for a moment.
Why should we measure again
after our rock samples
have been through weathering and erosion?
Why are we measuring again?
- [Boy in yellow](Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Look at your rock samples,
do they look the same
as what we measured in here?
- [Boy in yelow] No.
- [Teacher] No.
What happened?
- [Boy in yellow] You have to measure the difference.
- [Teacher] The difference, and why
would there be a difference?
What could we do to our rock samples?
- [Boy in yellow] (Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Changed dramatically when you
did the weathering on them.
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Let's use the same
(Background Chatter), what did you use
when you pre-measured?
I would keep it the same.
Why would I keep it the same?
- [Boy in yellow] Because it's (Background Chatter).
- [Teacher] Can we compare
centimeters to inches?
- [Boy in yellow] Yes.
- [Teacher] You can?
Think about that, because later
when you have to come back
and do the difference, how are
you gonna do the difference
with some centimeters and some inches?
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] How can you compare those two measurements?
- [Boy in yellow] (Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] You're telling me, you wanna go centimeters here,
but inches down here.
-[Boy in yellow] (Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] I would keep it the same.
They would make it
mathematically (Background Chatter).
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] You working on your difference?
Your difference in mass?
This your pre-mass?
- [Student] (coughing)
- [Teacher] Explain to me how you got to that.
- [Girl in purple] Where are the books?
They might add on to another
sedimentary rock, 'cause
it's like never ending.
- [Girl in yellow] For some reason, my
Sedimentary and my Igneous rock.
They both lost a half inch in length.
- [Boy in black] Yeah, mine too.
- [Girl in yellow] In my igneous rock
grams, it lost 20 grams
and my sedimentary lost 10 grams.
- [Girl in purple] Mine lost no grams.
- [Girl in gray] Mine gained grams.
- [Girl in yellow] Your gained grams?
- [Girl in gray] Yeah, I had 17 grams.
I had 17 grams, and
then it came back to 21.
And this one went up one.
Because when this one went up three.
- [Girl in purple] Maybe you should check that over.
'Cause it weathers and erodes away.
- [Girl in gray] Well, I'm guessing that most
of the bits and pieces of the
other people's stuff, went
into mine, and made it bigger.
'Cause, it can do that, it can.
See? Right there.
All around the--
- [Girl in purple] Oh! I see it!
- [Girl in gray] See? Other bits and
pieces of other people's
went into mine, and made mine bigger.
(Background Chatter)
- [Girl in yellow] With mine, a bunch of bits
and pieces (Background Chatter).
- [Girl in purple] And mine started to melt.
- [Teacher] Because your
observations say it crumbles apart,
it's breaking apart and moving.
- [Boy in yellow] (Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Okay, what about these gaps here.
- [Boy in yellow] These gaps?
- [Teacher] Yeah, how you gonna do that?
(Heavy Background Chatter)
- [Girl in gray] For some reason,
my Igneous rock (Background Chatter).
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Into the sample?
- [Girl in gray] It made it bigger.
- [Teacher] Made it heavier?
Did it have more mass after the (Background Chatter)?
Your protective sleeve's coming off.
That's a good possibility, that might
throw your measurements off.
Did it happen to anything else?
Any other sample?
Now you're working on a difference in...?
You gotta find the difference
in length and width,
and you're gonna find
the difference in mass.
That's interesting, you could
explain that away right there.
Mm hmm, isn't that the one,
Igneous, the one you were saying
got the strange results?
You can talk to me then.
(Background Chatter)
- [Girl in gray] Well, that's probably how
they make the canyons bigger.
Maybe because some of the rocks,
after rain and the sandstorms, they could
just pound together and
make a big old rock.
So...
Okay, so if it erodes off another rock--
- [Teacher] I'm listening, are you
talking about real life
rocks when they really--erode away
Mmhmm.
- [Girl in gray] And it starts to rain,
'cause a lot of times
it's like wind and rain.
A lot of times it takes the
sand away from the rain,
with the rain, and here's another rock,
which makes a bigger.
- [Teacher] You're thinking sometimes with real life
rocks, you could have actual
sediment mixing in with igneous rocks?
Right, do you remember how we talked about
how igneous can morph
back into sedimentary?
Those bits and pieces are
melding with igneous rock
when you have that blend, where igneous
is morphing into sedimentary rock, okay?
So that would also cause
reason for your measurements
(Background Chatter)
I like where you're going with that.
Try to make that connection.
You know, Unis was giving me
a hard time earlier about how
'metamorphic rock's not made of Laffy Taffy.
So how's this go back
to rocks in real life'?
Think about that.
(Heavy Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Some of our videos that we were watching?
About what salts quartz
in these two processes.
(Heavy Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] You have to let the water go down.
- [Girl in gray] 'Cause the heat inside
of it could've frozen.
'Cause they heat over there,
we had it kinda (Background Chatter).
(Heavy Background Chatter)
- [Student] Whoa, what's the answer?
- [Boy in red] 19 grams.
- [Boy in gray] 19.
- [Teacher] --Igneous--
(Heavy Background Chatter)
(Background Chatter)
- [Boy in gray] Igneous!
- [Teacher] How could you make that?
Explain it to your
little sister (Background Chatter).
She's not gonna be able to
understand that, she wasn't here.
What could you put on
your rock cycle diagram?
- [Boy in black](Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Okay.
So you're gonna have (Background Chatter).
- [Boy in red] This is 17.
- [Boy in gray] 17 for what? Igneous?
What about sedimentary?
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Tell me how Sean needs help.
- [Boy in yellow] Um, he needs help with (Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Okay.
(Background Chatter) where he's
trying to find the mass of
the sedimentary rock.
- [Girl in gray] What do ya mean?
- [Girl in purple] No, I was saying that
it may have gotten darker.
- [Girl in gray] Darker, because of the heat.
- [Girl in purple] Yeah.
- [Girl in gray] A lot of rocks do that.
- [Girl in gray] But it could be jus the pink.
- [Girl in purple] Yeah, it could be, I could
write down that, it could be pink.
- [Girl in gray] Yeah, what happened to my
metamorphic rock, is (Background Chatter).
- [Girl in purple] I can (Background Chatter)
- [Girl in gray] Yeah that's because of this thing.
- [Teacher] (Background Chatter)
in between our finger
and (Background Chatter)
- [Girl in yellow] Mine, it didn't get
darker than mine though.
(Background Chatter)
- [Girl in purple] So you could add
that to what you put in (Background Chatter).
- [Teacher] So how would
that affect our measurements?
How did it affect your width?
(Heavy Background Chatter)
- [Girl in gray] Igneous and
sedimentary rock could (Background Chatter).
- [Teacher, offscreen] Now talk
to me though, if it's in
(Background Chatter)
(Heavy Background Chatter)
- [Girl in gray] You wanna know why those are
there? Because a lot of rocks
don't have protection
that doesn't help them.
And a lot of kids drop theirs
inside their bag, which
mixed with the Sedimentary.
- [Girl in purple] It could (Background Chatter).
- [Girl in gray] And sooner or
later if it just stays in there
and rolls around, guess what it would do?
It would also become a sedimentary.
- [Girl in purple] It's just like the rocks,
it's just like the rocks in life
It's more similar to real life.
(Background Chatter)
- [Girl in gray] Yeah!
- [Girl in gray] The eroded bits would
stick to other rocks.
- [Girl in purple] So I just added, like bits.
(Background Chatter)
- [Boy in black shirt] We have bits and pieces.
- [Girl in gray] See, if I
was to shove this in my bag
and just roll it around in all of this,
this would also become this,
because this isn't on the mat.
This would begin to stick.
And when you ball it
together, it makes it appear
coloring to it, that show
that it's inside there.
- [Girl in purple] I think that the igneous
and the metamorphic rock,
(Background Chatter)
- [Boy in gray] After each sample, ones that
were weathering and erosion.
- [Teacher] So you're gonna compare
your two measurements--
pre-measurement, post-measurement--
to see if there's a
difference for each rock.
- [Boy in gray] Hmm.
- [Teacher] Hmm.
- [Boy in gray] Do we have to subtract?
- [Teacher] Do we? What's your key word that could
tell you what to do? Difference?
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Go show me, I know you're thinking.
You just told me, what key
word tells you what to do?
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Where were we?
Finding the mass?
After we've done the
weathering and erosion?
Okay, are you gonna get started?
- [Student] Yes.
- [Teacher] Yes.
Jack, are you finished with that scale?
Can we use manners, please?
Can we use manners?
Can you say please pass the balance?
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Talk to me guys, just for a
moment, about the differences
in those, in your (Background Chatter).
We've got Ashley's igneous,
we talked about that.
- [Girl in purple] I figured out
for the metamorphic that
changes did actually
happen, because they put
the sedimentary, came
on to the metamorphic.
- [Teacher] So we can
see again, how, just,
and it probably had a lot
to do with our service
and our bag, that's how
those pieces of sediment
got attached to our metamorphic rock.
- [Girl in purple] And I think it became darker
because the heat (Background Chatter) because of the pink.
- [Teacher] And because of the pink?
- [Girl in purple] Yeah.
- [Teacher] Okay, think about in
real life sedimentary rock,
when those levels, when those
layers are smashed together.
Okay, don't some of those
layers change the color
with all that heat and pressure?
Okay, that was your metamorphic.
Yes Brooke.
- [Girl in yellow] And also,
you get the igneous in
there, it sticks to it,
and you can just put it inside
there, cover the layers off,
and it actually gets
inside the metamorphic.
- [Teacher] So you all
noticed how your rock samples
are very true to real actual rocks,
and how they could
combine with one another,
and result in a completely different rock.
Okay? So, on your next
page where you get to make
your rock cycle diagram,
maybe you could use
those observations and
those understandings
when explaining your outcome.
Not the candy rock cycle, the real one.
- [Girl in purple] (mumbling)
- [Teacher] It says that you could
use a diagram, okay?
Using your textbook, Level
Readers Science Journal,
or the rock cycle experiment
that we just completed.
Anything you want to be able
to explain the rock cycle.
Okay?
- [Girl in purple] (Background Chatter)
- [Girl in gray] My igneous has gone down just a bit.