- Anybody tell me how much
cases usually run?
[Background Chatter]
- At Radio Shack, they're 30 dollars.
- Okay, you know what?
So we'll factor that in in a minute.
But Alex, you had your hand raised.
So I'd like to hear from you.
- I was just gonna say that
the 199,
tax is gonna come in anyway,
so [inaudible]
- What if you got a deal
about it that paid
the tax and shipping?
[Background Chatter]
- Okay, hold up.
Cynthia.
- But even though...
Even though if you use 12,
you're only gonna have a
couple dollars left over.
With the economy these days,
things are not cheap.
So you can't buy something
with five dollars.
You're not gonna get
a case for that cheap.
- That's probably right.
[Background Chatter]
- I'm gonna hear two more of you,
and then I have something I wanna drop
into this conversation that several
of you talked about,
and I think is really
important to point out.
So I wanna hear what you
two have to say,
and then I'm gonna go
back to something
several of you kinda mentioned.
Go ahead.
- It's better to have more money
than less money
because if you exactly calculate it to...
199,
then you'd still have zero dollars left,
but it's better to have
equal or more money.
- Okay, that's, you know I think you're right.
That seems like it just
makes sense, right?
And one more, yeah.
- Actually, when I bought my phone,
I got a case just for
about five dollars on ebay.
- Ebay, so you got a used one?
- And it paid for shipping,
so I didn't, yes I did.
- Okay well you know what?
I wanna talk about that
because that's actually
what you guys just said
is really important,
and several of you others mentioned it.
Maybe we don't want,
maybe I don't want to have
the exactly the price,
maybe I want to have at least...
200 dollars.
And if I say I wanna have
at least 200 dollars,
is there a way to say at
least with math symbols?
To make that equation
change so it says least.
'Cause right now, it says equal.
Is there a way to do
it so it says at least?
Colin?
- If you, you need to get
the iPhone and the case
in the same shipping order,
or else it's gonna cost
more for shipping.
- Oh okay.
So yeah, I need at least
a certain amount.
- Yeah.
So you're gonna [inaudible].
- Wanna jump in on that, guys?
- You need to put the greater than
or equal to sign.
- But what does that look like?
- The greater than sign
with a line under it.
- Okay.
And what's the word in
English that we have
for that symbol?
Yeah, say it again, Alexis.
- That least.
- It is.
So now, how much do
I need to save to get
at least 200 dollars, right?
So it's okay if I have
exactly or more than.
So that kinda talks about what
you guys are talking about.
Maybe I need more money,
if she wants more,
more than just a phone.
I'm sure she does, right?
- With the...
[inaudible]
What about the [inaudible]
just come with the phone.
Just that, or does it
come with something else?
Like a...
Charger, battery, or even a case itself.
- So again you're saying
I need at least 200 dollars, right?
Depending on what comes with the phone.
- [inaudible] like a Christmas special?
Like half off or something?
[Background Chatter]
- What you can...
Also think is where you gonna buy it?
And where is there's no tax and stuff?
So, it depends on where
you're gonna buy it.
If you want no tax, that means
like on Ebay or something,
but... [inaudible]
It might be 50 percent
off and stuff like that.
- Okay, interesting.
- I'm just saying,
it depends where you're gonna buy
your phone.
- Okay, no, I like that a lot.
- When I was doing my equation,
11 times 11,
I got 121.
So you would still have
a dollar left over.
And you know how Cassidy said that she can
get it on Ebay, that much.
Most people, they...
I understand that it's cheap,
and most people want it like that,
but I bought stuff off the line before,
and some of the stuff does work good,
and some of 'em you
drop them and it breaks.
So, it's not always good.
- Somethin' to pay attention to.
All right, I'm gonna change
the conversation a little bit
because I think you guys are
doing really really well.
Let's go with what you guys said
and say I need at least 200 dollars.
If that's true,
is there any way to find out,
or to answer the original question,
which Nick brought up.
How much money do I need
to save each day
based on what we have so far?
Where do I go from here?
- There is a way to solve it.
You grab 200 dollars,
and then you subtract 80 from it.
- Okay, I'm gonna stop
you right there.
I don't mean to interrupt.
Katherine, you're watching
this and I saw your paper,
what do you think about
what Najeem just said?
- Like [inaudible]
- Okay, and why is that?
- I don't know.
That's how you solve it in equality.
- Okay, so can you repeat
what you said?
- You subtract 80 from both sides.
- Okay.
I'm gonna go ahead and do
that right now.
And what does that leave us with?
- 120.
- And you know what,
I have a question.
What does that 120 represent?
I mean, if 200 is how
much the phone costs,
what's 120 about?
I'm not sure.
- How much you need to raise,
until then.
- Okay, okay.
And Nayanna?
Can you comment on what you think
might be the next step?
- Divide 12 from 120.
- Again.
- Okay.
And, somebody else, jump in.
- The answer was [inaudible].
The answer would be 10
because 12 and 120 equals 10.
- Okay, and Katie you were
ready to say something.
What would you say?
- I was about to say [inaudible].
- Equals 10.
X equals 10 and--
[Background Chatter]
- X equals at least 10.
- Oh, it was so you're not liking what
I wrote over here, Alexis.
- At least 'cause
you have to keep the
[inaudible] all the way down.
- Okay, Katherine,
what do you think?
- I agree with Alexis
because...
it can't just like change,
- When you say it can't change,
what do you mean?
- the side.
- Oh [laughs]
Okay, that's good [laughs].
I didn't know what it was
I'm just asking.
- And then you
have to put what X means.
[Background Chatter]
- Oh, Oh.
Oh, so what is the label?
What are the units we're talkin' about?
[Background Chatter]
Ah.
- [inaudible] the blue tooth.
If you wanna have a little extra money,
you could have more, and plus,
if you get a little extra money one day,
but you have the same another,
and you get a little less the next day,
you could raise up for another day.
- Oh, like if I'm going
to collect cans
and I don't collect as many cans one day,
but I collect extra the next day.
- Yeah, like that.
- Nayanna, you had your hand raised.
- When you have to add 40 to 200,
for the Bluetooth.
- Ah, that's an interesting idea.
So maybe we, so tell me what to write.
Instead of this, how would you change this
to incorporate what you just said?
- 80 plus X equals 240.
- Okay, are you pleased,
are you okay with that?
- I disagree.
- Cynthia.
- I disagree with
your answer on that one.
I don't agree that it's 10 because
if like they were saying
earlier if you wanted some extra money,
you would...
You should...
You should do 11
for a day because if
you do you'll get 132,
and then you'll have extra money.
- Okay.
[Background Chatter]
- But that's the problem [inaudible].
- What do you mean when you
say it's not asking?
- Well, it's not asking
for extra money,
or anything, it's just asking how many...
How much money you need per day.
[Background Chatter]
- Anthony, I noticed you've
got some stuff
written down.
What do you think about...
I wanna go back to what Nayanna said.
She says she's gonna
change the equation here,
and she put 240 up there, why?
Why did she do that, and
do you agree with that?
- Yeah, 'cause then you
would have a little
extra money left.
- A little bit.
- You would have a little bit
of extra money left.
- Okay.
- [inaudible] like
the Bluetooth in the case,
maybe?
- Okay.
- Isn't this another problem?
Another problem [inaudible]
not a part of this one yet?
- Yeah, 'cause they're
not asking how
much extra money do you need.
This problem, this question's
not asking how much
extra do you need for
a Bluetooth, also.
- Okay.
- How much are the phone and Bluetooth,
it's just asking for the phone.
- Okay.
[Background Chatter]
- I think because...
The question wasn't asking to
bring extra money into it.
We just brought the
extra money to round the,
make the equation easier
and round the
199.99 to 200,
and extra money is okay,
but we shouldn't change the equation.
'Cause it's not asking you to.
- Okay.
- This question isn't saying
anything about
case or a Bluetooth yet,
it's a yes question.
And this question talks about Bluetooth.
- Okay, so what
I kinda like is you guys
were doin' this problem,
and a couple of ya jumped
ahead to this problem,
which is no problem at all.
Let's jump ahead just for a
minute and assume that I did
want to get the Bluetooth.
Would this be the equation to represent?
And before I answer this question,
what I would like to do,
I'm gonna call on Olivia, and
then I'm gonna have everybody
switch so the pilots go
back to the co-pilots,
and the pilots come up, but not yet.
Let's hear what Olivia has to say.
- Would it be [inaudible] equals 12 X,
if you wanted to get it before Christmas?
Or would it be after?
- One more time,
I could barely hear ya.
- Would we still get
that before Christmas,
or would it be after?
- Before, before.
- So would it be 12?
- Comments on that?
- I agree with that.
[Background Chatter]
- Thumbs up if you think 12,
thumbs down if you think no,
we don't need 12 on this one.
Okay, Adrian, you have something?
- We need to know how much money
you earned each day.
- Well that's...
What do you guys think
about that question?
- Well that's what we're
finding out right now.
- I know, but how much you earn.
That's how much he has to save.
- Pilots, switch with
somebody in the back.
[Background Chatter]
All right, here we go.
So now, I have a question for you.
Can everybody turn around
for just a minute please?
Thank you.
Question for you.
If I wanted to graph
our first solution
on a number line,
what might that graph look like?
So will you guys agree that okay,
we need to earn a minimum amount.
And at least 10 dollars a day,
but if I wanted to graph that,
put that on a number line
represent that graphically,
what would that look like?
- It would be like a...
It would be [inaudible].
But the circle...
[inaudible]
- What kind of circle?
I didn't hear you.
- Shaded.
- So you want to put this up here?
- Yeah.
[inaudible]
- Amarra, I'd like to hear
your opinion on that.
- I don't, I never understood
the shaded thing.
I don't know why it's shaded.
- It's shaded because it's not,
I think if it's not shaded
it means greater than,
I mean greater or less than.
But when it's shaded I think [inaudible].
It means equal to or less than or...
With.
- Okay, Tara, do you wanna
contribute to that
[inaudible]
- Well, whenever it says greater than,
or equal to,
the dotted means it could
be 10 because it could
be equal to, or greater than,
which is over 10.
But greater than or less than
can't be that number so
it has to be open circle.
And than greater than or equal to.
- Anybody have an example of a problem
or words that we would
use to put an open circle,
unshaded circle?
In real life, what might we say
for something to represent
an unshaded circle?
- Go ahead, Al.
- Fewer than 14 students
have mechanical pencils.
- A little louder.
- I got fewer than 14 students
have mechanical pencils.
- So in that problem,
could 14 students have
mechanical pencils,
if you have fewer than 14?
- No.
- So that would be unshaded.
'Cause 14 doesn't count.
So in this question, Amarra,
the least number of money
I should save per day is how much?
- I think 10 is
a good answer.
because it does go into the number.
- And so would be shaded or unshaded?
- Shaded.
- Oh, is that the only
number amount of money
I should save each day?
Is that it?
Are their other possibilities out?
- Yeah, you could do--