♪ [singing] ♪
- [Teacher] Okay. Now, when we sang that
music scale, we were... We were actually
stepping up. We were going from low to
high. And if you'll look over at this, you
can tell these were the notes that we were
singing, from low to high. The first note
was a line note. Let's speak it together.
- [Together] Line note, space note. Line
note, space note. Line note, space note.
Line note, space note.
- Good job. Those notes were stepping. And
if you'll notice here, I've got carpet squares,
and I have them with line note and space
note.
- Line note, space note. Line note, space
note. Line note, space note.
- Good job. That's what we sang when we
sang our scale, and that's the notes that
you're seeing up there, are those line
notes and those space notes. All right.
I'd like for us... Will you please come
and find one of those carpet squares and
sit behind it? Sit behind the carpet
square of your choice. And let's go ahead
and sit up tall on our knees. Sit nice and
tall on your knees. And the next person,
come in and find a carpet square, sit
behind it, behind that hand chimes. And I
don't think we'll need... We'll need one
more person. The next person.
- [Boy] What about me?
- Five. Good job. All right. Now everyone,
even if you're sitting in your chairs, you
need to practice with me, because we're
all going to be playing the hand chimes today.
Do not touch your hand chime just yet.
Let's all just practice. Start off with
your hand up. Put your hand chime down a
second. We're going to just practice with
our arm only. And it's going to be
important that you do a good wrist action
because that's going to make a difference
in the way that it sounds. All right,
watching me. Hold, and again. Hold. Hold.
Asanti. Hold. Hold. Okay, stop. Now,
people down here, pick up your hand chime,
and let's see if we can get that technique
going. Get ready?
♪ [music] ♪
One more time. Good, Now let's...
Just place your fingers there under the
bottom to get it to stop. Good. Now, when
I point to each person, by yourself, you
will play the music scale. So do not play
until I point to you. Looking at me, we begin.
Start with the low C.
♪ [music] ♪
Good job! Let's do it again. That's the scale. And
these notes are stepping because it's line
note, space note, line note, space note.
Any time you've got two notes beside of
each other, that's a stepping melody. One
more time, starting with the lowest C.
♪ [music] ♪
Good job. Now, put your hand chime down a
second. We just heard a stepping melody.
Any time that you have a line note and a
space note beside of each other, two
neighbors playing, that's a stepping
melody. I want you to stand up, please,
and I'd like for you to stand up. Take
your hand chime, hold it, and...
♪ [music] ♪
That melody. Someone raise your hand and
tell me. What did it do, Logan?
- [Logan] Skipping.
- Actually.
- [Child] It leaped.
- You're exactly right. It leaped. Because
look at all these lines and these spaces
that did not get to play. That's a leaping
melody. Good job. London, do you remember
what the difference was between leaping
and stepping? I mean leaping and skipping?
Can somebody help us? What's the
difference between a leap and a skip?
- [Child] If you leap, it's more than a skip.
- All right. The leaping is more than the
skipping. Skipping... All right. You sit
down. Put the hand chime down. And you
stand up. You keep remaining standing.
Take your hand chime and you play.
♪ [music] ♪
- [Child] That was a skip.
- You are exactly right. That's a skip
when you just skip over one place, one
person. All right. Have a seat. You have a
seat. And I'd like for, Ashley, you
stand up. And what I want her to do is for
four times I'd like you to play your hand
chime, watching me. I'm going to let her try.
♪ [music] ♪
Someone raise your hand. What was that?
James, what was that?
- [James] Repeating.
- You're exactly right. That was a
repeating note. The one person, that one
pitch played four times. All right. Sit
down, please. Now, will you please stand?
You stand and you stand. Watching me.
All right.
♪ [music] ♪
Raise your hand, please. Tell me what was
that? Devon.
- [Devon] Stepping.
- A stepping pattern. And it went from
high to low. You're exactly right. Have a
seat. Now, last week I gave you a piece of
paper, and it was something that I wanted
you to do to see if you understood about
leaping, stepping, and repeating on the
music scale. If you'll look over at the
Smartboard, there is some notes there on
Number 1, some notes on Number 1. And you
were last week going to circle an "S" if
it was a stepping pattern.
You were going to circle an "R" if it was
a repeating pattern. Raise your hand if
you know what those notes on Number 1 were
doing. Christian, put your hand chime down
and you can come up, and circle whether
those notes in the Number 1, if they were
stepping, or if they were repeating.
You're exactly right, Christian. How did
you know that?
- [Christian] It was staying on the same
note.
- Staying on the same note, very good. And
thank you for walking around behind those
hand chimes. Number 2. Akrista, can
you walk around that other way and come
right here? And why don't you show us. Put
the hand chime down, please. Show us what
the notes in Number 2 are doing. Let's see
if it's doing a space note, and then a what?
- [Child]  Line note.
- Line note and then a space note. And she
is exactly right. Those notes were stepping what?
- [Students together] Down.
- Down. And Number 3. Thank you ma'am. Come this
way, right around here. And she's looking at
those music notes, and she's going to be able to
tell... They're right here, Number 3. All
right. Let's say it with her. Line note.
- [Together] Space note. Line note, space
note. Line note.
- Right here. Are they staying all the
same?
- [Child] No!
- They staying all the same? What are
those notes doing?
- [Child] They're stepping.
- You're exactly right. They're stepping
up. Thank you, ma'am. And tiptoe back to
your seat. Very good job. Now, I would
like for the last two people, B and C. If
you'll tiptoe to your seat, I'm going to
call you back up here in a few minutes.
The rest of the folks, you've got to be
sitting up nice and tall, sit up tall on
your knees. Let's see if they can play a
very familiar tune. I want you looking at
the very first note, the... The very first
note, Keiani. You have that low C. And
what do you notice about C? C, Keiani,
what's your note going to be doing? What's
the word when you have the same pitch?
Re...
- [Keiani] -peating.
- Thank you. He has a repeating note. And
G, Christian, what are you going to be
doing?
- [Christian] Repeating.
- Repeating. Adam, what are
you going to be doing?
- [Adam] Repeating.
- Repeating. So we have a lot of repeating
notes in this song. Sit up tall on your
knees. Sit up tall. Pick your hand chime
up. We're going to see if we can play this
familiar tune. Waiting. One, two, ready,
sound.
♪ [music] ♪
Very good.
- [Child] That was "Twinkle, Twinkle,
Little Star."
- It was Twinkle, Twinkle, Little Star.
You recognized it. All right. Put your
hand chime down a second.
- [Child] I was listening.
- You heard the melody. All right. Now let
me see. Sitting tall. I'm going to get
someone that's sitting back there in a
chair to help us out a little bit. I think
I would like for Christopher. Will you
come and point to three people that will
be able to show us a stepping melody? Oh,
don't raise your hand.
We'll let Christian choose. Three people
that would be able to play...
- [Child] Christopher.
- Oh, yeah, Christopher.
- Or you can call him "Chris."
- That's Christian.
- All right. Tell me which three people.
Just point to them. All right. He's
pointing to you. Stand up with your hand
chime. We're talking about stepping now.
Stepping. All right. Okay. Chris has
pointed to these three, tapped them on the
shoulder. Let's see.
♪ [music] ♪
If you think he picked out three folks
that did play a stepping pattern, will you
just gives a thumbs up silently?
You're exactly right he did pick...
- [Child] He did it.
- He did pick three. All right. Put your
hand chime down and sit down. I'd like to
call on Harmony. Will you pick two people
that can show us a leaping melody?
Leaping. So you can step behind them and
just tap them on the shoulder. Leaping.
Leaping. Leaping... Okay. Now, these two
people are side by side. There's a line
note, and a space note, and they're
neighbors. Someone raise your hand and
tell me what would they play? What would
they be playing if they're neighbors?
That would be a stepping. And I wanted a
leap, like a frog leaps over a whole lot.
So come and see if you can fix it. Real
quick. Somebody needs to sit down. Who do
you want to sit down? All right. Sit down.
And pick somebody that will be a leaping
melody. Like a frog leaping, leaps over a
whole lot. All right. He stands. Take your
hand chime. Play.
♪ [music] ♪
Now, she leaped over a space note and a
line note. Give a thumbs up if you think
she did it correctly. Yes, that is a
leaping melody. Good. All right. Sit down.
Hand chimes still on the floor. I'd like
for you to tiptoe very quietly back to
your chair.
What we did in that song, we had several
times that there was repeating notes. We
had a few times where we had some
stepping, side by side. And we had some
leaping melodies. When we played the hand
chimes it took several of us to be able to
play those melodies, the melody. If you're
playing a xylophone though, you could do
it right by yourself.
- [Child] I can!
- I would like, Keiani, will you step
around behind here? And Sheridan, you come
over and sit behind the xylophone that you
choose. And Dev, Devuan, Devuan, walk around
here. Walk this way. And he's going to be
the teacher. I want you to choose. Sit
down on your knees so that they can see
what you want them to do. Choose something
that you want them to play, and let them
see it. Turn it so that they can see it.
All right. What do you want them to play?
- [Devuan] Step.
- Play a stepping melody.
♪ [music] ♪
All right. Good, and stop. Now, someone...
Both of them did do a stepping melody. But
he was playing right here. Can somebody
help him out as to what might make it
sound better?
- [Child] A hit in the middle.
- He says, "Hit it in the middle." Hit
where the music notes are, those steps.
Let's try it again.
♪ [music] ♪
Play 'em soft.
Great job. That is stepping. All right.
Choose another one. Oh, now he wants a
leap.
♪ [music] ♪
Good job! What do you want, Devon?
- [Child] Devuan!
- Devuan. Repeat.
♪ [music] ♪
Good job. All right, thank you. Put your
mallet right there on the instrument. Lay
it on the top. That will be quicker for
today. And tiptoe back to your seat,
walking around the instruments. I'd like
for Wes H. to step around and find
yourself a xylophone. Step around over
here. Akrista.
Sit down tall on your knees. And what do
you want them to play? Tell them. She
wants you to play a repeating note.
♪ [music] ♪
Now those were both kind of high repeating
notes, very high. Do you think you could
play a low one?
♪ [music] ♪
Good job. Now how did you know that was
going to be low, Akrista?
- [Akrista] 'Cause the little ones are
higher. Bigger ones are low.
- You are exactly right. What else do you
want them to do. She'd like a what?