[Background Chatter]
- [Student] We started
testing out our theory
that it's an exponential.
- 'Cause we found out that the ratios...
- [Teacher] Does that verify
that it's an exponential equation?
- We thought it did but it doesn't.
- [Teacher] So why aren't you sure?
- I don't know.
- [Teacher] So the more disks I add,
I'm eventually gonna have a cap
on the minimum number
of moves that I can make.
- Isn't that a logistic function?
- [Teacher] So logistic function
would say that you're gonna have a cap
on the minimum number of moves you make.
And it would say at some point
you're gonna slow down
the number of moves you're adding on.
Does that make sense based
on what you've done so far?
- No, not at all.
- [Teacher] What do you think
is gonna happen instead?
- That it would increase.
- [Teacher] And what would that be?
- That's the exponential.
- But the numbers are
all really long decimals.
- [Teacher] So, I heard
someone in here earlier
say you were gonna scatter plot this.
So have you looked at your scatter plot?
- [Student] Yes
- [Teacher] Okay.
What might be other ways
to change an exponential function?
- [Student] I can get it out of my backpack.
- [Teacher] Based on what you had before
what was your gut instinct
with your ratio?
Before you did any of the arithmetic,
what did you think your ratio might be?
- Small?
I don't know.
I didn't really think it
was two automatically.
- [Teacher] But two's in your head.
Why is two in your head?
- [Student] Because doubling?
- Because there's doubling.
- [Teacher] Here's what I'm gonna suggest
to you guys.
You've got your scatter plot
on Marissa's calculator, right?
You're thinking that two
might have been the ratio.
Why don't you graph
two y equals two to the X
and compare it to what's happening
on your scatter plot
and see if there's a different way
that you might be able
to change the extremum.
- [Student] It's increasing
by a factor of 2.
She's trying it in an actual game.
- [Teacher] Normally I'd want you guys
to struggle with it right now
but it sounds ...
We're at 20 so what's your goal?
- 27, 28, 29, 30, 31.
- Good job, Caitlyn.
- [Teacher] Good job.
Now I'm convinced that that works.
You're seeing that the difference
is doubling each time, correct?
What kind of function is that suggesting?
- Exponential.
- [Teacher] And what do you suspect
is probably your factor?
- [Student] Two?
- [Teacher] Two?
So that's what I want you to look at.
How could you verify
that it's an exponential function
using any of the tools you have here?
Once you've found out this was
an exponential function
what did you do to figure out
what the function actually is?
There is a little bit of a trick to this one.
It has to do with some of the other
types of changes we do to functions.
Okay?
Figure out that.
When you get stuck again, let me know
and I'll be back.
- [Student] So you think that's two
to the power of X minus one?
- [Student] Why did you get minus one?
- Because with one it worked fine
but with two,
when you try to put in
X as the exponent,
two to the X so two times two is four.
So far X minus 1 is the exponent.
- [Teacher] What I'm hearing is
that you're convinced
that the factor is two.
And you're trying to
do some transformations
on this to make your y values fit
with what you got here, is that correct?
Talk me through again
why you guys think
that the exponent is x minus one
and then why you're adding
the one at the end?
(students laugh)
- Because there has to
be at least one move.
- [Student] We added the one at the end
because we were looking at
just the y values first.
- Oh wait, that doesn't work though.
If you have one,
so two to the zero is 1.
And one plus one is two
but that's ...
- Tell me more about this idea
of the plus one at the end.
You said that had something to do
with why you had to have a plus one.
- Is it a piece of the function?
That would be really mean.
- We were like well it has to double
and then we have to add one on the end.
- [Teacher] I think you
guys are in a great place.
I think you've got a good idea here
which is to take y equals two to the x
and find the transformation
that gives you this table.
So try more with the transformation.
I also like this idea you guys have
about how you have to have at least one move,
but I would think a little bit more about
how to pattern your moves,
that's just that you
need at least one move.
Alright, I'm going to
leave you guys to think.
I'll come back.
- [Student] So we found the equation
but now we're stuck at number four.
- [Teacher] Okay, so talk to me
about the equation
and tell me how you found it.
- [Student] The difference between...
- [Student] I was kinda thinking of
how this was relating to the difference,
so how it would relate to the y values.
- We saw the two to the x,
we figured "oh well, two to the four
to the 16. Well how do
we get to 15, minus one?"
- [Teacher] This is going back
to the algebra from last year.
So you saw that you had two to the x.
You noticed here that we have just
two to the x and then you go
back one using algebra.
You also talked about how
when you graphed two to the x
it matched up with your scatter plot.
Did it lie directly on your scatter plot?
- No.
- [Teacher] So what do
you mean by it matched up?
- It was close.
- It was the same curve.
- [Teacher] So how did you know
that created a transformation?
- [Student] Because whether it depends
on the number or which value it is.
It changed the steepness of it.
So we just knew it transformed it somehow.
Like we had to have it.
It wasn't the parent function.
- [Teacher] So what made you guys think
about doing a minus 1
after two to the x instead
of saying four times two to the x
or three to the x?
How did you know that?
Because if you'd done
four times two to the x,
you would have stretched it.
- [Student] Because it would have moved
to the left too...
on the graph.
- [Teacher] And what did that end up doing
to your y-intercept?
Okay, so that would be
my next question for you.
I agree with you guys
that definitely there's a transformation.
I agree with your algebra
and your understanding of tables,
you've done a nice job with that.
So how does a transformation,
what you've done is you've taken
two to the x, what does the minus one do?
Does that move this to the left?
Move it up or down?
- [Student] Well if you graph it...
- It moves it up.
- [Teacher] Okay.
So Jamie is saying that she thinks
that changing the a value
changed the slope of the function.
And you're saying
that you don't think the slope changes.
Okay, so you change the y-intercept.
And do you have a change
in the y-intercept?
- It's still zero comma zero.
- [Teacher] So you just
had two to the x.
Find out just two to the x.
What's the y-intercept of the graph?
What happened to your function
and how did the function get transformed
to achieve that?
- The y-intercept moved down.
- [Teacher] And does that match
what we've been talking about?
You take the function and subtract the value
and move down one?
Alright you guys said you were stuck
on number four?
- Yeah.
- [Teacher] Okay. Why are you stuck?
- So we figured out that you put
64 for x.
But the minus one doesn't do anything.
- [Teacher] Yeah, the numbers are so big
that it doesn't matter.
It actually does
change the actual number
a little teeny, tiny bit.
But our calculator can't see that number.
It looks like the same number on your calculator.
- [Student] So we have a number of moves.
- [Teacher] If each move is a second,
then how long is it gonna take
for the world to end?
Alright, now you guys are also
at the challenge question down here.
Which is, based on the patterns
you were seeing
and how the pieces were moved.
Why is your function which is correct
match the way the patterns that were made?
Okay? And I'll be back in a little bit.
I'm going to give you guys
about seven more minutes.
You should answer question four
before you try that.
(students laugh)
- [Student] So I got it kind of close.
Looking at just...
I did what you do to find a normal
exponential equation.
I plugged in y-two over y-one
and then to the square root of four.
- [Teacher] And are you
getting consistent ratios
between those y values of yours?
- No.
- [Teacher] You guys are correct
that this is exponential.
But if we're not getting
a consistent ratio
between y values then that suggests
that your original thought,
which was to start with two to the x
and do a transformation,
is on the right track.
So I really think you need to go back
to y equals two to the x
and find the transformation
that gets you to these y values.
- Okay.
- [Teacher] I'm gonna make a suggestion
to you again stealing from another group.
Try finding the differences
between all these y values
and see if you can see a pattern
between the differences
and the actual y values you have.
Alright, what have you guys got?
- [Student] Our answer was 30.
- Talk me through how
you got that function
and how you know it works.
- I realized that...
the table matches the graph
of two to the x but minus one.
- [Teacher] So you just
have that in your head.
Did you graph it
or did you just know
those numbers in you head?
- We didn't graph it.
We used the tables to confirm
that it was y equals
two to the x minus one.
Went to the table and
it was the same numbers.
- And I noticed here you've got
2 to the 64th minus one.
What's that for?
- That's from another number.
It's like a really high number.
One point eight times
10 to the negative 19th.
- Two to the 19th.
- [Teacher] While you guys figure out
how long it's gonna take
for the world to end
with that really huge number,
I'd also like you to think
about the answer to the challenge.
You guys spent a lot of time looking
at the patterns and how
these pieces are moved.
So I'd like you to think about
why your function has two to the x.
Why are you doubling those?