- (Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] So how would you describe that?
-(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Can you find the exact
spot where that is in the text
where you can find those?
So you basically have
found two character traits
to describe to me, right?
You guys have discovered
that he can be what?
What was one of them again?
- [Students] Jealous. Sad.
- [Teacher] Jealous. Or sad.
So I want you to find that evidence.
If you want to make those claims,
any of those are great ideas.
But now you have to dig a
little bit deeper into the text
and see if you can find this.
Can you find examples and see?
OK. Keep sharing.
You're doing a great job!
- [Girl 1] Toby wanted to play...
- [Girl 2] Because Toby was kinda jealous
because Bouncer
was outside by himself.
Didn't want to (Background Chatter).
Nobody didn't... and a little kid
wanted to go outside the house.
Well, I think he's thinking this himself.
Because he was thinking about what
the other (Background Chatter).
- [Girl 1] That's Toby.
- [Girl 2] So, he's kinda jealous
because he's talking
to the other little dog,
and every single time,
he wants to play ball with him.
But he doesn't want to (Background Chatter).
- [Boy] And the thing is, the lady said it,
in the story,
it made it sadder
than it usually would be sad.
That sometimes the stories
make it seem so sad,
so good that that can feel.
So, here where it says,
"Why does Andy need a new dog?"
Oh, wait.
"'Why does Andy need a
new dog?' wondered Toby.
"He already has me.
"Toby sighed and laid down
"Beside the dog.
"Maybe Andy doesn't love me anymore."
They had to make it
so that what happened,
and actually it's sad what happened.
It's not that it's sad,
but it's not so so sad,
but they make it like sad.
- [Girl 1] Toby wanted... (Background Chatter)
- [Boy] Toby wanted to play ball
and he got a new dog
and forgot, I was about to...
(Background Chatter)
- [Boy] Well, he didn't really forget about Toby,
because he still bought Toby his food.
I know!
Toby wanted to play ball,
but when Andy came,
he got a new dog.
And then, for the rest of the day,
Andy was playing with his new dog.
And Toby felt left out.
I say we put 'left out' somewhere.
- [Girl 1] He's so sad, jealous, and left out.
- [Boy] So, Toby wanted to play ball
with Andy,
but when Andy...
- [Girl 1] How do you spell Andy?
- [Boy] A-N-D-Y
- [Girl 1] Andy.
- [Boy] Andy.
- [Girl 1] Where do you see?
- [Girl 2] Oh, yeah.
- [Boy] When Andy told him
he wanted to play ball,
- [Girl 1] Where are you?
- [Boy] Andy.
- [Girl 1] Andy.
- [Boy] Toby wanted to play ball,
but when Andy came,
he had a new dog.
And you spelled with a silent (Background Chatter)
- [Girl 1] I think with the Andy...
- [Girl 2] Another dog?
- [Girl 1] A new... Like this one.
- [Girl 2] Another dog.
- [Boy] No, it's not. Well, whatever.
Who wants to... (Background Chatter)
(Background Chatter)
- [Girl] Just write. Just write!
- [Boy 1] I put 'Toby was jealous
because of Bouncer.'
Maybe we can put, because
he wanted more attention.
- [Girl] That's how my sister is.
She wants more attention.
- [Boy 1] We're not talking about your sister.
We're talking about Toby.
- [Boy 2] So, Toby was jealous...
- [Boy 1] Toby was jealous because a dog's there.
- [Girl] Because Toby was a dog
and Bouncer just came along
and he didn't like him.
He's jealous.
- [Boy 2] No. We have to write a
reason why he's jealous.
- [Girl] I know! Then we have
to do part of the test.
Part of the test!
- [Teacher] Did you guys
agree on a character trait
that he was at the beginning?
- [Girl] Jealous.
- [Boys] Jealous.
- [Teacher] Jealous?
Do you have at least one example,
and maybe two?
Do you have an example, Joaquin?
- [Boy 1] I'm going to put Toby
wanted more attention,
but Bouncer got more attention.
- [Teacher] Do you have an example
of why he wanted more attention?
- [Girl] I have one.
- [Teacher] Can you find it, Oscar?
- [Boy 1] When he was, like, maybe Bouncer
doesn't love him anymore.
- [Teacher] I only said that. Can you find that?
So when you write it,
when you explain it,
can you find that part and maybe quote it?
- [Girl] There's another reason...
When they came through the driveway,
he got all (Background Chatter).
And then when he came back, he lay...
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] So that's
like too many things.
- [Boy 2] Toby was jealous, cuz
- [Boy 2] Toby was jealous, cuz Bouncer
got more attention, instead of Toby.
- [Girl] No.
- [Boy 2] Yeah.
- [Boy 1] Oh, right here.
- [Boy 2] In the middle.
- [Boy 1] Toby, since nobody...
- [Girl] What paragraph is that?
- [Boy 1] Paragraph nine.
He wondered if Andy had forgotten
all about him.
- [Girl] Do you know why he paid
more attention to Bouncer?
Because he's a little puppy.
And little puppies need more attention
than big puppies.
- [Boy 2] Because little puppies
don't know what to do.
- [Girl] I know. And they're not even trained.
They have to train them more.
- [Boy 2] For like three months.
- [Girl] Yes. That's why he needs more attention
than Bouncer, yeah.
- [Boy 2] Toby needed...
Because Toby really knows how to...
- [Girl] And he knows, that's an old dog.
And you can see all the wrinkles.
- [Boy 2] That's how the dogs are.
Yeah, those dogs have wrinkles
when they're big already.
But they're still young.
- [Girl] OK.
- [Boy 2] Toby was jealous because Bouncer...
- [Girl] What did you write?
- [Boy 2] So. I have, 'In the
beginning was Toby..."
(Background Chatter)
- [Girl 1] When Andy had a puppy,
he liked Bouncer more than Toby.
- [Girl 3] Maybe.
- [Girl 1] And in the beginning, Andy was showing
the puppy opening.
Opening the puppy, and showing it to Toby.
- [Girl 3] Yes.
- [Girl 1] That's how he was like nervous.
- [Girl 3] Jealous.
- [Girl 1] Yeah, jealous.
- [Girl 3] And selfish.
- [Girl 1] Yeah.
That's what I put in the beginning.
And then Toby...
Remember the part when
he got the little ball?
- [Girl 2] Right
- [Girl 1] Yeah, and he was being jealous.
- [Girl 3] Yeah.
- [Girl 1] ...Bouncer. Because he was a new one.
And the old one was Toby.
- [Girl 3] And the part
when Andy closed the door
in Toby's face,
and he let him outside.
Then he felt loner.
- [Girl 2] I believe that,
Toby was getting (Background Chatter) Bouncer.
Because they would stay together,
and they slept the whole night together.
- [Girl 1] So they were being friendly.
- [Girl 2] Yeah, like starting to.
- [Girl 3] Yeah.
[Girl 1] Another thing that Bouncer was new.
And another thing, Toby was old.
So, Andy was used to Bouncer...
- [Girl 3] And Bouncer and Toby...
(Background Chatter)
- [Girl 1] And that's I think what Toby about.
It's Bouncer.
You know how the fence
went to (Background Chatter) Bouncer.
They get a kinda middle-something.
- [Girl 3] Yeah.
- [Girl 1] That's what I think.
- [Girl 2] When they started to get
(Background Chatter),
Toby showed Bouncer how to catch the ball,
that's when they started to become friends.