- But you're putting
children in your sweatshops.
- How are you gonna get more money?
How are you gonna finance
the country still?
- Both of you need to listen to Cambodia.
Because Cambodia...
- I am awesome, Cambodia is awesome!
- What are you doing to fix this?
- Well, for the money
problem, I'm not really sure,
but you can get loans for
other wealthier countries
and then as you're getting
better, pay 'em off and then for,
and then for child labor, you make a law
that kids have to go to school and learn,
so that way they can get
better skills and stuff.
And then put their, after that works
and everything to age laws.
I'm the only one with an answer!
- I have no child labor whatsoever.
- Whoa, whoa, whoa, I thought we discussed
that you do have child labor, but...
- Well, we do have some child labor
but it's more the grits going in
and making your child choose
the forms to get hired.
- So, what do I win as the
only one with an answer?
- How did you pull your
country off child labor?
You need to be giving them
suggestions and ideas,
OK, what can we do, what
can we do to crack...
- You told us some
solutions the other day.
- Right, so that's why you guys are
supposed to be discussing now.
- OK.
China do you wanna go ahead and...
- So, China, you know how to get rid of
all your child labor in your country?
You have a plan, you have
your whole plan in place...
- Pretty much.
- What's the first step,
what's the second step,
what's the third step,
what you're gonna do.
- Yeah, you wanna hear it?
- I do.
- First, we'll make it illegal
for children to work all day.
And the other half they go to school...
- OK, but wait a minute,
but don't your parents,
your families depend on that income
that those children are bringing in?
- Yes, but if they work half the day,
while they're at school,
they still earn money.
- But then they're
losing half their income.
- But then on weekends they can.
- But they work weekends
right now, anyway.
- Maybe we could establish
a minimum wage over there.
- Oh! Now there's an idea!
- What?
- They could establish a minimum wage.
- Yeah.
- OK, so you're gonna
establish a minimum wage.
- Yes, and going to
school to get a education
helps them get better
jobs when they're employed
so they can get more
money with better jobs,
so then they don't have that issue...
- So what are you going
to do in the process,
because you are gonna have to have
children leaving the workforce,
just starting to get their education
that takes several years for that
generation to become educated,
what are you gonna do in that gap?
You still have to have a plan
for those 12, 13, 14 years.
- What about programs
like those they used in
like the de, de,
depression, that's the word!
- OK, that's what you
guys should be discussing,
those are some of the things
you should be coming up with.
- They could start...
- Keep in mind that needs money.
- But then they would get
loans from wealthier countries,
and as they're getting
stronger and more...
- OK, take those ideas and work with them.
You guys are on the right
track, you're rolling with it.
- So, put that down,
establish a minimum wage...
- OK, Cameroon, what was your solution...
- Say the children stop
working, and the adults get it,
well it would be taking
money away from the family.
Not other than the ones
we came up with on Friday,
like have countries send money.
- What about that like education
like half school half work
campaign, it's like where
where you're working, part of your wages
pay for your school and
then you take the rest home
- And then, like, with me, in my country,
48% of working children
already go to school.
So, I guess all those times you mentioned.
But they only go for like six years,
from age 7 to...
Wait, I don't know.
- [Student in blue] OK, anyway,
that would help with
like the country being...
- France for the win!
Like the same thing but more...
- Coffee, OK, if it was our major export
it would get rid of
poverty and many things.
- Where's your country?
Where's your country?
OK, never mind.
I was thinking you move
at the same time, but no.
- If we work together with
the coffee export, like...
If we combine the export...
If we produce...
Well, I meant like from whatever we sell,
we could try to hawk them together,
to help each other create
better education...
- Y'all can combine your profits
in coffee, and begin making schools.
- You have an industry that brings in
a lot of potential money, correct?
- Right.
- OK, but remember, you don't sell
that product to the customers,
you're selling it to the businesses.
But that's bringing money
in to your businesses.
It's the businesses that hire
people and you create jobs.
So you need to figure out a way to take
that industry, that product and expand it,
so that it's bringing more
money and bringing more jobs.
Which is gonna help because
then you'll have adults,
you have 45% income.
- We can combine it so that children
who are of suitable ages can have jobs.
- What would be a suitable age?
- Eighteen.
- Eighteen?
This mine is not an easy job, is it?
It's hard work, it's dangerous down there.
To have twelve-year-old kids down there...
- You're still United Nations, correct?
Is that gonna be agreeable to you?
You can create laws that forbid
businesses from running her product.
So whatever she suggests to you,
you have to make sure
that that's OK, because,
remember, you can tell her,
sorry it's not gonna happen.
- Yup.
- Which means you have more money
going out than coming in, correct?
So you need to figure
out a way to change that.
You need some money coming in.
So what are the strengths
your country has?
That you could potentially build and grow,
when she's got the diamonds.
- I saw a pendant on the internet,
and it had like, a string
and there was like three fat
fond doves on one string.
- OK, that's a factory purchase,
but what you could make...
- I don't know.
- That's what you need to know.
What does your economy depend on?
I mean, you have to produce something.
- It says making foreign...
OK, I have a question, what
is a "foreign exchange?"
- It's Nestea's largest exporter,
so you are exporting product.
So you do have some products
that you're exporting.
Oh, you're Taiwan?
You have a lot of textile
factories, you make clothing.
Your country's the one that's
got all the sweatshops.
So that's what you need,
you need to build...
You should be suggesting
some ideas to her.
Giving her ideas, say, OK,
you've got a product to export,
but you need to do this, and you need to
do this, and you need to do this.
- [Student in green] They
need to find some way to pay.
- Exactly.
- Wait, I have a question
for the United Nations.
OK, how you said, setting up your steps,
well if there's not a lot of educated people,
then how are they gonna find teachers?
- Well, if you said, exactly...
Well, first...
- You could hire people from...
- Different countries.
Maybe if you like hired somebody
from like the US that's educated,
they could do administry of helping
like educating adults and
then they're educated.
They're doing the same
thing that kids are,
they've been in child labor and stuff,
plus when they got older,
they're just working again,
so they haven't really changed anything,
so to change that, I
guess, maybe if you got
other countries to come and educate them
and then after that
they could the educate the children.
So you couldn't get the
kids out of the work so fast
because you still have to
educate all the teachers.
And the kids have no where to go.
- Well, I say, since
they're already adults, that
we kinda like, work on the
children more with education.
I guess because the children are small.
- So, before you even take
the kids out of these places
You have to get all the
people, and you have to...
So you have to figure out some, like,
you're gonna have to figure out a timespan
of how long that's gonna take.
It's basically, you're taking,
elementary schools you like.
- I mean, they could set up a scholarship.
That way they could go from like...
- And even, your country could help pay,
help pay the people that are teaching.
Because in the long run, you're gaining,
that money's gonna be spent...
- The population is gonna face it,
they get the cotton for the clothes,
and get the food for their
teachers and all that.
- If we can help poverty...
To help pay for some schools.
- Yes, that would be amazing.
- We could also have all the adults work
the rest of their life,
like, insanely or something.
- I'm the government, I can say,
hey, there's laws now that
a kid's gotta go to school,
and he can't work so many days of work,
so many hours of work.