- Just take it in, but take your
tube off first. Before you pull it out,
before you pull the needle out, take your
vacutainer tube off, and this is...
- Pull it out again?
- Yeah. Use your two by two remember.
- Oh, yeah.
- There you go. Good job, Faye. And, guys,
it just takes a while. This is not
something you're going to learn
overnight. This is a skill that it takes a
little while to learn. You've got to get
hand movements down, you've got to figure
out what works best for you. You know, if
you need things placed in a different
position. But after this, you all can
start sticking the arms when you're not
doing your book work. Then, whenever you
feel like you got all your hand movements
down, you feel like you're proficient,
then I'll watch you, which I'll watch you
doing, then you all will stick me.
So what do you think, Cassie?
- Hmm?
- What do you think? Is it easier than you
thought, or harder than you thought?
- Easier.
- Yay, Faye. Those arms are a little harder
to get... Those veins are not as easy to
feel as...
- That's okay. She's doing a fine job.
Two by two.
- Sorry. You [inaudible] to draw blood from them.
- Pop your tourniquet. Engage your
safety. Good job. From down there?
- Yeah.
- They say not to use these, and you can
use hand veins, but remember, first
choice, second choice, last choice, and
then hand veins. If you're going to do
hand veins, you all have been through a
lot of the book work already, if you're
going to use hand veins, what kind of
needle are you going to use?
- Butterfly.
- Butterfly. Okay I know you all have seen
them use butterfly in the clinic. You guys
will actually rotate through the clinic
lab. We'll do it at Dr. Maderis'
clinic, so that you all can get more
sticks there.
- Is there some people who draw only from
around here?
- Not usually. Now, there are some people,
they'll come in and they'll say, "You
can't get blood from anywhere from me
except here." What that one lady told you,
is right here, right...
- I'm better at popping it out. Remember I
couldn't get it in.
- Good. It will be something that, after
you get these hand movements down, it'll
just happen. Because when I'm not talking
while I'm doing it, I mean, it just flows.
Because I have done it for several years,
but for some reason after you get older,
it's hard to talk and do something at the
same time.