- One eighth plus one eighth is [inaudible]
- Oh, one eighth, okay.
Is she adding one eighth
together a bunch of times?
Where do you see that?
Can you come up and show us?
- You have to get seven of them.
- Okay.
Katriana could you add
that number sentence up
above your picture also?
So I like how you're all thinking
while she's writing this.
There's a couple different
ways we can represent this.
I think Anielli and
lots a groups had their
hand up were right that she did.
I can see she took seven
pizzas and divided it
into eight pieces for eight people.
And I also see where, and
when I talk to Katriana,
she said, "Well I got one
eighth, plus one eighth,
and one eighth, and one
eighth and one eighth.
How much is that gonna add up to equal?
She's got one eighth, plus
one eighth, plus one eighth,
plus one eighth, plus one
eighth, plus one eighth,
plus one eighth.
- Seven eighths.
- Seven eighths, okay.
And that's how much pizza she told us.
What about seven divided by eight?
A bunch a groups kept their
hand down after Anielli shared
that number sentence.
But it's not a complete
number sentence until
we can finish that equation.
What would seven divided
by eight come out to equal
do you think?
Talk at your group for
just a minute again
I think we're just
a little bit unsure.
[Background Chatter]
- What are you thinkin' for
seven divided by eight?
[Background Chatter]
Let's come talk it over
with this group.
You check with this group,
I'll check with this group.
What are ya'll thinkin' up here?
[Background Chatter]
Well, what do you see
in her representation?
[Background Chatter]
You see how many pizza's?
Okay, seven pizzas.
- Eight people.
- And eight people.
[Background Chatter]
Did she divide those seven
pizzas into eight groups?
Okay, so we've just gotta
figure out how much then,
that's gonna come out to equal.
I'm not sure.
Talk about it as a group.
You can draw it on the back.
Okay.
Yes, thank you, ma'am.
Okay, thank you so much for
talkin' with your group.
What did you or someone
at your group think again?
If we've got seven pizzas
divided by eight people.
Katia?
- We've got 56 divided by eight
because there's 56 pieces,
and it's kinda [inaudible].
- Okay, so you noticed there's
56 pizzas, I'm sorry, 56 pieces,
and it's cut into...
- Eight.
- Eight slices.
So you were thinking something
a little bit differently.
Savannah?
- We, I thought the same way except
I thought that it was gonna be 56...
Divided by seven.
because...
Each one of them is shaded in,
and they're all going to [inaudible]
eight people.
- Okay.  Let me ask us all this.
I love that we're relating this back
thinking about some of our math facts,
and how that can tie in and help us.
But what did Katriana start with here?
What do you think the
first thing she did was?
[Inaudible]
What did she do, Steven?
- Drew seven or eight pizzas.
- Did she draw seven pizzas
or eight pizzas?
- Seven.
- Seven pizzas.
Is that what she did first?
Okay.  She drew out her seven pizzas.
So we wanna know, or we need to know that
that's what she started with.
What did she divide those pizzas into?
- Into eighths.
- Into eight.
We see she cut 'em into eight pizzas.
Brennan.
- I did [inaudible]
I was thinking either 700,
or seven tenths.
- Okay.  So we're thinking
back to fractions.
I think since we don't
have a definite answer,
we don't need to yet.
Let's leave this kinda open-ended,
but I'm gonna circle it so that we
remember to come back to it.
So we've gotta a great number
sentence that one thing
Katriana did was add up one
eighth, plus one eighth,
plus one eighth, plus one
plus one eighth, plus one eighth,
and she got seven eighths
and we're gonna
keep thinking about...
I saw a bit of agreement
that seven pizzas,
she divided by eight people.
But we need to figure out, ladies,
how much that would mean
each person gets.
So put a big arrow.
So as we continue let's
keep that in our mind.
Okay, thank you.
Can I have...
The person who put this one up in black.
Faith, was that you?
Will you come tell us what you did,
and what you think the
answer might be here.
How much pizza each person got.
- Well, I knew there
was eight soccer players,
so there were seven pizzas,
so I did seven pizzas.
Then I divided six of
'em up in to fourths,
and then I numbered 'em all.
And then when I got to eight
I started one, two, three,
back over again when I
got to another eight,
I did it again but then I
realized that there wasn't
enough, or more, so
I split the last pizza
up into eighths and that
equals up to eight people.
- Okay, and that equaled up
to eight people.
So how much pizza do you
think each person gets?
- Well, I think that each person
would get at least one fourth,
and [inaudible].
- Okay, so let's write this up here.
So you said each person gets,
let's put it up in black.
How much? Like let's say person number 1.
How much pizza do they get?
Will you show us?
- They would get one, two, three...
They would get three fourths.
- Okay.
- And then one eighth.
- Three fourths and one eighth.
Like this?
Okay, do you know how
much that is all together?
- That would...
That would equal up to four [inaudible].
- Okay.
So let's think about
this one for a minute.
Do you have any questions for Faith
about how she figured this out?
Okay, I think she did a great
job explaining her picture.
So she showed us where each person gets
three fourths plus one eighth.
Will you talk at your group?
How much is that?
How much is that total?
Thank you, if you wanna join a group.
Good explanation.
[Background Chatter]
Okay, group what do we think?
- Four twelfths.
- You agree with her four twelfths?
How did you come up with four twelfths?
- By adding those two together.
- How did you add them together?
- Three plus one would equal four,
and then four would be the numerator
because you added the two top numbers.
And if you added the two bottom numbers,
it would equal twelve for the denominator.
- Okay, so is there a picture,
or is there a way that we
could show this with pictures
that that would come out
to equal four twelfths?
[Background Chatter]
- See, on the back of your paper once
will you draw a representation
of four twelfths?
[Background Chatter]
How come?
- Because.
I thought that if the
denominators were different,
we couldn't add them up directly.
- Oh.
- So, we tried to get
the denominators the same.
- What do we call that?
- Equal to fractions [inaudible].
- I like that your thinking
back to remember
your vocabulary.
- I tried to tell Katia
that if it has a
different number on the
bottom then we're supposed to
add the [inaudible] on the bottom to--
- I don't know.
Have we learned to do that before?
- Well no, but I just thought about it,
and I've been practicing.
- Okay.
So if we haven't learned it
yet we've gotta think about
how are we gonna figure it out, right?
Okay, so keep thinking.
It's okay that we're debating
between a couple different
answers just tryin' to
explain to each other
why you're thinking four twelfths,
and why you're thinking
something different.
- I thought it was [inaudible]
because...
Whenever you add it up [inaudible]
And the denominator [inaudible].
- Okay.  So I understand where you got the
four slices.
But what size are those slices?
Would be my next question.
Because we wanna make
sure every soccer player
gets the same amount
'cause I would be upset if
I didn't get as much pizza as you did.
I like pizza.
[Background Chatter]
Okay.
- Okay, well it says four twelfths,
so we're shading four--
- Do you have 12 pieces there?
- We have one, two, three--
- Okay.
If I can have your attention back.
I know some of you are still discussing,
and doing a great job.
But I wanna make sure that
we've got time to get through
the rest of our solutions
before we're out of
time for the day.
Hailey, if I can have you
close the door again for us.
And can I hear what a couple
of your groups came up with?
I heard three or four different things
as I was going around.
Three fourths, Hannah said
each person gets three fourths
of a pizza and one eighth.
- Faith said.
- How much is that?
Yes, I'm sorry, Faith
said since ya'll sat next
to each other I still mess that up.
Three fourths and one eighth.
How much did you or your group think
that came out to be, Nathan?
- We came up with seven eighths.
- Seven eighths.
- Because when you take three fourths,
and then you take another
circle that shows one eighth,
then you divide the three
fourths into eighths,
then add the [inaudible]
the ones that used to be three fourths
and that equals seven eighths.
- Can you come up and show that to us?
I think, I think I followed in my head,
but did you all have
trouble making that picture
in your head?
- Yes.
- A little bit, yeah.
Can you show us?
You can draw it here, or over
here we've got lots of room.
- Nathan, you're right.
[Background Chatter]
- Shhh.
Okay, let's see what he does.
Okay, can you step to the...
step to the side so everybody
in the class can see you.
There you go.
- And then if you divide
that into eighths,
then you add one of the eighths
then you add this over here.
It comes out to be seven eighths.
- Can I just get in..
agreement or disagreement
somebody who had shared with us.
What do you think about what he just did?
I saw him draw three eighths at one pizza,
and one, or three fourths of one pizza,
and one eighth of the next.
And then I saw him cut
this one into eighths.
How many eighths was three fourths?
When you cut it?
Six eighths.
And then he put one more
eighth over and seven eighths.
What are you thinkin' about that, Brazy?
- I agree with him.
- Why?
- Because our group
said that we know that
four eighths is equal to...
twelve fourths is
equivalent to seven eighths,
and his picture we can
see that it's two
and when he was workin'
it out we could see that
it was right and so I agree with him.
- Okay, Brennan?
- I agree with him, but I have
a different explanation.
- Okay.
- One fourth is equal to two eighths,
but then you take--
- Oh, I'm sorry.
Let me write this as you're
saying it so we can follow it.
So you said...
- One fourth is equal to two eighths.
- Okay.
- So...
We multiplied the three and the numerator
with three fourths.
- Okay.
- By two, which comes
from the two eighths and it
would equal up to six eighths
plus that one extra eighth
it would be seven eighths.
- Okay, so you said
three fourths is equivalent to
- Six eighths.
- Six eighths, okay.
- And then just add
the other one, seven eighths.
- Okay, so
then you did six eighths,
plus one eighth,
equals seven eighths, like that?
Okay, can I just see a
quick, on your remotes,
do you agree or disagree
with Nathan and Brennan?
So, A is I agree.
B I disagree, or I'm confused.
- What's confused?
- We'll just do A and B.
A is I agree, I understand,
or B is I disagree, or I'm confused.
How are you feeling right
now about what Brennan
and Nathan just said?
They're two different explanations.
I just wanna see right now,
do you agree or disagree
with what Brennan and Nathan
just said.
And again they were
saying that three fourths,
plus one eighth is gonna come
out to equal seven eighths.
And they each kinda
explained it a different way.
One with words and one with a picture.
Need a couple more people to
vote if they agree or disagree.
Number three, number eleven we
need a vote from you please.
[Background Chatter]
Where is remote number three?
There it comes.
Okay.
What do we, what do we know
by looking at this graph?
What do we know by looking
at this graph?
Thomas?