Well, since there's less,
- The yellow has less water
- That's true.
- And more H plus.
- Because a higher
concentration of (background chatter)
- The higher the
concentration of the acid?
- Yes.
- So you think it's
something about the acid
that's causing the color.
- Yeah.
- What about the blue food coloring?
(background chatter)
This stays the same?
- Yeah.
- But why would you
think this stays the same
and it's the acid that's changing color?
(background chatter)
Okay, so the concentration
of the blue food coloring
is the same, but the
amount of acid is not.
So I must be changing
the color of the acid.
So it's the acid that's changing color.
- You're not
changing the color of the acid,
though.
- Anybody else got ideas about that?
That something else that could explain it?
That's one hypothesis.
- You put the same
amount of food coloring
in every time, right?
- Yeah.
- Wait, so the acid is probably likely to,
maybe like lose an electron?
- The acid loses electrons?
(background chatter)
What is an acid?
It gives up an H plus, right?
- There are more
moles of Hydrogen ions...
- Right, acid's dissociate.
So I got more molds of H plus in this one.
Okay, Emma, you have an idea?
- Well, there are more,
I think I might have gotten it confused.
Basically, there's a higher
concentration of acid
as you go along, right?
- So more here.
- Yeah.
There's more when it's lighter.
- Lowest, most.
- Yeah, I know.
- Okay.
- So that gives it more reason for a
more drastic color change, then.
Because there are more
H pluses, if you will,
that could cause it to jump in energy.
- Okay, so you got the idea
of energy is some kind of,
something's jumping.
Because you know...
- Could it be the
separation between the two sets
of the orbital in the food
coloring itself that's changing?
- Okay.
- Which is why the
blue color changes to the,
like, brownish yellow.
- So now what is your idea
about what's changing color?
- The orbital, the food
coloring is changing color.
- The food coloring is changing color.
- Yeah, the food, okay,
so that makes sense.
The food coloring is changing color,
but the acid concentration
is making it change color.
- Yeah.
- So the food coloring's like
the dependent variable, right?
- What is in the food coloring?
- That's a good question.
- That's what we need to know.
- What is in the food coloring?
The same thing that's in the
cabbage indicator, actually.
Well, something similar,
they're called anthocyanins.
And I have a little handout to
show you what they look like.
So, before we do that though.
Actually, no, I'll show you
a picture of an anthocyanin
and have you hypothesize a little bit more
about what might be happening here.
So here's an anthocyanin.
It's this molecule here.
So usually anthocyanins have
lots of benzene rings in them.
Okay?
So what is happening, what is
causing the different colors?
So we had the idea of
something to do with orbitals
and something jumping.
- In the food coloring.
- But the food coloring
isn't transition metal.
- It's not a transition metal, no.
- Can you still have that happen?
- Well, what else could there be?
- Well I think it's the O-H because,
- Is it like splitting up the p-orbitals?
- What makes you say that?
- There's like SP-3 orbitals
and I guess p2 orbitals
(background chatter).
- Okay, so are you saying
it's that splitting
of SP-3 and SP-2 orbitals
or the P orbitals?
- I was thinking
it's the P orbitals.
- Okay, so what here would
represent the P orbitals?
- Whatever bonded with the acid.
The O-H maybe?
- Oh, would it be the
(background chatter) no.
- Okay, so here's what we're going to do.
I'm going to give you this handout,
and what I would like you to do.
I want you to highlight
all of the double bonds
in one color.
Then I want you to highlight
all of the single bonds
in another color, okay?
You should have
highlighters by your table.
- Purple.
- I'll take green.
(background chatter)
- Do you want us
to do it for all of them?
- Yeah, let's
just do it, let's do it
for the first one to start with.
Anthocyanins in red wine, we'll do that.
So, anthocyanins are in lots
of different compounds.
Anything that has color
really, wine, grapes,
cabbage, red onions, food coloring.
- Are they, they're not
in colorless though, right?
Or are they?
- Say it again?
- They can't be colorless,
because it's colorless.
- Well, kind of, you'll see.
We'll explain that in a little bit, yeah.
- Is something colorless
because they don't have
any d electrons,
or like the d-orbital
is filled up with electrons?
Or are there other factors?
- Yes, that's true for transition metals,
- But for other things?
- For other things that are colorless,
what would explain why
they were colorless?
- It would have to
be a different orbital.
- Different wave length.
- Like the absorption, based on the bond.
Yes to both of you.
So Riley's idea is that
maybe, so what did we say
color came from earlier?
(background chatter)
Color in general, where does
color in general come from?
Reflecting certain frequencies,
and absorbing other
frequencies of light right?
Okay, so we can only see purple to red.
So is there another explanation for why
something might be colorless?
Because it ...
- Probably because
it's absorbing everything?
- Well, if it was absorbing everything,
what color would it be?
- Black.
- Oh, it's not absorbing anything.
- It's not absorbing anything?
Or not absorbing ...
- Any color.
- It's not
absorbing what we can see.
- It's not absorbing what
we can see, that's right.
It's not absorbing what we can see.
- It reflects all the colors.
- So, you guys see a pattern yet?
Can I borrow somebody's?
Let me borrow yours.
Let's put it under the camera
as an example here.
What do you notice?
- Were we supposed to highlight...
- Single bonds, yes.
What do you notice about the relationships
between double and single bonds?
The double bonds right next to each other?
- The double bonds are
next to the single bonds.
- The double bond
are next to the single bonds.
That's right, that's right.
Okay, in the first one, where you have,
What color is the first one, does is say?
- It just says colored.
- Red wine.
- But we have colored
and we have colorless.
Okay, so in the colored one,
how many, can you count how many times
it goes double-single,
double-single, double-single?
That's like a tongue twister.
(background chatter)
- It's seven in colored?
- I got seven.
- Okay, so now count colorless
and see what you get.
What did you guys get?
- For double-single?
I got like 14.
- Okay, so are you counting
double and single as ...
- Yeah, yeah.
- Okay so you basically got seven, too.
Okay, so do colorless now.
- Double bonds between
every single bond, between
the bonds with the C N-O.
- I got eight for colored.
(background chatter)
- I got 17 in the singles,
and eight doubles for that.
- Okay, what's the difference between
colored and colorless, basically?
And the number of double and single bonds?
- There are more
singles than colorless.
- Okay, not the total numbers,
oh wait, there's more
singles than colorless?
Okay, that's a way we can look at it.
Okay, see if the same...
- We got seven for colorless.
- Okay.
- Is it supposed to be the same number?
- No no, no it's not
supposed to be the same.
(background chatter)
Alright, let's hear
what Gracie has to say.
Say what you just said.
- So, in colored there's more doubles
and there's less singles.
So that means that
there's going to be more
of the single-doubles.
But then in colorless there's less doubles
and more singles,
so that means there's less single-doubles.
- Can somebody restate that?
Just so that I can make sure that you
understand what she said?
- Does that mean that if there are more
double bonds than there
are, that colors (background chatter).
- So, say it again.
- When there are more double bonds
there's a color, or something.
- Okay, when
there's more double bonds
there's a color.
Does that seem like the
pattern we're noticing here?
- It has to do with pi bonding.
- Why does it have to do with pi bonding?
- Because it's an overlap of p-orbitals.
- Overlap of p-orbitals.
- Which allows the delocalized
electrons to like...
- Okay, so what did you say, Con?
- Delocalization.
- Delocalization, the
delocalization comes from...
(background chatter)
Pi bonds, what is a pi bond?
It's the overlap of what?
- P-orbitals.
- P-orbitals, p-orbitals okay.
So when it goes
double-single, double-single,
double-single, what's happening there?
How does that create...
- It's like one big pi bond.
Like when you have, like earlier
you were talking about
whatcha-ma-call-its,
I can't articulate...
- Delocalization?
- No, like...
- One giant p-orbital?
- Yeah, like sort of,
yeah one giant p-orbital.
Like one giant pi bond,
it like expands from like
through different,
- Oh, and like a benzene shape,
and then that makes a circle?
Yeah, and it's not actually
like here's one,
here's one pi bond, here's
one pi bond, here's one.
It's like they're like all pi bonded.
- They're like all
pi bonded to each other, okay.
So in which case, in
which case are they all
pi bonded to each other?
The colored form, or the colorless form?
(background chatter)
- I'd say colored
because they are all
close to each other.
Like the pi bonds.
- The pi bonds, say it again.
- They're close to each other.
- They're close to each
other in the colored form?
So is there more...
- There's more double bonds.
- There's more double
bonds in the colored?
- Yeah, so they would have
to be closer to each other.
(background chatter)
- There are more
double bonds in colored,
less double bonds in colorless.
- Okay, so how many of you
say there's less double bonds
in the colorless?
Less double bonds in the colorless?
Three.
- There's only seven double bonds
in colorless and there's eight in colored.
And there's more leftover singles.
(background chatter)
- Wait, for
which one, for colored?
- Oh, you're counting the far left one.
(background chatter)
- Yeah, this one has eight.
- This is an intermediate one?
- So then it's seven and seven.
- Seven and seven, okay.
So how many, if you
were to try to connect.
So the idea is that it
makes one giant p-orbital.
If you were going to connect
all of the p-orbitals,
which one would have the
most gigantic p-orbital?
- Colored
- Colored.
Is that clear to everybody?
Why did you say colorless?
Did you say colorless?
- Yeah, I don't understand why.
- Because there's
a bunch of single bonds.
- Because the pi bond is
more in the middle of the two
other things (background chatter).
- Wait, for the far left?
- Does that make any sense?
- We're talking
about the far left one.
- Let's look at all three.
So which one of these is going to have
the most giant pi bond?
- The middle one?
- The middle one.
- Because it's an intermediate.
- And they're more double bonds.
- Does anyone
disagree that it's going to be
the middle one that would
have the most giant p-orbital?
Okay.
Alright, let's look
at some more down here.
Did you guys do, does somebody
have these highlighted?
- No.
- I think Rebecca,
you have them highlighted, right?
(background chatter)
- Okay, so let's look at these two here.
Can we apply our hypothesis?
So what is our hypothesis by the way?
- More overlap of p-orbitals
the more colored it is?
- Okay, the more overlap of p-orbitals
the more colored it is.
That's our hypothesis.
Is it supported by these
two on the side here?
- Can we highlight the exterior?
- So what do you think?
Is our hypothosis supported by these two?
Alright, Con, can you explain?
- Well, I mean it just
looks like there's a bunch
of conjunctions of single
bonds where the streak
of double-single is kind of broken.
- Okay, right, so there's
a streak of double-single,
double-single,
double-single, double-single,
double-single.
So imagine you start somewhere.
Have you guys ever heard
the song that never ends?
- Yes.
♫ This is the song that never ends ♫
- Okay, we're not gonna
sing it, it never ends.
So in this case, if we were
to just go around going
double-single,
double-single, double-single,
would I ever get to an end necessarily?
Would I here?
How about if I went double, still single,
double- single,
double-single, double-single,
- But that's single, single.
- Single, single.
So which one's going to have
a more extensive pi bond?
The top one, so that sort
of fits our hypothesis
that the more pi bonding there
is, the more colored it is.
Okay, so what causes
color in these compounds?
- Shared electrons?
- More shared electrons,
that are shared how?
(background chatter)
- Pi bonds.
- More pi bonds equals what?
- More area for
the electrons to move around?
- Okay, more area for them.
More delocalization, okay.
So let's take it back to this,
to our acid and blue food
coloring demonstration.
Why are these different colors?
What is happening here?
(background chatter)
Let's put this together.
- Oh, is it the H is taking more of the
delocalized electrons
because H is positive?
- What do you think?
- Because there's a higher concentration.
- So say it again.
- Okay so since H is a positive ion,
it takes more of the, since there's more,
it takes more of the
delocalized electrons?
- Okay, so it's taking more
of the delocalized electrons.
So how does that explain the color change?
Can somebody add onto that?
- There's less electrons
so I guess there's less...
- More double bonding?
- There's less energy absorbed?
- No, there's increased...
- So, is
more energy being absorbed,
or less energy being
absorbed when it's yellow?
- More energy is being absorbed
that's why it's yellow.
- Exactly, that creates further
(background chatter).
- Because there are more electrons bonding
with the H plus than there is in the...
- It's about absorption.
- Ah, okay Ruth, say that...