- Welcome to Mrs. Dunford's
first grade classroom.
Here you see a Word-Work center,
where students are working to build words.
All around the room,
student work is proudly displayed
along with anchor charts
to anchor student learning.
At Computer Center,
students are working on
differentiated computer
programs based on needs.
At Listening Center,
students listen to stories
to build their fluency.
Above them is our Word Wall,
which displays our sight words.
Our Center Chart.
The students are working
on the Smart Board
to integrate technology into reading.
Here we have students at Read To Someone,
where they are enjoying
reading books to each other.
Around the back of our
room, books are separated
into book bins for genres and
they have their book boxes.
At Read To Self area,
students read independently
and enjoy reading in our tent.
In the back, we have our
marble jar for compliments
and our How Was Your Day board,
along with our Helper Chart.
And last we have My
Table, where I work with
small groups based on needs.
Thank you for joining our classroom.
- Okay boys and girls,
we just read the biography
by Maurice Sendak.
Can you tell me what is a biography?
Let's see... Cassandra.
- A real story.
- A real story, you're
right. Kiss your brain.
What is it a real story about?
Christopher?
- It was a real story
about Maurice Sendak.
- It's a real story about Maurice Sendak.
A real story about a real what?
- [Christopher] A real author.
- A real author.
Could it be about something
other than an author?
- [Christopher] Yes.
- Yes, as long as it's
about a person, right?
A biography tells us about a person.
We're going to fill in
this graphic organizer
about Maurice Sendak.
It has different sections in it.
The first section says "Childhood."
Can you read that with me?
- [Everyone] Childhood.
- The middle section says "Life."
What does it say?
- [Everyone] Life.
- And that last section says
"Books." What does it say?
- [Everyone] Books.
- Good. And we're going to
fill things in from down here
to tell about his childhood,
what happened in his life,
and some books that he wrote.
Can you help me fill those things in?
If you're ready to help me,
can I see your hands up?
Good. Put your hands in your lap.
We're going to read this one first,
"Worked at a toy store."
Can you read it with me?
- [Everyone] Worked at a toy store.
- Hmm, where would that go?
"Childhood," "Life," or "Books?"
Andrea, what do you think?
- [Andrea] Life.
- Life. Why do you think that?
- [Andrea] Because...
Because...
- [Mrs. Dunford] What did he do?
- [Andrea] He wrote stories about...
- [Mrs. Dunford] He wrote stories,
but he "worked at a toy store"
and that happened during his what?
- [Andrea] Life.
- It happened during
his life, you're right.
Go ahead and move this
to where it says "Life."
Good job.
We're going to give her a
McDonald's cheer, ready?
- [All Children] ♫ Ba da
da da da, I'm loving it ♫
- Good job. Let's read this one.
"Where The Wild Things
Are." Can you read with me?
- [Everyone] "Where The Wild Things Are."
- Hmm, where does that one go?
Grace?
- [Grace] Books.
- [Mrs. Dunford] Why do you
think that it goes in Books?
- [Grace] He wrote it.
- [Mrs. Dunford] He
wrote it, you're right.
Can you move it where it goes?
(footsteps)
We'll move it just a little
bit closer. There you go.
Good job. We are going to give
her the Truck Driver, ready?
- [Everyone] (car honking)
Good job there buddy.
- Oh, but this one down
here, "Born in Brooklyn."
Can you read it with me?
- [Everyone] "Born in Brooklyn."
- Where would that one go? Stephanie?
- [Stephanie] Life.
- [Mrs. Dunford] It could go in his life.
Why do you think that it goes in his life?
- [Stephanie] Because
he was born in Brooklyn.
- [Mrs. Dunford] Because
he was born in Brooklyn,
that's a fact about his
life. Where else could it go?
When you're born you're a what?
- [Stephanie] Baby.
- [Mrs. Dunford] You're a baby.
So where else could that go?
- [Stephanie] Childhood.
- [Mrs. Dunford] It could go
in Childhood, you're right.
Good job. We're going to
give her a Fantastic, ready?
- [Everyone] You're
(spraying water) fantastic.
- [Mrs. Dunford] Good.
Let's look at this one.
"Won Caldecott Medal."
Can you read it with me?
- [Everyone] "Won Caldecott Medal."
- Hmm, when did that happen?
Houston?
- [Houston] In his life.
- [Mrs. Dunford] In his
life. Why do you think
that it happened in his life?
- [Houston] Because he wrote a book
and he got it for his book.
- [Mrs. Dunford] You're
right. Exactly right.
He wrote a book and he
won it about a book.
- [Houston] Would you put in "Life?"
- You're right, it went in "Life."
Perfect. Good job. Let's
give him the Piano, ready?
- [Everyone] ♫ Dun dun dun dun ♫
♫ You did a good job ♫
- So "Kenny's Window."
Can you read it with me?
- [Everyone] "Kenny's Window."
- Where would "Kenny's Window" go? Dylan?
- [Dylan] Life.
- Is "Kenny's WIndow" something
that happened in his life?
You can change your answer.
- [Dylan] Um...
- [Mrs. Dunford] Where do you
think "Kenny's Window" would go?
- [Dylan] Books!
- [Mrs. Dunford] You're
exactly right Dylan.
Why would it go in Books?
- I don't know.
- Okay, let's talk about
it. "Kenny's Window."
Was that a book that he wrote?
- Yes.
- Yes, So would that go
in Books for that reason?
- Yes.
- Yes. So can you move
"Kenny's Window" to Books?
- Yep.
- You've got to touch
it a little bit harder.
- I got it.
- Okay, good job. Right
there, Dylan, is good.
Thank you, Dylan. It's good there.
I'll move it up a little bit further.
There now it's out of the way.
- Can I do this?
- Okay, you want to do the disco ball?
- [Everyone] ♫ That's
the way, uh huh uh huh ♫
♫ I like it, uh huh uh huh ♫
♫ That's the way, uh huh uh huh ♫
- [Mrs. Dunford] Good.
Let's look at the last one.
"Liked bedtime stories."
Can you read it with me?
- [Everyone] "Liked bedtime stories."
- Where would that one go?
Let's see...
Cassandra?
- [Cassandra] Childhood.
- Childhood? Why do you think
that it would go in Childhood?
- [Cassandra] Because
his grandpa and grandma
read him some stories.
- [Mrs. Dunford] Because they
read him stories, didn't they?
Good job. That completes
our graphic organizer
on Maurice Sendak.
Now, I have your own
biographies for you to read.
Everyone should know where they go.
And your own shoe biography
for you to fill out
because remember we're going to do a
display in our hallway
that's called Famous Footwear
and have our shoes displayed
for everyone else to see.
Alright, right now I want you to stand up.
I want you to glue cotton on your shoes.
(stomping)
Stick some marshmallows in your mouth,
and go to your area to
read your biography.
(footsteps)
(inaudible)
- [Mrs. Dunford] Alright, I
want you to sit a little more
in a circle and then I
want you to read two pages
and then I want you to fill it out, okay?
(background chatter)
Can you read the title? Can
we read the title together?
Ready?
- [Everyone] "Joseph Burcheck"
- Good. Who's Joseph Burcheck?
- Him.
- Yep, that's right.
Open up to page two, Dalton.
There you go.
Stephanie, can you start for us?
- "Joseph Burcheck"
grandma and grandpa [inaudible].
There were lots of beautiful
plants and hills where they live."
- "Grandma had many books
she liked to read
and so did Joseph."
- [Mrs. Dunford] Good. Stop there and look
at your graphic organizer.
Look at your shoe.
Is there a part of that
shoe that you can fill out?
- Yes.
- Which part do you
think? You think Family?
And you think Childhood,
Dalton. Let's start with Family.
What part do you think would go in Family?
- Grandma and grandpa.
That he did what with Grandma and Grandpa?
- Read books.
- He read books with them.
What else did he do with them?
Can you re-read this part?
- "There were a lot of
beautiful plants and hills
where they lived."
- "They lived." What do
you think that means?
That he what with his Grandma and Grandpa?
- Lived.
- He lived with them, that's right.
So can you write that in Family?
Put that in Ideas. And
then let Dalton tell you
what he thinks goes in Childhood, okay?
- Got it.
(background chatter)
- [Mrs. Dalton] What
do you guys filling in?
(background chatter)
- How do you spell "lived?"
- [Other Child] L...
- No, lived.
- [Dalton] L-I...
V-E-D.
[Mrs. Dalton] Who does his live with?
- He cheated.
- [Other Child] Grandma and Grandpa.
- His Grandma and Grandpa? Is that what
you were going to add to
the graphic organizer?
You're exactly right.
You're doing a good job.
Jenn, I think she needs the marker.
There you go. Keep it up.
Keep up the good work.
- [Girl] H-E R-A-N [inaudible]
(background chatter)
- [Blonde Woman] "Her family
was quick to hang up her work."
Your turn.
- [Group] "Her family was
quick to hang up her work."
- [Blonde Woman] Nice job.
And we have a Family section
on here, so what do you think Dylan?
What did her family do?
- [Dylan] Put her pictures up.
- That's exactly right,
they "hung up her work."
Good job Dylan.
I'm going to show you where. Right here.
T-H-E
- Do you know why they're
putting that in Family?
Can you tell me? Because
her family did what?
What did her family like to do?
- Put pictures up.
- Hang up her pictures, that's exactly why
they're adding it to Family.
- [Blonde Woman] Go ahead and
finish what you need to write.
- [Mrs. Dunford] You've
got to finish it, Dylan.
You're doing a great job.
- [Blonde Woman] There you go, her work.
(background chatter)
- Why is this a biography?
- [Little Boy] Because it tells by a...
girl and she's writing books.
And she was reading books and writing.
- You're right, it's a biography.
A biography is a story about a real person
and that's exactly what she was.
Can you read me one of these?
- "When Amy was little,
she liked to read."
- [Mrs. Dunford] Good.
And why does that belong in Childhood?
- Because she was doing it as a child.
- [Mrs. Dunford] She was
doing it when she was little.
You're right. You're exactly right.
Now, who's going to fill in the ideas?
Who knows where did
she get her ideas from?
Do you know where she got her ideas from?
- [Little Girl] From the books.
- From the books. Well, actually,
where did she get the ideas for the books?
Can you read this part for me?
- "Amy liked [Inaudible]
about a lot of books.
Things people say help Amy."
- What helps Amy?
- "Things people say."
- Things people say. So where
does she get her ideas from?
- People.
- People and the things
that they tell her, right?
Things that they say.
Can you write that in the Ideas part?
- Yes.
- Good job. The things that people say
are what help her and give her ideas.
Houston, can you help her direct that?
That would be great.
You guys are doing a fantastic job.
(background chatter)
- [Houston] Oh, you wrote the wrong stuff.
You're writing on the wrong side.
(background chatter)
- She's writing that whole section. Why?
Can someone tell me why she's
writing that in Childhood?
Clint, do you know? Why is
she writing that in Childhood?
Why is she writing that
Joseph did things with his
Grandpa in Childhood?
- [Clint] Because he used
to watch him play guitar
and go in the woods
with him and talk nice--
- Did he do that when he was an adult
or when he was a child?
- Child.
- Right, so is that why
it would go in Childhood?
- Yes.
- Jeffrey, can you tell me
what is this story about?
- [Jeffrey] It tells real stuff.
- [Mrs. Dunford] It tells
real stuff about what?
- Joseph Burcheck.
- Joseph Burcheck, yep.
That's what it does.
It tells real things about
him. You guys are doing great.
Keep up the good work.