- At first, we put only tap water in it,
and then we all of a sudden changed it.
- So, but there's still tap water in
with the oily water.
- So, you think that's why
the control got messed up
because it had too much
- [Voiceover] Well, that's not
variables changed.
- [Voiceover] my only reason.
- What's the other reason?
- My other hypothesis for the control cup
not growing was, like...
the seeds were duds.
- [Voiceover] Were your
guys's the oil ones?
That one's not yours?
- [Voiceover] No.
Ours is the one that's all grown.
- Oh, why don't you go get your cup
and show people?
- So this is oil?
Okay, well the oil one
did grow really fast
and all of a sudden,
it died, it looks like.
Kind of.
So, like at first, it was
normal with that thing,
and then, well--
- [Voiceover] I don't
understand that chart.
- Yeah, me neither because it looks like--
- It looks like it didn't grow,
then it grew really, really fast,
then it went down.
Super (mutters).
- What happened was it grew,
and then it over-polluted,
and then it just died.
Looks like that.
- Well, like. ...
(students laugh)
- Well, like, what I don't get
is, I see the other oil one,
it seems like the oil one is
growing bigger than the other ones.
- [Voiceover] It just, like,
suddenly grew all of a sudden.
All the oil is the same with
the control, which you have
all of a sudden, all of a
sudden, also these diagrams.
Also, in the control diagram, that went
back down to zero centimeters.
- I don't know.
- Yeah, this chart might have messed up.
(boy mutters)
Because that means both these plants die.
- And then the control regrew.
- [Voiceover] Yeah, it
doesn't make any sense.
- [Voiceover] It doesn't.
(students chat)
- It turned white, and then
it died and turned brown
because on my chart, it grew point...
it grew ...
it grew 0.14, and then 0.14 again,
and then 0.04, so
like alive, dead, alive and stuff.
- When it grew the second time,
did it grow or did it subtract?
- The second time, I think it died,
and then the last time
it just kept on growing,
but the first time it started growing,
it grew, second time
it grew one centimeter.
- What did you put in to help it grow?
What did you put in it to help it grow?
- Oily water.
- So, did the oil or the
manipulator control grow more?
- The...manipulative one (mutters)
grew more because it
grew and then it died.
- So, why do you think it did that?
- Because, like, I, what I thought
is that it was too much oil on it,
and then oil gets on the leaf, it like,
it helps the plant
grow or something.
Just killing other--
- Doesn't the plant feed off the leaves?
So, the oil got spread on the leaves,
and then it's feeding
the oil, then it died.
- Look at yours compared to mine
because yours is way more controlled ones
than ours does because the only one we had
was the experiment plant.
(students chat)
- Do you, I think the
reason why the vinegar
or the acid rain made
it grow because, like,
acid is good for you, and
it's mixed with water,
so it's not too bad for the plant.
But I think it got way too much acid,
and acid actually eats things.
It kills it, and that's
why I think the plant
is all dead because, like you said, Nolan,
it did grow, because acid is good for us,
but yet when we have too much, it dies.
So, that's why I think this
plant is all shriveled over.
- I agree with you because
acid is part water, and
that's what rain is,
but there's a little bit of acid
so water's good for you. But acid,
it doesn't grow, it's
not good for you, so--
- [Voiceover] Well, actually,
it is good for you, but not a lot.
- I think you're--
- Maybe just a little bit of water
in it more than acid rain,
and then when we kept
spraying the acid rain on,
maybe it got too much acid rain.
And then the acid rain
overtook the water and died.
So, it like decreased by a lot.
That's why I think it's just
like the Red Bull because
Red Bull is, like gives
you really much energy
and then you just crash
without any energy.
See right there?
Just like Red Bull.
- [Voiceover] It increases
and then decreases.
- What'd you think, Misha?
- Well, yeah.
I think like what you said, Nolan, because
the regular plant grew
just fine, and then that,
the experiment grew, like, good,
and better than the regular one,
but then it, like, the
acid overtook the plant
just like Nolan said.
- What else I noticed
about my control plant,
it started big at first, and
then it decreased in size.
Then it got bigger, so it's
going off and on in size.
So, it actually did kind
of better than this
because at the end, it
did better than that one
and the last opposite ...
- It like, died, after the second one,
it only stayed for a couple
of days or a couple weeks.
- Yeah, but it was only
to a point it was living
because, when I did my second observation,
it was still kind of full, but
it was broken on the side. So it started
falling into a point where it fell in
and got buried in the
oily water, basically.
(students chat)
- It died.
- My actual skin and everything,
the plant grows faster,
but it also dies faster, and I figured
from like the oils on my hand--
- Why do you think it did that?
- Because the oil on your hand--
Because the oil on your hand
may not be the exact same thing
as, like, oils in a car, but
oil still has the same base.
- But how does it make
the plant grow faster
if you touch it with your hand?
- I don't know.
Instead of wearing gloves, maybe it's just
the stuff inside of
the oils and everything,
but it grew faster, and also died faster.
Like, the plant that we
have now is dying faster,
but this one, since it has
water normally and everything,
it's healthy, and stayed
big the whole time.
But the other one is like that
(mutters) but it died.
- If you have, what you
were saying earlier,
when you have oil on your hand,
and then it was, you polluted it with oil,
don't you think you polluted that one too?
- No, well, like, it's,
my whole point is that it
speeded up the process.
- [Voiceover] What speeded up the process?
- Like the oil, when I
plant a bean or something,
when I plant bulbs for tulips or something,
and I touch it with my
hands instead of my gloves.
Then it actually seems,
I may just be paranoid,
but it grows faster, and then my mom put
hers with gloves and it didn't grow as fast.
I don't know the depth of
that part or something.
- I don't get what you're saying.
Are you saying that you have a magic touch
and you just make plants grow faster?
(laughs)
- No, I think it's just
the oils of your skin.
- So, what would the oils in
your skin do for a plant?
Like the oil for your plant here?
- Is it the same like
the oil that we used?
- Like, it didn't make them healthy,
but it just made it grow faster because
this one took a little
bit longer to get bigger,
but the other one--
Show me your data that suports that.
- This?
- [Voiceover] Yeah.
- [Voiceover] What's your
data that supports that?
- The ...
These ones.
- Yeah, the one the data that
supported it was that, oops,
is... (clears throat)
is it went with the control.
It already had grown,
and it was after a week,
and ours still hasn't grown. And
it was growing at 0.16 centimeters
per day and then the next time,
it was growing 2.7 centimeters a day.
- [Voiceover] So, what does that tell you?
- That it was growing a lot faster,
but it wasn't necessarily
growing as efficiently.
- Okay.
What do you mean by inefficient?
- Efficient.
- What do you mean by efficient?
- I mean, like, it grew
faster, but it wasn't
necessarily healthy for the
plant for it to grow so fast.
- So, was there other
evidence that you would use
that would prove that it wasn't healthy?
- Yeah, because the leaves now,
they're all gross and blotchy, and
they're dying and they're crunchy
and not as soft and smooth as these.
And they have a shine to
them because of the oil.
- What, did the rate
of growth confirm that?
- At first, it was kind of
spiked for a little bit,
and then it started going back down,
and now it's dying a lot
faster than the natural plant
because these plants, it grows
in a steady period of time.
With that, it grew really fast,
and now it's dying really fast.
- [Voiceover] So, what
conclusion did you get?
- That oil still makes the plant grow,
but it's not necessarily healthy for it.
- Do you agree?
- Yeah, because me and ...
Because my group,
my experiment, when we did this,
it was growing super fast,
and now it's like dying and stuff.
And we think that the oil
has a chemical in it that
speeds up the process
of the plant growing, but then it
speeds up and of slows down the process
of the plant dying because ...
- On the grass a little bit,
and the number of leaves
will only be like two,
and then it shrivels up and died.
And then the color would stay light green,
and kind of brown, like
how it is right now,
and then my data was,
according to my graph,
the acid rain plant grew
more than I thought.
It grew 25 centimeters, but
it started to die because of ...
(students chatter)
It turns light brown, and started to die.
The leaves increased from two,
all the way to six leaves by the end.
- Okay.
My question was, what would the effect be
if I changed the water to salt water,
and I put, if I change the water to salt,
I predict that the plant will stay
the same height as the control plant.
I predict a number of
leaves will stay the same
as the control plant.
I predict the color will
be white-ish gray-ish.
My manipulator variable
is water to salt water.
According to my data, I was correct
because the height was the same,
and the number of leaves were the same.
The data shows the height of both plants
were zero centimeters
and the number of leaves
was zero on both plants.
The rate of the growth was zero.
On the salt water, there was crust
on it, and it was ...
- [Voiceover] Restate that
so that Jessica gets it,
and see if Jessica knows.
- And then like, we were saying,
Olivia was talking about
maybe how it looks burnt,
and then, like, you know how water,
it attracts a lot of light,
and so people get tan.
- [Voiceover] Yeah.
- [Voiceover] Faster, and then so,
maybe the shine for the oil
maybe, it attracted more
of the heat from the light,
and it burnt the leaves, so.
- [Voiceover] Like, the glisten from it.
- [Voiceover] Yeah.
Maybe that's why it looks all burnt and...
- Because it reminded me of when you
see the old movies like
how it's a burnt reel,
- Piece of paper.
- Something like sands off
in the reel of a video,
and you just see a hole get
bigger on the burning screen.
That's what it kind of reminded me of...
- Because it has a
brown wrinkle around it.
- And then it's dark, and
then it's kind of brown
and crisp, so that's what
it kind of reminded me of
and that's what made me think of it.
- Yeah, and then, how
I thought of the idea of
it attracting the light and heat
was how Olivia said that
when you're in water,
it attracts more heat and light to you,
so maybe that's how.
So, that's how I got the idea
of maybe that's what happened.
So, do you have anything to add, Jared?
- No.
- You, Jessica?
- Okay.
- Okay, so I think the reason why mine
didn't grow like before how
the salt would have absorbed the water.
Because when Mr. Kelson sprayed it,
all of the salt right
here, you could feel it.
It's all stuck to the top, so the water
can't get down to the soil and all that.
So, it can't grow at all.
(students chat)