- Well, let's say about like a plane.
A plane can use the wing to, like,
slice right through the, the wind,
making it just fly with ease,
but let's say the wing was vertical,
and then it would just be
working like a parachute
and just stop its fall.
- Okay, did everybody
hear what he said?
- No.
- Daniel, did you understand
what Jonathan was saying?
- Yeah.
- Okay, so does that make
sense to you then,
Daniel?
- Yeah.
- Okay, John?
- About the thing, the last part,
did he say vertical?
- Yeah, like, like, like,
vertical, like pointing upwards.
- Oh. Okay.
- What do you think?
Reese, what do you think?
- Um, what Jonathan said?
- Jonathan, would you kind
of say it again?
Reese would really like
to pay attention
and he'd like to hear.
- Yeah, I'm saying, like,
like a wing,
it uses, like, like,
like a V shape of a duck,
of a duck squad.
Like every single wing
goes down each part
and then it's just like a V.
- Okay.
- Shayla?
- Um, I said they fly because
the air pressure in the wings
gives it stability to keep stable
and make sure it doesn't
fall onto the ground.
- Okay.
Kelsey?
- Um, I think that if the
aerospace vehicle was in space
then I think it would
just float in space
because there's no gravity.
- Okay, we're kind of...
yeah, Ramaji?
- Okay, I'm kind of lost...
- Ramaji is lost, let's
help her find herself.
No, that's a good thing.
Because, I'll be honest,
I'm a little lost.
So tell me where you are.
- Like, I thought we were
supposed to put, like,
why we think they were built,
not how they were built,
like, like, I wrote, um,
I think aerospace vehicles
fly to improve society and help,
and new aerospace technology helps
build modern things.
- Okay.
Can everybody understand where Ramaji
went with her answers?
Kelsey?
- I'm totally lost now.
- Okay, here's what happened, okay,
so let me see if we can find
this a different direction.
Um, in reading all your
different sentences,
most of us had a purpose
for aerospace vehicles flying, okay,
or some of you wrote
that they fly both in
space and in the air, okay,
and so we're not kind of getting
where I want to get to.
So can I, for a second,
kind of change the discussion?
Just because... Yes, John?
- Is it, like, when you
take a rocket, like,
on the rocket it has, uh...
two wings and like one tail?
- Great, so,
his question that he asked,
does a rocket have
two wings and a tail?
Um, here's what's happening.
Mm, I thought the vehicles would help you,
and what I'm seeing is,
having the vehicles is
making you try to figure out
what it is about how
this vehicle was made.
And I'm not as concerned about
how this vehicle is made, okay,
as I am the science behind
how it flies and why
we design it that way,
does that make sense?
- Yes.
- Okay, so can we go a different way
with me for a minute?
Each of you has a picture
of a hot air balloon
on your table, correct?
Okay.
I know, I took yours, Reese,
which is why you don't have one now.
I need to know something, okay?
This vehicle doesn't have an engine, okay?
Okay?
Now, I want you to think
about this for a minute,
and I want you to discuss
it at your table
before we talk whole group.
I want to know how does
this hot air balloon fly,
how does it get in the air,
and how does it stay in the air?
And is it possible you don't
know anything about this?
- Possibly?
- Possibly.
It is possible, okay,
it is possible, Joelle,
you don't know anything about this, okay.
So I want your table group to share
what you know for a couple of minutes
about a hot air balloon
and how it flies, okay?
And I'm gonna come around and talk
to different groups, okay?
So how does this
hot air balloon fly?
[Background Chatter]
Okay, so you two start the
discussion at this table.
[Background Chatter]
So, discuss that,
because some of us did
have a good concept
and some of us don't, okay?
So share in your group.
Okay, what do you two know?
[Background Chatter]
Okay.
Has an engine, a propulsion engine?
[Background Chatter]
Okay, but is that an engine?
Okay, so now you can
do your discussion.
What did you come up with over here?
[Background Chatter]
So the fire blows hot
air into the balloon.
[Background Chatter]
Okay, without it, it would do what?
It would fall down, okay.
Okay?
So, any idea why the hot
air makes the balloon rise?
What do you think?
[Background Chatter]
Okay, okay.
[clapping]
Ooh, that was awesome.
You are so good today.
Um, I think
we're now getting somewhere.
So let's talk about this hot
air balloon for a minute, okay.
So, I've heard some different
things around the classroom,
I want to know how does that balloon
get into the air?
Nathan?
- The fire in the hot air balloon
blows the, the balloon up
to where it can float down.
- Okay, Shayla, do you agree or disagree?
- I agree with that, because, yeah,
because you pull on a cord
and like, it lights up the fire and stuff,
and then the fire pulls in air
and it, like, shoots it up with the fire.
- So, is the fire being shot
into the hot air balloon?
- No, air is.
- What kind of air?
- Hot air.
- Hot air is being shot up
into this part.
Okay. John?
- Didn't they say one of
those, like if you compare...
- They can't, Jonathan can't hear you.
- Oh, sorry.
If you compare a hot air
balloon and a balloon,
they're, you use hot
air for the air balloon,
and you use the helium
for a small balloon,
yeah, and the,
it's not really air, kind of,
I thought it was steam.
- Okay, okay.
Now why would you think it was steam?
- Because you know how when you just, um,
when you put like a fire,
fire in one place,
it sometimes can turn into steam? Maybe?
- The fire turns into steam?
- No, not the fire,
but like when it's, when it's done...
- Ann Maria says she thinks
you need the word "water."
- Yeah, because when you heat up water,
then steam comes up out of it.
Because steam is, like, moisture.
- Steam is like moisture that's...
- In the air.
- In the air, okay.
Ramaji?
- I agree with you, John.
[laughter]
Okay, I think what he's saying is,
because in air and the
fire is there or whatever,
and so then when they're
getting pushed up
that comes and like, then...
I'm lost here!
Okay, like then the steam,
like,
yeah, you were right
about the moisture part,
but it, but there is no way
that, like, water is in this...
- There isn't water in there!
- Yeah, I mean...
- Reese, be supportive.
[laughter]
- I mean, there's moisture in the air,
but still, like...
fire is a big part of it!
- Okay, can I ask a question?
Okay?
Do I need water
in order for the hot air balloon to fly?
- No, no you don't!
- Ramaji says no,
Laura says no?
- I said no.
- Mariah says no.
Kelsey?
- I'm totally lost!
[Background Chatter]
- Kelsey, it's okay to be lost, okay.
Kelsey,
you're, if you're lost,
you need to know where you are.
So here's the question,
what do you feel like
you know and understand
about what's been discussed so far?
- I thought I was
understanding everything
until John said...
I'm so confused right now!
- So tell me...
- John was talking about steam.
I would agree, Kevin,
John was talking about steam.
So the question is,
prior to that, Kelsey,
okay, prior to that,
what would be your understanding
of how the hot air balloon flies?
- Basically,
nothing before that,
I just think it's steam,
because of like hot and air,
because, or like,
there would be like a
fire inside of the air
and then it would be steamy...
- Okay, let's see if I can
bring around some concepts.
Ramaji and John, can you let
me have two seconds, okay?
Um, we have a concept of
this fire that's heating air,
but we also seem to
have a concept of water
that gets heated and creates steam.
Correct?
But I'm also hearing,
and I just want to make
sure I understand,
I'm hearing that the steam
isn't necessary
for the balloon to go up.
John?
- Well this is, this is
how I thought it was steam.
Because you know how
sometimes there's clouds,
and you, you want to go
up in the air balloon,
and sometimes it might rain,
like when you're in the air balloon
sometimes it, like,
when you pass through a cloud
and the air is super hot,
it actually turns into steam I think.
- Okay.
Ramaji?
- Listen, I've got to come over here.
- Okay, so like, like...
- You two can put your
hand down for a minute
and I'll go to you next.
- So like, steam is,
I think it's putting pressure,
like on the balloon to like,
make it go up?
- So we feel like we
have air pressure, okay.
- I don't agree with Ramaji though
because with the air
there's no steam involved,
there's like, kinda like what John said,
he said when the planes come
up the hot air pushes it...
- Okay, I'm gonna ask...
Oops, I didn't let you speak.
- Well, like, it's just like,
like comparing this to
a regular balloon,
with helium it would float up
just like an air balloon,
but you can't put helium
in an air balloon.
- Does everybody understand that?
So if I put...
okay, that is an awesome analogy!
So everybody listen.
If I put helium, helium is a...
- A gas!
- A gas, okay, helium is a gas,
so if I take a regular rubber balloon
and I put helium in it,
the helium because it's a gas,
helium floats,
that makes my balloon float, right?
Whereas if I just blow up
a balloon, what happens?
It just falls down on the
ground and I got nothing, okay.
On the flip side, Kevin,
what she's saying is,
with a hot air balloon,
instead of filling it with helium,
I'm filling it with hot air, okay?
Now I have a question,
I think you've got to think
really deep about this one.
If hot air, Reese,
is what makes my hot
air balloon go up, okay,
I want to know,
would it be easier for me
to fly my hot air balloon
on a warm day or on a cold day?
Just think about it for a second,
just think.
Would it be easier for
my hot air balloon,
do you think,
to fly on a hot day or a cold day?
- What about on a windy day?
- Ooh!
Okay, she said what about
on a windy day.
Let's assume that there's a slight breeze,
on either day, okay,
but the temperature is either warm
or the temperature is cold, okay?
Kelsey?
- I personally think that
it would be better
to be on a hot day,
because then the sun would be
helping with all the hot air
so then it would make the air
inside the hot air balloon
warmer to help it fly higher.
- So I'd get radiation into the balloon?
Okay. Ramaji.
- I think a cold day.
- And why on a cold day?
- Because, like,
there's not, I mean,
even on hot days,
there's still, like,
low humidity sometimes,
and so, like, it,
you basically with fire would kind of...
I don't know, not set your hair on fire,
but like...
[laughter]
No, when it's cold there's
no moisture in the air,
so like, it would be, like,
like helium, but like...
- Okay, Shayla?
- I think that it's a hot day.
One of the reasons is because
there's hot in the hot air balloon,
and if it was on a cold day,
there's a fire in the thing,
in the hot air balloon,
it could blow out the fire
and that could make the whole thing
just plummet to the ground,
and people could die.
- Okay.
Ann Maria?
- I think it would be
better on a cold day,
because, well, I don't know if
this actually really makes sense,
but, like, the hot air would be working
against the cold air--
- Exactly!
- And like if it's on a hot day
it would be like the same.
- Just a second.
So Ann Maria,
if the cold...
if the warm air is in
the hot air balloon,
and it's a cold day,
what would you expect to
happen to the balloon?
- Go up.
- And why would you expect
the balloon to go up
on a cold day faster than on a hot day?
- Because...
like, the hot air would be...
pushing against the cold air,
faster than it would be
pushing against itself?
- Okay.
Over here.
- I agree with Shayla on the hot day,
because, like, a regular air balloon,
just regular heat would make it go up,
but if you had the sun hitting against it,
I think, it would help with radiation,
like the sun would help out...
- The fire?
- Yeah, how it has something
to do with radiation.
- Okay.
- I think the sun hitting
against the balloon
would make it go up higher.
- Okay. Nathan?
- I think on a cold day,
because it would give it
less chance of popping
from the hot air,
that might pop it.
- Awesome.
Kevin, what do you think?
- I think the same, hot air,
because I've never seen
a hot air balloon
fly when it's cold.
- Okay. Dakota?
Oh wait, Kevin, I have a question for you.
How do you define a cold day?
Okay, what's the,
okay, here's my question, okay.
You said you'd never
seen a hot air balloon
fly on a cold day,
and what I'm asking is,
is there a particular
season that you would say
the air would be too cold?
- Winter.
- Winter, okay.
Dakota, what do you think?
- Uh, I think, uh...
- Kevin, Dakota can think on his own.
I know he can.
- I don't know.
- Cold day, warm day,
what do you think?
- I think a warm day,
because it would be easier to fly?
- Okay, Daniel, what do you think?
Cold day, warm day?
- I would say a cold day,
because the hot air
would meet the cold air,
so it would be more enhanced,
going up you'd get more from the hot air.
- Okay, I need to kind of
bring this to a close real quick,
and I know you two have lots to say,
Tyree, did you want to
add the last comment?
- Yeah.
Uh, I think the hot day,
because who would go out on a cold day,
when the higher you get,
the colder it gets.
- Okay, Tyree says
who would go out on a cold day,
because the higher you get,
the colder you get,
so Tyree's logic here is that
if I'm going to go in a hot air balloon,
I don't want to get really really cold.
Okay, ladies,
I know you have lots to add, okay,
but I kind of want to
bring this to a close,
but I need to know a crucial question.
So everybody has to
commit to this question.
I want you to--
don't do it until I tell you to!
Ready?
You're gonna hold, um,
you're gonna hold your arm straight up
if you believe the better day
would be the warm day,
and you're gonna hold your hand
at the side of your shoulder
if you believe it would
be the cold day
that would be the better day.
I didn't say go yet!
Okay, on three, everybody.
So, does everybody understand?
This is cold,
this is warm, okay?
Ready, one, two, three.
Okay.
Okay, now hands down.
I have just two more questions,
and then we're gonna close
out today's lesson, okay.
Question number one.
I want to know if you've
ever heard the word...