(kids talking)
- Yeah, I wanna
talk to you some more.
- This is cool, that's probably how you
attract them is start doing this.
(kids talking)
- Hey, tell
me why you think, Adam,
he's able to do this again.
- Because he has these legs,
like his legs stick to the ground
so I think they can do it
because they stick to the
ground to get the strength,
then he pulls it up and he does it again.
- Hey, that
sounds like a connection
to what we've been learning about
the structures and the functions.
Yeah, so when it's time to
start making those connections,
I really want you to write
that down with your team.
Just make sure that
that gets on your paper.
Okay, I want you writing out,
how many paper clips
is this beetle pulling?
- Two grams.
- Two grams, right
now mathematician get busy.
(kids chattering)
- Okay.
I'm gonna keep putting another
one on here to make sure.
- Put four on there,
let's see if he can do it with four.
Hey little buddy, don't, don't, don't.
No, no, no, no, pull him away.
- What am I doing?
- He's making a sound!
He's making a sound!
- He's making a hiss--
- He's making a hissing sound.
- You think?
Why do you think he's hissing?
- Maybe because he thinks
we're trying to hurt him.
- Yeah, for self defense.
- Yeah, alright.
Let me go check in with some other teams.
You all keep working on your beetle.
- Okay.
(kids talking)
- What's going on
at your all's beetle team?
- He's pulling-
- The beetle
is pulling two times its weight.
- Two times right now?
- Yeah.
- So how many paper clips
is that that he's pulling?
- Two.
- Three, three.
(kids talking loudly)
- He's pulling three.
(kids talking)
(giggling and laughing)
(coughing)
- Your beetle's not moving.
You think it's because of the loudness?
- Yeah.
- Class city class,
should you be going to
other team's beetles?
I know it's fun, and I
know it's interesting,
but should you be going to
other team's experiments?
- No, ma'am.
- You need to
be engaged with your team.
Okay.
- We're trying to--
- Okay.
Did he pull two?
- He's pulled two
and then we're gonna--
- He has pulled two?
Okay.
So let's see, let's just give him
a little nudge in the rear.
- When I put a pencil right
here, he'll go after it.
- Oh, well see if that
works, do you think--
- I know, like earlier he was trying
to get out of the bucket.
- Let's see if he
can pull it? He's doing it.
He's moving.
- Oh my gosh.
(kids talking)
- I see he's moving
some, but I haven't seen
the paper clips move yet,
that's what we have to wait and see.
Are the paper clips going to move?
- Wait, I have to do my job.
(gasp)
- They're moving!
They're moving!
So he just pulled three grams?
Okay, so...
Did the beetle pull three grams?
Beth, where's your sheet?
Go ahead, help.
(kids talking and chattering)
Talk to each other about what's happening.
- Woah, you can't hold him,
you have to leave him on the table.
- Wrecking ball!
- Somebody pick these up.
- I got it.
- You hold
him up, good, teamwork.
You hold him up.
- You're hurting
him, you're hurting him.
(kid yelling)
There we go, now we've got
four paper clips on there.
Now, lets put the paper clips behind him.
Now...
Talk to each other.
- I think he's, I think he'll be able
to pull many, many, many.
Right now.
- I think the
beetle may be able to pull--
(kids talking louder)
- Eight, eight.
- That's how many we have.
- Oh, this
team over here has eight,
I might need to go over...
(kids talking loudly over each other)
- Woah, wait, wait, wait.
- Get a green.
- Let's see him in action.
- I am noticing that
we underestimated our beetles, didn't we?
(kid yelling in victory)
(kids talking)
We underestimated our beetles, didn't we?
- Yeah.
- Our beetles may be able to
pull more than we anticipated.
- We can do nine.
- Okay.
- Not yet, not yet.
- Keep working,
mathematicians keep track.
- He's going.
(kids talking)
- Talk to me team
about what's going on.
- He can talk.
- It can pull nine times...
- It pulled eight.
- Its body weight.
- It is pulling
nine times its body weight?
Wow, how many paper clips is
- Nine grams.
- Nine grams?
Holy moly.
Did any of you all
predict that this beetle
would be able to pull nine grams?
- No, we only did
all four.
- We only
thought four, he'd pull four.
- We only thought four.
We only thought four.
Okay, are you all making any connections?
How in the world is this beetle
able to pull nine grams of paper clips?
Nine times its body weight.
What do you think--
Oh now look, when it's on
the desk is it able to do it?
- No, its harder for
him to do it on the desk.
- Why can't
it do it on the desk?
- I think he might have a better grip
on the construction paper.
- What grips better?
What structure is gripping better
on that construction paper?
- Because it has--
- It's because
it's got,
it's got like suction cups
and I guess it's not used
to the slippery desk.
- It has claws to pull it.
- It's pulling it.
- I think it looks really--
- It's what, Abby?
- Even though it's really loud
in here its still moving.
- It's still moving even though
it's loud in here, that's right.
- I think it just wants to go to Justice.
- You think the beetle's trying
to go to Justice?
I don't know about that.
Are you gonna try a tenth paper clip?
- Yep.
- Yes.
- Look, look ten.
- Ten paperclips?
Let's see.
(kids talking)
(squealing)
(kids talking loudly)
- He's taking your pencil.
- He's wants to get your pencil.
- Oh, why do you think?
- Because it's
wood.
- Because he likes wood.
- And what type
of animal is the beetle?
- Bess, Betsy beetle.
- But what do they do?
Why do they eat wood?
- They are...
(kids talking at the same time)
- It's pulling ten!
- Why does the
bess beetle eat wood?
- Look at him, I don't know
if he's pulling ten or not.
Look at him.
- Because he's a decomposer!
- He is a de--
He is barely pulling ten.
He's having to work really, really hard.
- Yeah.
- I think it's probably time to
stop adding them to the beetle, you think?
- I put max.
- Maximum is ten.
- Do you think we can add--
- Class city class,
if your beetle is struggling
and, like, arching its back and, like,
flipping its legs, but
it's barely pulling it,
it may be time for you to give the beetle,
we don't wanna be mean
to the beetle.
- Our max was ten.
- Okay. So, we're left on,
thank you for taking them off.
(kids talking)
- Alright class city class.
- Yes, baby, yes.
- Put your eyes on me.
Oh, I'm waiting.
I'm waiting.
Thank you.
Most of us have come to the point
where the beetle is struggling, okay?
And having a hard time pulling the weight.
At this point, if your
beetle is struggling
it is time to start the
summarizer and the connector job.
Okay, so I wanna hear
you talking, summarizing,
connecting what has happened.
(kids talking)
- Let's give him a rest.
- Yeah, let's give him--
- Wait, don't pull that.
- Oh my gosh.
- How many is he pulling?
- Seven.
- Okay, here,
I'll bring you some more.
Where are the rest of your paper clips?
- Right there.
- Get off.
- He's starting pulling.
- Okay, oh be nice
to my beetle friend.
- I'm trying to.
He keeps on getting his foot
stuck to my hand.
- Hi little buddy.
Oh, I almost touched it!
(kids talking)
- We learned
before that beetles...
- Hang on, you're
learning that beetles what?
- That beetles are really strong,
but with their little legs
and their thorax maybe.
- Their thorax you think
is what makes them really strong?
- Because the thorax, it may be
the biggest part in their body.
- Yeah, it is
probably the biggest part.
What else on their legs,
what on their legs are helping it?
- Their...
Look at it.
I know what it is.
Their...
- The thing that's sticking to the table
and helping it move faster.
- Okay, so the
sticky part on their feet?
- Here, let me do it.
- Yeah, okay.
- You all have
done a really nice job
noticing what structures of this beetle
are helping it to be so strong.
How do you think it uses that in the wild?
Like out in nature?
How do you think it uses that?
- It's functional and it almost--
(student talking drowns out speech)
- You may even think it's cool,
but he could use his wings to fly away.
- Some beetles
do have wings to fly away,
but what do you think is,
I need you in your seat Nathan,
what do you think it's using to move?
Its, that's a lot of
strength.
- Its abdomen?
- Right, okay, its
abdomen is, but in nature.
What might it use that for?
- It might use it to catch its prey maybe.
- Okay, what does it...
What does it do?
What does it eat?
- It may eat...
- Casey, say
it again to your team.
- Organic
and it breaks it down.
- It breaks it down.
What is that called?
What type of insect would--
- It's a, it's a d...
- A d...
A d...
(laughs)
- A d...
- A D.
- A disposer.
- Not a disposer, close.
- A decomposer.
- That's it!
(clapping)
Not a disposer, but a decomposer, good.
And so okay think, it's okay.
Think about if it was trying to
dig into the wood of a tree.
Wouldn't it have to be really strong?
- It can make a hole.
- In the wood of the tree.
- That little thing, the little...
might be to decompose the wood.
- So it can bite and then break down.
- It's really gonna have
to be biting harder.
- Yeah, that mouth
part is really strong to bite.
Okay, so now may I have your attention,
how many do you have?
- We have 10.
- You have 10 and it's pulling it,
let's send him home.
- I want 11.
(squeals)
- They're moving, look at his legs
how hard they're trying to pull.
You might, he might be able to pull 11.
- I'm gonna give him one extra.
- No!
- No 12.
- Okay, you
all keep working on that,
you're doing a great job.
- Thank you.
- I wanna come
back to my very first team.
- Carrying 10.
- 10?
- Ours can carry 11.
- Yeah.
- It did?
- And he pooped on the paper.
- Okay, it pooped?
- Twice.
- It pooped twice?
- Yeah, twice.
- Okay, let me put this here.
I don't know where to put it.
There we go.
So what are you doing?
Are you adding 11?
- We're gonna see our 11 puller.
- You're gonna do 11?
What connections can you make?
- The legs are like a crayfish.
- The legs are like a crayfish?
- Yeah.
- How?
- They have joints.
- They're jointed.
How do you think those
joints help that beetle
to pull 11 times its body weight?
11 times, how do those joints help it?
- The beetle is like a, able to grab on.
- Yes, so, Tim's saying
something, say it loud.
- It helps it walk.
- It helps it walk, but--
- And escape from predators.
- And escape from predators, how?
- Because--
- What might it do with
those powerful legs?
What did we notice them
doing in their containers?
They get under the what?
(noise drowns out kids)
- They get under the rocks and the dirt.
- Like, Tim, like when
he was on the corner
Tim was, like, picking him up,
and he was holding on to the paper.
- He was holding the paper?
- Tim lift him up.
- Okay.
- Oh yeah, it's neat.
- I can make a connection.
- What's your connection?
- If we didn't have jointed legs
we couldn't walk up stairs, if
we didn't have jointed legs.
- If we didn't have jointed legs,
we couldn't walk upstairs, right?
Is that what you said Coner?
- You're okay.
You're okay.
Alright, I want you talking to each other.
Help Halle, she's writing
down some of your connections.
Help her, team, help her.
(kids talking)
- Talk to Halle.
- What's another thing?
- The aphid's have pincers
and the bess just have...
- Tim's telling you something.
- It has little
like claws.
- Hang on,
Tim's telling you something.
Listen to Tim.
- The aphids have pincers and
the beetle has these things,
that helps it eat out the wood.
- They look like little--
- They look like pinchers.
- The beetle has....
a pincher like a crayfish.
A pincher
like a...
- Oh, this could pull 11.
- Good
connecting, keep connecting.