- Well, we all thought
that a diamond might be
a pure substance.
- [Teacher] Why?
- Well, I think a diamond
can only be cut by itself,
and can only be cut with
a different diamond.
- [Teacher] OK.
- So that's really dense, so we thought
that if anything was added to it,
something else would be able to cut it.
And that would be something
else that was less dense.
- So, interesting.
What is, um ...
You're talking about density.
What is density?
- It's a characteristic property.
- A characteristic property.
So this is good.
You definitely should be
starting to lean towards
what you know about characteristic
properties of matter.
Okay?
That is key to helping you
understand the difference
between pure and mixture.
Who can tell me what a characteristic
property of matter is?
Hannah?
- A property that stays
the same regardless of
the amount of the substance.
- Yeah, a property that stays
the same for a substance
regardless of the amount.
So what I'm hearing you
say, is that you think
the ability to cut into a diamond
has to do with its density.
And you're saying that because
you can only cut a diamond
with a diamond, it must mean that
the densities are the same.
And so, since the density is the same
for the whole diamond,
that means it's one substance.