- [Teacher] That's heavier
automatically sink.
Hang on one sec.
And then, we'll try to
work through this one.
If something is heavier
than something else,
will it automatically sink?
Are ships heavy?
Do ships sink?
Occasionally, right?
Especially if you're on that cruise ship,
like last week, did you hear about that?
- [Boy] It depends on the--
- [Teacher] Okay, now we're talking about
depends what it's in.
So, now we've got all these
different ideas working.
Holy cow.
Yes, ma'am, anything else to add?
- I was gonna say, I don't know why,
I'm just gonna hook on
this whole list of things,
but, like, a tin can
will float if it's empty,
because of the air
that's stuck inside of it
holds the object up.
So, if that was hollow, I'm guessing
that it would most likely float.
So, the ships are hollow in the bottom,
the air that keeps it up,
but the bottom, how part of the ship
goes in water is because
part of it isn't hollow.
That part sinks, but the air in the boat
will keep it up and
that's how things float.