- What part of soccer
you really want to know?
- What about the measuring
or even the measure?
- That's what you've got to figure out.
- Or how long you can.
- Okay.
- I mean how many like,
times you can do it.
- Okay, so you could sit there
and count how many bounces,
kicks, or you could sit
here with the timing.
- How much you can do it
and how much time you need.
- Okay, how many per minute.
So, you've got lots of ideas.
You're going to have to choose that.
Do you need a little more time
to bounce it off each other?
- Yeah.
- Okay, so I think you
have both come up with,
all four of you.
You guys come up with an
experiment to support each other
and you two come up with one.
And you'll collect your data
and you'll collect your data
and then present it as a company.
How about that?
(Inaudible) soccer team or company.
Alright?
Alright, you've got a good name.
Alright, that's part of it.  It works.
Catch your attention.
- I know, Stephanie.
- We're having trouble.
- Because we barely decided on it.
We didn't do the friction one, but
the one where you drop the marble in the
the shampoo bottle.
The little car that you pull back
and see how far it goes.
- (Inaudible)
- Okay.
- And the parachute one,
so I thought of the parachute one.
- What do you think?
- Yeah.
- You're a team on it, okay.
So, what are you going to
measure with a parachute?
- (Inaudible)
- Pardon?  Yeah, you're going to use
metric, which is centimeters.
Stephanie's got control of the metrics.
So, can you tell me what your experiment
is going to look like
with these parachutes?
- Well, we don't know how far (inaudible).
Because we know we can't
throw it out the window.
- Oh no.
- It's too far.
- Okay, but you know what...
- Maybe on the counter?
- You guys are coordinated,
I would let you stand on this counter
and you could kind of
measure different heights.
How high you could...
You could do some test runs, right?
- Yeah.
- Don't you think scientists
would do test trials
before they make a real decision?
Okay.
- Yeah.
- And you know what?
If you'd like, if we have time,
I want you to do test runs in here,
but we could do a final
drop off the balcony
and get it clear.
- That's what I was thinking.
- Okay, but I do want you to
do test runs in here first
and then we could do a final.
But make your hypothesis,
what you're thinking
because I think you're on a roll here.
It's going to be good.
- I don't like his interview.
- So how far?
- In this experiment,
can we put like some sort
of weight on the parachute
to see how fast or something?
- Okay, I think you're making
another experiment, right?
So, what's your first experiment?
- Just how fast it would drop by itself.
- How fast from one distance?
- Yeah.
- Okay, so one distance
you're going to see
how fast it'll drop.
And then you're going to compare that to
from that distance.
- Adding weights to it.
- Okay, alright.
- Well, I wondered how
far will the parachute go
from different heights.
- Okay, so she's got one experiment
and you've got another one.
Do you want to do two in one
and kind of combine it together?
You do yours and you do yours.
Because you only can change one
variable at a time, right?
- Yeah.
- So, what's your variable
you're going to measure?
- I'm going to measure
the distance, how far.
- How high, different distances.
And what are you going to do?
- (mumbles)
- And you're going to time it, right?
- Yeah.
- Okay, and you're going to do,
what's your variable that
you're going to change?
- The weight.
- Okay.
But you're going to see how fast it drops?
- Yeah.
- Alright, so I think you're
going to need another paper.
- Okay.
- Because you've got two
experiments going.
Are you going to support
each other in each one?
- Yeah.
- That's pretty cool, double points.
How are you guys doing?
Oh, I like it.
Okay, tell me about this one.
- Okay, so we're going to get two or three
different size basketballs,
like a really small one
and maybe a medium one
and then...
Yeah.
And then we're going to like
have two meters or a meter
and like drop it from there.
So, like how high it bounces
depending on its size.
- Oh, so the size of the balls
to see how--
- High it bounces.
- Okay.
- If it bounces higher (inaudible)
(inaudible).
- What do you think?
- I think the small
one will bounce higher.
- Because there's less material to like
have to drop from there.
- Like when in gym class when they have
the huge balls for exercising,
if you drop a bigger one
usually it doesn't go up as high
and the smaller ones do bounce higher.
- So, based on your observations.
You're a good observer.
- [Voiceover] So, your
large ball went the highest
and you thought the small one would.
Whoa, are these your averages?
- [Voiceover] Yeah, they're my averages.
- Wow, okay.
Good.
So, how are you guys going
to present it as a team?
- She's probably going to
do like what we thought
would happen (mumbles).
And I'm probably going to do the results
of what actually happens.
- [Voiceover] Are you
comfortable with that?
- Uh-huh.
- Okay, to make it really
clear what you did?
- [Voiceover] Yeah, yeah.
- Okay, I think that'll be really good
because this is great,
this is great to show,
and then you're writing
your conclusion with numbers
in it, I like that.
And then you told, yours
was rejected, right?
- Yeah.
- Okay, now does that
mean you're a failure?
- [Voiceover] No.
- Do you guys mind going first?
- Sure.
- [Voiceover] Because if they
see that yours is rejected
and yet you still could write
up a scientific experiment,
I think that might give
them some confidence
and it'll take the pressure off them
because they don't really want to go first.
- [Voiceover] Okay, so let's go.
- (Spanish)
(mumbles) Aqui tenemos que cambiar la
friccion sobre dos.
(Spanish)
Tenemos que cambiar.
- [Voiceover] Oh wow,
the graph looks good.
And your data chart looks good.
So, Jenni will you shows yours?
- On the first dictation thing
when we have to go up there,
do we have to go up by step,
like show everything?
- [Voiceover] What do you think?
- Or just show our graph?
- [Voiceover] What do you
think would be the best?
- [Voiceover] I say showing the graph.
- Should we show like, our question
and then should we show the whole thing?
- [Voiceover] What do you think?
- I don't know.
- [Voiceover] I think so.
Showing both.
- Okay.
- But it's probably the
most important thing
to convince them.
I'd definitely show your data.
- [Voiceover] Okay, we'll show his
because it's better than mine.
- Okay, very good.
And let's see, yes it looks professional.
So, these numbers...
How many times did you do this experiment?
- Three times, wait, four,
three, twelve.
- [Voiceover] 100, I don't know.
- [Voiceover] Because there's
five and there's three.
15 times.
- Okay.
We've got one, two, three,
four, five trials here.
Is that correct?
- No, we went up three,
but he wrote trials
for these.
- [Voiceover] Oh, okay.
So, we can fix that?
- [Voiceover] (Spanish)
Que dibujaste? No tienes que poner esto.
(Spanish)
Tienes que poner esto.
- It's very neat.
So, you added one, two, three
and divided by...
- [Voiceover] By three.
- [Voiceover] Okay, alright,
that's how you got the average?
- [Voiceover] Yeah.
- [Voiceover] Okay, and
who figured out the answer?
- Me.
- [Voiceover] Jenni.
- Wow, Jenni.
- We did, was it highest to lowest?
- [Voiceover] Yeah.
- Highest minus lowest, divided by two.
- Awesome.
You definitely should show this.
And then this would be uncertainty.
- [Voiceover] Yeah.
- And these are the mounted distance
with different kinds of...
What are these five things?
- [Voiceover] The shoes.
- [Voiceover] Okay.
- [Voiceover] It gets tiring when you have
to do it three times.
- [Voiceover] Right.
Now my question is, if
you didn't have the shoes
how did you get the data for it?
- [Voiceover] I did it at my house.
- You did them at your house?
Okay.
And then what's this one right over here?
- [Voiceover] The socks.
- Okay, and that's one you
definitely did at school?
- [Voiceover] Yeah, we did it here
and we also did the Vans here.
- And the Vans.
Alright, so that's good.
Would you explain that to the class?
- [Voiceover] Yeah.
- That these you did at home
and these you did here
and so would you have
any sources of error?
- Yeah, because of the surface.
Like at his house it would have been
not like floor, it would be carpet
or something like that.
- [Voiceover] Yeah, what's your floor like
where you did it?
- [Voiceover] Well, I had to do it like outside
during the rain.
- Oh my goodness.
Okay, so you've got to explain that
and then do you think that would
affect your experiment any?
- [Voiceover] Yeah.
- Okay, maybe it would.
And so what would a scientist do
in the next time?
- Would have done it in a dry place.
- [Voiceover] Yeah, do it in a dry place.
- [Voiceover] (laughs) Yeah, I like that.
Okay, so you'll tell
that for the next time?
- Yeah.
- But I really liked how
you guys didn't give up.
How you actually did the socks
compared to your Vans.
- And you know how you pull those out
what are (inaudible) research,
we could have done your boot.
- [Voiceovoer] Oh yeah, my boot.
Yeah, I could have.
Want to do my boot?
- [Voiceover] No, I'm good.
- No (laughs).
- [Voiceover] My legs are tired (inaudible).
- Okay, I'm sure they are.
- [Voiceover] Well, did
you accept or reject
your hypothesis?
- Accept.
- [Voiceover] We accepted it.
- [Voiceover] And tell us why.
- Because (inaudible).
- [Voiceover] You've got
the evidence right there,
don't you?
- [Voiceover] The experiment,
like that one question we had,
it goes with the real world
or something like that.
(inaudible)
- [Voiceover] Could you
repeat this experiment?
- The whole thing?
- [Voiceover] Yeah, or could
anybody do this experiment?
- Yeah, it's easy.
- [Voiceover] It is?
Did you write your procedure so it's easy?
- (inaudible)
It's hard to write a procedure
because it (inaudible).
- [Voiceover] Okay, and if you had to do
this experiment over again,
would you do it any differently or not?
- No.
- [Voiceover] Would you
test for anything else?
- (inaudible)
- [Voiceover] Good point.
How much pressure, right?
Okay, alright, any other questions?
Nice job. Thanks.
(class applauding)
Jenni's team.
Sorry to rush you guys,
but we got the idea.
(class chatting)
- [Voiceover] What was your experiment?
- Our experiment was to find out
what types of shoes would work
to do the moon walk.
(inaudible)
uses four different pairs of shoes
like Adidas, (inaudible),
Converse or Vans.
The Adidas would go the farthest.
The Vans (inaudible).
(inaudible)
- [Voiceover] No, just show the data.
- You were correct.
(inaudible)
And you were correct
because the Adidas were here
and the first time it
went like 112 centimeters
and the second trial
it went 118 centimeters
and the final was like 12
and then it was like 116.6 centimeters.
(inaudible)
We accepted our hypothesis.
Jenni, continue this.
- [Voiceover] Why me?
- [Voiceover] Because you're professional.
- Well, we were going to do
an interview (inaudible),
but we forgot to.
(inaudible)
So, what do we do?
It's really bad.
- [Voiceover] Why do you
think it's bad, Jenni?
- I don't know.
- (Spanish)
Esta bien, esta bien.
- Well, here's the amount of distance
and here's the kind of (inaudible)
and I marked them as the
average they all went.
So, we can see that the Adidas went more
than the Vans did
because the Vans were like, the lowest.
(inaudible)
- [Voiceover] Will you tell
us about your source of error
because that was interesting.
Because you had a good way to solve it
if you did your project over again.
- Oh, yeah.
Well, it's because Jose
did half of the experiment,
he did it at home
and the other part of it we did here
and I think it did it different
because he did it in the rain
and we did it like on dry.
So, I think that affected the experiment.
- [Voiceover] There's probably
different traction on shoes.
- (Spanish)
Si.  Simon.
- [Voiceover] What kind of
shoe would you try next time?
- A boot.
- [Voiceover] Oh, like my
major walking boot (laughs).
- Si.
- [Voiceover] Alright.
What would you hypothesize would happen
if you tried my boot?
If you look at the...
- Well, because it's soft,
so I think it'll go farther.
- Possibly go farther.
- [Voiceover] Okay, alright.
That would be interesting to try out.
Does everybody see how this can apply
to real life?
- (inaudible)
- (Spanish)
Tienen preguntas?
Hablan en ingles, no espanol.
- [Voiceover] Can you
explain how this would apply
to real life, if you
aren't just moon walking?
- Jose?
- Jenni?
- Don't look at me.
- I don't know.
- [Voiceover] Go on the actual moon.
- [Voiceover] Gym class.
- [Voiceover] Yeah, gym class.
- [Voiceover] Does anybody
change out of their shoes
for gym class?
- [Voiceover] Sometimes.
- [Voiceover] Okay, some people do.
- [Voiceover] I don't.
- [Voiceover] You don't?
- [Voiceover] Yeah, like
these shoes, they slide a lot
like, in the gym (inaudible).
- [Voiceover] Okay, so it
might be different shoes
for different jobs?
- [Class] Yeah.
- [Voiceover] Okay, well thank you.
Nice job.
Good, we have time for
our last presentation.
Thank you.
(clapping)
Alright, sorry to rush everybody.
I know you could talk more about it.
Thanks for being a good audience.
(class chatting)
- Hello class, how are we doing today?
- [Class] Good.
- So our title was
dirty water versus clean water.
Thank you.
Our experiment had to do with a sailboat
in four different types of water.