- [Student] Like, learning is
supposed to be a privilege,
not a burden.
It's like...
Supposed to be...
Like, that's why we're America.
We have the choice, you're not
supposed to be forced to...
do it.
- [Teacher] Okay.
- [Student] Um, but like,
about them picking a
random person, they might,
they might not just go
pick a random person
if they have to vote, because,
if they have to vote,
then they're gonna go
see that candidate,
candidate's political
beliefs are, and what
he or she is gonna do for the country.
- [Teacher] Okay. Trevor?
- [Student] But, if um...
they're not gonna know which one to pick
if they're not educated, or,
don't know about the person.
- [Teacher] Okay.
- [Student] What if they don't know how to read?
In their researching.
They don't know how to read.
- [Teacher] Okay.
- [Student] Do you want me to say my question?
- [Teacher] Yeah, go, ask your question.
- [Student] Okay, um...
If only, like, when we don't have...
the law, only 60 percent vote,
so, how is that supposed to show
what America really wants?
How is that supposed to
show what president we want,
and what choices we wanna do?
- [Student] But, if,
we do get the other 40 percent
that already don't wanna vote,
then they would just pick one,
and that still wouldn't be the,
the will of the big United States.
- [Student] And outta the 60 percent
votes, you could just make your,
uh, votes outta that.
- [Teacher] What do you mean?
- [Student] Like, the people that did vote,
just, choose a person who
did get the most votes.
- [Student] But we wanna see what
America as a whole really wants, not what
a little over half of America wants.
- [Student] Um, our founding fathers
vote for the right to vote,
for, for freedom,
and so, I think we should use that wisely.
- [Teacher] Okay, elaborate
on that a little bit.
Say that one more time.
- [Student] Um, if our founding
fathers vote for the right to,
or fought for the right to freedom,
then, I think we should
use that correctly.
- [Teacher] So, you think,
that, if the founding fathers
looked at this law, they would say,
'this is not what we meant, when we said,
you know, we want people
to vote for our leaders',
they didn't want us to force people,
they still wanted it to be a freedom.
- [Student] Didn't we like,
like,
have the law,
for,
like, trying to get the opinion of
the whole population of America?
The other 40 percent,
it still, wouldn't be like,
their decision, because they would just,
pick one, they wouldn't really care.
So, they're not really
getting any difference,
by not having the law.
- [Student] But we're not forcing
them to do that,
we're forcing them
to help America.
- [Student] So, you're forcing them...
- [Teacher] Okay. Jackson,
can you respond to that
point?
- [Jackson] Um. Yes, if you, like,
if we don't force people to vote,
then, maybe the poor,
just can't make it there.
And if we say, 'oh, you have to vote',
then we,
then we could like
provide them transporation
to get to there.
Also,
if poor people won't vote,
that means rich people will vote,
and they'll just...
vote for the person
who they believe is gonna keep them rich,
and that they'd not go against that.
- [Teacher] Do you think that that
represents the majority of Americans,
if only those, wealthy,
or, at least, middle to upper
class people are voting?
- [Jackson] No.
- [Teacher] No.
- [Jackson] Because if the poor people don't vote,
they're already poor,
that's already bad enough,
and they don't get to
voice their opinion, and
in a democracy, too.
That's just even worse.
- [Teacher] And that's a big
segment of people, right?
So, you're saying that,
really,
a lot of these people, maybe it's that
it's not that they don't want to vote,
it's that they don't have the opportunity,
we need to provide some more...
public, um,
opportunities, like,
opportunities like public transportation
to allow them to vote,
to make it easier.
Okay?
- [Student] 'Cause it's,
not only
poor and uneducated people,
it's just people that
really don't care that much,
and like,
when making
those people vote,
like kind of what she said, they could...
most, a lot of 'em could
try and break the law,
if you force them to vote.
Because they just don't want to
and they really don't care,
and like, if there's somebody who has...
who doesn't care but,
they're being forced to vote,
and they have a really busy job,
and they have a lot going on,
they wouldn't have time
to research, or anything,
and so they could,
they would just have to go out there
when they did have to vote,
they'd just vote for someone,
'cause they never had any time to
do any research or look
at something about the...
people to vote for.
- [Teacher] Okay, let's
come back to that point,
'cause I think we still
have some questioners,
who haven't...
asked their question,
who's, who's up next?
Jaylen?
- [Jaylen] Um...
you say there are, different ways to...
give them their complete and to vote,
but, what are those ways?
- [Student] What'd she say?
(Chuckling)
- [Student] Well, if you have, things...
- [Teacher] Hold on. Let me,
let me make sure they
heard what you're saying.
Say it again, but say it louder.
- [Jaylen] Okay. Um...
(Chuckling)
I say, it's different
ways, to get them to vote,
but what are those ways,
that you get them to vote?
- [Teacher] Does anybody have
a ready response for that?
- [Student] I can't hear her.
- [Teacher] She's saying,
you guys are saying there are better ways
than compulsory voting laws,
there's other and better ways, so,
what are those ways?
- [Student] Like,
just because they're poor,
doesn't mean they can't know that like,
you can like,
hang up posters, or like,
get someone to hand out
flyers or something.
It doesn't have to be all electronic.
- [Jaylen] I'm not talking about poor people.
(Chuckling)
- [Teacher] Well, she's saying...
- [Student] It could help anybody, really, but...
- [Teacher] Okay. Respond...
- [Student] Well, but there are poor
people that wanna vote,
they don't have a chance to.
- [Student] Excuse me?
(Chuckling)
- [Teacher] Well, hold
on, hold on a second.
Hold on, hold on,
'cause I, I'm not sure that y'all are
understand what her point is.
Say your point again.
- [Jaylen] Um...
- [Teacher] With some passion.
- [Jaylen] With passion?
(Chuckling)
- [Teacher] 'Cause
that'll make your point.
- [Student] Just scream at her.
- [Jaylen] WHAT are different WAYS that
(Chuckling)
you can get the American people to vote?
- [Teacher] Besides.
- [Jaylen] Besides posters, because
a poster's not gonna...
- [Student] It's compulsory voting.
- [Teacher] And besides these laws,
what are some better
ways to make people vote?
- [Student] Well y'all keep sayin' go and like,
pick up people, and
providing transportation,
well instead of doing
that to make them vote,
you might as well just
do that so that they
might have the opportunity to vote
rather than having to vote.
- [Teacher] So you don't
necessarily have to
have these laws,
to still provide some public services
to encourage people to vote.
Okay.
- [Student] And like,
we all know that we get those like,
very long phone calls that are like,
vote for this person because,
they're gonna do all this stuff,
and like, that then, like,
someone who gets that phone call could
actually think about it, and then like,
'maybe I should vote for that person',
and you see the big...
billboard thingies that have the
big names on it, and all
the signs in the yards,
and so, that could make you think,
'well, maybe I should go vote,
since...
all these people are saying we should
vote for that person.
- [Teacher] So you,
you think they should
have an increase in...
in publicizing elections, we should,
we should have more advertising
when elections come up? Okay.
Okay, (Backgrond Chatter)
- [Student] Well, if you were to like, have
election... (Background chatter)
um...
that would like, cost a lot of money,
to have like a lot of, um...
transportation going around.
So, um, and it's like,
not a lot of people are gonna use that
transportation,
then why, just like,
(Background Chatter)
so, why not just make them vote, cause,
they already have public
transportation out there.
- [Teacher] Okay.
Let's top on that one,
we'll come back to it,
because we've got one more question.
- [Student] Uh, if we didn't
require people to vote,
what would happen if...
what would happen if like, nobody voted...
decided to vote?
- [Teacher] Say that one more time.
- [Student] If we didn't require people to vote,
what would happen if like,
nobody decided to vote?
- [Student] Or a small majority of people.
- [Teacher] Okay.
- [Student] Well, people have
different opinions, like,
some people think that we
put a voice out into the government,
and say what we want,
and then, some people think, like,
that, we...
that every vote counts.
And...
basically, there's...
like, five...
three million people in America,
and I don't think every single one of them
would not vote.
- [Teacher] Okay.
Any other responses?
- But we already have 60 percent voting.
I mean...
and, so...
we know every,
some--people are going to vote.
It's just the people who...
don't care about politics,
and,
just, like,
when we had the survey,
people, a lot of people didn't vote
for the midterm election.
But, on the other hand,
some people did.
We're always gonna have a group
that doesn't vote, and a group that
is voting, and if you make them vote
they're not gonna care.
Even, as more,
as they did when they weren't voting.
- [Teacher] Okay,
I'm gonna go ahead and open up the floor,
because we've asked all the questions, so,
pretty much anybody can answer or ask,
but let's try and keep
it on the same topic,
so, if you are raising your hand,
make sure you're responding to what the
last person said.
Okay?
Uh, let's see. Connor.
- [Student] Oh, like you said, every
vote counts, but like,
we need more people to vote so we know
that, like,
we know the exact number,
of like,
who is going to be
the president, or,
in the
House of Representatives,
or the Senate.
So that theres a better chance
that they will get elected.
- [Teacher] Okay, so,
we need a more accurate
portrayal of what people think.
We need more people to vote
so we really know what Americans think.
Okay.
- [Student] Well, I agree with Connor, but,
going back to what
everybody over there is saying,
they're all saying,
'oh, they, they won't care,
they wont,
they wont care or anything and,
they wont pay attention
to what happens', but,
I mean, if we can...
make like...
some kind of exception for like,
special needs people,
for the deaf and blind and...
then um...
also, we can get people to stand out
in front of a booth,
and once they'll go,
130 people,
get there,
you can do a speech about...
both candidates,
and their ups and downs.
- [Teacher] Okay, so you're
saying actually have,
people at the voting polls
that are kind of breaking
down the two sides.
Maybe for those people
who didn't take the time
to research it.
Okay.
- [Student] Um, one of y'all keep sayin',
we keep sayin' that they might not care,
but like, in actuality,
if you, if someone doesn't care,
and you force them to care,
not only is that kinda like,
convincing, like, brainwashing them,
it's also,
if you force someone to do something,
they're not going to want to anymore.
So that wouldn't be helping anything.
- [Teacher] So you're saying it's,
it's gonna actually make them more bitter,
toward voting,
if you force them to do it.
Okay.
- [Student] And, someone said that
it's gonna be for the good of the country,
for making them vote,
but, if they could choose a bad,
a bad person,
'cause,
it wouldn't be for the
good of the country then.
- [Teacher] Okay, so if
you force them to vote,
and then they go and
vote for a bad person,
that's not gonna be
helping the country at all.
Okay. Jason.
- [Student] Um, like, um,
you could, um,
for those people that can't vote,
or um,
you could...
put the...
they could put the polls,
the voting polls near...
where those people,
uh, live,
and um,
so that, they could like,
if they can't drive there in a car,
they could just walk there,
because it'd only be like,
maybe a block down their way.
- [Teacher] Okay.
- [Student] You could like, open
a public train, like,
so they don't have to pay to go as much.
- [Teacher] And then make it free?
- [Student] Yeah.
- [Teacher] For that day? Okay.
Alexandra, what do you think?
- [Student] Alright, um, well like,
making people vote is gonna
make them more interested
in like, the country,
and then they'll actually care,
'cause like, they're not gonna wanna like,
break a law,
and so then they're gonna actually care
about the country,
and so they won't just be
choosing a random person,
they're gonna actually start caring and,
start thinking about
who they should choose.
- [Teacher] You really think if,
if we force them to vote, then they,
they will become more
interested in politics
and they'll go out and research it. Okay.
- [Student] Like, just like,
if you make some,
make everyone vote,
then it's really not gonna
change their opinion,
they're still gonna have...
like, they're still gonna...
not really care as much as the person that
would go out and vote
without being forced.
So you're really not
getting an accurate...
number of what they think they want,
because they still...
just because you're making them vote
doesn't mean they're gonna...
necessarily pick the right person.
- [Teacher] Okay.
- [Student] Um, they're always saying like that,
60 percent vote, but,
we still have this 40
percent that haven't voted,
well, everyone, like even the poor people
and the uneducated,
well everyone knows that
there's a presidential election,
or some kind of election going on,
you can't, it's like,
impossible to not know about it,
and so really, it's their choice...
that they didn't vote,
most of the people who
aren't poor but they're like
middle class (mumble) like,
they won't make the choice to vote, if...
- [Teacher] Okay. So you're,
- [Student] A lot of people have
made the choice to vote.
- [Teacher] So you're saying,
the presidential election,
everybody knows about it,
everybody probably has an opinion
because it's all over the place, so,
60 percent of people are voting,
and 40 percent are not,
obviously those 40 percent know
that they don't wanna go and vote.
- [Student] They've chosen not to vote.
Most of them have chosen not to vote.
- [Teacher] Okay.
- [Student] You know, I have to disagree with you,
when you say that if we
just tell people to vote,
they'll just pick a random person.
What I think is that,
if people are being told to vote,
they'll just go in there and say,
'well, if I'm being told to vote,
I just might as well
just pick someone good'.
You'd think that they would
actually try and think
about something before they vote,
like the term 'look before you leap'.
- [Teacher] So you think,
if they have to go to
the effort of voting,
they're at least gonna think about it.
They're at least gonna
form an opinion. Okay.
- [Student] Um,
like, you put, of, um,
you (mumbles)
you could like, make the offices,
make the person take the day off,
and like,
sort of give them the day off.
- [Teacher] And that's...