[Background chatter]
- We all know it's splash.
Just put it next to it.
- Your turn.
- Okay, let's see.
- [Teacher] How are we doing?
How many animals do we have?
Do you have a few?
- We think mussel...
- It can be in the middle.
- It can be in the high
tide and the low tide.
- Because it can move around.
And then it eats clams
and clams would be in the high tide.
- It can grab on to the wave.
It eats clams.
- It says this eats clams.
- I saw the, of the mussels sort of
in the mid-high tide one day.
- When you were out at the tides before?
- Yeah.
- Excellent, so you're using some of your
previous experience to help you.
Good, excellent.
Okay, I'll be right back.
- It's a snail.
The shell protects its soft part.
As a hermit crab grows,
it moves into a new shell.
It may take an empty shell
or steal one from another.
- So it's like war.
- I think that would be in the high.
- Yeah, that's a high.
- Yeah, I think the high tide.
- I thought it would be in the mid or low.
But no.
- Well it could move down there.
- What's your next one?
Tuesday, put this circle right
on top of the clock.
Same time.
Same height.
Wow, that's pretty interesting isn't it?
Good for you.
Oh, you're looking at your first
one. What's your first one?
Yeah, just line it right there on the clock.
- That's eight.
- Yep, like eight.
Yeah, excellent.
And Margo you're getting
your first measurement?
Negative one!
Oh, awesome.
Monday's negative one.
Hello Kazhu,
I will show you where you need to go.
- It's negative something.
- I don't know what negative.
It's right here. Look here.
12 o' clock, I think everyday.
- [Teacher] Did you find
out they went that low?
- Yeah.
- Mine went to negative six!
- Wow!
- I didn't put Tuesday.
and then I'm going to put a block under it.
- You had one that went really low.
Look at that.
Awesome.
You set that up first
pretty well, didn't you?
Look's like we got Monday
and Tuesdays getting done.
Wednesdays are being worked on.
Perfect.
So much to hear, what it is you guys
are gonna discover from the charts.
- [Student] Let's do a worm.
Whatever that says.
They have a veil of flaps on each side.
The worms usually stay buried
in the sand.
If a wave comes,
it swims back down toward the sand
and wiggles into it.
- I'm pretty sure that's low.
- [Student] Yeah.
- No, how about maybe high?
- High tide.
- No, but the waves crash
there a lot actually.
- Splash!
- There's more of the sand.
- Yeah, I think it would be splash.
- [Teacher] Want to try splash on that one?
Good.
And you guys thought that because
what did it say?
- It said it buries in the sand
and if a wave crashes
it has to wriggle back down.
- Okay.
- So, it stays in sand as much as it can.
- How many does Nate have?
Oh, two.
- [Teacher] The whelk?
That's a scientific name.
That's a tough one, isn't it?
- Ah, it's hard.
- It's hard, it's okay you can skip it.
Just say "look for
the whelk on rocky beaches."
- "On rocky beaches
and on rocks, sift, or
muddy gravel beaches."
"The shell of the snail can reach
about two inches in height."
"It is a scavenger, feeding on kin.
It also preys on injured animals
such as limpets"
"The snail has also..."
- So, I thought the sentence said
"it also preys on injured animals,
such as limpets."
So "preys on them" what does that mean?
- I think I know.
- What do you think, Andrew?
- It means catch them and eat them.
- It catches them and eats them.
Where do you think that would need to be
if it's gonna eat limpets?
- I think it would be in the high tide.
- Oh, you've got both of them.
So, you also might want to talk to Addy
and find out what Addy has.
And try to figure out where those guys are
before you place your whelk.
No, so Addy what do you think?
What is one of yours?
Let's find out what yours are, right?
- Under each shell.
I think it's already
in the high tide zone.
- I thought it would be in the splash.
- Wait, no.
- High, high, high.
- Yeah, high tide.
Okay, the limpet...
- Guys, I thought it
would be in the splash.
- No, remember you gotta, like, figure.
Okay, I'll let you two go.
- I thought it would be splash because...
- No, I don't think that...
- The thing should be
underwater most of the time.
- It says "Watch for
whelks on rocky beaches
and muddy or gravel beaches."
- It could be in the middle.
- True.
Yeah, mid.
- Okay, mid.
No, you have to say
where the other food is.
- I put it to high splash.
- Okay, you go, then you go.
- Guys look, too much heart.
One that was lower than...
negative four.
And this is negative four.
- [Teacher] What do we have?
Margo, did you finish your graph?
Excellent.
How are you doing on yours, Joshua?
You finished?
- I'm on Friday.
- You're on Friday.
So, maybe you two should start setting
up your circle.
Pick your question, Margo.
Joshua.
And this is your question.
And set up your circle right on there.
Grab your graph and a chair.
And sit in your circle
off to the side there.
- I think it's either low or splash.
- No, not splash.
- Not splash.
Otherwise there wouldn't be anything.
- Lower mid.
- I'd think low.
- No.
- No, remember at the aquarium,
they were underwater completely.
No things sticking out.
- Only some of the spine.
- Yeah, but the rest,
it was just...
boom there.
- I am doing it.
I'm doing the sand dollar for my...
report.
And it's high.
- No, remember at the aquarium also,
it was at the bottom of the tank.
Remember?
- [Student] No, it was at mid.
I remember, I checked.
And also anyways...
I'm doing the sand dollar.
- Okay.
- [Teacher] Okay,
so Margo, do you have
your question with you?
So, everybody gets a chance
to converse and talk about
the answers to that question.
Or maybe you might realize something
or come to a realization
about your information.
And all of you can
contribute to the answer.
Okay?
So, go ahead.
- Were there any patterns you noticed
doing your graph?
What are they?
- I noticed that first it went
to medium then it went lower
and then it went higher and higher
the third, fourth, and fifth time.
- My pattern was that each time...
each level started
getting higher and higher
and higher and so it's really high.
- Mine would go to 12, to 12,
then it would go to 11,
and then it went down to 10
and then it went down to nine.
It went lower and lower.
- [Student] And it was kinda like a mix.
- Monday and Tuesday were the same
and then it started going higher
and higher and higher,
all the way.
- What was unexpected?
I'll go first.
It went lower than the average
on the chart.
It went lower and then it started
going higher and higher.
- I thought it was just gonna stay
in the negative parts
but it actually went up to the nine.
- [Student] In mine,
I expected it to be some different levels,
but it kept going higher and higher
and higher and then when it started
to go even higher it just
kind of stayed the same.
- Mine went higher and higher and higher
and higher again.
Okay, who's next?
- [Student] I am.
Unless you want to go.
Read your question.
- What was your highest tide?
What was your lowest one?
My highest was Tuesday and Friday.
They were both negative one.
And Friday and Thursday,
they were both negatives.
Everything was negative.
- [Teacher] Everything
was negative on yours?
Wow!
Negative.
- Even one below the negatives.
You have five negative.
Negative five.
- [Teacher] Yeah, that's right
because you're grabbing,
you don't realize you'll
get a negative five.
- That tide's really low.
- [Teacher] Very low tide level, yeah.
Margo has her hand up, go ahead Margo.
- On the day that was highest, was Friday.
It went all the way up to nine.
And my lowest was Monday and Tuesday
because they're both negative one.
- Oh, and my lowest was Thursday.
(mumbles)
- Thursday and it was 9.
- [Teacher] Thursday and it was nine?
- Yeah.
- [Teacher] And Maia what
was your lowest tide?
- My lowest was Monday.
It was about at eight
and then it starts going higher
and my highest was at 12.
- So, I'm wondering now
if we look at all of our charts,
all of our graphs,
who had the highest tide of everybody?
Who had the highest?
So, you had a 12.
- I had two twelves.
- No, she had 11.
- So, it looks like maybe Callen and Maia
have close to each having a 12.
- I have the lowest score.
I have the lowest.
I think Joshua got the lowest
with a negative five reading
on his.
Anybody else have a negative five?
- No.
I have a negative one.
But no negative fives.
- [Teacher] Okay, alright.
So, whose question's next?
Alright, I'll be right back.