- [Voiceover] Okay, so tell us
a little background about Ed.
- Alright, well it showed
that he had chest pains
and also his vital signs showed that
his heart was very weak so we thought
he was having a heart attack
and also he was unconscious.
- [Voiceover] Okay, so
because of his complaining
of chest pains, be subtle
from conscious or no?
- He called and he
talked to the paramedics,
but it also said he was obese and so that
could contribute to it as well.
- [Voiceover] How do you
suppose that contributes
to having a cardiac condition?
- Generally, it can clog your arteries.
- [Voiceover] What can clog your arteries?
- The fat that builds up.
- [Voiceover] Okay, from being obese?
- Yeah.
- [Voiceover] Okay, is
that one of the, I guess,
physical signs that someone may
have a heart condition?
- Yes.
- [Voiceover] Okay, okay, alright.
Go ahead.
- It is also his blood pressure.
It said it's at variable levels,
so that means his heart
isn't working properly
or consistently. So, that means
it could also contribute
to a circulatory system,
it could damage it.
It's also another sign of a heart attack.
- [Voiceover] Okay, so the variable heart,
or actually the variable blood pressure.
And some of you had questions about that
when you were doing your research.
You were wondering what
did this variable mean
and I think what you
said is exactly right,
it's not normal, okay.
They state the variable meaning,
it wasn't working how it should.
Okay, so sounds like this
guy had some definite issues
both with his vital signs
and with his history.
So, tell us a little bit why
you ranked him number one
compared to let's say, you ranked, who was
your number, hmm?
Who was your second, who proceeded him?
Nelson.
Nelson, so you got Ed ranked over Nelson
where some other people had Nelson
ranked number one, so, what do you think?
- Well, he's unconscious now so that means
his heart attack started some time ago
and once you have a heart
attack you need treatment
immediately, and since
his heart attacks aren't
his title, he needs it.
I think it's important
to see, to get treatment.
- [Voiceover] To get medical care?
- Yeah.
- [Voiceover] Okay, if
he doesn't get treatment
what do you think could happen?
- Probably, he'll die from the heart attack
if he doesn't get treatment or paralyzed.
- [Voiceover] What do
you mean by paralysis?
Why do you think he
could become paralyzed?
- I'm not sure if it's a
stroke or a heart attack
if you go through it if
you get paralyzed or not.
- [Voiceover] Okay, you're
not sure if it's a stroke
or a heart attack that
leads to possible paralysis?
- Yeah.
- [Voiceover] Anybody
like to comment on that?
Question, go ahead Jordan.
- It's a stroke.
It has a brain clot
and then that will cause
partial, I can't say it.
- Paralysis.
- Yeah that word, but heart attack.
You could have a heart attack after
that using different parts,
not paralysis.
- [Voiceover] Good point.
So, Jordan says having a stroke
can cause paralysis.
What system is being affected
when you have a stroke
that could lead to paralysis?
What system in our body is that?
- [Voiceover] Nervous system.
- [Voiceover] Yeah, nervous system.
Okay, understand?
Doban, Jake, got that?
Alright, so you guys have Ed,
you ranked him number
one and then you ranked
Nelson number two along with quite a few
other people.
It looks like we have
some consistencies there.
Let's look at group B.
You had Nelson ranked number one,
but then you did have
Ed ranked number three.
So, you didn't think Ed
was as serious having
this heart condition compared to Nelson
and/or Monique?
- Well, Nelson and Monique had the most
critical vital signs.
They seemed the most, the worst,
because their temperatures
were in the critical zone
and above where they started,
so they were overheated
and they probably had
heatstroke or hyperthermic.
So, they were not, and
they were dehydrated too.
When your body starts to dehydrate
that's not, it really
messes up all your systems.
So they were...
- [Voiceover] What systems?
- Cardiovascular system,
the respiratory system,
the immune system, everything's
just being attacked here
because with Eve, let me see this,
his heart rate was way below normal
and that's the cardiovascular system.
His temperature was completely 109
from all the heat from the canyon.
- [Voiceover] What's the
normal body temperature
for that of a human?
- The normal temperature
is 98.6 and he's at 109.
- [Voiceover] He's at 109 folks.
Okay, I think this was one of our hypers
if you remember, Nelson and Monique
were our two hypers that were airlifted
into the hospital, okay?
So, he's at 109.
- Isn't this like the immune system?
- [Voiceover] Mmhmm.
- Yeah, so that's the immune system
and then his breathing rate is way down.
It's at 10 respirations per minute.
- [Voiceover] 10 respirations per minute?
- And the normal's like 20,
so he's down to half.
So, I think that his vital signs
were way more out of whack.
- [Voiceover] Did you count
in on the blood pressure?
- The blood pressure?
- It's really low and that means
his circulatory system's not working right
which means blood's not getting
everywhere it needs to be.
Which means he could end up having,
I don't actually know if
it would lead to a stroke,
but like if everything's not
getting blood everywhere,
his brain might not get enough blood.
He could have brain damage
or something like that.
- [Voiceover] It's
interesting she said stroke,
talking about Nelson.
Was Nelson having any type
of nervous system symptoms?
- [Voiceover] Seizures.
- [Voiceover] It was seizures.
- [Voiceover] He was having seizures.
Is that, is a seizure an event that occurs
as a result of something going wrong with
the nervous system?
Absolutely.
Think about all the
systems you just named.
What's going on with Nelson?
Cardiac, nervous, circulatory, immune.
- Dehydration.
- Entire (mumbles)
bringing in dehydration.
Digestive, not enough water.
This guy is having a rough time, isn't he?
So, if you're pretty confident
in why you ranked him
number one.
- [Voiceover] Yeah.
- Okay, comments?
Anybody?
- Well, the reason we ranked him three
was because we thought
that he was most likely
going to die and so we
thought that his daughter
was a higher priority because...
- [Voiceover] Monique?
- Yeah, because she has a
better chance of survival.
- [Voiceover] So, you ranked him three,
and it's interesting you
said, "We thought he was
going to die."
He was maybe beyond that point of help.
- Yeah.
- [Voiceover] Okay, so
why'd you rank him three?
Why not rank him seven?
- [Voiceover] Well, what if he has a shot?
- [Voiceover] He's got a chance.
- Yeah.
- [Voiceover] Okay, he
has a chance over Mark.
- That wound to the chest.
- [Voiceover] Yeah, because Mark got shot
in the chest, didn't he?
- You'd save him though.
- [Voiceover] It's interesting you said
if he has a shot.
Mark's the one that got shot.
(laughing)
- He was more stable
than Nelson was though.
Mark was.
- [Voiceover] Mark was more stable?
- Yeah.
- [Voiceover] Interesting,
you're bringing in
the whole fact of, now you're triaging it.
You're saying okay, Mark's
a little bit more stable
even though he's got this gun shot
and they were kind of vague in what
they said about the gun shot.
We don't know what kind of gun it was.
- But I feel like if you rank him a three,
he's at such a critical
position that it's either
you rank him one, because he
needs treatment right away
or he's going to die.
- [Voiceover] Okay, so you're saying,
he's got to be one, based
upon all the symptoms,
based upon his vital signs, the condition
that he was brought in.
If you're not going to rank him one
you might as well just let him die.
Is that what you're saying?
- Or early on.
Like, you can't wait too long, I guess.
- You've got to rank him
one to three, otherwise.
- [Voiceover] So he's
like, what group were you?
- We're F.
- [Voiceover] You're F, so you had him,
okay you had him at a two.
- Yeah.
- [Voiceover] Okay, alright,
so you're saying
he's a top three?
- Yeah, especially.
- [Voiceover] You had a hand up.
- Oh, I was just agreeing with him.
If we thought we had any
chance we should be like
let's not waste any time to finish this
either that or just make him seven.
- [Voiceover] Okay, good point.
Brian?
- Well, were were thinking...
- [Voiceover] Speak up
a little bit please.
- Well, we were thinking that even though
he's unconscious and having seizures
he was a crooked patient,
but compared to like
the other ones like Albert or Mark,
his symptoms weren't
that of like great danger
as the others, and even
though his body temperature
was 109, that could
have been because he was
going through heat stroke,
but now that he's in Asprins
they're a cool environment.
- [Voiceover] You bring up heatstroke.
Why do you think he's
going through a heatstroke?
- Well, I don't know,
because he was unconscious,
and they said he was
dehydrated and everything.
Well dehydration can be due to heatstroke
and like I also figured it'd be heatstroke
because his daughter...
- [Voiceover] Monique.
- Yeah, I'm sorry, Monique,
it said that she was dizzy
and nauseous and if she
was in the same environment
as Nelson was, then it's more likely that
their symptoms are close to each other
because if she's going
through like nauseous
and like dizziness then it's
most likely that he is too
because they're both in
the same environment.
- [Voiceover] Very interesting.
I want to come back to this point.
Ryan you've got your hand up.
What were you going to say?
- I was just going to say that Monique
has the same symptoms for heatstroke.
- [Voiceover] You're exactly right.
Now my mind instantly goes somewhere here.
Jordan, your hand was up first.
- I was just going to say
that since their temperature's
so high, they're probably in shock
and always their temperature
is almost basically fatal
levels, so just putting them,
they're going from a really
hot environment to a
really cold environment.
Or really cool compared
to where they were.
If they'll put them into
more shock which can
also be fatal, which
means they're not exactly
just because they're in a hospital,
doesn't mean they're necessarily going
to get better right away.
- [Voiceover] Okay, obviously
they need some treatment.
You don't want to go from
one extreme to the other,
but do you agree that they
need to be cooled down
quite a bit?
- Yeah.
- [Voiceover] They need to get cooled down
and what else do they need?
- Water.
- [Voiceover] Water,
lots of water, correct?
Yes?
- You can't really say
that Monique's symptoms
can apply for Albert too because Monique
was having like an allergic reaction to
the bee sting.
So, that's probably what most
of the symptoms are from.
- [Voiceover] We forgot
about the bee sting.
It says she's dizzy,
nauseousness, has cracked lips,
is having difficulty breathing, has a rash
on her legs and stomach.
Okay, she got stung by a bee.
- Like, you were saying,
the reason we put Monique
as number one besides
experiencing possible
heatstroke, we also have her experiencing
a very bad allergic reaction to the bee.
It shows here that with
the difficulty breathing,
the bee sting, her body is having a very
poor reaction to the bee sting
and that if left
untreated for longer times
without getting pills and
stuff like that or EpiPen.
- Getting what?
- [Voiceover] EpiPen.
- [Voiceover] You know what it is?
- [Voiceover] Just say EpiPen.
- [Voiceover] EpiPen, yeah.
Epinephrine.
- Epinephrine.
- Yes.
- It should elevate them in the
largest sense
where she could potentially
have life threatening
without her entire like,
respiratory system is closing off,
she loses her breathing possibly.
- Absolutely, she's having
the preliminary signs
of an allergic reaction here.
Here's where my thought went and I said
we'd come back to this point.
Maybe Sean, you were going to comment
or somebody else.
They're both out in the
wilderness, this canyon,
they're both having heatstroke symptoms.
Actually, Monique got stung by the bee,
she's having separate issues there.
You don't see anything else different
about these two individuals?
Sean.
- One got to stay put
for a long period of time
and assured a maybe cooler spot
while the other still had to keep going
up through the sun and the heat
to try to get to the top.
- [Voiceover] Do you think that would have
a difference in their physical?
- One gets to rest while the other still
has to keep going and going and going
another what, third of the way.
- [Voiceover] Excellent point, you know.
What's the other issue between these two?
Jack, you know?
- Well like, they're both
in the same environment
and they both have symptoms of heatstroke,
but Monique got stung by a bee
and at the same time Nelson has no signs
of any external trauma
or anything that happened
to him that caused the symptoms.
So, it could have even
been a seizure or a stroke
made him lose consciousness and causes
a temperature to rise so
high is because he was
probably thinking that
there was something off.
- [Voiceover] Interesting, interesting.
Yes?
- Would it be their age?
- [Voiceover] Age, excellent.
Look at the difference in their age.
How old's Monique?
- 18.
- Yeah, she's 18.
Nelson, the dad right?
He's 51.
I'm not saying 51 is old,
but there's a big difference
between 18 and 51, plus
the fact you add in
what Sean said, he's got
to hike out of this canyon,
he's going to try to find help, right?
Is he having to expend a lot more energy?
- Yeah.
- And he's got to go uphill.
- He's go to go uphill, yeah.
It's hot, he's got no water,
he's got to go uphill,
he's losing, basically, control of his body.
No energy, no water.
Erin?
- And that's why we had
Nelson as number one
and then Monique would go second
because they both had
like the heat problem,
but Nelson was having,
it was much more severe
with him because of
his age and everything.
And Monique, she was sitting
there for three hours
after being stung by a
bee, so it wasn't like,
so we put her close up to the top because
there was, she's already
been waiting for long enough.
She needs to get help like right away
because she was sitting
in the shade waiting
for hours while her dad
had to go struggle up
the top of the canyon.
So, they were in a really bad situation
and they just needed help immediately
because they'd been
struggling long enough.
- [Voiceover] Absolutely.
What?
- During our discussion
we were kind of using...
- [Voiceover] Speak up
a little bit, sorry.
- Okay so, during when we were discussing
the age, we were thinking
also Monique but...
- [Voiceover] Which group
were you real quick?
- E.
- [Voiceover] You were E, okay.
- So, like what we thought was that since
Monique is 18 years old, verses Nelson
is a 51 year old, well like, it makes sense
that Monique has a stronger immune system
because she's more young and she has more
nutrients in her body whereas Nelson
could be different, but
we don't know if he has
any diseases like diabetes
or high blood pressure.
It doesn't show, but I'm
just saying in general.
We were writing specific
about his other health
because I wrote that down.
- [Voiceover] Age related diseases.
- [Voiceover] Age related diseases, yeah.
So, we're missing some medical history.
- Yeah, so it's possible
there because he's older
and because his immune
system isn't as strong
as Monique's is, we have to like,
or doctors have to like
protect them with treatment
more early because his immune system
is much more weak
compared to his daughter's.
- [Voiceover] Absolutely.
As doctors, medical
history is so important.
It's so important in the triage process
and we've been through this folks.
You know, you go to the doctor's office,
you go into the hospital, you know,
in addition to while they're
taking your vital signs,
what are they asking?
What are they asking when you go in?
- Medical history.
- [Voiceover] Oswell?
- Have you had any previous stuff?
- [Voiceover] What's stuff mean?
- Like surgery, so like problems.
- [Voiceover] Okay, other
medical conditions.
- Yeah.
- [Voiceover] Okay, what's
another question they ask?
Very simple.
- [Voiceover] Has it ever happened before?
- [Voiceover] Has it happened before?
- [Voiceover] Is it hereditary?
- [Voiceover] Could it be hereditary,
what's your family's history?
And I think that's what Brian,
you were relating to back there.
What are you here for today?
Okay, let's look back
in the chart, should I?
- At this moment when he
comes into the hospital,
he's obviously not
having symptoms of having
high blood pressure in the past
and high blood pressure
might have actually helped.
- [Voiceover] Oh, so you're asking about,
you're referring to Nelson?
- Yeah, because if he
had high blood pressure
then that might have
actually helped keep his
blood pressure up to normal
if it went down severely
because of what happened in the canyon.
But because it's so low, I
would guess that he doesn't
have a history of high blood pressure.
- [Voiceover] Okay, you might
want to disagree with that
and take history out of it.
Blood pressure is obviously low.
I think we addressed this a second ago.
Why do you think it's low?
Sarah?
- Because everything else that's going on,
it's also affecting blood pressure.
- [Voiceover] Yeah, I
think, I truly believe
with the limited amount
of information we have,
I truly believe that
because of the dehydration,
the heatstroke, the no
energy, no nutrients,
I literally think this entire body,
all the systems...
- [Voiceover] Shutting down?
Shutting down.
I really do think that.
But it's a good point that you bring up
because his blood pressure's 85 over 50.
Does anybody, has anybody ever taken
their blood pressure before?
Okay, 85 over 50, that's low.
I mean that gets to
borderline point where,
you know, you're dizzy, I
mean you could have an episode
because that pressure of your blood going
through the circulatory
system, it's not high enough.
I mean that gets borderline,
with instead of having
to take medicines for high blood pressure,
you got to take medicines to
bring your blood pressure up.
I think his body's just shutting down
and you bring up a good point,
but I think in this case
just with everything else
going on, I think his
body's just shutting down.
Okay.
- Honestly on the side of that,
besides you were saying
like high blood pressure
could actually help.
During the scenario that he's in,
high blood pressure
like with it's problems
that it could cause with
it's possible weakens
the heart, could have actually killed him
during the long, extended
time of trying to get
to the paramedics.
That was due to the fact
that the high blood pressure
has the (mumbles) of hurting
muscles at a much different rate
than most people.
That this test could have possibly failed
during the time to get to a
paramedic without (mumbles).
And plus even had he survived
the high blood pressure
and got on the top, the
shut down of major systems
in his body would have still
caused the blood pressure
to get down so that there's
no possible low levels
that could even cause problems.
- True, yeah Blythe?
- Like on the graphs, I
feel like there's Nelson,
his blood pressure and the
blood pressure of Elders
was like similar because it was 80 over 50
whereas Nelson was 85 over 50.
But we just talked about how like, Nelson's
blood pressure could be
low and this other instance
it might not be, but with Elder
he has a head injury and...