- Stationary point.  Did he move?
Okay, some of the other groups are
moving their fingers around,
sometimes they were releasing
from up here and up here,
so do you think your data might
be a little more realistic?
- Yeah.
- Yeah, okay so, now one thing,
what type of formation do you guys have?
[Inaudible]
- Good. Put an adjective in front of it.
- Extremely strong.
- Strong. A strong positive.
Do you think every
correlation around here
is gonna be the same?
- No.
- Okay, so yours is probably going to be
one of the strongest ones.
Remember that correlation coefficient?
- R, it went from positive
one to negative one or zero?
- Oh yeah.
- What do you think
yours would be close to?
- One.
- It'd be really close to--
Then we'll get to that
shortly guys, later on. Okay?
- So you probably would have
one that's a decimal 999
or really close.
- Okay, so you're trying
to find your slope?
- Yeah.
- So what is your slope?
- Two.
- Two, okay, so over
here we're gonna put--
And now, does everyone
have the exact same?
- You do?
- Pretty much.
- Oh, most groups who are
four people are slightly off
depending on where
you put the line.
Okay, here's the slope.
So you just told me
your slope is two,
now what am I asking you to do?
What is your--
[Background Chatter]
- No, we're not done yet.
What is your--
- It's 2.0.
- Read the question.
[Background Chatter]
- Okay, what's the slope of the equation?
The slope is--
What did you just tell me?
- Oh, two.
- Two.  Okay now, what's the
real-world meaning of that?
What does that mean when
you say yes, those are two.
- Okay now, we can go back to that,
I just want to talk to
you about the solution.
Just on your slope,
you said it was two.
That was perfect.
But now, what's the
real-world meaning?
- So the slope is the
more rubber band...
- What are you looking at?
[Background Chatter]
- So it's one and two...
- One.
[Background Chatter]
- Why can't it?
- So you want to put five? Okay.
Ten over. Okay, so now you're
telling me your slope is,
ten over one.
10?
[Background Chatter]
Okay, well I'm asking
you what's your slope.
Now you're saying your slope is 10.
That's what the slope is but
I want the real-world meaning.
So what were you saying?
- For every one rubber
band that drops...
- How do you know?
How do you know--
But where are you getting...
I need a little more detail though.
It's dropping what?
10, 10 centimeters.
So, 10 centimeters for every?
- One.
- One rubber band.
Okay. Now, what's your y-intercept?
- Seven.
- Seven. Now is your y-intercept
directions to get somewhere else
or is it telling the exact location?
What's the y-intercept?
Because a slope, isn't that directions
to get somewhere else?
What's the y-intercept?
I want the entire--
It's zero seven.
So can you write
zero seven down please?
Write zero seven down.
And now, tell me what the real--
When I ask you what the
y-intercept is, yes, zero seven.
Now what's the real-world meaning.
- ...subtract out of seven...
- So what's this saying?
Translate that for me.
You're saying there's
no real-world meaning,
what's that saying?
[Background Chatter]
- So, before we put any
rubber bands on,
this already moves
seven centimeters.
What does that mean?
Going into this lab, did I
know if the real-world meaning
was gonna make sense or not.
There's been a few groups
today their
y-intercept has a real-world meaning
- zero zero.
But did I know where
your line was gonna go?
No. But if it went straight through zero
would that make sense?
Zero rubber band?
So--
- So what's the real-world meaning?
- Well, what do you think?
This y-intercept that you had,
does it have a real-world meaning?
No.
So yeah, it doesn't have
a real-world meaning.
What slope did it?
Okay.
Once again, did I know that coming in?
Depended on your data.
Good job.
[Background Chatter]
- Guys, you're asking If
you plug into this,
four times three, that's 12.
- But yeah.
Three, two and four.
I think it says three. Okay?
So what's your equation...
Y equals 3x plus 12? Okay
so let's talk about that.
- No, no it's one,
intercept the y...
- It really doesn't play
out with that algorithm.
- It makes no absolute
sense whatsoever.
[Background Chatter]
- Yeah but you find air.
- Oh that makes sense.
- But this...
- What are we talking about?
- We got one anyway,
but really that's it.
- Wait one second,
backtrack for one second.
So, what did you say here?
- Five-thirds.
- What is a five-thirds?  5/3.
Okay, so what's the real-world meaning?
- Every five inches there is three
rubber band.
- Okay. So now does the
ball go on a rubber band?
So flip that around
so you're saying
two rubber bands,
the figure is going--
- Yes.
- Okay, does that have
real-world meaning?
Does that have real-world meaning?
- Yeah.
- Yeah. Okay,
Now you're saying what,
your y-intercept is--
can I see your graph
paper for a second?
- Yeah.
- Okay. So yeah, it looks
like it's around--
Does everybody have the same?
- No.
- Do you think everyone's
gonna get the exact same line?
- We didn't really have
an intercept slope,
we just looked at...
- We just...
- Yeah, which sounds great because
you're all gonna draw that
line slightly different,
so go with one then.
- What does that y-intercept--
Is that directions
or is that a location?
It's a location, isn't it?
So can you write the exact location?
Because you're only counting one.
What's the order of pairs here?
You have a pair of zero
one, so write that down.
- Pair of zero ones.
You have a pair of zero ones.
- Yeah.
- What's zero represent?
- Zero rubber bands.
So when zero rubber
bands were attached,
how far did that--
- One.
- One inch.
Does that make sense to you?
So when there's zero
rubber bands attached,
you figure out one inch?
Alright, let's demonstrate that.
Let's see. Can I see
that for one sec please?
Okay, let's go back to
before we started.
Zero rubber bands
attached, what's happening.
Okay, what's happening right now.
Zero rubber bands--
Did he already move one inch?
- No.
- So, Does the y-intercept come in?
- You said...
[Background Chatter]
- Because you just told me
it was five inches of three.
Yeah. What are we discussing now?
The data, or the equation for the...
Okay? Now so, does this
y-intercept make sense?
- No.
- Zero rubber bands
are removed. So does the y-intercept
have real-world meaning?
- No.
- Does the slope have real-world meaning?
- Yeah.
- Did I know your
y-intercept wasn't gonna have
real-world meaning?
- Yes.
- No, because there's some people today
that actually have real-world meaning.
What would be a y-intercept
if it made sense?
- Zero zero.
- Zero zero. Zero rubber bands equals--
- Zero inches.
- What were you saying your slope was?
So let's discuss three.
The slope is three, what's
the real-world meaning?
- How many rubber bands would you
need in your description?
- Grabbing one rubber band,
does that make sense?
Okay, now, so now what anout your
y-intercept would be at 12.
Now you gotta figure...
Let's discuss this right here.
[Background Chatter]
Now, I think you're thinking ahead.
But this line looks like
it's crossing up here to--
Where is it crossing?
It's crossing at--
We're going up three,
look, three, six, seven.
Yeah I was looking like around four.
So let's discuss this.
You have six?
That could be perfect,
but we know the exact
way a line likes to go.
Let's go with Monique, six.
What's that saying?
Let's go to a pair,
to the y-intercept.
Zero pair, zero six.
So what does that mean?
So write that down, zero pair, zero six
for the y-intercept.
And what's that actually mean?
- Zero rubber bands in front of the six
equals how many inches.
- So, this was the figure.
Zero rubber bands attached,
does that make it already
move six inches?
Does that make any sense at all?
So does the y-intercept
have real-world meaning?
Could it still have
real-world meaning?
You were thinking ahead I think,
when you drew your line.
Because what's the only
y-intercept that makes sense here?
Zero rubber bands--
- 81 inches.
- But you didn't move.
But does that mean you
can decide I want to
make real-world meaning and just
draw my line down the zero?
Because what am I looking for?
The equation for the line of--
Is yours the equation for
the line now?
Your y-intercept makes sense,
If you knew the equation
for the y-intercept.
- You plug in 81 inches for X right?
- Did you end up with a negative?
[Background Chatter]
- You're fine.
You what?
[Background Chatter]
- Minus what? Oh, minus one.
I wanna discuss it.
If you're y-intercept is...
What's the order of pairs...?
Zero, negative one, so what's
the real-world meaning?
[Background Chatter]
What's that mean?
What's the zero represent?
[Background Chatter]
Okay, so zero rubber bands,
what's your y-interception?
At zero rubber bands,
how far does it go now?
- Negative one
- Did he already go one,
or did he reach it?
So does that make sense?
Zero rubber bands and
he's already traveled one?
Does that make any sense?
So does the y-intercept?
Does that mean your y-intercept
just didn't end up happening?
- Yeah.
- When you know how to
use this it works,
[Background Chatter]
With zero rubber bands,
how fast are you going?
Zero? Zero.
Okay, does that mean
your data's all wrong?
No, that's the way
your numbers work.
Could you slope this out
instead three?
What's that mean?
Three, three what?
Four is still, Five is...
So three...
Three what?
Let's go and do number five.
Distance, so what would
your distance be?
Inches. So it's like
three inches is over one--
So that makes sense.
So, does your slope
have real-world meaning?
- Yeah.
Okay.