♪ [clapping and singing] ♪
- [Teacher] Now, I'm going to get to what
we are beginning to learn today. I'm going
to go ahead and put my tie up here...
Now, is there anyone who can tell me what
this is? What is that, Daniel?
- [Daniel] A dotted eighth note.
- This is a dotted eighth note. Who can
tell me what this note is? Sedekia?
- [Sedekia] One sixteenth note.
- It is a sixteenth note, so we have a
dotted eighth note and a sixteenth note.
Now remember our rule that we just went
over this morning about the dot. With that
in mind, can somebody tell me what the
value of that note is? Cole?
- [Cole] It would last for like three beats.
- [Instructor] Three beats...
- [Cole] And then you would have a sixteenth note.
Okay, I think you're on the right track, it would last
for three of something, but not three beats, Landon?
- [Landon] Three fourths of a beat?
- It would be three fourths of a beat, so
let's think about this, remember, an
eighth note in 4/4 time gets half of a
beat. Everybody, what's half of a half?
- [student] One fourth.
- One fourth, so the dot is worth one
fourth of a beat, that means that this
dotted eighth note is three fourths of a
beat. Well that sounds a little bit
complicated, but all you need to do is
think about this and apply it down here.
So who can tell me what I would write for
counts under this dotted eighth note?
Raise your hand. Lydon?
- [Lydon] Would it be one, e &?
- One e &, because that's the same as
having three of both, and Jaylin what
would go here?
- [Jaylin] a e.
- Okay, so this is just another way of
writing this. Let's do a measure of
counting that. Ready? And, go, and...
- [together with clapping] One e and a
two, and one e and a two, and one e and a
two, and one e and a two, and...
- Now, I want all my first row to do that
four times, okay? And, go, and...
- [students] One e and a two, and one e
and a two, and one e and a two, and one e
and a two, and
- Second row, ready, and, go, and...
- [students] One e and a two, and one e
and a two.