- Consider what you read
about organic lettuce
and Rosie from Omnivore's Dilemma
and from what you're reading
do you feel it's worth
the extra cost and effort to eat organic?
Yes?
- So, for some organics
I believe it is worth it
and others I don't.
Industrial organic I don't
believe it's worth it,
because for the lettuce in
the book Omnivore's Dilemma,
they said it takes about ten
fossil fuel calories to make
one calorie from lettuce,
and I don't believe that's
energy efficient at all.
But other farms, other industries,
or other organic farms
like Polyface Farms,
they use all natural energy,
not a lot of fossil fuels go into it,
and I think it's more efficient.
So, organic like that I believe is better,
but industrial organic I
don't believe is better.
- That's a good point.
I was wondering is somebody could
expand on the difference between
industrial organic and organic.
Phil, if you want to pick someone.
- Eli.
- So, normal organic food, like
what started the idea of organic food,
was completely different from organic food
that you buy at Whole Foods nowadays.
Like, what the people originally
thought the concept of
organic food thought of
was like the local, sustainable
farm like Polyface Farms,
where it's completely energy
efficient and they use
all natural resources like grass
and just stuff like that to feed
their cows and other animals.
But industrial organic systems,
it's pretty much the same as
normal industrial food system, except
they don't use antibiotics or
pesticides to make their food.
They still have animal rights...
There's still animal
cruelty and stuff inside the
the factories, and stuff like that.
Araceli.
- I agree with Eli, because
when I read organic,
I thought organic was good.
But then basically it was the same thing.
Like the chickens, they
still got fed corn,
but they had an open door,
but they were so fat
they couldn't go through.
Like, why pay the extra money
for something that's
going to be exactly the same
as the other thing?
- I think it is worth buying organic food.
Because even though the
animals are treated the same,
and even though it still
wastes a lot of fossil fuel,
we save a lot of farmland
from being put, like,
pesticide and everything on it,
so we could have chemical free land.
And also we save our
water system from being
poisoned by the chemicals we use.
So, it might cost a little bit more,
but it's worth it.
Matt.
- In response to, I guess, Eli,
it's not exactly the same,
there are definitely the perks
to the industrial organic
system with the lack of
chemicals and hormones.
But yes, I can definitely agree that
it's a very similar thing,
it doesn't solve all the problems
with the industrial system.
- I don't agree with what was just said,
that when you farm without
pesticides it's better,
because in Omnivore's Dilemma,
even though they farm without pesticides,
they crowd the ground so much
that it destroys the land.
So, it's not necessarily better,
it just sounds better.
- I just like Simone's
point, because I think that
a lot of the problems are still there,
and even though it might
be a little bit better
without the pesticides, I
think it's still important
to eat real organic food.
I think that would be the best.
Industrial organic is a
step in the right direction,
but I don't think it's
close enough to where
we should be with our food system.
- I agree with Molly that
industrial organic foods,
on the face, are both...
They're worth paying for because
they're the food that we should be eating,
but in other ways they feed
into other problems with pollution.
If you want the right type of food,
you have to create a food
system that can sustain
a country as large as the United States,
but still has healthy animals.
And animals that have evolved to eat,
only being fed, that is
at a cost low enough
to feed everyone in the United States
like we are fed now.
- I was going to also ask a
couple personal questions,
since I was talking to your mom about
how does your eating habits
change, do you think,
now that you feel like
you're more aware, or...?
- She says that she always
bought grass fed beef,
and I try to eat healthy,
but in the case of fast food, of course,
I go and eat fast food.
But lately I've been badgering her,
and asking her if she
could get a grass fed steak.
I've been waiting for
that for a long time.
The corn fed steak that my dad gives me
smells bad and it looks bad, so...
(mumbles)
Anyway.
There's nobody asking.
- I don't think organic's really
necessarily healthy for us,
because humans are still
trying to figure out
what vitamins we still need,
what essentials we still need.
Like people are still
discovering that plants have
certain essentials that
we never knew we needed.
So, how can we tell organic's good for us
if we don't know what organic is different
from what we get from normal food?
- I thought Curt brought a
good point up too, which is
the best organic is just
straight from the farm to the buyers,
but it is a great point
that Curt and Greg brings up
which is that that way can't
feed as much people as
the industrial organic
or just industrial food.
- I completely agree with that.
It's implausible to try to
make what they call beyond organic food
at such a high amount, because it really
consumes a lot of land
and a lot of energy.
We read in the Omnivore's Dilemma with the
moving the chicken
coops so much every day,
that's a lot of land for very little meat,
and honestly that would
not be able to sustain
the whole country.
Lisa?
- So, I kind of agree
with what you're saying,
but it doesn't have to
necessarily be a few big farms
that are completely going organic.
If there's little farms
all over the United States,
then meat can go to those people
around there.
It might not happen all of a sudden,
but little by little people
are going to learn that
organic is better.
Whether it's more expensive or not,
it's healthier for us
knowing that the animals...
When the animals are not
fed on natural stuff,
that in turn is bad for us.
Ashley?
- I agree with what everyone said,
and that the point that
Paulina brought up about
we're still trying to figure
out what vitamins are what
and what's good for us.
Because I feel like it's more
better to spend even just
a few more cents, if organic
food isn't that expensive,
and go to certain places.
A few more cents on the local,
home grown organic food,
because I used to buy meat from the...
What's it called?
The meat section.
- [Female student] The deli?
- Deli, yeah, there you go.
And I used to buy meat there,
and I thought it was all
fine, you know, whatever,
until I went to the doctor one day
because I was getting really injured,
and she was like, "You're
missing all these vitamins,"
and she gave me all
these vitamins to take.
And I didn't know that that
was missing inside my food,
and then I go to the organic
section of the supermarket
and it's not even, like,
vitamins that were missing in
the meat, it's vitamins that
were missing in the drinks
that can be found in organic food.
For example, like the naked juice
has these vitamins
already included in there,
just because it's, like,
naturally grown and organic.
So, I was willing to spend the
extra dollar for my health.
So, I feel like if people realize
how important it is for your health,
that scare will wake them up
and they'll be able to spend the dollar.
- Okay, well, I agree.
I think that it's worth the
extra cost for organic,
because, like, in the book it said
when we buy organic food,
we're voting with our
forks, and we're voting
for the type of food we want.
And if we go organic, then
the producers will think
that most of us want
organic, so they'll start
growing more and selling
more organic food,
so that it might become
cheaper in the long run.
- I personally don't really care.
(students laugh)
Like, if it's cheaper, that's cool,
because if it has pesticides on it
you can just wash it off.
And animal's rights are nice,
but they're going to be killed anyway.
It's like, they're all going to die anyway.
They're going to die, so...
Michael.
- I like it.
(students laugh)
And yeah, I mean, even
though organic's good,
we still have a lot of cheap food
that feeds a lot more people
that have lower income.
So, we might not be, like,
the healthiest nation,
but at least we give
an opportunity to feed
every single person in the United States.
So, I kind of like that.
They don't have to worry about
paying high prices for food,
even though it's bad for my health.
And even if it is bad,
I could just exercise.
(students laugh)
So, I think it's a
personal responsibility to
watch what you eat.
So, we should be open to that.
- Even with the
industrialized food system,
we're still not feeding everyone.
If you go to like, the
Appalachians and stuff like that,
you still have kids that
are starving every day
because their parents
don't make enough money
to buy even the cheap food.
So, I think that it's not
that we need to focus less
on the cost of everything,
and just figure out a
better way to produce food
and grow it, and to make sure that
it gets where it needs to go.
I think we need to worry
about cost later on,
and try and focus on a way
to do that in the short term,
so that in the long term we can feed
as many people as we need to.
Lisa.
- I see how you brought
up the Appalchians,
but my question to you is is
it more important to worry
about issues here, where it effects us,
or would you find it more important
to focus, like, worldwide?
Like, you could focus on problems that
people have outside, but, like,
wouldn't you (mumbles)
focus on start here,
make sure that we have what we need first,
and then branch out?
- I think that with that, like,
with a lot of people
who get stuff locally...
So, if you're saying locally like,
are you talking, like, Chicago?
- Don't you think it's better
to start locally and then...
Like we get better locally,
and then we get better statewide,
and then we'll go on until everybody has
enough money to do this, or their food,
everyone can buy their food.
- I think so, but you also
have to take into consideration
that even if we do something in Illinois,
that doesn't guarantee
that other states are
going to adopt the same policies.
And I think if we focus
on doing something for
United States, and worry less
about the other countries,
even though, politically,
it might not be the right thing to do,
worry less about the other
countries at this time.
But I think we need to take
a step back and focus on
just fixing as much as we can on a whole,
and then going down
into the smaller levels
and seeing, okay, how
can we make this better
on a local level?
Chris?
- I think that we can't really
make it perfect,
like the way Polyface Farms is,
because of how the cities are laid out.
Because the cities are
too big to have farms
in reasonable reach of the people there.
So, I think what we have to do
is have this industrial organic,
which still is, I mean,
a lot more worth it,
because it keeps the
biodiversity in the soil,
and I read in the book
they said something like
that the size of the state of New Jersey
was, like, a dead zone at the
end of the Mississippi River
and the Gulf from all the
pesticides and fertilizers that flow down.
And that's (mumbles) problem
that we should focus on.
- Well, I agree with Teresa that
we should start only in the US,
because we can't just
make a generalization
that other countries are using corn
and are eating unhealthy just as we are.
We only know that the
US is eating unhealthy
because, according to Omnivore's Dilemma,
King Corn, and Food Incorporated,
the problems are only
occurring in the United States.
So, if we want to solve this problem,
we should start from the origins,
because we started using corn massively,
creating problems, and stuff,
not because of other countries.
Well, maybe because we imported
corn from Mexico and they dominated out
other corn types, so
we started using corn.
But we should start focusing on more of
what's the problem over here,
instead of other countries,
because we have to solve
our own problems first
before we become worried
about other problems, maybe.
Yeah.
- I was going to say that it is worth it
to spend the money in organic,
because even if it's just
a little bit of farms
here and there, people seem to be willing
to travel the extra mile just to get that
healthy piece of food.
Like in Polyface Farms, people came
from hundreds of miles, I think,
or 100 miles, just to get
their healthy chickens
or the healthy food.
And with Jerry, I wanted to say that...
Well, nevermind.
(mumbles)
- Okay then.
So, I remember Gabby said
how we should be focusing on
making as much food as possible
for everyone in America,
and that's the issue we
should be working on.
But that's really what
the food industry does,
like making the most food possible.
They pretty much put
everything else aside,
besides mass production.
They don't really care
about animal rights,
or worker safety, or anything like that.
They just put as much work as they can
into making more food,
and like Gabby said, people in America
still can't afford this food that's
cheaper than it's ever been in the past.
So, it just shows that,
really, we can not go back to
just normal farms, because
there's no way just
natural farms like Polyface
could ever sustain a
population as big as America.
Like, we kind of dug ourselves into a hole.
Yeah.
- Okay, so what do you
think we should do then?
If we've dug ourselves--
(students laugh)
If we've dug ourselves into this hole,
even though if we're going to be producing
less food that's better quality,
I agree that is better,
because then you're
taking the animal rights
into consideration, the
workers' rights and everything.
But then either we have
to figure out a way
to change how people eat,
and so people are eating
a bigger variety of food,
or somehow figure out a different way
to be able to feed everyone.
Because, at the end of the day,
either we're going to have
a lot of people who die
because we change this,
and we change it too fast,
and we're not ready to adapt to it,
or we can do it slowly and
try and figure out ways
so that everyone somehow survives.
Eli.
- Okay, well, I think
that we should really
just follow the model of, like, France,
or some other country
in Europe or something.
Because they have a way better...
People in France are so much healthier
than people in America,
and they don't eat nearly as much food.
They still aren't starving,
most people in France
aren't starving or anything.
So, there are countries,
it's just not left them.
- Okay, I don't know if this makes sense,
but if they have, like 20,000 chickens
in one pen, do they
have to feed them corn?
Like, what's wrong with mass production,
but making it a little healthier?
Why can't they just
give them something else
that's maybe not all
corn, maybe half corn,
or half corn to little corn?
And then, metaphorically speaking,
this totally reminds me of Hitler,
and, like, how he took over all the people
and made them work to
death and everything,
and that's like what they're
doing with the animals.
They're just working them to death,
and they have no rights
or happiness whatsoever.
Deja?
- I think the answer to your question is
that most people just want money,
so they'll buy whatever's cheapest
and pay low wages to people
just so they can make a lot of money.
I think that's the answer
to your question about
why don't they just choose
another food instead of corn.
I think it's because of money.
- But also consider, what about...
What about the industrial organic?
Doesn't that address this whole problem
of how the chickens are fed?
Even though they're raised in coops?
- [Male student] They're still fed corn.
(female student mumbles)
- Molly.
- Okay, so I think that
it's a really good idea
that Matthew brought up a while ago,
that the industrial issue,
it can't really be solved
by using beyond organic.
I think we've moved on from that.
We can't really go back to beyond organic,
because we wouldn't be
able to feed enough people.
And then just to Adam's point,
I don't think that we're
not producing enough food.
I think the problem
is that the people don't have
enough money for the food.
So, I think that producing more
food wouldn't really help.
- [Female student] I was going to say,
everyone keeps talking
about mass production
and that view would feed everybody.
But if you think, we actually
waste a lot of food too.
That's actually important.
I think we saw a picture or something,
all of it gets thrown out every day,
or they have ads on it on TV.
If we're so worried
about feeding everyone,
why don't we eat better ourselves,
and stop buying so much
food we don't actually eat?
- Well, either, whether you
guys want to change it locally
to outside or outside to inside,
I like the idea that you guys
think about spreading the idea.
Whether it's taking France's ideas
and taking it onto ourselves,
or just ourselves spreading it out.
Because (mumbles) so obnoxious,
they would go out to
McDonald's, my family,
and be like, "Do you know what that eats?"
And then just start talking.
We're like, "Shut up,
don't tell me what it eats.
"I'm going to eat it."
And now my mom asks me, she's like,
"Is this good?"
And then I read it, I'm like, "Yeah,
"it has this and this and this."
And now she turns to me
and, like, asks me should
we buy this, should we not?
So, I think I have changed
a little bit at least,
having been