(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] So how is that energy?
- [Boy in gray hoodie]
Different things like jules.
Which are increments, which are similar.
(Background Chatter)
- [Boy in gray shirt] kilowatts hours and BCU
- [Teacher] Okay.
- [Girl in t-shirt] You could also measure
it with a thermometer,
if it's kinetic energy sometimes
- [Teacher] Okay.
- [Girl on the end] I have an cubic
feet, tons, and gallons, too.
- [Boy in gray hoodie] That's mass.
And volume
- [Girl on end] Oh, cause it was like...
(Background Chatter)
- [Girl on end] Hold on.
- [Boy in gray hoodie]
Totally different thing
- [Girl on end] I don't remember
(Background Chatter)
- [Boy in dark hoodie] While she's looking at that,
what are some cons of nuclear energy
that most people are concerned about?
- [Boy in gray hoodie] Well, there are no
(Background Chatter) no explosions.
That's a totally different process
with nuclear bombs and nuclear power.
- [Girl on end] Oh, I have...
- [Boy in gray hoodie] And it states, in lots of
articles, about nuclear waste,
that it produces very little waste.
At all.
- [Girl on end] Well I have a cubic feet,
it's for like, natural gas.
Tons is measured for coal.
Kilowatts hours is for electricity.
- [Boy in gray shirt] It doesn't
pollute the air.
You could inject the water back
into the earth to reuse it.
Like you could put the water
back in and keep reusing it.
And then, the disadvantages
for geothermal energy is,
the gasses that are released smell bad
and efficiency is only 15%,
which isn't, it's not that great.
And there's a limitation of it.
You can't just like keep
reusing it and reusing it.
- [Girl in gray] I think that would
be like a possibility
for a scenario, but like, we
don't know if it's warm enough
to be able to do that.
- [Boy in gray shirt] Yeah, if there
was a good spot around our area,
it might be good but--
- [Teacher] How would you know if
your area was a good spot?
- [Boy in gray shirt] I don't know.
They would have to do tests and stuff
- [Girl in gray] Plus,
I don't know that people
would want it in their backyard.
- [Girl in pink] It's hard because, Cranberry,
if we're thinking of
where those people, well,
like a civilized area.
People really don't want something--
- [Girl in gray] That smells bad.
- [Girl in pink] Yeah, that.
They don't want any disruption.
- [Teacher] And where are you most likely
going to see geothermal energy come from?
There are--
- [Boy in gray shirt] Inside of the earth.
- [Teacher] Right, but it's inside of the earth,
but it comes out in what ways?
- [Boy in gray shirt] In geysers.
- [Teacher] In geysers, or what else?
- [Boy in gray shirt] I'm not sure.
- [Teacher] Volcanoes.
- [Boy in gray shirt] Oh.
- [Teacher] Yeah, so, who, that's
definitely something.
You don't have volcanoes
everywhere either.
- [Boy in gray shirt] Yeah.
- [Teacher] Right?
And you definitely wouldn't
want that in your backyard.
- [Boy in gray shirt] And sometimes, if
there would be a good area,
maybe the state, or the
country, would buy the property
to like put it there,
because it's a good spot.
Sometimes they do that
for like mining and stuff.
They like buy the property.
- [Teacher] Okay, Okay.
(Background Chatter)
- [Girl in pink] I had hydro-electric.
And some of the pros that is,
it doesn't pollute at all.
And the actual running
of the power plant is really cheap.
And then it's really reliable.
So, say there was a big
power-outage in the area,
the hydro-electric power plant
could get that running again.
But, it's run by building dams in rivers
and they're extremely expensive to build,
which can be fixed by partnering up
with someone else who needs that.
A different, a business or something.
But it can also cause flooding upstream
for the animals, and people, and houses.
- [Girl in gray] I have a question for you.
Do you have to have like a big river
or could you use like a little creek
like we have around here?
- [Girl in pink] I don't think you could
necessarily use the creek.
- [Teacher] The Connoquenessing?
- [Girl in pink] Yeah, but, yeah you have
to have like a big river.
and it has to be fairly out of the way.
- [Girl in gray] Would it like cause flooding?
- [Girl in pink] Yeah, you couldn't have
any houses really upstream,
because could--they'd flood.
- [Teacher] And for example, your science book says
that the Hoover Dam, which
is on the Colorado River,
it created a waterfall of 400 feet,
which is more than twice as
high as the Niagara Falls.
So you're talking about
a river that you would
have to be able to create that drop,
because the water creates
the kinetic energy.
Am I saying that right?
- [Girl in pink] Yeah.
- [Teacher] And that's what causes the electricity.
- [Girl in pink] Correct.
- [Teacher] So, if you could create
something like that
with the three rivers we have here,
that might, that might work.
- [Girl in pink] And again the whole--
- [Boy in gray shirt] Yeah, the three
rivers, that could do it,
because there's a bunch of
big rivers in Pittsburgh.
- Yeah.
- [Girl in gray] Yeah, but if you build that
up, wouldn't that flood?
- [Boy in gray shirt] Well, not
in the middle of the city,
you could maybe do it
like out of the city,
cause the rivers aren't just
like in the city, they go out.
- [Girl in pink] And also, if you have a good area,
flooding wouldn't matter so much,
if you pick the right area.
Which I mean, I guess, the whole thing...
(Background Chatter)
So definitely not in Cranberry, here.
Where we live.
- [Girl in gray] Well we get a
lot of rain around here,
so, I'm just... like flooding
would be like a problem.
- [Girl in pink] Yeah.
- [Boy in gray shirt] We're sort
of in a drought right now,
there's not been a big
rain for a long time.
- [Girl in white] Does it harm the
animals that are in the river?
- [Girl in pink] It's better for
farmers because down the streams
the water is deeper and
there's more fish and stuff,
but there's less...
plants and stuff.
Like upstream it floods
the animals and homes,
and so it doesn't really
hurt too much down stream.
I guess it depends,
because the farmers need deeper waters,
but not if there's less life in it.
Because that's what
they're trying to achieve.
(Background Chatter)
- [Girl in gray] Rachel tell us about yours
- [Girl in white] My energy is fossil fuels.
The pros were that it's the most effiecent
of most of the energy sources we can use.
It's easy to find if you
know, in the general area,
of where it's at.
It makes up half, or more, of our energy,
in the United States.
The cons are that it's non-renewable.
There's a limited supply.
It makes a lot of
pollution when it's mined.
It's expensive to transport.
It harms aquatic life with pollution.
It takes millions of years to form.
- [Teacher] That's something I didn't
know about fossil fuels,
that it takes a very long time to develop.
- [Girl in white] It has to be, like, compacted.
- [Teacher] Uh-huh.
- [Boy in gray shirt] So maybe the big plant,
it might be able to, not might be able,
it would probably run out fast,
if we started using it a lot,
so there wouldn't be a point
in making this huge plant,
and then it just run out.
- [Teacher] Yeah.
- [Girl in pink] So it might be
something people would
use more often in the future.
Just little by little, like
just for little things.
What do you mainly use it for?
Like energy, but like...
- [Teacher] What falls under the
umbrella of fossil fuels?
- [Girl in white] Coals and oils.
- [Teacher] And natural gas.
- [Girl in white] Yeah.
- [Teacher] Yeah.
- [Girl in gray] And you said it
(Background Chatter)
when you mine it, so we would
have to transport it here.
There's so many people that live here
that wouldn't want that.
- [Boy in gray shirt] Isn't that what
happened in Mexico?
What's that called?
The Gulf of Mexico, yeah.
Weren't they mining for
fossil fuels, like oil?
- [Teacher] Oil, yeah.
- [Boy in gray shirt] And that happens,
so that's like a natural disaster.
And that's happened a bunch of
times, so it's not that safe.
(Background Chatter)
- [Girl in gray shirt] So for our scenario,
what do you think would be the best two?
- [Boy in gray shirt] Maybe nuclear
around here, out of the way a little
so it wouldn't create any huge explosions.
(Background Chatter)
- [Boy in dark hoodie] So thermal energy
transfers into electrical energy
- [Girl in gray hoodie] So it's kind
of like biomass, cause they both,
you burn both of them,
except yours you use--
- [Boy in dark hoodie] Mine's not renewable
- [Girl in gray hoodie] Yeah, yours,
you use like uhm...
What's it called?
- [Girl in floral shirt] Like plants?
- [Girl in gray hoodie] Fossilized
plants and stuff.
And for biomass you just
use waste or woods scraps
and stuff like that.
- [Boy in white shirt] Actually, isn't the,
isn't the fossilized, or
fossil fuels, or whatever,
don't they keep on making them?
- [Girl in gray hoodie] Yeah, fossilized,
yeah, but it can't,
it takes so long to make them,
because you need all the
pressure and the decomposing,
like plants and animals,
that once it runs out,
it's going to take a
while for us to get more.
- [Teacher] Like thousands of years,
it takes to replenish.
- [Girl in gray hoodie] Yeah.
(Background Chatter)
- [Girl in gray hoodie] It takes a long time.
- [Teacher] Yeah, it takes a very
long time, for sure.
- [Girl in pale hoodie] So I think,
Keeton, I don't think yours
would be the best for
our community to use.
- [Boy in dark hoodie] It's running out anyway,
yeah, so.
- [Girl in floral shirt] How much
pollution does it cause?
- [Boy in dark hoodie] A lot.
- [Boy in white shirt] Why does the world
just use it, if it's running out?
- [Girl in pale hoodie] Why waste it?
- [Teacher] We talked
about the efficiency.
What's the efficiency cost
of fossil fuels?
- [Boy in dark hoodie] I wasn't sure.
I couldn't find the exact--
Uh, 38 to 47%.
- [Girl in gray hoodie]
That's actually really good.
cause like biomass was
only 22 to 30 or something.
- [Teacher] So that may
have something to do with
what your decision is, right?
The efficiency of the energy.
- [Girl in gray hoodie] I think so.
- [Boy in white shirt] I just (Background Chatter).
You should save some of it.
You don't need to save
it but it's not that
good of an idea, to rely
on this energy source
that's not going to last forever.
- [Girl in pale hoodie] That's why I say,
you could also
use that as a backup plan,
because if we use
something that's renewable,
like Katelyn's, or something,
but something like a disaster happens
that could always be
our, just our fall back.
That we know we could
use that if we have to.
Just like an emergency generator.
It's like, you know it's
there, if you need it,
you can use it, and it
can last for a little bit.
- [Girl in gray hoodie] Since it
is running out, would you guys say
that it would be better
for us to use it now
or save it in case--
- [Girl in pale hoodie] Oh, definitely save it.
- [Boy in white shirt] Save it.
- [Girl in floral shirt] I say save it, too.
- [Boy in dark hoodie] Now I actually
think save it, because--
- [Boy in white shirt] I think probably save it.
- [Girl in floral shirt] I would say to
save it because if something would happen
and then you would need
to use that specific type
then you'll be able to go back to it,
but if you use it all, then
you couldn't go back to it.
- [Teacher] So, what are you all proposing
as your primary energy source?
- [Girl in pale hoodie] Biomass.
- [Teacher] Okay.
- [Boy in white shirt] Cause it doesn't
cause that much pollution.
- [Girl in pale hoodie] And then they
harness that pollution like Katelyn said.
They capture it and then they
use it for different things,
like growing trees or--
- [Girl in gray hoodie] Cause the
only thing that, the only pollution
that really comes from
it is carbon dioxide.
And they have a way of
capturing the carbon dioxide
and using it to fabricate
metal and create paper
and use it in greenhouses and stuff.
- [Teacher] Wow, interesting.
- [Girl in gary hoodie] Yeah, I
thought that was pretty good.
- [Girl in pale hoodie] So I think Katelyn's
definitely provides the most
for the community, definitely out of all.
- [Girl in floral shirt] Yeah, I
(Background Chatter)
...have high effiecency rates
so you'll be able to get
like a lot of usable energy out of it.
- [Girl in gray hoodie] Yeah.
- [Boy in white shirt](Background Chatter)
...the Colorado River, isn't
actually renewable energy's that good
of an efficiency rating.
- [Teacher] Actually, actually the...
the hydro-electric energy
is nearly 95% efficient.
- [Girl in gray hoodie] Wow.
- [Girl in pale hoodie] Once you build it,
since tidal doesn't use any fuel either
It's just once you built
it, but the down side
on building is it costs so much.
So, I don't understand
why people would want
to use that amount of money whenever
because you could use
that on different things.
You could do it to create more biomass.
Like if you wanna try to look
up ways to make that fossil,
plant roots, or plants,
just, try to find research to
make that happen more quickly.
speed up the process,
so it wouldn't be a non-renewable resource
like fossil fuels or anything.
- [Boy in white shirt] There's no, they said,
the small streams and like
rivers and stuff like that,
they only create like a
small amount of energy,
and so we can't really do
that in Silicone Valley...
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] What about the
three rivers in Pittsburgh?
Could we not somehow harness that?
- [Girl in floral shirt] We were talking about that.
- [Boy in white shirt] I was like
talking about redirecting the river.
- [Teacher] Redirecting the river.
- [Girl in gray hoodie] Just making one big one.
- [Teacher] Yeah.
- [Girl in gray shirt] I think that we
would be able to use
the three rivers in Pittsburgh,
because they're all pretty big rivers,
so if we just put like one dam in there,
and then we harness the
energy from all three,
I think that we could get
a lot of energy from it.
- [Girl in pale hoodie] I don't think it'd
be enough energy,
like to completely rely on it.
I think that we'd still
have to use other resources,
to still create energy
because I know the title,
it only creates 10 hours of energy a day,
but I don't know if that means, like,
an hour of that energy
runs like a power plant.
It didn't exactly say
how much energy is used
to do one thing.
So, I don't,
I don't think that'd be a good idea,
to completely rely on that,
and put it in the three rivers.
- [Teacher] And doesn't then, the,
with the title energy, too,
there has to be a difference in the--
- [Girl in pale hoodie] The low and high
- [Teacher] Difference in the low and the high.
- [Girl in pale hoodie] Yeah, three meters of low and high.
- [Teacher] Yeah, so where did you,
find out where in the world
there is that difference?
- [Girl in pale hoodie] Yeah. They
said the biggest title...
it was in France or something.
But we don't have any in the United States
because we don't have an
area that we can put it in
that has that big of a difference.
- [Teacher] Oh, wow.
- [Girl in pale hoodie] So there's none used
in the United States,
and I don't think we could use that, then.
- [Girl in gary hoodie] Well, what you were
saying before about how, like,
each energy source, we
basically have to fall back
on another one.
- [Girl in pale hoodie] Yeah.
- [Girl in gray hoodie] Because none
of them we could completely rely on,
to supply all of our energy.
I think that we would definitely
need at least two choices.
- [Girl in pale hoodie] At least two.
And if we had to pick
two, I would pick biomass
and then your nuclear because you said
a little amount takes it a long way.
- [Girl in floral shirt] Yeah, like
you only need a little bit,
and it can produce a lot of energy.
And the efficiency rating's pretty high.
It's like 35%, so, yeah.
- [Teacher] Wow, that is pretty high.
- [Boy in white shirt] Remember you
said it was like really hazardous?
- [Girl in floral shirt] Yeah, it doesn't produce
a lot of air pollution,
or greenhouse gases,
but if like one small accident is made,
then it can cause like
a really big disaster,
which would be bad for
a community of people,
since there are so many people in it.
- [Girl in gray hoodie] I think that--
- [Boy in white shirt] Katelyn and
Kelsey were talking about like
(Background Chatter) different kinds
of energy sources,
and according to issels, uh, issues...