- Three.
- Oh, it makes like a cubic graph.
- It's like a cube.
- Oh, whoa, that's pretty cool.
- What about...
what if only two of them are the same?
- It's like a quadratic.
(inaudible)
- All right, so as we go
through the investigation now
we're gonna look at,
try to come up with conjecture for that.
Numerically, why do
you think that happens?
If two factors are the same.
- Because it makes... like,
because if you have two factors are the same
that's the same as, like,
squaring one of the factors.
- What happens if you square numbers?
- They become positive, I believe.
So, it's always positive for that section.
- Very nice.
Okay, keep on, keep on going with that.
- All right.
- [Student] Just say A, B, C, D, E, etcetera.
E is the zeros of the law.
- I'm on the first one.
- Why are they the same?
They're squared.
- (background chatter)
- Go to Google Docs.
See if you can do files.
- The file is gray.
- Okay, so what's gonna happen is
you're gonna have a factor formula.
Unlike the other one we had it instead.
And what you want to look at is look
at the factors, and look at the zeros.
What's the relationship
between the factors and zeros.
You may already know
what the relationship is.
Can you predict what it's gonna be?
- That the factors tell you the zeros?
Like the numbers and the factors
tell you what the zeros are?
- And why would that makes sense to you?
- Oh, because when it's X and
you have a number after that,
that's where it is on the X axis.
So, that could be where the zeros
in a set right, maybe?
- Teresa, does that make sense to you?
You look kinda confused.
- Like, so X minus one is...
No, that is wrong then.
- Well here, look at your flag.
Look right here. It's sittin' right here.
So X minus one.
- So that's one.
So, there's one one.
And then X minus two is the there too.
- Oh, so it's the opposite of the form.
- (background chatter)
- So, if you haven't factored form
then you know that it's even zero.
- (background chatter)
- [Student] Yeah, yeah.
It would be equal to zero right?
- Yeah, you're right.
Remember in algebra one
the zero chronic thing?
- Yeah.
- All right, so that does make sense.
Does the end behavior make sense?
It's in factored form, but
what's the degree of that?
- It's three.
- It's the third degree.
- And what does a third degree,
what did we learn last time.
- It can intersect three times.
Does it?
- Yeah.
- And what's the end date?
- Down and up.
And it is, right?
- Yup.
- So, that makes sense.
- That does make sense.
- Why don't you try it
with quadratic factor here.
And why don't you put in an extra factor.
- Just edit that.
- Just add that X, whatever
something we've not used yet.
- What's the F in this one?
- [Student] The eraser.
- But you added this one, right?
- Yeah.
- So what do we except's gonna happen?
How many zeros are we gonna get this time?
- [Student] Four?
- [Teacher] What's the degree?
So, what should the end behavior be?
Because you weren't here last time,
so let's see if you pick it up.
So, if it's fourth degree,
what's gonna happen on the right?
What's gonna happen on the left?
- [Student] Both... (inaudible.)
- [Teacher] Good.
- [Student] Yay.
- [Student] High five.
- [Teacher] Get rid of the space
after the parenthesis.
- [Student] Which one?
- [Student] Between the
parenthesis and the F.
Yeah add a space.
- [Teacher] There's not an F.
See the sliders here?
- [Student] This F was
there to start out with.
So, just delete it then.
Yeah, just delete that.
So, X minus E is just that.
- [Teacher] So we expect...
did it come out the way
you excepted it to come out?
- [Student] Yeah, there's four zeros.
- And if you slide those zeros,
go ahead and slide some zeros
and see if it still makes sense.
- Oh, that's good.
- Oh, because it changes whatever
the final one would be at.
- So, if we had, like, X plus something,
where is the actual zero?
- Oh, it is X plus something,
it's the actual place that it is
instead of the opposite of the place.
- So if we say X,
X plus three, where's the zero?
- Negative three.
- Does that make sense?
Because X plus three equals zero.
- Yeah.
- All right, what's the
next question on there?
- Does the Y intercept change?
- All right, so let's look at your zeros
and look at your Y intercept.
As you change the sliders,
does the Y intercept change?
- [Student] We can't see our Y intercept,
you gotta scroll out.
- Mr. Dillard, would you get me
me the mouse over there?
The silver one.
- Yeah, it's a lot easier
to do this with a mouse.
- [Student] I got it.
- [Student] Other way.
Because the Y intercept is...
- Now it might be really...
- Yeah, it's right there.
- Why don't we try making
some of these factors smaller,
so that we can see it a little better.
- [Male Student] I got it.
- [Female Student] Oh, fine.
I see how it is.
- [Student] Okay, can you see it?
- [Student] It's like at negative 15.
- Okay, is there a relationship
between that Y intercept
and the factors?
Or the zeros?
Why don't you guys talk it over.
- [Student] What are the zeros?
- [Students] So, the zeros are,
what are the zeros?
And the zeros are all the numbers that are,
they're the opposite of this.
So, it would be negative
two, four and a half,
and one.
- [Student] Wait, what's the Y intercept?
It's 15?
- [Student] Two.
- Yeah, it's down here.
It's actually 18.
- And it's negative 18.
- Four and a half times two is nine,
times two is 18 times one.
It's 18.
You multiply all the end numbers together
and you get the Y intercept.
- Well, that's nice.
- That is cool.
- [Teacher] But, why does that make sense?
Why would that work?
- Why does that work?
- [Student] Oh! Because to get the Y intercept,
the Y intercept doesn't have an X value
so you just,
in order to factor this equation,
you would just multiply
all the end ones to get it.
- Oh, yeah because it's the
numbers after X, like, almost...
- zeros... zeros?
- [Teacher] Well, are the numbers after
X the actual zeros?
If it said X plus three.
- The roots.
- [Teacher] X plus three, what would
the zero be for that?
- [Students] Negative.
- So, they're the inverse of the zeros.
- The opposite.
- The opposite, yeah.
- [Teacher] You have to be careful
with the word inverse
because it has a lot more meaning.
All right, so, if we know what the zeros are,
and we multiply those and
we got the Y intercept, right?
- [Student] Yeah.
- [Teacher] What about A?
What happens when you slide A around?
Does that change?
- [Student] Slide A around.
- [Student] I already know what should happen.
- [Student] You can just use the mouse.
- [Student] I can't click it.
- [Student] Move.
- [Student] Oh, that's why.
- It changes the middle one.
- [Teacher] Did it change the zero?
Start with that.
Does it change the zeros at all?
- [Student] No.
- [Student] No, it doesn't change the zeros.
- [Student] Well, okay, go back to...
- [Student] It's not changing the zero.
Well actually...
- [Student] Well, it's just changing it's steepness.
- [Student] Yeah, it's changing it's
steepness and the width,
but it's not changing the zeros.
- [Student] Well, yeah it does,
because when it's flat then
every number's changed.
- [Student] But when its flat, but that's only
- [Student] If A is zero,
since they're multiplying everything by A,
then if A is zero, everything is zero.
- So, yeah, you have a zero
degree polynomial at that point.
- [Student] Yeah.
- Okay, so other than when A is zero...
- [Student] All it's changing is the
steepness of the graph.
And not changing the zeros.
- So, does that change the Y intercept?
- [Student] Um, yes, it is changing the Y intercept.
But I think it still works out as, um,
you can still multiply all of them together.
- [Teacher] Does that make sense?
Check and see if it still works.
- [Student] Oh, whatever A is,
is A is the opposite of the Y intercept.
Because if A is four then
the Y intercept here is,
or that might just be...
- Well, that's a good conjecture.
Check some of the other things
and see if it still works.
- [Student] Um, try changing, yeah.
- (background chatter)
- [Student] Yeah, no, that's not right.
- That would be cool.
- [Student] It was just the way I had it.
- And, that's one of the
nice thing with the sliders,
because you might see a connection,
but you can quickly see
if it works for all cases
and not just one case.
- [Student] The Y intercept is six.
Yeah, it's still, ah,
when you change A, it's still going to
effect the Y intercept, and
as changing, as multiplying
all the numbers together
and then multiplying by A.
- [Teacher] Does that make sense?
- [Student] Yeah.
- [Student] So, all those numbers
multiplied together is still...
six.
Keep going with this,
because the next thing
we're gonna look at is
what happens when some of
the zeros are the same.
When we use the factor more than once.
Okay?
Keep going.
- (background chatter)
- [Student] Are we on six now?
- [Student] Yes.
- [Student] What happens when two or more factors
are the same?
So, make E and E.
- [Student] I'm gonna make them all three.
- [Student] I work hard for you guys,
you criticize me.
- [Student] Um, the E, the E.
Oh, it makes the,
when they're the same...
- (background chatter)
- [Teacher] Try changing one of them.
Try changing one of the sliders.
- (background chatter)
- [Student] We figured that one.
It just turns out to be the opposite.
- [Teacher] So, go ahead and change one slider.
Just pick one other than A.
Pick B or something like that.
- The opposite of that
variable becomes the...
- Y intercept.
- That doesn't explain the zeros.
- [Teacher] Now, something we want to find out,
- Is there a relationship
between the zeros
and the Y intercept?
- Oh, there is.
When you change the Y, then the zeros
equal the opposite of the Y intercept.
- Okay, what happens if you change two?
- [Student] No, it doesn't.
Oh yeah, yeah it does.
- Oh yeah, zero does.
The one that isn't the
same numerical I think.
- [Student] The right most zero becomes it.
- When you move them, the Y intercept
and the zero both change at the same rate.
Because if you move, like, C
steadily to the left,
once C is two, negative two...
- [Student] Jacob said, "Half the time, when you
multiply them all together you get it."
- (background chatter)
- [Student] Yeah, that's what we're discussing.
- [background chatter]
- [Student] The absolute value of the Y intercept
and then the absolute value of the zero,
if two of the factors
are the same that's in.
- [Student] If all of the variables are
the same except one of them,
it becomes the zero,
it becomes the zero and the
opposite of the Y intercept.
- [Teacher] So, now as you slide,
you'll actually be able to see the Y intercept.
- [Student] If you set
all the variables the same
and change one of them,
it becomes the zero and the opposite
of the Y intercept.
- [Teacher] Okay, so on Dave's right here...
(background chatter)
- [Student] Yeah the multiplication,
in case you, like,
if you multiply all the zeros together,
you get the opposite of the Y intercept.
- (background chatter)
- [Student] Does it have to do
with the factor formula?
- [Teacher] Yeah.
- [Student] Yeah.
- [Teacher] So, the absolute value of the...
- If you multiply the zero,
- [Teacher] So, does it make sense algebraically?
- [Student] Yes.
- Why does it make sense algebraically?
- When you find the factor
with that new grouping
you have to, it becomes the opposite.
- But Y intercepts, algebraically.
- [Student] Because the Y intercept is when
all the X's are zeros,
so you're just left with
the one that doesn't have an X on it.
And that is the multiplication
of all the factors.
All the numbers.