So, what we're going to do then
is try to find two words, just like
Fernando and Nicolet told us
that mean the same thing.
So here are some little friends
poking out of this wall
and I'm going to read these words to you
in case they're a little
hard for you to read
and then I'm going to ask
for volunteers to come up
and match synonyms, okay?
If you want to read them
with me you can, okay?
- [Class and Teacher] Happy, tiny, small,
silent, little,
quiet, glad.
- [Teacher] Right.
Some of these words too
you might not even know what they mean,
but once you work with
synonyms a little bit
you're going to actually
make your vocabulary
a little better.
You're going to learn
what more words mean.
Okay, so that'll help
you read and everything.
Nicolet.
- [Voiceover] That's silent and quiet.
- Okay, you want to
come up and match those?
Let me put it on pen.
Okay.
You have to move over a little bit.
Great, okay.
Is she right guys?
Good.
How did you know that those were synonyms?
- Because both of them
mean that...
Because both of them mean...
Both of them mean the same thing.
- [Teacher] Okay, they mean the same thing
or what else, Jabril?
Oh, you have another one you want to mark?
They mean the same thing right.
You can make up a sentence like
we should be quiet in the library
and then you could take out the word quiet
and put silent in.
We should be silent in the library.
That's how you can check it
to make sure of it.
- It's like a better word.
- A better word, quiet or silent.
Okay, Fernando, you see one?
Okay, what do you see?
Oh great.
Can you tell us what you have?
- Happy and glad.
- [Teacher] Happy and glad.
Okay, pick a sentence for those.
Can you think of a sentence?
- I'm happy.
- [Teacher] Because?
- Because my birthday is coming.
- Okay, I'm happy because
my birthday is coming.
Let's take out happy.
You guys can take it and throw it away.
Take out happy and put this word in.
- Glad.
- Okay, now say the sentence with glad.
- I'm glad because my birthday is coming.
- Alright, very good (applauding).
Okay, you ready Jabril?
You got one?
Okay, what did you find?
- Smiley and little.
No, small and little.
- Okay, is he right guys?
- [Class] Yes.
- He is, very good.
You started to say
smiley and little, right?
But then you said, wait a minute,
those aren't...
What is that called?
Those aren't...
- Right.
- Synonyms, right?
So then you remembered that
word is small and little.
Okay, very good.
Anyone else?
Who hasn't gone?
Barbara.
- But there's no words.
- Is that all of them, alright good.
- [Voiceover] No.
Tiny and little.
- Oh, small, little, and tiny,
they all go together, don't they?
That's right, there's
three words that mean
the same thing.
Small, tiny, and little.
Okay, so there can be more
than one synonym for a word.
That's a good point.
Do you guys want to
practice saying synonym?
Cause it sounds likes it's hard to say.
Let's clap it, ready.
- [Teacher and Class] (clapping) Synonym.
- Let's try again.
- Let's just slow down a minute.
- [Teacher and Class]
(clapping) Syn, o, nym.
(laughs)
- Alright, we'll keep practicing.
Okay, now we need to read these sentences
and find out which ones have synonyms.
Okay, let's start with this one.
Nicolet, can you read that?
- The dog is angry.
The dog is mad.
- [Teacher] Are those synonyms?
- [Class] Yes.
- [Teacher] Which two words?
- Angry and mad.
- [Teacher] Okay, you want to come on up?
You're going to circle those
sentences and that dog.
Look at his face too.
Okay, if you're writing,
you could use the word mad.
That's kind of, like I just call it
a first grade word, sort of.
You want to bet a sparkle word
so you could say he's angry.
You could also say he furious.
The dog is furious.
That's an even better word, right?
A better synonym.
Jabril, you want to do the next one?
Okay, can you read these?
- The dog it sick.
The dog is ill.
- So sick and ill, are those synonyms?
Good.
Oh, you're getting
creative with our circles.
Okay, Barbara, you want to read this one?
- The dog is sad.
The dog is crying.
- Okay, are those synonyms?
- Yes.
- Well, sort of.
He would be crying if he's sad.
I'm not sure that they
mean the same thing.
Like if you said, Barbara fell down
and now she is crying.
Right, that's something
that you do, right?
Barbara fell down and now she is sad,
but it doesn't really mean the same thing.
It's close.
You want to try this one?
- The dog is happy.
The dog is glad.
- Okay, happy and glad,
do those mean the same thing?
What do you guys think?
Yes, you agree?
Okay, so then she's
going to circle that one.
Put a big circle around the whole thing.
Okay, great.
OK, who hasn't had a turn?
Fernando, can you read this one?
- The dog is surprised.
- [Teacher] Oh, good reading.
- The dog is--
- Scared.
- So surprised, see his face?
Is surprised and scared,
are those synonyms?
- Yes.
- Okay, who says yes?
Fernando says yes.
Who says no?
Okay, what do you think?
If I'm surprised, I just walked in
and everyone's throwing me a party,
I said (gasps) I'm so surprised.
Would I also say I'm so scared?
- No.
- [Teacher] No, I'd
probably be really happy.
So are these synonyms?
- [Class] No.
- No, okay, nice job guys.
Okay, let me see where I want to go.
Okay.
Alright, the next thing we're going to do
before we do this, is I'm going to see
if you can match some synonyms
with a fishbowl and a fish.
Who likes fish?
Really?
What's your favorite animal?
Favorite pet?
Do you have a favorite pet?
Do you like (mumbles)?
- Dog.
- [Teacher] You like dogs?
- Cats.
- [Teacher] You like cats?
- (mumbles)
- [Teacher] Do cats eat fish sometimes?
- Yeah.
- [Teacher] Uh-oh, uh-oh, well.
- They eat mouse.
- [Teacher] They eat mice, right.
- Fish.
- [Teacher] Well, we're
going to do a fish game
and you're going to do
this with a partner.
Okay, I'm going to ask Jabril and Barbara
to sit at the back table.
Hold on a minute, wait
for your directions.
And we are going to move those things
out of the way.
And you're going to see if you can match
the synonyms together.
The fish with the fishbowl, okay?
Now be sure like when we've
worked with pairs before
that one person's not doing all the work
and the other person is
just, you know, watching.
Okay, make sure if you
think two words go together
then you say, do you think these words,
or are these synonyms?
You need to talk to your partner.
You need to agree, okay?
So you two can go to the
back table with those.
Mix them all up.
Mix all your fish up and
put them on fishbowl pouch.
Okay, and I'll come over and
help you read some of the words
that you might have trouble with.
Okay, mix them all up.
And I'm going to walk around,
but I want you to try
to work kind of your own
a little bit with your partner.
Okay, so let me help you read this word.
Tease, messy,
speedy, sleep,
sprint.
Okay, so those are your fishbowls.
Run, fast,
sloppy.
This looks like brother, but it's bother.
- Bother.
- And doze.
Doze.
Okay, so you guys can sort of
see what you can put together
and I'll be back in a minute, okay?
Make sure you're talking to each other.
Do you need help reading?
Stare, mad.
(mumbles)
Friendly, scream.
This is nice, angry,
(mumbles), yell, (mumbles).
So you need to talk to your partner.
Says.
- (mumbles)
I want to put it on speedy.
- Oh, speedy, yeah that's right.
- [Teacher] Hold on, she's talking to you.
- I want to put it on...
- [Teacher] Friendly.
Do you agree that those are synonyms?
Okay.
- Can you help me with this word?
- Angry.
- Tease.
- [Teacher] Tease.
- Okay, look.
- [Teacher] What word
means the same as tease?
Did you talk to your partner about those?
Make sure he agrees with what you chose.
- What was this?
- [Teacher] Doze.
- Doze and sleep.
- [Teacher] Are those synonyms?
Okay, do you know what--
It's hard if you don't
know what a word means
so I can help you.
Do you know what the word doze means?
- Yeah, it means that like you're tired.
- Um-hum, and you might doze off.
Like if you're watching
TV and all of a sudden
your eyes are closed, you dozed off.
- And then sleep.
- And sleep.
Okay, so do you agree with that?
Which ones did you pick there?
- Scream.
- Okay.
- (mumbles)
- Did you ask her?
- No, I didn't.
- No, ask her.
- Is this bother?
- Yes.
- Do you know what bother and tease mean?
- They both mean like they're bothering.
- Okay, like my sister keeps bothering me.
My sister keeps...
- Touching me.
Teasing me.
- Teasing me, right.
You can use those words
kind of the same, right?
Okay, so you can run around the track
or you can sprint around the track.
This one actually goes here.
Now you have speedy and messy,
sloppy and fast.
Okay, what'd you find?
Stare.
- This means because
they both mean that they're matched
and this one (mumbles).
- [Teacher] Scream and yell, right.
- (mumbles)
- [Teacher] Soaked.
Great.
Okay, looked and stare.
Nice and friendly.
Angry and mad.
Wet and soaked.
Yelled and screamed, awesome.
Okay, bring your fishbowls back over.
Okay, how'd everybody do over here?
- [Class] Good.
- Okay, everybody choose
one bowl and one fish.
Just one that you think you
can make a sentence up with.
Okay.
So you can choose any
bowl with a matching fish
and you have to make up a sentence
where you're going to use both words,
both synonyms.
Okay, Barbara, you ready?
What did you find?
Which two words?
Tell us your words first.
- Friendly and nice.
- [Teacher] Okay, so are you
ready to make up a sentence?
- I am nice and friendly.
- [Teacher] Okay, you put
them in the same sentence.
Does anybody have a way that she could
make her sentence different,
because nice and friendly
could mean anything.
You have an idea?
- This time I'm using friendly.
- [Teacher] Okay.
- I am friendly.
- [Teacher] How about a new classmate?
- Yeah, a new classmate.
- Okay, so that's using friendly.
Now you're going to take out this word
and use the synonym, I am?
- I am nice to everybody in my--
- [Teacher] To the new--
- New student.
- [Teacher] Classmate, right.
You use the same words in your sentence.
You just are going to change your synonym.
Okay, good job, very good job.
Okay, Nicolet.
Show us your words first.
What do you got?
- Doze and sleep.
- [Teacher] Okay.
- I'm using the doze.
Doze means that I am...
- [Teacher] You can put
I-N-G at the end if you want.
Like dozing.
- I am dozing out in the car.
- [Teacher] (laughs) Okay.
I am dozing out in the car.
- And then I am sleeping in the car.
- [Teacher] Okay, did she do that right?
- Um-hum, yes.
- [Teacher] It makes me
think of when you're on
a long trip, right?
Has that ever happened to you?
- Um-hum.
- [Teacher] Yeah, when have you done that?
- I've done that when
we went to Charlotte.
- [Teacher] Okay, and you took
a little sleep in the car?
- Um-hum.
- [Teacher] Okay, alright, Fernando.