- Who's gonna do the skyscraper?
- So we got to put size, color, and shape.
- Size, color, and shape.
- Ok, I'm gonna do a skyscraper
- Beau, is that for the
past or the present?
- That's for the present.
- Skyscraper?
- [All boys] Present, the present.
- [Teacher] The present, ok.
- [Brown sweatshirt] And
the pyramid is for the past.
- [Beau] Yeah
- [Teacher] And you'll do
a pyramid for the past?
- [White Shirt] I was
gonna do a log cabin.
- That's what I was gonna do.
- [Glasses] But we have
to use different things
because we don't got no logs.
- [Brown Sweatshirt] Well,
actually, they still make
log cabins now.
- [White Shirt] We can
use brown for the logs.
- [Teacher] Jonathon says they
still make log cabins now.
- [Jonathon] They do.
- [Glasses] Yeah, they do.
- [Teacher] We don't really
make pyramids any more, do we?
- [Boys] No.
- [Jonathon] Yeah, but they
could be hidden in Egypt.
- [Beau] Yeah, but there is four lines.
What we gonna do with the other two?
- [Teacher] What I want you
to do is list three details.
- [Glasses] Color, size, and shape.
- [Teacher] So, what shape will
your skyscraper probably be?
(chattering excitedly)
- [Glasses] A rectangle!
A rectangular prism.
- [Teacher] A rectangular prism?
That's what Dillon said.
- [Beau] Rectangle
- [Dillon] Rectangular Prism
- [Teacher] Okay.
- Then you can talk about your pyramids.
Ask them, they're your team.
- [Jonathan] A square pyramid.
- [Dillon] Triangle
- [Teacher] Oh, he said a square pyramid.
- [Jonathon] Yeah, let's do it.
- [Dillon] A triangle.
- [Teacher] You think it
should be a triangular pyramid?
- [Beau] Yeah, I'm with Dillon.
- [Teacher] Well talk about it.
Which one do you want to do?
- [Jonathon] I thought square pyramid
was more like a real pyramid.
You know, because it has four sides?
- [Teacher] It does have four.
- [Jonathon] A pyramid
only has four sides.
- [Dillon] Well a triangle has four, too.
- [Teacher] It does?
- [Dillon] One, two, three, four.
- [Teacher] That's a square, honey,
because it has four.
Well, if it has three sides,
how many sides does it have?
- [Dillon] Three.
- [Teacher] Three.
So, you have to decide.
- [Dillon] So, we could take a
square and make it like a ...
- [Teacher] Dillon agrees
a square pyramid,too.
I love having y'all together.
- [Jonathon] Let's do square pyramid
and rectangular prism.
- [Teacher] Good deciding.
- Alright.
- What are you guys discussing, right now?
- We're discussing what all we wanna do.
- I like that. Okay.
- [Grey Sweatshirt] We're not
sure what play we're doing?
- [Teacher] You're not sure
what play you wanna do?
- [Navy Sweatshirt] Because everybody
keeps picking everything.
- [Teacher] So, how are
we gonna figure it out?
- [Navy Sweatshirt]
But I agree with Randy.
- [Teacher] So, what do you guys agree on?
- [Randy] I agree with my plans.
- [Black Shirt] He wants
like an old time car,
and I don't agree with that.
- [Red Sweatshirt] But,
we don't understand
how you do an old time car.
- [Teacher] How do you do a play, or skit,
about an old car?
That's what you need to tell them.
- The only time --
(all speaking at once)
- [Teacher] Okay.
- [Navy Sweatshirt] Aaron said
something about the classroom
and that I was going to be the teacher.
Or something like that.
- [Grey Sweatshirt] I
wanna be assistant teacher.
- [Teacher] Randy likes that.
- [Red Sweatshirt] And this
is two people from the past
and two people from the present.
- [Teacher] Hear what Jacob said.
- [Jacob] Jacob wants
to be assistant teacher.
- [Black Shirt] You're the
teacher, assistant teacher.
- [Teacher] So when will that
be in the past or the present?
- [Jacob] Present!
- [Red Sweatshirt] Haley could
be a teacher from the present
and then me and Randy can be from the past
and then they can be from the present too.
And then we'll come to where they are,
then they'll have to show us what changed.
- [Teacher] Did y'all hear Aaron's idea?
You can say that to them.
- [Jacob] I like Aaron's idea.
- [Teacher] Listen to
what Aaron just said guys.
He has an idea that you may want to do.
- [Aaron] Ian and Jacob and
Haley are from the present.
And me and Randy are from
the past and we come.
And, they show us all the
stuff that has changed.
- [Jacob] I agree with Aaron.
I agree with Aaron.
- [Haley] I agree with Aaron.
- [Randy] Or we could do,
like, you two are teachers
and like me and Aaron and
Ian are like students.
And then, them two teach us.
- [Teacher] Oh, that's an idea.
You could do...
- [Aaron] But then how do we do the past?
- [Teacher] Well, but
you could do the past
and then, how, could you do
a skit about the past, and
a skit about the present?
- [Kids] Yeah.
- [Teacher] They would be the same
except one is the past
and one is the present.
- [Randy] To where like, no one had desks
and then in the present we have desks.
- [Teacher] Oh. What do you think, Ian?
- [Ian] I wanted to do
people from the past and future
they all meet together
and do things from the
past and the future.
- [Teacher] Well are we doing
the future or the present?
- [Kids] Present
- [Ian] Well then people
from present and past
and they do things from
the past and the present.
- Okay. Well, decide.
It sounds like you got
some really good ideas.
- [Ian] Why can't we just do one
if they are doing stuff from
the past and the present?
And you choose your own people
who live in the present.
- [Teacher] Well, Ian, if
your working in a group
should everybody do their own thing
or should we work and kind of
come up with the same idea?
- [Ian] Yeah, you choose your own people
but you do it in the present.
- Sounds like y'all have to just keep on.
You may just have to make a decision. Ok?
You may just have to make a decision.
Sounds like you are doing great, guys.
- [Blue Polo] How do you
spell transfer trucks?
- [Teacher] Huh?
- [Blue Polo] How do you
spell transfer trucks?
- Transfer trucks?
Let's sound it, let's tap it.
What letters?
- [Blue Polo] T
- [Teacher] Trrr
- [Blue Polo] A- N- C- E- R, or something.
- [Teacher] Trr, like tree.
- [Shannon] T- R
- You got it, Shannon.
Did you hear Shannon?
Let's tap it, Ta'jarius.
Trr..Aaa...
- [Ta'jarius] A
- What letter is that?
Nnnn
- [Ta'jarius] N
- Ssss
- [Ta'jaris] C, K.
- [Grey Shirt] S
- [Teacher] Ssss, Transssss
- [Ta'jarius] S
- [Blue Polo] I got S.
- [Kids] F
- [Teacher] F.
How do you make "er' at the end of a word?
- [Grey Shirt] E.R.
- You got it.
There you go, and you know trucks.
So, what are y'all doing
with transfer trucks?
- [Grey Shirt] I don't know.
He's the one who wanted to write it.
- [White Polo] Why was
this on Noah's desk?
- [Ta'jarius] Case has some names.
- Yeah.
- [Teacher] Ok, but what...
But why did y'all, um
You're describing what
each persons' job will be.
And I have that, "Noah
and Ta'jarius and Madison
are gonna" do what?
- [Blue Polo] The waves.
- [Teacher] What kind of waves?
What are y'all showing from
the past and the present?
- [Blue Polo] I wanna
do waves in the present.
- [Teacher] Do waves change
from the past to the present?
Do you mean like ocean waves?
Have those changed over time?
- [Blue Polo] I'm doing transfer trucks.
- [Teacher] What's it suppose to be?
- [Grey Shirt] A.
- [White Polo] I'm doing transfer trucks.
- [Teacher] How have
those changed over time?
- [White Polo] Horses
carried them, with like,
umbrella's over them.
- [Teacher] Very cool.
And we saw that kind of wagon
on the smart board earlier.
And you said that was like a truck.
- [Grey Shirt] You could
pull that up, back up there.
- [Teacher] I could pull it back up.
Do you wanna see that again?
Cash, do you wanna do the illustrations
for the trucks over time?
Shannon, what are you doing?
What are your illustrations gonna be,
showing change over time?
- [Ta'jarius] She might
do cars or something.
- [Blue Polo] Do you wanna do cars?
- [Teacher] You don't have to do cars.
- [Blue Polo] You don't want to?
- [Teacher] Lots of things
have changed over time.
(all speaking at once)
- [Cash] You can actually
buy food and not hunt it.
- [Blue Polo] How do you spell Shannon?
- That's one of the things you could draw
the change from the, maybe
you'll do washing machines?
- [Cash] Yeah. Yeah, that works.
- [Blue Polo] Yeah. Cars change.
- Do you wanna do transfer trucks?
- [Shannon] No. You're already doing them.
- [Teacher] Guys!
- Do you wanna do washing
machines, Madison?
Draw a washing machine next to that?
- [Blue Polo] You wanna
do washing machines?
- [Teacher] Can you hold
that up so they can see it?
because Shannon can't see it.
- Where did ya wash your clothes at?
- Turn it over like this, and
you'd rub them against here.
- Different, isn't it?
- Yeah.
- When I was little, my
great- great- great- great-
great- great- great- grandma, grandfather
he had a washing board
he took a picture of
and then when I was big
I was allowed to see it.
- Very cool. There was a picture.
Alright. It sounds like
you've got some work to do guys.
I love the idea of
showing the illustrations
of the trucks over time
and the cars over time.
I think we need to think
about waves, though,
because waves are a natural thing.
People don't really build
and change those, do we?
No, so we need to think about something
that has changed over time.
And don't forget our books--
- [Ta'jarius] Buildings! Buildings!
- Buildings have definitely
changed over time.
Alright guys.
Keep it up you are doing great.
Alright, let's see what
you guys are up to.
Okay, what's going on over here?
- [Black Sweatshirt] Well,
we're thinking about--
- [Pink Shirt] About Cassa
coloring, Ann coloring,
and me coloring and
drawing, and her drawing.
- [White Shirt] I love drawing.
- [Teacher] You love drawing.
- [White Shirt] That's what I
love. I love typing at home.
I love all of it.
- [Teacher] Very cool.
Alright, so what kind of
things are you gonna show
how are you gonna show past
to present with your clothing?
- We're gonna show the style, the color...
- [Teacher] Okay, can you tell
me what you're gonna draw?
- [Black Sweatshirt]
We're gonna draw dresses.
- [Teacher] Oh, dresses.
- [Black Sweatshirt] And shoes.
Like, dresses and the shoes
that they would wear.
- [White Shirt] I can get my old dress,
My mom's old dress she's got,
I have it, and I can design it.
- You can?
- [White Shirt] Uh-huh.
(inaudible)
- So are you all four
going to show dresses
from the past and present?
- Yes.
- Or are some of you gonna do past
and some of you do present?
- We're gonna do it all together.
- I love that.
- Them two are coloring, I'm coloring,
and me and her are drawing.
- Very nice.
- You're drawing?
- Yes, we're drawing, I'm coloring.
- Very, very nice.
Well, it looks like you guys
are ready for your next page.
Let me ask you this, how has
clothing changed over time?
- The color has definitely changed.
- The colors have changed?
- And the shoes.
- [Glasses] Ladies used
to wear long dresses
and now they wear not
that long of dresses.
- Oh, so they used to wear
really long dresses and now...
- [Pink Shirt] They have short
dresses that come up to here.
- [Black Sweatshirt] Yeah, and
shoes they wear lace-up boots
- [Teacher] Laced-up boots
- I think my mama has them,
I won't be able to wear them,
but I might be able to bring them.
- Oh, that'd be cool if you bring those.
It sounds like you have great ideas.
- And they wore hats back then.
(inaudible)
- 'cause I'm thinking about my mom's dress...
I mean, I can design it.
- I am very, very pleased with
how much you've accomplished
together in your group, let
me get you the next sheet.
- [In Unison] Okay.
- [Pink Shirt] We all have our things done
and we're going to get it.
- And we all have each
others' phone numbers.
- Here's the next sheet.
Let's look for a second.
"Who will design the piece from the past?"
and, "Who will design the
piece from the present?"
Now that doesn't mean
it has to be separate.
Right, you can take it home.
- [Pink Shirt] Well, me and her...
- Well, it sounded like we're all, okay?
- [Pink Shirt] Yeah, we're
all basically doing it.
- Okay, "Why is this change
important to people today?"
and, "How could this continue
to change in the future?"
Hmmmm.
There's some questions to think about.
(inaudible)
So have you worked on this some more?
You've decided to what you're gonna do?
Skyscrapers and pyramids.
- They're doing the pyramids,
me and him is doing the skyscrapers.
- Them two are doing the pyramids,
we're doing the skyscrapers.
- That was nice. Good
going, coming up with that.
Good job.
- We're doing a square pyramid.
- [Teacher] You're doing a square pyramid?
- Yeah.
- That's easy, all you gotta
do is start out as a square
and draw triangles at the top.
- So when I was with you
before you said this is hard,
we don't know what we're gonna do
and all had different
ideas, and as it turns out
this is kind of easy.
What made it easier?
- [Beau] Working as a team!
- Working as a team.
- Dillon, would you mind
sitting over here, sweetie,
so that everybody can hear
and see what you're doing?
- [Dillon] Yeah.
- Kinda off by himself over
there, huh, sweetheart.
Alright, the last thing you
need to fill out on your papers
is "How has this changed over time?"
Buildings, how have
buildings changed over time?
- Pyramids, pyramids been tooken down.
- Did we ever build buildings out of gold?
- No.
- I got something. Pyramids
have been tooken down
to make more space in
Eygpt, like more land.
- [Teacher] Okay.
(all speaking at once)
- What about buildings in general?
How is this building
different from McWilliams?
- [Dillon] It's bigger!
- It's bigger and has more space.
- Which one is bigger?
- [Kids] McWilliams!
- [Beau] And it's newer.
- It's newer, so how do you--
- It's newer or it's smaller?
- He says it's newer.