- [Teacher] Start using the
principles of design, okay?
So you look at the packet
for the principles of design.
With the principles of design, you gonna
be telling me what you
see in the work of art.
So instead of shapes,
you may be telling me,
what's something you
see in your work of art.
You've got "Gold Is Where You Find It."
What's one thing you
see in the work of art?
- [Studen] Gold.
- [Teacher] You see gold, what else do you see?
- [Student] The miner.
- [Teacher] Miner, and what is the miner doing?
- [Student] Drilling.
- [Teacher] Drilling, okay, so
those would be all stuff
that you see in the work of art.
So go ahead and start on the
second part with analysis,
if you're ready to start on that.
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Alright, are we doin' alright here?
- [Student] Yeah, we don't get how
was the work created.
- [Teacher] Okay, you may have
actually answered that
when you were up here.
If you look at the packet right here,
and the title of the work of art
is "The Sky Pond."
1933 to 1934, can you
read the rest for me?
Who it was who created it?
- [Student] Kauvar--
- [Teacher] Kauvar--yeah, close enough.
- [Student] Smith--
- [Teacher] Smith.
-[Student] --Born: Cape--Ugh, this is hard.
- [Teacher] If you can't pronounce it, just
do the best you can.
- [Student] Giradeau, Missouri--
Missouri, 1893. Died:
Denver, Colorado, 1977. Oil on canvas.
- [Teacher] Uh! What did you say?
- [Student] Oil on canvas.
- [Teacher] Is how it was created and it was about,
this size right here, okay?
So that tells you how the
work of art was created.
Later on, you're gonna look at why
the work of art was created,
and what purpose it served.
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Yes?
- [Student A] What do I say, how--
- [Student B] I know what we do!
It says, if they draw it in three-dimensional--
- [Teacher] Okay.
- [Student B] And they take
some kind of colored pencil,
or painting, and then
sketch it like you do,
and then they go from dark to light.
- [Teacher] Yeah.
- [Student B] And, then they
make the texture from,
the sun is over here, and there's
a little bit of shade because,
this would be covering all this.
There would be a shade right here.
So it's over here, it would
be lighting everything
on this side of the tree,
- [Teacher] Yeah.
- [Student B] and this side of the house,
roof, and that side of the house.
- [Teacher] And you've got,
are these shapes back here?
Or are those somethin' else?
- [Student B] These are shapes.
- [Teacher] Okay, are shapes
flat or three-dimensional?
- [Student B] Three-dimensional.
- [Teacher] Shape forms are
three-dimensional, alright?
- [Student A] Oh yeah.
- [Student B] Yeah.
- [Student A] So those are forms?
- [Teacher] So those are forms, yeah.
But you were right about everything,
You were right about the sun,
you were right about the
texture, the shading, everything,
that's really good.
So you can tell a little about this
on how you think the work was made,
and also relate it to playing
with your pen on your finger,
and also oil on canvas.
Continue working, please.
(Background Chatter)
Alright, so y'all are on analysis now?
And what work of art do y'all have?
Y'all have got "Subway."
Alright, so what are y'all lookin' at
in the Subway for analysis so far?
- [Student] It's something, asymmetrical balance.
- [Teacher] It's asymmetrical balance?
- [Student] Yeah.
- [Teacher] There are three types.
You've got symmetrical
balance, when everything
is exactly the same,
you've got asymmetrical balance
when it's weighted the same.
So there's the same
amount of weight visually.
It's not exactly the same.
And then you've got radial symmetry,
which is a project we
did a little bit earlier.
Okay? Good.
(Background Chatter)
- [Girl] So, is it saying that shapes,
especially right here,
these shapes are more rounded
versus straight and flat.
'Cause these are more 3-D than these.
These kind of have shadows and are free.
So, we were saying how
that makes the consistence more complex
than the simpleness of the,
outside factors, I guess?
- [Teacher] Yes, mm-hmm.
Good! Keep going.
Alright.
- [Girl with Pink Shirt]
Would this be water?
- [Teacher] That is
possibly water right there.
Yes it is.
And what part are y'all on?
Y'all are on the analysis right now? Okay.
And y'all are lookin'
at the "Valley Farms"
by Rose Dickinson?
Okay, cool.
So what do y'all have so far for analysis?
- [Girl in Grey T-Shirt]
Colors from the scene
go together, it can show--
- [Teacher] Could you speak
a little louder? Sorry.
- [Girl in Grey T-Shirt] Colors
from the scene go together.
It can show, a straight web is going
along the farm with the bridge in there.
A small fire is going on,
with smoke coming from the flames.
Smoke is coming from the mountains.
- [Teacher] Sounds good, keep going.
Alright, let's check in over here.
How are y'all doin'?
- [Student] Good.
- [Teacher] Okay, wow, y'all have
got a lot for an analysis.
(Chuckles) Alright,
what else do you have?
So y'all are about ready
to start on analysis?
- [Student] Yes, sir.
- [Teacher] Okay, so let's look here.
Now tell me how all the answers
from the description you just made,
are related to each other,
i.e., how the effects were organized,
complement one another, or
create harmony or distress.
This step can often be the most confusing,
because it is very similar to the first,
and can easily overlap.
A good suggestion is think
about all the principles of art:
movement, rhythm, variety,
portion, emphasis,
and balance, and contrast
work together, okay?
So think about how they work together
to create this work of art, and tell me
everything you see in the work of art,
but not by shape and colors.
Alright.
- [Boy in Beige] The shapes
and colors of the background
create a texture that will--
- [Boy with Jacket] What?
- [Boy in Beige] A texture--
- [Boy in Beige] The-- (sighs)
The shapes and colors of the background,
create a texture that will--
- [Blonde Boy] Like he is actually
drilling near a cave.
- [Boy in Beige] Creative.
- [Teacher] Now, would you say,
these warm colors or cool colors?
- [Boy in Beige] Warm
- [Blonde Boy] Warm, way warm.
- [Teacher] Warm? Now why would you say
they're warm colors?
- [Boy in Beige] 'Cause they're darker.
- [Teacher] They're darker? Okay.
- [Boy wearing Jacket]
It shows that the colors
of the background...(Background Chatter)
- [Boy in Beige] Yeah.
- [Teacher] Now something else.
Does it look like he
blends into the background?
- [Boy in Beige] No.
- [Teacher] He doesn't?
- [Blonde Boy] Yeah, uh-huh.
- [Teacher] Okay, so think about that too.
If he stood out, he would look like
he maybe didn't belong,
but it kind of looks
like he belongs there.
I like what you said, keep working.
I'll be back in a minute to check on you.
Alright, Guys.
Turn around.
Alright, what are y'all workin' on now?
Analysis?
-[Student] Analysis.
- [Teacher] What do y'all have for
analysis so far, Patrick?
- [Patrick] I didn't get that.
I got one for variety and balances.
- [Teacher] Okay, so something is different
from this picture.
Can you just read to me what
you have so far, please?
- [Patrick] Something's different
from this top picture,
because the floor is
green beneath the room,
because it's different, because I thought,
I thought the floor's just one color,
so that's why it's different.
- [Teacher] Okay, that's good, and it's
also different from up here.
You could say that there's a contrast.
Let's look for the definition
of contrast in here.
Do you all know what the
definition of contrast is,
or what contrast is?
- [Boy in Red] Two things
are very different from--
- [Boy in Black] I was on
balance, I'm on balance now.
- [Teacher] Okay, so contrast is what?
One more time, I'm sorry.
- [Boy in Red] Two things
that are very different,
and have a large contrast.
- [Teacher] Okay, so
would you say cool colors
and warm colors have a strong contrast?
- [Boy in the Corner] Yeah,
because they're bright colors
and they give out perspective.
- [Boy in Black] What about the two Cs?
- [Teacher] Okay, two C's, so?
Keep going.
Alright, what part are y'all on now?
Analysis?
And y'all have got "The Subway", okay?
So, can you read to me what you have,
or tell me something
that you haven't added,
but you were about to?
- [Blonde Boy] Jaymen's adding that.
- [Teacher] Okay.
- [Jaymen] I wanna add,
it has radial balance,
because you can kinda see
where the center print is, and then
you can kind of see all these
people, all these stuff.
- [Teacher] Okay, now I have a question.
Have y'all seen that there's a commercial
on a few months ago?
- [Blonde Boy] It's a radio commercial!
- [Jaymen] Yeah!
- [Teacher] The TV, where
she's sitting in the train,
and she's watching the TV,
someone's reading the newspaper
and she's watching the TV?
And she steps out, and it looks like
they may have gotten the idea,
from that ad, from this work of art,
'cause there's lots of
people on the train car,
they're reading newspapers and she steps
into the future, by actually reading her's
on a Samsung Galaxy or
something like that.
So that'd be a good connection
to popular culture, okay?
- [Blonde Girl] Hello,
I was just (Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Which one we
were talkin' about earlier?
Okay, sounds good.
What's up?
Okay.
Alright, what ya on?
Okay, what added, or what
have y'all gotten to
since I was last over here?
- [Girl in gray] We see the
ocean behind the mountains,
green grass is covering the farmland,
and the lines on the mountains
are curved, not pointed.
The mountains are curved.
- [Teacher] Okay.
- [Girl in gray] The houses are spread apart,
the sky is a light green-blue.
- [Teacher] Sounds good, and it sounds like
y'all are just about
finished with analysis,
so are y'all gonna be moving
on to interpretation next?
Okay.
- [Girl in gray] Yeah.
- [Teacher] Active listening, right hand.
Active listening, left hand.
Ladies and gentlemen, a lot of people
are having really great
and meaningful discussions
in the groups, but please remember
that we are all doing
different works of art,
studying them, and we're also
discussing them together.
So that everybody's able to work
without yelling across,
can we take it down just a
notch, a little bit, please?
Keep it a little bit lower?
I'm not telling you to whisper,
and I'm not telling you
to stop what you're doing,
'cause your doing a great job.
Just let us take it down a notch, please.
Keep working, please.
Alright, how are y'all doin' over here?
- [Student] We're doing really good.
- [Teacher] Okay, what can you tell me about
your analysis on this work of art?
- [Student] It said that for the first question,
well, the first thing,
we said the artist Douglass Crockwell
is using repetit-- well, is
repeating shapes and colors
to create a visual image of the painting.
And right now, we're writing,
how classes are organized.
- [Girl in Plaid] And how it's saying
what we introduced for description.
- [Teacher] Okay, now, with "Paper Workers",
Now let's look at the workers.
The workers, do they
look like they stand out
from the industry and from
the industrial aspects
of this work of art?
- [Girl in Green] No.
- [Teacher] They kind of
look like they blend in.
So could they actually be considered
to be parts of the machinery?
- [Girl in Green] Mhmm.
- [Teacher] Okay, so
that's something you may
wanna think about when
you're working on analysis,
or when you switch over to interpretation
in just a little bit.
Can you go touch the keyboard
to bring the Smart Board back on, please?
Alright, what are y'all workin' on now?
- [Boy in jacket] I don't know.
- [Teacher] You don't know, okay.
You don't know what
principles you've covered,
or you don't know what
aspect of the painting
you're working on right now?
- [Boy in beige] We're
working on analysts,
and so far we've covered how the miner
and the vat ground relate to each other.
We covered what colors they have
and how they can relate.
We're about to work on shapes.
Shapes are in there.
- [Teacher] So let's
think about texture, some.
- [Boy with beige] Yeah, we are.
- [Teacher] Look at the definitions, okay.
And let's look at...
I wouldn't look at space or balance,
variety, and you may wanna look
at the definitions of proportion, okay?
- [Blonde Girl] Okay, we are completely,
totally, and absolutely,
confused of analysis.
- [Girl in Black] I'm not!
You're just--
- [Teacher] Analysis, okay.
- [Girl in Black] I'm not!
- [Blonde Girl] I'm completely finished.
- [Girl in Black] She's going all haywire.
- [Teacher] Okay, what's
wrong with analysis here?
- [Blonde Girl] I don't know.
- [Girl in Black] Nothing!
- [Girl in Black] Nothing's
wrong with the analysis.
- [Teacher] Nothing's wrong with analysis?
- [Girl in Black] She's going haywire.
- [Blonde Girl] I do not
understand what art is.
- [Teacher] Active
listening, right hand please.
Active listening, left hand.
Table four, please.
Ladies and gentlemen, when
we stopped a moment ago,
because we had gotten too loud,
let's take it down to a whisper now.
That way everybody can hear themselves
without getting too loud.
So right now, let's take it to a whisper,
for our discussions, please.
Alright, with analysis what you're doing
is you're looking at the
principles of design.
Don't worry about balance.
Let's flip to the beginning.
Now, let's look at texture.
Do you have a texture in here?
- [Girl in black] Yeah.
- [Teacher] And what kind
of texture do you have?
- [Girl in black] Well it's really bumpy,
but some of it is smoother,
like a snow.
- [Teacher] Okay, so that's what you
could talk about in the analysis.
Also in the analysis, with balance:
is it asymmetrical,
symmetrical, or radial?
Now, symmetrical is when things
are the same on both sides.
Radial is when it's radiating out
from a point, like a rim or a pizza.
Is it either one of those?
So, I'd look a little bit
at asymmetrical balance,
and then variety.
I look at the definition,
and then determine
what variety you see in
here, and after that,
go ahead and move over
to interpretation, okay?
That way, if you're being frustrated,
you don't have to get bogged
down and worry about it,
you can move to the next step.
You might find that easier, okay?
Keep going, thanks.
Alright, so y'all are
on interpretation now?
- [Student] Yep.
- [Teacher] Okay, what are y'all about
to do for interpretation?
Can someone read me the
interpretation part?
- [Student] Basically, how does the
painting make you feel?
What does it make you think of?
Don't say you think a
painting sucks, artwork sucks.
That said, that goes in the next step.
What do you think,
What do you think the artist
is trying to communicate
to you as a viewer?
- [Teacher] Okay, so let's bring the painting
back over here so you can see it
while you're working on the questions,
and think about telling me
a story, or what's going on.
Now, does this look like
you're in a cafeteria?
- [Students] No.
- [Teacher] Does it look like you're in a school?
- [Girl] Oh yeah.
- [Boy] No.
- [Boy] It looks like a barber shop.
- [Teacher] Okay, and
what does it look like
is going on in the barber shop?
- [Boy] He's shaving,
cutting someone's hair.
- [Teacher] Now what about over here?
- [Boy] These guys are probably
waiting for their turn.
- [Teacher] Okay, that's what you need
to tell me in interpretation.
What all is going on, or everything
the artist had within the work
of art that tells a story.
We're talking about the story
that's created in the work of art.
Alright, what part are
y'all on, interpretation?
- [Blonde Girl] Yeah.
- [Teacher] Okay, so...
- [Blonde Girl] It kind
of makes me feel like...
- [Blonde Boy] It makes me feel sad.
- [Blonde Girl] It was,
when I think of it before,
and it really doesn't make me feel sad.
I'm not really sure how it makes me feel,
but I kind of think that
maybe he was trying to say,
it went from-- 'cause
this is kind of simple.
- [Teacher] Okay.
- [Blonde Girl] And I keep
going back to the simple
and complex for some reason.
But, I think he was trying to say
that maybe things were simpler,
and it kind of got more modern.
- [Teacher] I like that, I like that.
And also, one thing that
this makes me think of,
is earlier this year, we studied
the artist Jacob Lawrence,
and one of his was a work of art
of a guy on a train, controlling that
with only industry in the background.
With the big cog or wheel here,
it kind of looks like a train over here,
with industry in the background.
But I like what you're saying
about the calmer times,
and the more difficult times,
and I think that would be a great thing
to have in your interpretation.
- [Blonde Boy] It doesn't
look like a train, though.
- [Teacher] Yeah. (Chuckles)
Alright, how are y'all doing?
Y'all doin' alright?
Hey, what part are y'all workin' on now?
Y'all got "Valley Farm?"
- [Girl in Pink] Yeah.
- [Girl in Grey] Yeah.
- [Girl in Pink] Interpretation.
- [Teacher] Okay, what
do y'all have so far
for interpretation?
- [Girl in Pink] This
painting makes us feel bright,
but kind of boring.
The smoke from the mountains
make us wonder who is making it.
We also wonder,
"Why is there a fire with nobody there?"
- [Teacher] Okay, sounds good.
Ah, can you put your stool back up on two legs?
One more time? Thanks.
Alright, what are y'all on right now?
Analysis, and y'all have
moved on to interpretation?
- [Student] Mhmm.
- [Teacher] Sounds good.
Active listening, right hand.
Active listening, left hand.
Right in here, we have
about seven minutes left.
This should give enough
time for most everybody
to finish their interpretation,
and start on their judgment today.
After you get finished
with your interpretation,
one thing I would like you to focus on,
is why you think the
work of art was created.
Think about the time period,
in which it was created,
and why the artists were
creating works of art.
Think about your work of art particularly,
and you'll be able to have a space
on your paper to answer that,
so continue working on
what you're working on.
We have about seven minutes.
Next time you come in,
what we're gonna be doing is
we're gonna be working on presenting.
So, those groups that have enjoyed this,
will be able to look at
the Smithsonian packet,
find their information,
add that to what they've been doing today,
and then present on their findings
regarding what they thought
about the work of art
along with what the
historians thought about--