- [Narrator] She saw sparks in the sky
and a beautiful panda bear
appeared in front of her.
- [Panda] Don't be scared, I'm
your Fairy Panda Bear.
I will turn you into a beautiful princess
so you can go to the parade.
- [Daisy] But I don't have anything to wear!
- [Panda] I will wave my bamboo wand
and I will take care of it.
- [Narrator] The Fairy
Panda Bear waved her wand,
and suddenly Daisy was
dressed in a lovely gown.
On her neck was a dragon
necklace that glowed.
- [Panda] Don't forget, when
the fireworks are over
the magic is done.
- [Narrator] Daisy walked
up to the celebration,
and everyone looked at her.
No one knew who this
beautiful princess was.
The Prince of China saw
her from across the parade.
He went right to her and said,
- [Prince] Hello beautiful princess.
I like your outfit.
Do you want to hold my
dragon puppet with me?
- [Daisy] Sure!
- [Narrator] Daisy was
having the best time
of her life at the parade.
Suddenly, she saw the
fireworks show in the night sky
and she knew she must leave
before the magic wore off.
- [Daisy] Sorry, I had a wonderful
time but I have to go.
- [Narrator] Daisy turned
and ran, but she caught
her dragon necklace on a
stair post and it fell off.
It stopped glowing as it hit the ground
and the prince picked it up.
- [Prince] But I don't even know your name!
I feel nervous because
something bad might happen.
- [Narrator] The Prince
looked all over town
for the girl who would make
the dragon necklace glow.
He went to Daisy's animal farm.
Out in the distance the
Prince saw a little shadow
by the animal pen. Could that
be the girl from the parade?
- [Daisy] Can I try the necklace on?
- [Narrator] Daisy tried the necklace on
and the prince smiled when the
dragon lit up like the sun.
- [Prince] Tomorrow we should be
married, right in the morning.
- [Daisy] Alright, then we shall.
- [Everyone] And they
lived happily ever after.
(Applause)
- [Ms. Turner] Let's give our puppeteers
a round of applause!
- [Audience Member]
Bravo! Bravo! (whooping)
- [Ms. Turner] That was awesome you guys!
(Audience Chatter)
- [Ms. Turner] Class?
- [Class] Yes!
- [Ms. Turner] You're going to earn
yourself another smiley.
Class class class?
- [Class] Yes yes yes!
- [Ms. Turner] Boys and girls if you
are on the list of children
that are going to go out
to work on an art project
could you quietly stand
up and walk to the door?
If you are staying in
with me for our work,
will you sit hip-to-hip with the
person that... (Background Chatter)
I'll get it. (Background Chatter)
No, Ms. Turner wants to do it.
Please sit hip-to-hip with your partner.
Good job Zoe that was awesome!
That was so cool. (Background Chatter)
Okay, just a second then.
Alright, (singing) ♫
turn your bodies this way ♫
- [Class] (singing) ♫ Okay ♫
- [Miss Turner] (singing)
♫ Criss-cross applesauce ♫
- [Everyone] (singing) ♫ Okay ♫
- [Teacher] Who's your partner?
- [Student] Zoe.
- [Teacher] Can you sit hip-to-hip with her?
DeShaun face this way.
Alright, if your legs are
criss-crossed then look up here.
Wow. Theodore why don't you pop up
and go close the door for me.
Alright, this morning
when we were talking about
the books about China, Xander
wrote down a lot of the things
we were talking about that
were different between
us and the people that live in China.
So as a class we figured out that
they have a different flag,
they eat with chopsticks,
which is really neat,
- [Child] We do too.
- [Ms. Turner] Sometimes we do,
right? They have a different alphabet,
they have water buffalos there,
they have the Great Wall of China,
and they speak a different language.
And they also have dragon puppets
which you just saw on the...
- [Everyone] Puppet show!
- [Ms. Turner] What we're gonna to do now
is we're gonna talk about
things that are the
same between our culture
and the Chinese culture
and we're gonna use
our listening stones.
So Toban, I'm gonna be coming around
and I'm gonna give a listening stone
to one of the people in the group,
and if you're holding the listening stone
you're gonna say one thing that's the same
and then you're gonna
pass it to your partner
and they're going to say
one thing that's the same.
And then they're gonna pass it back,
and we're gonna go back and forth
and see if we can start to
talk about what's the same.
We know a lot of things
that are different.
I'm curious of what's the same.
Could you please sit
knee-to-knee with your partner?
Can we show them
knee-to-knee Zoe? Like this?
Facing your partner, like
we do-- There you go!
I'll give you a Band-Aid
in a minute Finn, okay?
Can you sit knee-to-knee
with Graham? Like this?
- [Child] I have another
thing that is dis--
- [Ms. Turner] Another
thing that's different?
- [Child] Uh-huh.
- [Ms. Turner] What?
- [Child] They have more dramatic
designs on their clothes.
- [Ms. Turner] They have
more dramatic designs
on their clothes? We saw that
in our research material.
As soon as you get the listening
stone, I want you to say
something that's the same--
and RJ you might want to
start saying like, "we both..."
might be a way to help okay?
(whispers) RJ you have
the listening stone.
Okay? So look at Zoe, listen
with your eyes and your body
and say, "we both..."
and see how many things you can think of.
(Background Chatter)
- [Student] Can I be the stone keeper?
- [Ms. Turner] You may, yes.
- [Child] We are the same
as them, because we all...
(Background Chatter)
- [Child] We all have eyes.
- [Ms. Turner] We all have eyes, yep.
- [Student] We all have clothing.
- [Student] We all have hands. We both can see!
- [Student] We are the same as them.
- [Ms. Turner] How are
we the same as them?
- [Student] We wear clothes.
- [Ms. Turner] We all have
to wear clothes, right?
- [Student] We all have beds?
- [Ms. Turner] We all have beds.
- [Student] Can we do something different?
- [Ms. Turner] You may say
something different, yeah.
- [Student] We both have to sit down.
- [Student] We both have a mouth.
- [Ms. Turner] We all have hair, yep.
- [Student] No, some people can be bald.
- [Ms. Turner] That's true,
some people can be bald.
What else between us and the
Chinese culture is the same?
We all have shoes.
(Background Chatter)
We can all walk and we can all do things.
- [Student] We all have bodies.
- [Ms. Turner] Did you guys see
anything from the puppet show
that made you think of something
that's the same between us?
What?
- [Student] We all can make things.
- [Teacher] We can all create things
and be really creative.
Did you see something from the puppet show
that made you think we were the same?
(Background Chatter)
- [Ms. Turner] We all have clothes.
Did you see the clothes
on the puppet show?
- [Student] We all have dragon puppets?
- [Ms. Turner] There are a lot of dragon
puppets at Chinese New Year.
- [Student] Oh, we all have puppets.
- [Teacher] We all use puppets.
- [Other Student] That's what I was just going to say!
- [Teacher] Okay, we all use puppets.
- [Student] We all have an alphabet.
- [Teacher] We all have an alphabet,
even though it looks different.
Alright I'm going to see if
we can earn another point.
Class?
- [Class] Yes?
- [Ms. Turner] (gasps) That was so good.
Boys and girls hey, can everyone
turn their bodies this way?
Alright let's share out
now, we had the chance
to pass the stone back and forth,
I just wanted to quickly
hear one thing per group
of something that you
thought of that was the same.
Zoe and RJ can you tell me one thing
that you talked about in your group?
- [Zoe] We both have imaginations.
- [Ms. Turner] We both have imaginations!
- [Zoe] And RJ said we both have brains.
- [Ms. Turner] We're all pretty smart
aren't we? Finn and Graham,
can you tell me something
that was the same?
- [Finn] We both see.
- [Ms. Turner] We both see.
- [Graham] We both have rotten teeth.
- [Ms. Turner] What do you mean by that?
- [Graham] We sometimes all have rotten teeth.
- [Ms. Turner] We have to
go to the dentist sometimes?
Yeah, okay. Xander and Nazarette,
what did you guys find in your group?
What? You tell me, what's
the same? We both...
- [Xander] We both can make things
like necklaces and fireworks
and actually Chinese people
were the first people
to invent gunpowder and
that's what makes fireworks.
- [Ms. Turner] Did you
hear that boys and girls?
Finn did you hear what Xander said?
He said that the Chinese were
the first to invent fireworks.
- [Xander] Because they were the
first to invent gunpowder
and gunpowder is what
powers the fireworks a lot.
- [Ms. Turner] That's cool.
Wait wait wait, it's
Anna and Toban's turn.
Anna and Toban, tell me
something that's the same.
- [Anna] We both have families.
- [Ms. Turner] We both have families.
Did you think of one Toban?
- [Toban] We all have dragons.
- [Ms. Turner] We all have dragons?
- [Toban] What does that say?
- [Ms. Turner] I'll tell you in
just a minute, okay?
And DeShaun and Gabrielle
you're the last ones.
What's something from your group?
- [Gabrielle] We talked about...
- [Ms. Turner] We both...
- [Gabrielle] We both...(mumbles)
- [Ms. Turner] What's
something that's the same?
- [Gabrielle] We all have rainbows.
- [Ms. Turner] We all have rainbows?
Yeah, they see rainbows in China
and we see rainbows here.
And DeShaun what about you?
What's something that's the same
between us and the people in China?
- [DeShaun] We're gonna have the
same melanin as somebody.
- [Ms. Turner] We have the same melanin?
- [DeShaun] Yeah.
- [Ms. Turner] What do you mean by,
"we have the same melanin as somebody?"
Here sit up so I can hear you.
- [Little Girl] I think he means we have
the same melanin in our skin.
- [Ms. Turner] We have the
same melanin in our skin?
- [Zoe] Cuz we
both have light skin.
- [Anna] Yeah but what if the
people in Africa have...
- [Student] I'm not talking about them.
- [Ms. Turner] The people
in Africa have dark skin,
they have more...
melanin.
- [Anna] Yeah but the people in Asheville.
- [Ms. Turner] Oh, in Asheville. In our
city we have lots of different
colors of skin and
different kinds of melanin
but in China did it look like
their skin was pretty similar?
Yeah, yeah.
Alright, so this is what we're gonna do.
Does everyone see these circles over here?
- [Class] Yeah.
- [Ms. Turner] You're gonna come up
and you're gonna pick one
off our chart and you're
gonna go draw a picture
of something that's the same between us
and the people in China
and then you're gonna come
and you're gonna stick it back up.
And this is actually a word bubble chart.
Okay? So when I see you're sitting nicely
I'm gonna call you up and
you come pick your color
and I have brand new markers at the table.
Alright, Zoe and Finn
come pick your color.
Xander and Nancy come pick your circle.
You're gonna draw a picture
of something that's the same
between us and the Chinese culture.
You can write words too.
Okay, the rest of you.
It says, "We will go on hug patrol today."
We're gonna see if we can earn it.
You're gonna do orange?
- [Little Girl] I wanna do pink.
(Background Chatter)
- [Student] Can I do green?
- [Ms. Turner] You have to do orange or...
Alright. So what's the
same boys and girls?
Thank you.
(Background Chatter)
- [Ms. Turner] I love brand new markers!
- [Anna] We have to do
something on the same.
- [Ms. Turner] Something that's the same.
Anna what are you gonna do?
- [Anna] We all have families.
- [Ms. Turner] We all have families.
- [Toban] Can I sit by Anna?
- [Little Girl] I'm doing green.
- [Ms. Turner] Can you sit by Anna, yes.
Anna, Toban's gonna sit next to you.
Sometimes you can say, "we both..."
Or "we all..."
(Background Chatter)
- [Ms. Turner] Xander that was cool.
How do you spell melanin?
You just sound it out.
We all have brains,
we're all pretty smart?
Can you write that in words on there?
You guys are such good writers.
RJ, what are you writing?
what are you writing RJ?
Can you read it to me?
What do you mean by it,
"we all have rooms"?
- [RJ] We all have our rooms.
- [Ms. Turner] We all have art rooms?
- [RJ] Bedrooms.
- [Ms. Turner] Oh bedrooms, we all have bedrooms.
We're gonna make a word bubble.
Can you read it to me? We all...
- [Finn] We all have a heart.
- [Ms. Turner] We all have a heart.