- Yeah?
- I have a question. It says how does the
[Inaudible]?
- Skip predictions. Move on. Yeah. Olympic
athletes--how does your data compare to
Olympic athletes? How does your data
compare to the class average?
[cross talk]
Yeah?
- Do we do the predictions?
[cross talk]
- It does help to have somebody look at it
with you. Sometimes it's not as obvious as
you think. Scott, we're going to stay on
task, right? Good.
[cross talk]
We're not doing predictions, right?
- No.
- So, take a look at patterns. What you
want to do for this question is look at
patterns. Do you see any patterns there?
Okay, good. It's not necessarily worse, by
the way. It's definitely different. It's
worse, Skye, if you're like dead. If we're
talking about heart rate and yours is
worse...
So, we still have a little bit to learn
how that affects you if you are inactive
or not.
- [inaudible]
- So, let's look at the pattern, there.
You see that? That's kind of what I was
thinking. You just missed that one. Again,
one of the things we can talk about then
is data collection. Exactly. Come on,
let's go.
- It's not the same numbers. It's the same
pattern.
- Right.
Good. Any patterns that you guys are
seeing back there?
- Yeah.
- A little bit? What might that be? This
is science, be more specific. Are there
any patterns for number four? You guys
skipped it? It's okay. Yeah. Four. You
don't have to do predictions. You compare
to athletes. Don't do it for predictions,
but do it for your class data and
athletes.
[cross talk]
Okay. Now, that's a perfect, simple
question. Now we take that information and
put it into number six. Hopefully you're
going to make the mental jump that we need
here. What does heart rate have to do with
homeostasis? If we challenged our body
with a little bit of exercise, you know
how heart rates work, now the question is
why. How does that keep us alive? There
you go. Good.
How much more time do we need?
[cross talk]
Did you get this one right? If you guys
did then you understand the process, hands
down congratulations. Make sure you share
your answers. Make it quick, I don't want
people in and out. We good? How about a
drink? Here you go. We got it. It's good.
No, I've got it covered, okay?
Two more minutes remain in your seats. Number
six--there you go. You're good. Good job,
Scott. You're very subtle and very
helpful. Thank you. Remember, we've got a
mic that's on there. All right, got two
more. Thirty more seconds, right? Then
you're back in your own seats.
If you can do six, you're the best.
Ten seconds or so.
Get in your own seats for
the next ten seconds.
[cross talk]
Two things are going to happen--we're
going to start off with simple answers,
then we're going build upon them and then
hopefully we'll get to the more creative
ones at the end. This class, we have
enough time to do that. So, let's do that
right off the bat.
Question one. Daryl, can you read it or
would you prefer to have somebody else
read it?
- I can read it.
- Okay. Good.
- "What is the hypothesis being tested?"
- Okay. So, let's talk about it. In our
experiment, we were looking to get
something measured. What is a valid
hypothesis for this experiment? Scott
we've got and then Alicia. Alicia, let's
go.
- How does exercise affect your heart
rate?
- Good. Now, that's a step in the right
direction. The hypothesis has got to
include the concept-- Alicia and anybody
in her group want to help her out--it's
got to include the concept of homeostasis.
So, can we do that? Can we tale a look at
our aim, a look at our model
hypothesis--how does exercise affect heart
rate? That's a good start. Anybody else
have something else different that would
support our understanding of homeostasis?
You're yawning. You okay? All right. Let's
sit up. Thank you.
Little bit more. Good. Good. Like you're
playing third base, okay Matt? Good. Let's
sit back now. There you go. Got it.
Anybody else? Go ahead.
- If we do exercise then our heart rate
will change.
- Okay. So, that's kind of what Alicia
said. Go ahead.
- It should keep going up and then when
you're not, it goes down.
- Again, a great, great hypothesis if we
were at a third or fourth grade level,
that's something we want to do. But we're
not at third or fourth grade. It's a tenth
grade class here. I want you to get out of
your seventh grade minds and add this
concept of regulation. You want to try?
- How does homeostasis affect your heart
rate?
- "How does homeostasis affect your heart
rate?" Think about that, okay? You want to
reword that? Which causes which?
- Oh, how does your heart rate affect
homeostasis?
- Good. But now we've got to remember. We
combined exercise in this. Kevin?
- How does your heart rate change to meet
the needs of your muscles and cells in the
body?
- You didn't use the word "homeostasis,"
but, "How does your heart change to meet
the needs of your cells and your heart in
your body?" Excellent. I don't need you to
write that. I just need you to understand
that's the direction we're going. You want
to try now?
- I had almost the same thing. I put,
"Heart rate changing throughout exercise
to the needs of homeostasis."
- Homeostasis. Now you guys are closer on
it. So, this is about how does your body
adapt itself, even when stress with
exercise to maintain balance, to maintain
homeostasis. In the beginning of this
unit, you guys remember I had the balance
board up here? How many of you got on it?
I forget. One person? Two people? That's
it? Three people? Do you remember how hard
that was to do? Did we throw things at the
people?
- Yeah.
- Was that easier or harder to stay
balanced when that was happening?
- Harder.
- No, I thought it was like easier.
- What's the room for error? How easy is
it for one of the sides to touch or how
not easy is it?
- It's very easy.
- Same with homeostasis. That margin of
error--we're in a small range here. If I
take your temperature, Dustin, and it's
98.6, does that mean you're healthy or not
healthy?
- Not healthy?
- Okay. 98.6?
- No.
- But what if you're 102? What if you're
101? What if you're just 100? What does
that tell you? You want to try? So, 98.6
is normal. But what if somebody takes your
temperature and you're at 100 degrees or
101 or 102? What does that tell you?
- It's not normal.
- You want to give me a word for that?
- Sick?
- You would be sick. You'd have a fever.
Something would be wrong with you. You
would be not normal, right? Good. That's a
small number. 98.6 and if you have 101,
you've got to see a doctor or something.
You've got to get rest. You've got to get
medicine. You've got to do something to
help your body heal. All right. Number
one, done.
Number two and three--Daryl, you did a
good job reading the first one. Richie,
can I ask you to read the second one?
- Sure. What are the controls in the
experiment?
- Okay. So, controls--another word for
controls anybody, real quick?
- Independent variables?
- No. Not at all. Constants. Things that
don't change. So, above the word
"controls, " can you guys write the word
"constants?" Things that stay the same.
So, Savannah, good, good opportunity for
you to learn, okay? So, when we say
controls, we're talking about the exact
opposite of a variable, which is a thing
that changes. Everything stays the same or
constant. What are some the examples of
the constants that you have in this
experiment, the controls? Go ahead.
- The three categories?
- The three categories. We mentioned
everybody in the same three categories.
Okay. Go ahead.
- The amount of time you're giving us.
- And how much time was that? Do you
remember?
- Two minutes?
- Two minutes, two minutes, two minutes.
The amount of time was the same.
- The temperature?
- Temperature in the... ?
- Stairway.
- Good. Because if you were going to talk
about your own temperature, actually that
changes. Again, that's a whole other topic
about homeostasis, that when we exercise,
we start sweating, right? So, you're
talking about the temperature in the exact
place. Okay. Anybody else? Go ahead.
- Where we exercise and then the height of
the stairs, like if one stair was higher
than the other, then it would be harder.
- Right. All the steps are the same. Now,
here's a control one kid said in my last
class and the other kids disagreed with
him. He said the exercise was the control,
that we all did the same thing.
- No.
- Do you remember what we did? We walked
the stairs. Did we all walk the stairs the
same way?
- No.
- Well, some of you kids hustled, right?
Like two minutes, you were like bunnies,
like gerbils on the stairway. You were
just going crazy. Others were just walking
and it was okay. Good. Let's move on.
Three, independent and dependent
variables. That would be helpful. Thank
you for your hand up. We only need one
answer of the two and somebody else will
give the other one. So, dependent or
independent, whatever you want.
- Heart rate is the dependent variable
upstairs.
- Okay, one second. One second. So, tell
me a little bit more, though, Daryl. Is it
heart rate and how do we measure the heart
rate? Take a look at your graph. Your
dependent variable is going to be very
well described on your graph. Help me out.
Go ahead. Okay. You're looking at it.
Somebody want to help him out? What is the
dependent variable of this? He's close,
but he's not close enough to be right.
Savannah?
- Number of heart beats per minute?
- Per minute. You had to have the per
minute on that, okay? That's the standard
that we use in science. Independent
variable--Kelsey, would you like to try?
- I'm not sure I know it.
- Okay. That's okay.
What did we introduce in this experiment
to affect our heart rate to see if we
could stay balanced?
- Exercise?
- Bingo. So, your independent
variable?
- Exercise.
- Exercise. Two minutes of exercise is
what we did. Very good. Your back group,
you have another one or it's all up here?
Okay. Four, how does your data compare to
the Olympic athletes? How does your
personal data compare to the class? Now,
remember, we're scientists. So, you just
can't say, "It went up and then it went
down," or whatever. You can say that, but
it's got to be justified with some sort of
specific numbers. Richie had his hand up
first, okay Justine? Okay. Go ahead.
- My heart rate predictions were very low
because I didn't have any idea and then my
actual heart rate was higher than the
Olympic athletes because they're used to
running a lot.
- Okay. Here's a good example of what I'm
talking about. First of all, what you did
with predictions is great. We didn't
actually have to even do that one for this
question, but that's great. Richie, when
you say they were higher, what do you
mean? Your resting rate was higher? Your
post exercise rate was higher? Your
recovery rate was higher?
- All of them.
- Okay. You've got to include them in your
answer. You have to include that in your
answer. You've got to be specific. Go
ahead, Matt. Margaret, you're next, okay?
Yeah. Go ahead.
- My prediction, I had low numbers, but
after doing the experiment, only one of my
numbers was lower than the Olympic
athletes.
- Okay. So, again, what was that one
number?
- Post-exercise.
- Post-exercise was lower. Wow. That's
rare, by the way. Did you see the class
data compared to you, then? We weren't
supposed to do the prediction, but I'm
getting so many hits here. How many of you
to a look at your prediction compared to
other people?
Quite a few people. You guys when you were
doing this, you asked me, "What's the
normal range?" And I didn't tell you. I
wonder what you would say your prediction
is after I gave you a range. I
purposely didn't just to let you see,
just like you said, "Mine was off because
I didn't know any better." Good. All
right. Five--super important question
here--oh, I'm so sorry, does anyone else
want to contribute to the Olympic
athletes? I'm so sorry. Go ahead.
- My actual heart rate was higher than the
Olympic athletes, but for the exercise
one, it was only seven heart beats lower.
- Okay. So, what does that mean to you?
How close to an Olympic athlete are you is
what I'm asking.
- I guess it could be exercise. Like with
the Olympic athletes, I know it wouldn't
be like anything for them. For me to be
like that far off is kind of like
impressive.
- Right. And how would you know that?
Didn't you say you had like a cousin
who...
- Does crew.
- Does crew at the Olympic level or just
does crew?
- She does crew at an Olympic level.
- Wow, a premiere athlete, then.
Fantastic.
- What's crew?
- Crew is when you row a shell or row a
boat. There's singles, doubles and quads.
- Oh yeah.
- Fantastic. Anybody else before we move
on? Christina and then Scott.
- I noticed that we're just like, like I
realized we're all, like, the same because
when the Olympic athletes went up, class
average went up and ours went up, so I
noticed it was the same pattern, just like
depending on what we were doing it was
different than the Olympics and all that
stuff.
- That's the big picture I want everybody
to see here. Take a look at your graphs
one more time. Do you agree with what
Christina just said? Forget about your
prediction number. Did you see that
there's a pattern here?
No matter who you are as an individual in
this class or as a class average or as
Olympic athletes, when we exposed our body
to exercise, what happened in all cases?
- It went up.
- So, we would say it increased. Okay.
What happened when we rested,
post-exercise? Yes?
- It decreased.
- It decreased. Right. So, there is a
general pattern. Excellent job, Christina.
Go ahead, Scott. Make it quick.
- I had the same thing as her.
- Okay. Good. All right. Key question--if
we can answer six, we've got this lesson
down pat. When muscles are active, cells
use nutrients and oxygen at a higher rate
and produce waste, chemicals and heat more
rapidly. What does heart rate, how does
heart rate demonstrate
regulation/homeostasis in the body? I've
got three hands up. I didn't see the
order. I'm sorry. So, I'm going to go four
or five hands up. I got one, maybe two, I
don't know, Gabby, three, go ahead.
Richie, if someone leaves something out,
it's yours.
- When you're exercising, like, you're
using more nutrients and oxygen so the
blood has to carry more nutrients at a
faster rate so your muscles get it. It
does that to maintain homeostasis. So,
it's, like, using it constantly.
- Okay. Daryl? She did a good job. I'm
going to change the question for you. What
if your body didn't do that? What if
you're running up and down the stairs,
Daryl, and your heart rate didn't
increase?
- It would have a hard time maintaining
homeostasis.
- Okay. Excellent. And what would happen?
What do you think?
- You'd be dehydrated and wouldn't sweat
or anything.
- Well, I don't know if you'd be
dehydrated.
- You wouldn't get as much oxygen because
it wouldn't be working as fast and you
wouldn't be like... So, it might get
stuck in there while you're running up and
down...