- Today I'm going to introduce to you our
new project, and it's based on the concept
of surrealism. When you look at this word,
you should recognize a smaller word within
it. Does anyone recognize the smaller
word?
- Real.
- Real, that's right. The word "real."
And we know real is the way things really
look when we see them, or the way they
appear. But the word "sur" transforms that
word. And because this is a French word,
"sur" means "beyond." So now what the
word "surrealism" implies is beyond
reality, or the way things really appear.
So what does that look like? It looks very
dreamlike. It doesn't necessarily make
sense. A lot of different things go on in
surrealism, and I'm going to show you a
few examples right now. These are the
three characteristics that we're going to
focus on. The first characteristic is out
of place objects. If you look at this
example up here, what's out of place in
this picture? Can anyone tell me? Trevor?
- The guy's face.
- What's over his face, just floating
there? Can anyone tell? You're up close,
Matthew. You see what that is?
- An apple.
- It's a green apple, okay? And that is an
out of place object. Definitely surreal.
These are examples of surrealism. This
example right here. What's in here,
Jordan?
- Train.
- There's a train coming out of a
fireplace. Okay, again, an out of place
object. These are two examples of one of
those characteristics of out of place
objects. Another characteristic that you
see are unreal scenes. Scenes that do not
make sense. They're beyond real. What's
going on in this scene? Kurt?
- There's, like, giant butterflies.
- Yeah. The butterflies grew. They're
huge. Now they're like the props on the
windmills. What's going on in this? Can
anyone tell? What makes that surreal?
John?
- Like, huge makeup.
- Yeah, the si-, again, the size of such
little things grew tremendously, and
they're filling up the room. Also, the
interior of the room is now looking like
the sky. So what made these unreal is the
artist changed something that was small
and made it really, really big.
The last characteristic that we see in
surrealism is... there it is. Normal
objects acting abnormally. So in these
examples I'll go through real quickly. Do
you see these clocks? They're not acting
normally. These clocks are melting,
they're dripping, they're stretching,
they're falling down. You can see that. In
this one, the artist drew a person looking
into the mirror, but does he see his
reflection?
- No.
- No. The mirror's not operating normally.
It's surreal. It's beyond real. What it's
doing is it's showing the back of his
head. And again, in this one, it's kind of
hard to tell, but there are three swans,
and the reflection is of three elephants.
So the reflection in the water is not
acting normally. These are three
characteristics of surrealism, all right?
So why surrealism? Why this style of art?
Does anyone have any guesses of why
anyone, or why these artists created
something like this? Yeah?
- Because it's like a modern form of art.
- Okay, yeah. That's actually a very good
definition. Cara?
- Maybe to make it look interesting.
- Okay, good.
- To make it look funny.
- Okay, good. Guys, those are all
excellent, excellent answers. Here is
another thing that went into surrealism.
Like lots of art, it's influenced by
what's going on around it or what happened
before it. So these three boxes represent
three other styles of art that influenced
the ideas of surrealism. And the first
style of art is known as Dada art. This
type of art is where the artist took
things, and they tried to make something
that wasn't considered art. They took
random objects, like a bicycle wheel and
the stool, and put it together and said,
"Okay, this is not art." And that was an
example of the style. They also took a
famous painting like the Mona Lisa,
scribbled mustache and a beard. There it
is. That's not art. And that was really
the whole idea of Dada. It was like
anti-art. Another thing that influenced
surrealism was symbolism. Symbolism was a
style of art in which the artist tried to
depict an idea of something.
And in this example, it's the idea of
death. There's this dark angel depicted
over this man, who's already halfway down
in the ground. All this white snow that
symbolizes life around him. And it was
just the idea of what that might look like
using symbols. And that's what that one
depicts. The other example, or another
influence of surrealism, is metaphysical
painting. This one's very, very hard to
understand, and that's what the idea was
with the style. It was to kind of paint an
unreal or illogical situation. Basically
one in which you do not know what you're
looking at. You don't know what the
objects are. You might know something, but
you don't know why it's there or what part
of it it is. And it's very, very illogical
and doesn't make sense. These three styles
of art in the boxes influenced surrealism.
So when you look at these three styles of
art, you can kind of see what they led to.
They led to this style of art, which is
known as surrealism. So now... where to
start. Here's what's going on today.
Today, you are going to start with...
and you can open your folders up, and
you'll see this slide. What we're going to
do is we're going to start drawing today.
We are going to start by making a
connection, all right? And if you look at
this example up here on the board, or, and
you can look at your slides, too. What
we're going to do... you can just take
your stuff off, Leann, leave it back
there, and then join your table, okay?
What we're going to do is I want you to
come up with something that means
something to you, and that's like your
theme to start with. Maybe it's a hobby,
an activity, a memory, anything that's
meaningful to you, that's your starting
point. Then what we have to do is we have
to give it an element of surprise. So
these are our options that I just
discussed. Those are the characteristics.
Do you want to move it around, change the
location of it? Do you want to make the
sizes different and create an unreal
scene?
Or do you want to make objects in it doing
something that they shouldn't be doing?
Let me give you an example. Lily, what's
your favorite food?
- Strawberries.
- Strawberries. What's your favorite
holiday, Joe?
- Christmas.
- Jacob, what's your favorite animal?
- A dog.
- Okay. So this is my surrealist example
to you. You have a Christmas tree, but
instead of a Christmas tree, you have a
big strawberry standing up with
decorations on it, and then you have dogs
putting those decorations on it. So that's
kind of an example of taking things that
are meaningful to you and putting them
into a surrealist example. These are some
examples that I have that I did. These are
some of my drawings. This first one, and
sometimes you don't even know where these
drawings are coming from. I wanted to take
an object and stretch it. I wanted to make
it act abnormally. So I chose a spoon. And
what I did was I thought, well, a spoon
needs to catch something. So this spoon is
stretching out trying to catch the
raindrops. Why? Because it's really dry
wherever it is. You can see all the
cracks. So that was kind of like my first
idea. The second sketch that I did was I
wanted to do something with a tropical
type of a setting. An unreal scene in an
unreal place. So what I thought was, well,
pineapples are tropical. Why not cut open
a pineapple, and there is my tropical
beach with all the little palm trees,
okay? You're probably wondering what we're
going to do with these. Today is
sketching, but what's going to happen is
this is going to turn into a watercolor
painting. This is an example of what the
painting might look like when it's all
done. I chose the pineapple one, all
right? So we are going to be doing a
watercolor painting, but today we need to
kind of come up with ideas of what that
painting's going to look like. Up here on
the board, I think this is going to help
you a lot. This is a bunch of different
examples of surrealist paintings, and
there's a variety of different things that
the artist has done. They might be food,
they might be animals, they might be
instruments, they might be people, they
might be landscapes. There's lots of
things to look at. I want you to use this
as your primary resource to help you and
guide you through your drawings. I'm going
to give you paper right now. Use this
sheet. Start with making a connection, all
right?
Start with making a connection, and then
look at the different options and ways
that you can make it surreal, all right?
- How do you draw hands?
- Hands? That's... okay, hands. You know
what? This is just a sketch. So this is a
detail that doesn't... or this is a part
that you don't really need to worry about.
So tell me what's going on. What makes
this surreal?
- Um...
- That's what I want to know.
- Because it's the birthday party in the
present.
- Okay. So which of these options do you
think you're focusing the most on?
- This one.
- Okay, and why?
- Because a present usually doesn't open.
- Okay, so the present, so the party is
within the present. So the present gets
opened up, and then there's a party. Okay.
What else can we do to make it, like,
maybe a little bit more, like, bam,
something going on? That's the only thing
I was thinking about, you know? Like,
maybe...
- Like balloons and...
- Yeah, balloons. Like, they're com-,
they're flowing out. That'd be really
cool. All right, that's good.
- What should I, like, do for, like, for,
like, the face?
The face on a...?
- Baseball.
- Baseball. And what are we using for the
parts of the face?
- So this is a baseball bat.
- Okay.
- And I...
- These are the baseball bases.
- Oh, the bases, okay.
- Yeah. And this is
[inaudible],
and this is...
- Okay. So you're combining, you're
combining...
- A lot.
- ...a lot of different things. So why
freckles?
- Because, like, I thought putting more
into it would make it more interesting.
- Okay. You know what I think would make
this really more interesting is the
background. What's going on around the
face?
- Um...
- Think about it. Think about it. What
could we do? Where could this be?
- In the sky?
- I don't know. So what would represent
the sky? What could you draw to represent
the sky?
- Clouds?
- Try that. Maybe draw some clouds. I
think, I think that's going to make your
picture more interesting. Something like
that.
- Because, like, someone hit a home run.
- Yeah, okay. And maybe some action lines
around the ball. You know, like a little--
- Yeah.
- That looks really good. I like that. I
like that one a lot.
- A dog eating pizza.
- Okay, Brittney. Yeah.
- I don't know how to draw horses.
- A horse?
- Yeah.
- Why do you need a horse?
- Because I want to draw, like, a horse
[inaudible].
- What were you going to do?
- Like...
- A horse...
- A horse with a farm inside of it.
- Inside of it. So what do you mean inside
of it, though?
- Like, in here, do, like, a farm, and
cows, and...
- Well, here's a suggestion, because I
like your idea a lot. Why don't we... we
can use this as a resource. Why don't we
draw, I'll help you with this, just the
back of the horse, okay? So we'll just
work, we'll focus on, like, the neck and
the back, and then the tail kind of coming
down like this, okay? So you see where I'm
going with this? Now what I'm thinking is
why don't you draw your farm scene on the
back? Like, almost that it's, like, kind
of been placed on there, like a little
miniature scene. Like, so maybe on here,
you could draw the silo, the barn, and
everything on there. Good? Eyes on me.
- One, two, three.
- Okay, guys, you're doing a really,
really good job with your sketching and
everything, and I don't, I want you to
keep going. But we do need to stop for a
minute. And based on the drawings that I'm
seeing, I see some really good examples of
surrealism, and you're showing me that you
understand it. I bet you that if you saw
an example of surrealism with some other
styles of art, you could pick out the one
that represents surrealism. Take a look up
here on the board. I have three Tabasco
sauce posters, okay? One, two, three, and
four. Show me with your fingers, holding
them up in the air, which one of these is
an example of surrealism. Think about it
for a minute. While you think about it,
I'm going to wiggle my mouse so I can...
okay.
What's an example of, which one is a...
Jess. Okay, everyone had four. That's
good. Why? Why that one? Why'd you pick
that one?
- Because, like...
- Nope, hold on. I was going to let Jessie
answer first. What makes that one surreal?
Think about it. Michael, go ahead.
- The sides are, like, coming off the
bottle.
- Okay.
- And the pepper's, like, putting out the
sauce.
- Okay, good. Anything else? Erin?
- It's, like, out on this, like, island.
- Yeah, definitely, definitely. Like, a
lot of things make this one surreal. What
does surreal mean again? Who remembers?
- Me? It means, like, not, like, like, not
real, but, like, in a different form.
- Right. Beyond real. Beyond real. Okay?
And this is a great example of that.
Beyond reality. Okay? Here's what I need
you to do now, okay? I have one more...
Oh, I might have to re- ...I have one
more slide that I want to show you up on
the board, and if you open up your
folders, you'll see this. You'll see this
slide. And I printed it out for you. What
I'm going to have you do right now, in the
next couple minutes, I'm going to have you
switch your drawing with someone at your
table. You might have to switch three
ways, or four ways, or one way. And I want
you to assess the drawing that you get.
Now, if you get one that has lots of
drawings, just pick one of them, okay?
Here's what I want you to do on the sheet.
This is easy. First thing. What's the
first thing that you notice about the
drawing that you just received? Write it
down. Maybe you noticed a big basketball.
Maybe you notice... whatever it is,
write it down. Then I want you to check
these little circles. Whichever of these
options that you see that that person
used, I want you to check them out. Okay,
Michael? And then I want you to write.
This is the one that everyone stumbles
with. They're like, "What does this mean?"
All I'm saying is, what do you think that
person meant in that drawing? What do you
think the meaning is? If you don't know,
put a question mark. All right? And then
what suggestions do you have for that
person? Maybe they, you know, if you did a
background, it would look really nice. Or
maybe, you know what? Maybe you've got to
lose something. You've got way too much
going on. I can't tell what it is. So this
is not going to take you very long, but
it's important because it shows that,
shows me that you understand what you're
looking at, and it also helps the person
get a better drawing, which is going to be
used for the painting. So I want you to
switch drawings right now. Everyone
switch. And I want you to use the sheet,
and I want you to fill it out based on the
new drawing that you're looking at, okay?
So you're going to do this independently,
and I'll come around and I'll check with
you in a little bit. That's the first
thing that you see. Write down the first
thing that you see, all right? So, Lily,
what's the first thing that you see in
your, in this picture?
- [inaudible].
- Okay. What do you think it is?
- Okay. What do you think this is as a
whole? Don't say anything, because I know
it's yours. But this is good, because this
is going to help you to make it better if
you need to. So what's the first thing
that you know? That you th-, what do you
see? Just maybe you recognize it just as
water. Anything else?
- Maybe a blanket
[inaudible].
- Okay. Write that down. Okay, that's a
good start. What's the first thing that
you saw? Almost everything is crooked.
That's a good ob-, that's a really good
observation. Because everything is
crooked. Good. So what options do you
think were used in this? Now, which one
did you select?
- Normal object acting abnormally.
- That's right. It's clearly these objects
are acting abnormally. That's good. That
was a good, that was another good
observation. So you just keep moving
through.
Did you write down your first reaction?
- Mm-hmm.
- Okay. And... okay. So normal objects
acting abnormally.