- In my opinion I think the grandpa shows the most
leadership because he stands up for
himself, telling the principal, "I should
not pay $15.00 because then it wouldn't be
a scholarship."
- [Teacher] Okay, thank you very much. I
like the way the way you show, you know,
how much he pays for one day and not have
to pay for the scholarship jacket. Thank
you very much.
- I agree with Julia, because you should
not choose people for, like, what kind of
races they are or their culture. You
should choose them for what they've been
through like their hardest work or
something.
- [Teacher] Okay. So you mean they had
jobs, they had work it was right to feel
that. Very good, good job. Okay.
- I think Martha because she earned the
jacket instead of buying it.
- [Teacher] Okay.
- In my opinion the grandpa showed the
greatest leadership because he was wise,
and a great leader is wise.
- [Teacher] Okay.
- I agree with Alejandro that the
grandfather is the leader because he
didn't pay for the jacket.
- [Teacher] He didn't pay for the jacket.
So you thought because he didn't pay for
the jacket then he's a great leader. You
think you know just because he did not pay
for the jacket that's what made him a
great leader.
- No, I think that what makes him a great
leader is that he stood up for himself
instead of just saying, oh, okay, here's
the money.
- [Teacher] Okay, so a greater leader
should stand for what he believes. Is that
what you are saying?
- Yes.
- [Teacher] Very good. Thank you very much
for clarifying that. Go ahead, Daniel.
- I was going to say that I agree with
Jennifer.
I think that a great leader should stand
up for what they believe.
- [Teacher] Thank you very much. Go ahead.
- In my opinion, I think Martha showed the
greatest leadership because she showed
wisdom because she earned that jacket by
getting straight As and being a good
student.
- [Teacher] All right. Thank you. Go
ahead, Lisette.
- In my opinion, Martha's grandpa is a
great leader because a leader needs to be
a strong person like Martha's grandpa.
- [Teacher] Very good. So you need to
stand your ground. Very good.
- I think that the person who showed the
most leadership was Martha. Even though
she thought she was going to lose what she
had earned, she believed that even though
the teachers, they, they, some wanted to
give it to someone else, but some knew
that she had earned it and she, she spoke
up, not keeping it quiet and keeping it to
herself.
- [Teacher] Okay. So you feel a great
leader, you know, she speak up, you know,
when something is wrong or in the way.
- She shouldn't just keep it.
- [Teacher] Very good.
- She has to tell someone.
- [Teacher] Very good, good job. Go ahead.
- It seems to me that Martha showed great
leadership because she did all the things
that she did so she could win the jacket.
- [Teacher] Okay, what are some of the
other things, you know, that Martha did.
- She got, she got, since she was in first
grade she got good grades and she tried
not to get in trouble, and be a good
student.
- [Teacher] Okay, so that means, you know,
she has worked hard all this time. Very
good. Thank you.
Okay, go ahead.
- I believe that Martha showed very good
leadership because she wanted the
scholarship jacket so bad that she didn't
give up on trying to get it.
- [Teacher] So a good leader, you know,
she'll try to do whatever it takes, you
know, to get what he or she wants. Is that
what you're saying?
- Yes.
- [Teacher] All right. Good job. Thank
you.
- In my opinion I think Mr. Schmidt is a
great leader because he was fair, you
know, to fight for Martha and not the
other girl.
- [Teacher] Thank you. Who is the other
girl?
- [together] Joanne.
- [Teacher] Huh?
- [Teacher] Okay, so Mr. Schmidt was fair
enough, you know, to fight for Martha
instead of who?
- [together] Joanne.
- [Teacher] Joanne. Thank you very much.
- In my opinion it's Martha because she
fight for the jacket and she tried her
best.
- [Teacher] All right.
- In my opinion I think Mr. Smith because
even though Martha was poor he still said
that she deserved the sweater because of
her good grades.
- [Teacher] Because of her good grades.
Good job.
- In my opinion I believe that the one
that showed leadership was Mr. Smith
because he was honest and fair to Martha.
- [Teacher] Very, very good. Thank you
very much.
- I agree with her because Mr. Booney just
wanted the person that had money, which is
Joanne. Her father owned the only store in
town. So, Mr. Schmidt was actually being
fair.
- [Teacher] Okay. Thank you for adding on
to that. Now who is Joanne's dad? You
know, because everybody was saying I could
hear Juan, you know, when Juan said
because of Joanne's dad. Who is Joanne's
dad? How can we describe him?
- He owns the only store in town.
- [Teacher] Hmm?
- He owns the only store in town. What
else?
- He's also part of the school board.
- He's rich.
- School board.
- [Teacher] Huh?
- He's part of the school board so they
had the decisions like, in the school,
like, what they do and stuff.
-[inaudible]
-In the story he gives money to the
school so maybe that's also why they
wanted to pick Joanne so they got more
money.
-[inaudible]
- [Teacher] Very good. Thank you very
much. Now that everybody has contributed,
now let's look at the next question. The
next question is this: what does Martha
represent to you? Think about the
leadership qualities that Martha showed.
What does Martha represent to you? Not
only the leadership qualities, all the
other things that Martha represents, okay?
Anybody can start. Anybody can start. Just
jump in.
- I believe that Martha to me represents a
great leader. Her experience and triumph
illustrate importance in leadership such as
never giving up.
- [Teacher] Thank you for sharing that.
- She represents someone who will find the
truth and will solve it. She stood up for
herself and she listened to what her
grandfather had to say.
- [Teacher] Very good.
- It seems to me that she was a smart and
outgoing girl because she worked hard and
speaked up and no matter how you look or
where you live you have to be treated
fairly.
- [Teacher] Great. Like that. Anybody can
jump in.
- It seems to me that Martha is not a
leader because her grandpa speaked up for
her about the scholarship jacket.
- I disagree because Martha did speak up
for herself. Her grandfather just told her
what to say.
- I disagree because like,
her grandfather gave her most of her
ideas. If it wasn't for her grandfather
she probably would've tried to get the
money. But like her father said, I mean
her grandfather said that a scholarship is
not a scholarship unless you pay for it.
- I agree with Daniel because like, well
yeah, I agree with Arkie because the
grandfather actually had to tell the
principal that they shouldn't have to pay
for it instead of Martha going to speak to
the principal in person.
- I disagree with that.
- I disagree.
- I disagree with Daniel and Javier
because even though her grandpa told her
what to say, her grandpa didn't go up to
the principal and actually tell it was actually Martha
who went up to the principal and got ideas
of what to say.
- I agree with Myra because it's true. I
mean he didn't go, Martha actually had the
guts to say what her grandfather had said.
So that's why I say that Martha had most
of the guts to do that instead of the
grandfather. The grandfather might've said
that, but she was the one that stood there
and said it. That took a lot of courage to
me.
- [Teacher] Okay. So you know that was a great
leader should be courageous enough. So I
like what Arkie said, Arkie said, you
know, I disagree that Martha was a leader
and Arkie open up that. Thank you very
much, Archimedes. Thank you all of you for
sharing that. Any other person?
- To me Martha represents a hard worker
because since first grade she worked hard
to get her good grades and not get in
trouble.
- [Teacher] Okay. She worked really hard.
Thank you.
Any other person that wanted to add
something?
- It seems to me that Martha is a
[inaudible] that proves that it
doesn't matter her race or color, she
could do anything the same as anybody else
can do.
- [Teacher] Wow.
- I agree with Ashley because a lot of
people discriminate, like Mexican people
or like Mexican Americans, just because
their family or their ancestors came from
somewhere else and they're not from the
United States.
- [Teacher] So you know what has Martha
done to straighten that or to disprove
that?
- She showed that who cares where you're
from or who you are, you can always do
your best.
- [Teacher] Okay. So you know there was,
Martha is representing to us that we can
do whatever we put our mind in doing. If
we really work hard we know that it will
work. Is that what I'm hearing from all of
you?
- [together] Yes.
- [Teacher] That it doesn't matter what
race, you know, if you work really hard
you know that you can achieve. Thank you
very much for sharing that.
- I really admire her because I know some
people who have been made fun of just
because of their race and it's somewhat
sad because some people aren't allowed to
do things just because of their skin color
or where they're from. What I think is
that it doesn't matter what you are. No
one is bad except for the person who's
making fun of your race. You are not the
bad one, it's the person who's making fun
of you.
- [Teacher] Thank you very much. Any other
person that wants to add something to
this?
- I agree
- [Inaudible]
- because in a poem it says you
can't persuade anyone unless you have the
courage to make them, like, persuade them.
- [Teacher] Thank you very much. Now let's
go on to the last question. Thank you very
much for sharing. I could hear from all of
you. The last question is what other
stories have you read that share a similar
theme with Scholarship Jacket. Think of
other characters that have faced difficult
choices or situations. Okay? So think of
that. What other stories have you read,
okay? Anyone can start.
- I think Crossing the Wire is somewhat
similar because Pablo was Mexican, too,
and they mistreated him and denied him a
job. However, he worked as hard as Martha.
- [Teacher] Thank you for sharing that.
You call that Crossing what?
- Crossing the Wire.
- [Teacher] Crossing the Wire. Thank you.
- I think the story of Martin Luther King
is pretty similar to The Scholarship
Jacket because they discriminated a lot
against African-Americans because of their
color, but Martin Luther King stood up for
his race and said that we should not
discriminate others because we're
different. We're all the same just because
of color doesn't separate us.
- [Teacher] Thank you very much for
sharing that.
- I agree with Jennifer, Martin Luther
King said that it doesn't matter where
you're from or who you are, everybody
inside is the same and all of us are
brothers.
- [Teacher] Thank you very much for
sharing that.
- I have seem the movie The Blind Side
which is pretty similar to the story.
Michael shows great leadership because he
is an African-American and he is poor and
he tries to pull himself up to be able to
play at a Catholic school to play
football.
- [Teacher] Thank you.
- I agree with Carlos. I've also seen that
movie and the movie has a lot of great
leaders definitely Michael.
- I agree with Carlos because in that
movie, Michael, from the beginning he
didn't want to go to school, he actually
had really low grades and the family he
had, they're from another race, and even
though he had really low scores, they got
him a tutor and they helped him, like,
reach his goals so he could play football
for the school he wanted to play.
- [Teacher] Wow. Thanks again.
- I have read The Outsiders, which is a
story about two classes of people, the
Greasers and the Soches. The greasers get
treated real dirty because of their lower
class.
- [Teacher] Okay. At the end what
happened? Did they succeed like Martha?
Did they achieve?
- Some of them died.
- [Teacher] Some of them died, okay.