- Like compared to osteoblasts... the
osteoclasts to be more efficient, and work harder
than the osteoclasts, therefore you're
[inaudible] more than you are building, so
that ratio can cause brittle bones.
- [Instructor] So what--Okay, [inaudible]
right?
- Yeah.
- One's up, one goes down.
- Yeah, if you're taking away more than
you're putting back--
- No, I'm sorry, why don't
osteo...
- 'Cause there's a lack of estrogen and,
or testosterone that is triggering the
osteoblasts to work.
- We kind of hit on that a little, I don't
know.
- I kinda did, but I kinda didn't.
- What causes osteoblasts to work?
- That it? Okay, so when they're saying
that the osteoclasts are working more,
what they're not saying more than they
used to work, they're saying more compared
to the osteoblasts, okay? It's not like
the osteoclasts have been activated and
are elevating their activity. They're just
doing what they do. It's just because the
blast activity dropped, which you guys got
that, the blast activity dropped. Why did
that blast activity drop?
- Because there weren't enough hormones to
trigger the action of osteoblasting
Good.
- Is everybody get that? 'Cause see now,
the blast activity's what's really
dropping. And the clast activity keeps
going, like it normally goes, but relative
to one another, you have more clast
activity, less blast activity and
therefore you're losing bone. Everybody
got that idea? Okay, good, you did a good
job reasoning that out. Okay, you can keep
going, Matt.
- Okay, our next question kind of gets off
of like, the description of osteoblasts
and it says, "How can osteoblasts-- or,
how can osteoporosis be prevented?"
Brooke?
- Well, they recommend having, like, a
good number, a good amount of calcium
intake, a day, about 1,000, 1,500 milligrams,
you could do that, something simple like that
could prevent like, osteoporosis in the long run.
- All right.
- I would also suggest regular exercise in
order to, kind of build up the bones
with weight bearing exercise, so that
there's less, there's more bone actually
broken down.
- Basically, a healthy lifestyle and
refraining from smoking and alcohol
lots of other stuff and then bisphosphonate for
extremely high risk.
- Along with everything else, there's a, I went
to the Food and Drug Administration, you
can have Zoledronic acid, which can be
injected every two years for, like,
prevention along with the diet and
exercise.
- Anybody else have anything they'd
like to add?
- I was going to say hormone replacement
therapy then some other... [inaudible]
- Nobody else? Okay. Now who's on to how is
osteoporosis diagnosed?
- Yeah, I found the most current one is a
form called Dual Energy X-ray Reabsorption
Test to test the bone density, you get a
score of either one or below, means you're
normal, one to 2.5 is osteoporosis, 2.5
and above it's just, your bones are gonna
break any time.
- All right. Anybody else?
- There's just a bunch of ways that they
measure the bone density, so there's like
a centimeter scanner and then a quantitative,
that's what they use, 'cause it's like really
hard to detect osteoporosis sometimes and not
[inaudible] so you kinda need more ways to test...
- Good.
- You can also take a sample of your
[inaudible] and analyze it to see if
there's any signs of erosion or anything
that'll lead to osteoporosis.
- Okay, what's that called? Anybody know
what that's called? What is it?
- Bioscan.
- Good.
- Before you even go to the doctor, like, it's
really hard to diag--, like, there's not really
symptoms of it. But some of the symptoms are like
bone pain and tenderness and stuff like that,
and breaking bones with little or no
trauma.
- What do we call that when a bone breaks
with little or no trauma? What kind of
fracture?
- Traumatic.
- Traumatic would be if it was, kind of
trauma. Pathological, good job, yeah!
Pathological fracture, that would be a
pathological fracture, if there's a
disease under there, like osteoporosis,
which has made it weak enough to break.
Good call! So, somebody mentioned the
scanner, Zach, right? You talked about
that? The abbreviated, what did, what was
the full name of that scan again?
- Dual Energy X-ray Absorption.
- Okay, has anyone ever heard of a DEX
scan? DEXA scanner, that's where the D-E-X
comes from, Dual Energy X-ray, DEXA scan,
and that's very common, yeah?
- Is that like what the guy from Pursuit
of Happiness, [inaudible]... ?
- Yeah.
- I don't know if you ever saw that movie.
- I didn't.
- Yeah, the bone density scanner.
- I didn't know if that was it.
- Yeah, okay, so, how did they, what the
general, how they actually, what bones do
they look at in the scanner?
- I think it was the wrist, the hip and the spine
those are the most common places for osteoporosis.
- The lumbar part of your spine,
because that's the first to go
- Why?
- What else is important to consider if
you, if you think about the type of bone
being affected, what type of bone being
affected? What type of bone? I should remember.
- Trabeculae.
- Yeah, so that's a spongy bone, right? So
trabeculae of the spongy bone, why would
the lumbar vertebrae be particularly
vulnerable now?
- It's a spongy bone.
- Yeah, it's an irregular shaped bone, but
the body of the vertebrae, is basically a
cortex in, and it's a spongy bone in
there, it's all trabeculae. What was the
other bones that you said, Madhura?
- Wrist and hip.
- Okay, so hip as in, what do you mean by
that do you think, Robert?
- Ilium.
- Ilium!
- It's all a spongy bone.
- A spongy bone in the ilium, good place
to look for it. But, here's the thing, what
about the wrist? How come, think from a
practical scenario, how come the wrist?
Yeah, Lexi.
- I think it's 'cause you use it like, so
often, that they [inaudible] is probably
the most common [inaudible] because you
use your wrist for like basically...
- Do you use it a lot? Another possible
reason?
- Yeah, Kevin?
- Because it's a lot of like small bones so, they
may be easier to break, or like, be more fragile.
- Okay, that's a possibility. Mikey?
- I would say 'cause it's easy to get to,
like, it's pretty hard to take like--, and
actually have your hip where they do like
biopsies going in to your hip. It's kinda
hard to get like a good angle, but like
your wrist can, there's not a lot of like
skin or muscle covering it, so they can
like put it under a scanner and get a
pretty good picture.
- Okay, thank you for that. That's exactly
why they use the wrist. I mean the wrist
bones, when you think about 'em, you know,
they're not weight bearing, so they're
probably not the best to evaluate for
osteoporosis, it would be better to
evaluate weight bearing bones, but they do
have spongy bone in them, they're little
irregular shaped bones, which have a
cortex with some spongy bone. So there is
some material in there to evaluate, but
you don't have to disrobe, you don't have
to do anything, you just put your arm in
the machine and they can do what's called
a screening, a screening test. Has anyone
had a screening test for anything ever
before? Or thought of, ever heard of
screening tests being done for other
things? No? Not familiar with the
screening tests?
- I think I've had one.
- Have you?
- Yeah, because, if I had, like, it wasn't
for bones though--
- It could be for anything.
- Like they were looking for appendicitis,
but they couldn't find it so they were
doing other-- all these other kinds of
tests, I don't know if that...
- Well, a screening test, it could be, it
could be a screening test. Screening tests
are basically more generalized testing,
not the most specific, but meant just to
give you a clue if something needs further
evaluation, okay? So if you put your arm
in the scanner, and it was towards the low
end, it's not the best for making an end
all, you know, quantitative diagnosis. But
it's a good for determining if we should
go ahead and do a scan of the lumbar spine
or ilium, you see? So that's why the arm.
So it's interesting that you brought that
up, that was really good, 'cause it really
helps us look at the whole, "Where is this
occurring?" and "Why do they use those
specific bones?" Okay, Matt, anything else
there?
- Our next question, we have already said
how it's diagnosed, we know what it is.
So, how can we treat osteoporosis?
- Well I said, I found online that there
were really no treatments, like true
treatments for osteoporosis. It's more of
trying to prevent it, by getting enough
calcium and all the other stuff we said
before, because you can't really treat it
once it's gone.
- Well, that's funny, I found something a
little different, there's a few medicines
right now, like talking about, you've seen
all those commercials and weird stuff that
actually do prevent it. Now, they're
actually saying, like helping you actually
reabsorb the calcium that you've lost from
the bones. But it's, also something kind
of funny I saw, if the bones start to
become more dense, they also found that
like around your jaw, starts to
deteriorate faster, some reason
actually get like sore throat. So I was
wondering if anyone, try to reason that
out. Because I could not figure out why,
just your jaw starts losing calcium, but
your long bones, start gaining it.
- Are you saying that they're taking
medication and then they're experiencing
pain? So that--
- Yeah, like the calcium [background chatter] to
deteriorate. But like your long bones it's
like your limbs and everything start to
become more dense.
- Is your jaw a lot of [inaudible], is it
one of those bones... ?
- Yeah, some, but there isn't a whole lot
in there, there is some.
[Background Chatter]
- Is it a more compact bone?
- Probably a more compact bone in your
jaw, there isn't a lot of cavity space, or
spongy bone space there. Maybe that has
something to do with that?
- Even having a sore throat, I don't know
why that would affect it at all. Maybe
because it's a horrible medicine.
- I don't know, like the thyroid gland, like this
one, or the parathyroid, this is like calcium
[inaudible] like bone absorption, so
maybe, I don't know, it's not working as
efficiently, so it's not getting the
through to the jawbone.
- Or maybe it's working too much or
something. Maybe since your jaw is losing
calcium, and it's kinda gaining, like
losing its calcium, so it's probably
starting the beginning phases of
osteoporosis. Your hyoid bone, isn't your
hyoid bone isn't it... ?
- Sort of high.
- It doesn't really touch any other bones,
but it's... kinda in there.
- So it's kinda in your throat, so that
could be like, I don't know, it's kinda
unusual.
- Just answer this one with the general
area, 'cause there's a lot of instances
where you couldn't sit or lay down, for
like three hours after you took it because
it would deteriorate your esophagus. So I
don't know, there were a lot of really bad
side effects just...
- Well, what I was wondering, I kinda see
like some doctors like, just wanted you to
be aware in order to treat it would
be prevention, would be the other side to
treatment, just go do like those lifestyle
changes. Instead of like thinking "Oh,
I'll wait until these signs come up, and
have platelet scans and I'll take
medicine." Just to be proactive about it
and have those lifestyle changes like
not being a smoker and don't drink
excessively, and like, have those good
workout regimens so you prevent it
rather than treat it.
- Yeah, seems like a disease that's either
prevented or managed, not so much treated,
but I thought, I think someone mentioned
this before but the bisphosphonates...
'cause other people who get osteoporosis
are people who take corticosteroids,
for like, asthma, like in your
inhaler. So it's something that inhibits
bone breakdown, so it doesn't sound like
it treats it, but it kind of manages it so
you don't break bones...
- Yeah, did anyone request a name, a name
brand Fosamax? Did we see that? Yeah?
Did they tell you how it worked?
- No, actually--
- No, well, Fosamax is like, did you see
something there, Zach?
- Yeah, wasn't that the bisphosphonates
bind to the hydrocapsin crystals in bone
and inhibit osteo, osteo-something bone
reabsorption?
- So they're inhibiting which cells?
- [together] Osteoclasts.
- Okay, yeah, so that's how Fosamax and
those work. They inhibit the osteoclasts,
so they're not building bone, though You see the
difference?
- Yeah.
- They're not really building the bone,
they're stopping the erosion, it's a
little different.
- But if you have like dead bone, or old
bone that needs to be replaced, wouldn't
that just inhibit it just as much because
there's still old calcium sitting in your
leg that... ? I don't know, whenever
there's waste in your body that doesn't
get dealt with, I mean, like when you have
an appendectomy and there's waste in your
appendix, that like, it can kill you if
there's like waste in your body. So, maybe
that would just prolong the process of
osteoporosis, not so much as help it in
the long run. I'm thinking, 'cause,
any time you're keeping like, something
that's old in your body that's not good.
Like, you eat something, you have to like,
you have to digest it, and I don't know.
- Yeah, it's a good thought process. Good
thought process. So that's what Fosamax
works that way. So if we were gonna try
and design something and our job is to
design a drug that helps, let's say
someone who has osteoporosis, let's assume
they have it now. What types of
mechanisms, in other words, what types of
things will we try and get a drug to do?
What would we want it to do?
- You want it to like stimulate the
osteoblasts like a little bit better. And
someone already mentioned this, but they
had like estrogen supplements, like
supposedly like help out with that. Maybe
stimulating more osteoblast ability.
- Okay, well go with that a little bit
about the estrogen replacement. Did anyone
request that as a therapy? Yeah, Kevin?
- And there's like these, like it's, like
hormone therapy and we have like estrogen
patches, where you can take it as a pill.
So it adds estrogen to your body so, it
balances out your loss of estrogen, and
raises it.
- Yeah, there's like, he was talking about
the hormone replacement, but I also read
on Google Health that it's rarely used and
it's not used twice with women. I don't
know if that has anything to do with it,
I can Google it. I guess like if you use the
treatment once [inaudible].
- Any ideas why? Anybody find out why
estrogen replacement, they used to, you
know what? They used to give estrogen like
they give vitamins, it used to be "prevent
osteoporosis by taking extra estrogen."
Seriously, and it wasn't all that long
ago, how come it isn't get--
- Because then your body stops producing,
its like, natural estrogen, so...
- Good idea, maybe. Any other poss--, Nick
any idea you can think of?
- I don't know, you're not producing enough?
- So because you're not, we should get
more, well, how come, have anybody heard
of anything that's related to estrogen
therapy, bad things?
[Background Chatter]
-Facial hair growth
- Well, testosterone can increase facial
hair growth, someone else over here?
-Cancer.
- Cancer, and that's the problem, they saw
incidences of, particularly breast cancer,
went up substantially, and so that's why,
Artie, they're saying that, you know,
hormone replacement, it's still being
used--
- It's rarely used.
- Yeah, but not like it used to be, not
like it used to be.
- So if we could stimulate the osteoclasts to work
properly, or blasts, to work properly then shouldn't
you like, have like some sort of treatment to, like,
make the osteoclasts work as efficiently as the
osteoblasts? We would have like, sort of a difference
in their relationship.
- Good idea.
- But isn't that the job of the osteocytes
to basically maintain the bone? So
shouldn't we find a way to, like,
make sure that the osteocytes are
maintaining the bone? Because if the
osteoblasts are going to do their job once
they're stimulated. But they have to be
stimulated, so show me if you're looking
for a way to stimulate them more than...
make a more efficient solution at the
osteocytes.
- No, that would be more like a genetic
thing, 'cause your osteocytes, your DNA
is like breaking down as you get older. So
it's like not, it's like, I don't know, is
it mutating? When it gets older? I don't
know a lot about genetics, but I know your
DNA kinda breaks down as you get older,
and so that makes your cells not as
efficient. So it might be more of a DNA
kinda thing. Where you have to engineer
that DNA-wise to make your osteocytes work
just as well when you're, like, 78 as when
you're 12. So it might be in like that
area, but I don't know a lot about that,
so...
- Yeah, it's interesting where you can go
with it. All right? You can take this,
because even Artie even you were saying
something about hormones before with maybe
why that treatment gave a sore throat.
What were you saying about that?
- I don't know, maybe it had to do with
the parathyroid gland. I don't know, maybe
it like produced too much, I don't know,
the jaw bone, and it reached the jawbone
first and I thought that it had too much
and like released all of it and went to,
the rest of the body...
- So which hormone of the calcium related
hormones would we wanna increase if we
thought along those lines?
- Maybe that's why your jaw's--, if you
release a lot of that hormone then it's
building your jaw up and when you're
building bone you get growing pains. Maybe
it was like a growing pain thing in your
jaw? Maybe.