(class chatter)
- [Voiceover] Yes,
I think if it's really, really quiet,
and you want to talk about something,
then, go ahead.
But if a lot of people
obviously want to talk,
probably a good idea to raise our hands.
Okay, what else?
- [Voiceover] Be involved?
- Be involved, yes.
I will be keeping track of
who contributes to the discussion.
Because everybody has an opinion,
but I need you to express that opinion.
What else?
- [Voiceover] Don't criticize
other peoples' ideas.
- Don't criticize other peoples' ideas.
Okay?
What might you do instead?
(classroom chatter)
Suggest something,
give your outlook, give your opinion.
Okay.
Give your argument.
But don't insult the other person's ideas.
This is a safe place
to share ideas, okay?
Now we're going to have three jobs.
I'm going to need a task master,
a reader, and a time-keeper.
- [Voiceover] Time-keeper!
- You want to be the time-keeper?
Alright, you need to
let us know when we've got
about two minutes left of the class.
- [Girl in Necklace] I
want to be the task master.
- [Teacher] Okay, so what
does the task master do?
- [Girl Wearing Necklace] They make sure
that everybody's on task.
- [Teacher] Yeah, what else?
What might that look like?
- [Girl in Gray Hoodie] Subjects get off,
or out of control.
- [Teacher] So, people get
off subject, we could,
a little bit of crowd control.
What about if everybody wants to talk
and they start raising their hands?
- [Girl in Gray Hoodie]
You get to pick on one.
- [Teacher] Yeah, task master gets to call
and make sure every body
gets their chance to talk.
Okay?
Yes?
- [Voiceover] Is there a praiser?
- [Teacher] Actually, that's a good idea.
Let's have a praiser.
- [Boy in Blue Shirt] I want to be him.
- [Teacher] You want to be the praiser?
Alright, Michael is the praiser.
What's the praiser do?
- [Voiceover] Oh, can I do that?
(class chatter)
- [Girl in Blue Jacket] Dang it, always.
- [Voiceover] You can team up with me.
- [Girl in Blue Jacket] Can we?
- [Teacher] This class,
yeah, you guys want to be a team?
Okay.
So, what is a praiser?
What are you guys going to do?
- [Voiceover] Give compliments.
- [Teacher] Okay, give compliments.
Compliment their ideas,
their expressions, okay?
And then I need a reader.
Preferably somebody on
that side of the room.
- [Voiceover] I don't know how to read.
I'm unavailable.
- [Teacher] You'll read?
- [Voiceover] No.
- [Teacher] Who would like to read?
(classroom chatter)
- [Teacher] About five seconds
before I call on someone.
- [Voiceover] I'll do it.
- [Teacher] Okay so,
the questions are all up here,
there's five of them.
You're going to read them so the whole group
can hear.
- [Voiceover] Okay.
- [Teacher] Okay?
Alright, so,
task master...
- [Voiceover] Oh, I'm here.
- [Teacher] Okay,
you're on task now,
and we're going to start by having the reader
read us the first question.
- [Girl in White Hoodie] Okay,
should people own ideas?
(laughs)
- [Boy in Varsity Jacket]
I don't really think so,
I think it should be shared,
like for public opinion.
Like, public knowledge,
like how they were
putting the genome stuff
out on the internet.
- [Voiceover] Great thought.
- [Boy in Varsity Jacket] Thanks.
- [Girl in Blue Jacket] You're doing good.
- [Boy in Black Beanie] Well, I think that
the information should be shared,
but the people who found
it or came up with the idea
should get credit for it.
- [Girl in White Jacket] I think that
if you come up with an idea,
shouldn't you have some like,
you have conferences,
everybody gets together
and talks about stuff.
So, why don't you have
scientists and stuff, that
like created this idea,
come together and have a
conference and talk about it,
so then ideas are spread out
through all those companies and stuff.
And then the people that made,
that contributed to it,
have like a patent, I guess you would say,
or just like,
copy, or not copyright it.
- [Voiceover] Like discovered by, or?
- [Girl in White Jacket] Yeah, like that.
- [Voiceover] Good opinion.
- [Voiceover] So, coming
together would be easier then.
- [Girl in White Hoodie]
Sometimes I feel like,
if...
If no one gets credited,
or gets, yeah. (laughs)
They won't want to
like...
They won't want to--
- [Voiceover] Put the
information out there.
- [Girl in White Hoodie] Yeah,
put the information out there.
Like they won't have something to,
you know...
- [Voiceover] Work for?
- [Girl in White Hoodie] Work for!
There you go. (laughs)
- [Girl in White Jacket] Yeah,
because I think that everybody
like wants a part of
getting like (mumbles).
Because you want that credit,
because you put all that effort into it.
So, why not
get a little bit of credit?
That makes it worth it.
How do you like that one?
- [Voiceover] Okay, second question.
Should people own genes?
- [Voiceover] No.
- [Voiceover] Yes.
(class chatter)
- [Boy in Varsity Jacket]
Well, you kind of already
own your own genes.
I mean you kind of, they're your own.
Like any, unless you clone yourself,
I mean, nobody else has
the exact same stuff.
(mumbles)
You could.
- [Teacher] Let me give
you an example of an idea
of somebody owning a gene.
The breast cancer gene that
was discussed in the video,
which is actually a lack thereof,
of a particular part of a gene,
that is patented by a particular company.
Which means they found it,
they spent money to find it,
so they own the patent on it.
If you are a person,
you don't have to be female
just to look for this,
but if you are a person
who would like to go look for that gene,
you have to pay a patent
fee to that company
because they found it.
That's what it means to own a gene.
- [Girl in White Jacket]
I think owning a gene
is just having a company
that has a lot of money,
that can be like, "Oh I'm
going to put a patent on that,
"so boo-ya, can't take it."
- [Girl in Black Jacket] Yeah
I don't think that's right.
I mean, if someone,
they should like put
it open to the public,
because I mean if it's a
gene like, say breast cancer,
they should't just keep that private
and make they pay for it.
- [Voiceover] Yeah.
- [Woman in Glasses] So,
it's sort of like owning
a part of a human.
If you own a gene by a corporation,
it's like owning a part of the person
who has that gene, or
doesn't have that gene.
So...
It's sort of a moral issue.
Would you want to be owned by a company,
just that little tiny part of your DNA?
I wouldn't.
- [Voiceover] Excellent point.
- [Voiceover] You would?
- [Voiceover] Good job, Jenna.
- [Voiceover] I wouldn't.
- [Voiceover] Oh, okay.
- [Voiceover] You
practically just went against
everything we just said. (laughs)
- [Voiceover] Anybody else have any input?
(classroom chatter)
- [Voiceover] I agree with Jen.
- [Girl in White Hoodie]
Okay, third question.
Would you want to know if you
carried a gene for cancer?
- [Several Students in Unison] Yeah.
- [Several Students in Unison] No.
- [Voiceover] I would not.
- [Voiceover] Well, it
depends on what age I'm at.
- [Boy in Varsity Jacket] Because like,
then you have that whole impending like,
doom your whole entire life,
like, "Oh, I'm eventually going to get cancer,
"might as well just die."
- [Boy in Black] That's why I die,
(mumbles)
- [Woman in Glasses] But if you do know,
then you have the chance
to actually deal with it.
- [Voiceover] You're going to
have to deal with it, anyway.
- [Woman in Glasses]
Yeah, but if you knew,
you would have all that time
to realize and to put things
in order in your life.
You would know,
you would live life to the fullest,
I would.
I would live life to the fullest if I knew
that I actually had this cancer.
I would know
and I would do the best I could to
live my life without settling.
- [Girl in Blue Jacket]
Yeah, so the shadow of you,
that eventually (mumbles).
- [Woman in Glasses] And that
would just push me forward,
considering--
- [Voiceover] Drive yourself.
- [Woman in Glasses] Whatever I do.
Yeah.
And maybe, just maybe if I knew,
I would work to try to cure it myself.
So, then I would be helping
other people as well.
I would want to know.
- [Teacher] Remember that
there are no right or wrong
answers to these questions.
Please feel free to share.
- [Girl in White Jacket] I think my,
what's it called, my opinion,
I'd want to know so that,
if you didn't know,
and you have kids you could
be passing it on to them,
and wouldn't that hurt you to see that,
to have your kids have cancer?
Like, I would think that.
And then, if like I did,
I would want to know,
I would, like Jen said,
live life to my fullest,
and...
Because some things, like,
if I was, per se white,
I would go tanning,
wouldn't that hurt your cancer?
Because like, radiat--
Well that's what causes it,
you know what I mean?
I'd just do things
differently if I had it.
- [Teacher] Remember what
they said in the video,
it's often a maybe.
It's not a "you will have this,"
it's a maybe.
There are things that they can check for
that they can say definitely,
you will or will not get,
like Huntington's Disease,
which is a very devastating disease.
Remember how they talked about Tay-Sachs,
which kills very early?
Huntington's is somewhat similar,
but it kills later in life.
And starts to show signs mid-30's,
and usually death is
somewhere in the 40's or 50's,
so that's significantly earlier,
since life expectancy is in
the 70's in this country.
So...
Would you want to know,
yes or no, if you had
something like Huntington's,
which is definitely a yes or no,
but what about in a
situation that's a maybe?
- [Boy in Beanie] I don't
want to know if it's a maybe,
because then you live with that fear
that you might get it or you might not.
- [Woman in Glasses] I
would still want to know.
- [Voiceover] Yeah,
because what if your body
starts shutting down like,
one night, and you just start
twitching in your sleep?
(laughs)
Wouldn't you want to know
that's from cancer,
rather than your brain's messed up,
and drugs or something, I don't know.
- [Girl in Black Jacket]
Yeah, I think I'd want to know.
I mean like,
instead of just
not knowing what's causing all this stuff
happening in your body.
Some think it's because I'm
a very curious person. (laughs)
I'd want to know what's going on.
- [Girl Wearing Necklace]
I would want to know.
Because like Jenna said,
like one night you're just
having a seizure or something,
you could take, like, medicine,
like that they prescribe to you
because they know what you have,
rather than just like,
trying to deal with it, and
like, that you could die,
because you never even
knew what was happening.
So I'd like,
want to have that back-up plan with me.
- [Teacher] So, just to clarify,
we're talking about an offense end,
rather than a defense team.
So, rather than waiting until
you have it and reacting,
taking preventative measures
ahead of time.
- [Woman in Glasses] Like
an inhaler for asthma.
Some people have to take their inhaler
every single day, twice a day,
morning and the afternoon,
but there's other people
who don't have it as severe,
or a higher risk,
not as high as a risk,
who only take it
when they're having an asthma attack.
So, what you're saying is,
having like the pill
every day, constantly.
I would still want to take that chance.
- [Voiceover] So, you
would you want to take the pill?
- [Woman in Glasses] Yeah.
- [Girl in Black and
Gray Hoodie] If you know
you have cancer early enough,
can't you get rid of it?
Can't they get rid of it?
If it's like...
(classroom chatter)
- [Teacher] Yes, the earlier you know,
the better chance you have.
- [Girl in Black and Gray Hoodie] Yeah,
that's why I would want to know.
- [Girl in Gray Coat]
I don't think it would
matter that much because
even if you do have cancer,
that doesn't mean you're
going to die from it.
Like, you could get hit by a car today,
and nobody could tell you that,
nobody could predict that.
So, I don't think...
I wouldn't want to know,
like if I was going to,
if I have cancer or anything.
I don't know, I don't think it's--
- [Girl in White Jacket] You don't know
that that cancer's going to (mumbles).
- [Girl in Gray Coat] Yeah,
and then I'm just going to be
in fear all my life, like,
thinking, like "Oh, I'm
going to die from that."
When that's not necessarily...
Like, the, you know,
exact thing that you're going to die from.
Like, it's not a guarantee, so.
- [Voiceover] Very good.
- [Voiceover] Yeah, it's because of that--
- [Voiceover] Great job!
- [Boy in Varsity Jacket]
It's because of that maybe,
that maybe, like you might be,
like how that guy on the video said,
you have a 99% of
getting a heart disorder,
you might be that one
percent that doesn't get it.
And you spend your whole life preparing,
spending all this money
on preventative measures,
and getting all these
pills, setting up stuff,
and then you go through
your whole entire life,
and you don't even get it.
- [Voiceover] That's true.
- [Voiceover] That, he does have a point.
- [Voiceover] But then wouldn't you want
to take those precautions, because--
- [Voiceover] You'd be happy that you did,
but then you spent all that extra stuff.
- [Voiceover] But what if that extra stuff
is what made you not get it?
- [Voiceover] No I mean, you don't like,
you don't, get all the stuff just in case,
and you don't take,
it's like, you don't
even take the medicine.
It's only for like, when you have like,
Travis said, if you have a
seizure, you can take that,
it stops it.
- [Girl in Black Jacket]
Well, that's kind of
just like getting hit by a car.
- [Voiceover] Exactly.
- [Girl in Black Jacket]
Preventative measures
is like, looking to see if there's cars,
and if you don't look I mean,
you could get run over, you could not.
(classroom chatter)
- [Boy in Black Beanie]
But then you also, like,
what if you lived in fear of getting that,
taking all these precautions,
is kind of wasting your life,
trying to prepare for something that
may or may not happen.
- [Woman in Glasses]
That's why people should,
at the right age when you
have the right maturity,
decide whether you want to know or not,
and not have it mapped
out when you're born,
whether you're going to die or not.
Or by what.
- [Girl in White Jacket] In
the movie, how they just like,
took that thing.
- [Woman in Glasses] Right.
- [Girl in White Jacket] That
would be freaky as a woman.
Like, you just went all
throughout nine months of that,
and now you get to find out
that your child's going to die in
33.3 years, like,
it's kind of freaky.
- [Voiceover] That actually
brings us to our next question.
- [Girl in White Hoodie] Okay.
What genes would you want to know
your children had?
Why, and how would that change
you as a parent?
- [Voiceover] I wouldn't
want to know, at all.
I mean, that's part of giving like,
human birth, the surprise, I guess.
- [Voiceover] It's a gamble.
- [Voiceover] You can't always like,
create the perfect human being.
- [Boy in Varsity Jacket]
Well, if you could find out,
what genes they were going to have,
could you fix them?
Like how that person
got rid of the forehead thing?
- [Teacher] Right now, no.
But that is
a direction we're heading in.
You can, right now,
completely sequence your child's genome,
if you have the money,
and get an approximation
of what they will look like
and what effects that--
- [Voiceover] That's messed up.
- [Voiceover] I don't care
what my child would look
like, I don't really care.
But, I just don't,
like you could prevent it from having,
these like, life-threatening diseases,
like cancer or Huntington's,
or like Parkinson's Disease, Alzheimer's.
- [Girl in White Jacket] But then again,
that's a way of like too, like...
I would want to know
life-threatening diseases,
but not,
because like you can cure, like seizures.
You can like, can't you?
Like, my friend's been cured of that.
She had them and then now she doesn't anymore
because she took medicine and stuff,
now she doesn't have it.
But there's people that
have been taking those medicines,
and then still have it now,
which doesn't make sense.
- [Teacher] Is that cured, or treated?
- [Girl in White Jacket] Treated.
- [Teacher] Yeah.
Cured means that you no
longer have the disease.
Treated means that it's
managed with medication, or--
- [Girl in White Jacket]
It's treated, then.
Wait, it's cured.
Yeah, it is cured. (laughs)
But, anyways (mumbles).
- [Teacher] How would that
change you as a parent,
knowing that?
- [Voiceover] You would know
what to do if you have it.
- [Boy in Red Jacket] Stay
with your child at all times.
(laughs)
I don't want my kid dying.
- [Voiceover] Your kid's
going to be in like a stroller,
until age 13.
- [Voiceover] See, it wouldn't
change me as a parent.
It just wouldn't change me.
- [Girl in White Jacket] I think
it'd make someone stronger.
Because going through
all of that hard times,
like with your child and
it being sick and stuff,
wouldn't that make you
stronger than having
a normal, healthy child?
And make you closer to them?
- [Voiceover] But you
would still love your child
the same way.
You would still try to
have the best memories with your child,
either way.
If you knew that this,
that your child was going to die, or not.
You would still do the same thing.
Except maybe change their diet, or...
- [Voiceover] Take more precautions.
- [Woman in Glasses]
Yeah, more precautions. Pad their room.
They're going to be falling over
and hurting themselves or something.
But, you wouldn't change your experiences
with your child.
- [Voiceover] I would.
- Well, I wouldn't.
Would you Bernard?
- [Voiceover] What?
- [Woman in Glasses] Change
your experience with your child?
- Yeah.
- [Voiceover] Just don't go to Disneyland,
it's not worth it.
- [Boy in Blue Shirt] It's not worth it,
he won't even remember it.
- [Boy in Red Jacket] Nope.
- [Girl in White Hoodie]
Oh, the fifth question.
What does any of this have to do with you?
- [Voiceover] Like as
in personally, or as in?
- [Voiceover] That's a good question.
- [Girl in Black Hoodie] I'm confused.
- [Voiceover] Say that again.
- [Girl in Black Hoodie] As in personally?
- [Voiceover] Yeah, both ways,
as in persoanlly and as
in a generation.
(classroom chatter)
- [Voiceover] Give yourself super powers?
- [Girl in Necklace] Hey, stay on task.
(laughs)
- [Voiceover] Good job, Stella.
- [Girl in Necklace] Thanks. (laughs)
- [Girl in White Hoodie] I
guess you're just kind of
getting us ready for the future, you know?
Like, thinking, like about your children,
like, in the future,
like what if,
like what if you really wanted to know,
and then like,
what would you actually do about it,
if you've never thought about this before.
- [Voiceover] Is this technology possible?
- [Several Students At Once] Yeah.
- [Teacher] Not quite yet.
So, who's going to have to
make those decisions?
- [Several Students At Once] Us.
- [Voiceover] Our generation.
- [Woman in Glasses] This generation
and next generation.
(classroom chatter)
- [Woman in Glasses] The genes are us.
And if you want to know
everything about yourself,
if you want to know,
then you have to go through the genes.
But if you don't want to know,
then you don't have to.
- [Girl in White Jacket] Yeah.
And so those people
that think it's like...
That want to know, should...
Wait, what?
Never mind.
- [Voiceover] Should be able to.
- [Girl in White Jacket]
Yeah, should be able to.
And then, the people
that don't want to know,
shouldn't harp on them,
they should just keep their
opinions to themselves.
And see it from their eyes too,
and just have an open eye to it,
not
being so negative.
- [Teacher] So what happens if,
say half of society,
would like to have
their genomes sequenced,
or their children's genome sequenced,
and the other half does not want to,
or doesn't have the means to,
because it's probably going to cost money.
Right?
What might that,
how might that impact
society as a whole?
Not just the individual.
As in this country,
individual's rights are paramount, right?
Hmm?
- [Voiceover] So, it'll be messed up
like it is already.
(laughs)
- How?