- Dan do you have any background
knowledge about density?
- Like if someone
says, "It's dense out,"
- Yeah.
- Then it would be kinda wet.
- So if something's really,
like if there was a dense fog
- yeah, it'd be...
- So if there was a dense fog,
what does that mean to you?
- That there's a lot.
- There's a lot of it, okay.
So you're in San Francisco,
and they're like,
"Hey, there's a really dense fog."
You might expect that
there's a lot of fog.
Alright, what would be the
opposite of a dense fog?
- A not dense fog.
- No fog or like a really thin fog.
Okay, Jackson, do you have
any background information?
- Well I thought that,
isn't it like how close
the molecules are together?
- How close the what?
- The molecules are together.
- How closely they are... okay.
- Yeah. Like say you're trying to go
through a screen door.
And like, they aren't
really very close together,
because they'res holes.
- Okay.
- And say, you're trying
to go through a brick wall.
- Okay.
- And they're really close together,
so it will be harder to go through.
- Would you say then, which one
would be densest, the brick
wall or the screen door?
- The brick wall.
- The brick wall,
and you would say that because?
- Because the molecules
are closer together.
- The molecules are closer together.
Okay, anybody else have
any ideas about density?
Yes ma'am.
- Isn't it like how compact
something is?
- Okay, so give me an example.
- Like um don't
know how to say this ...
kinda going back to the container thing.
If we could have luggage, and
you fill it up so much,
the luggage case is like so filled up,
it's so dense.
- Okay, so let me
take that to the next level.
So, let's pretend
we're going on vacation.
- Okay, we're going on vacation.
Raise your hand if you have
a place you want to go.
Or maybe you're going there next week.
I'd be so jealous if you said Hawaii.
- Oh yeah.
- I could be.
- Reese where are you going?
Or where would you want to go?
- Uuh, Mexico.
- You're going to Mexico?
- Well not this break,
in the in the summer.
- In the summer.
Alright, so let's build this scenario.
He's got one of those
big, huge rolling bags
that you're gonna put
all of your swimsuits in.
84 swimsuits right.
To go to Mexico, because you
don't need other clothes.
Flip-flops, swimsuits, and
a t-shirt, and that's it.
- Okay, so you got
your huge luggage...
we're gonna pile,
all this stuff in there.
I'm gonna zip it up.
What does that have to do with density?
If it's absolutely packed full,
what does that mean
for the luggage?
Yeah.
- That the particles are
so close together that
it's leaving them in...
- Is the volume of the
luggage changing
if it keeps its shape?
- Or is, the mass of
the luggage changing,
because you're adding
more stuff to it.
- The mass
- So you change the mass,
because the luggage
is staying the same.
Okay, your mom says, "You
can only bring one swimsuit,
"one flip-flop, a pair of
flip-flops, and one t-shirt."
So I take everything out, now
did I change the volume by it,
or did I change
the mass of the luggage?
- The mass.
- I just changed the
amount of matter, right?
So then, the luggage
with tons of stuff in it,
we said was...
what dense or not dense?
- Dense
- And dense, and so the luggage
with a little bit of stuff in it was?
- Less dense.
- What changed the
density of the luggage?
What are the other conclusions to
what changed the density
of the luggage?
Peter, what changed the
density of the luggage?
- Less amount.
- Less amount, and in science,
which word do we use?
- Umm
- Volume or mass on that one?
- Umm... mass.
- Less mass, less stuff,
less matter in the luggage.
Awesome, we're gonna
do this little scenario
with a demonstration, so
you guys need your clickers.
it's gonna be an A or a B
type answer on this one.
So get your clicker ready,
and I'm gonna show you
a couple of clips.
- Cheese! Ooooh!
- Cheese.
- Can we eat it?
when some people in here don't like it?
- I know well, more for me, right.
- What?
- Alright so, this is cheese.
This morning, I went to Safeway
and I purchased this cheese
that is extremely
difficult to open.
And I bought certain
kinds of cheese
- Can I have some?
- [Teacher] Alright. So...
- Do we get to eat the cheese?
- You do not.
- Aww dang it!
- Sorry.
- Why can't we eat it?
- So here's your question
- [Sighs]
This is cheese A, okay.
Anybody know what kind
of cheese that it is?
- Grayson, what's cheese A?
- Umm... Swiss?
- Swiss, what's
your observation that
led you to the inference
that this is Swiss cheese?
- That is has the little
holes in it.
- The little holes in it.
Okay, this is regular old...
- Cheddar
- Raise your hand... Yeah, Dan
know what it is?
- Cheddar or...
- This is a Cheddar cheese.
- Okay, So this is cheese
A, and this is cheese B.
I want to know which
cheese is denser.
Okay, so with your clicker,
I'm gonna put this
up on the screen,
I want to know,
cheese A the Swiss cheese,
or cheese B,
- Are they supposed to be numbers?
- Well, it's gonna be an A or a B.
Right so cheese A or cheese B.
Alright, and if you need to
see the cheese again, walk around.
In the meantime, I'll
put this question up.
I want to know is cheese A the densest?
Or is cheese B the densest?
Okay, so this is
multiple-choice, A or B.
There we go, go ahead and click it.
And let's see what you guys think about
which cheese is the densest.
- So the Cheddar is B?
- So A is the Swiss, B is the Cheddar.
- That doesn't make a lot of sense.
- A is the Swiss...
- Are we each going
to be able to get a piece?
- Please don't talk
while we're doing this.
- My clicker isn't working
- It's not working?
Which number are you?
- 83.
- Is it on?
- Yeah
[student laughs]
- Are you pressing the
right button, "Send?"
- Oh there it goes.
- Okay. good
- It probably didn't power.
- Alright, make sure
you clicked in please.
And then, let's look at what we think.
Okay 92% of you, said that
the cheddar was the densest.
So, we had another 8%,
so two people said
that this was the densest.
So here's what I want you to do,
I want you to pull a partner, who's just
the person next to you.
So you guys are gonna be partners,
you guys are partners,
and you're gonna be a group of three.
Partner, partner, partner
Mattie and Grayson,
and you guys will partner.
Sydney and Jackson,
and it's kinda gonna
go crossways here.
So you guys will be a partner.
You guys are a partner,
and you guys are a partner.
Right, you're going to
turn to your partner,
tell your partner which cheese
you thought was the densest,
and then I want you to
come up with a conclusion,
that you could say, "Cheese
A was the densest because..."
or "Cheese B was the densest because..."
So take 30 seconds to talk.
[Background Chatter]
- Less mass,
- Cheddar
- So what is the definition of density,
from here to the cheese?
Which one is denser, the one
with more stuff or less stuff?
- More
- So which of these has more stuff
- Ooh
- Nice of you guys, and
you're not very nice.
[alarm goes off]
Okay that was 30 seconds.
Okay, choose which person
in your group is gonna be
Swiss cheese, and which
person gonna be Cheddar.
- Swiss!
[Background Chatter]
- Cheddar
- Swiss Cheeses, raise your hand please.
- Woo!
- Swiss cheese?
And I need a conclusion
from you, so make a
statement for me. "We thought
"cheese A was the densest
because..." so Erica,
- We thought cheese B was the densest
because it didn't have any holes.
- Because it didn't have any holes,
okay.
Does anybody have a different explanation
why they thought cheese
B was the densest? Matt.
- Well, because cheese
A had holes, the holes
don't take in the part of the, technical
isn't part of the cheese.
- Okay
- So...
- So the inside of the holes,
what are the holes
actually made up of?
- Air.
- So there's air in there, but
it's not part of the cheese.
So then, what's true about
the Swiss cheese then Reily?
- It has the less cheese.
- Less cheese, compared to its what?
- Compared to has all of it.
- So it's all cheese
and this is part cheese.
What can we say now
about their volumes?
- Umm, they're pretty
much the same.
- Okay, so the volume
is the same.
Jackson, what can we say
about the mass of the Swiss
compared to the mass of this guy?
- The Swiss has less
mass than the Cheddar cheese.
- So the Swiss has
less mass then the Cheddar.
But they have the same
volume, can we figure out then
which one's the densest?
Which one's the densest?
[girls singing]
- What's both, alright.
You had a chance to talk
about it, let's vote again.
Do you think cheese A is the densest
or cheese B is the densest?
After our little discussion.
Cheese A or cheese B.
A is the Swiss, B is the Cheddar.
- So we want to know
who's more dense
- More dense yep,
Which one is more dense.
More dense.
Is A more dense or is B more dense?
Let's see if we get an
agreement on our inference here
about which one's denser.
Look at that, we were able
to change two people's minds
just through discussion.
That's pretty awesome.
- I thought it would
be eight people.
- Well we went all the way
to 100% here.
So that's good. That means
that everybody agreed,
at least in terms of the cheese.
So, as a demonstration...
- What!
- Well I need a snack,
this is really hard work
being a teacher.
- It's hard to be a student.
- That's true.
Okay, ready for demo number two?
- Yeah
- So cheese number one, number two,
first we need to talk about, what
sinking, floating,
and suspending means.
- I know it
- So in order to talk about
this, I have these fun objects.
I don't know, has anybody
stayed up late enough
to see David Letterman?
- Yes!
- Oh gosh, I lost an animal.
[students laugh]
has anybody on David Letterman ever seen
the game show he plays
called, "Will it float?"
- Yeah, I've seen it happen.
- Have you Wyatt?
What does he do?
Do you know what he does?
- Well I saw it a while ago,
so I don't relaly remember.
- So you're not really sure?
Anybody wanna guess what
he does on the show?
- He throws stuff in water.
- He takes some stuff,
then he puts it in water to
sees if it floats or not.
- That's pretty much the gist
of the game show.
So I have, for your viewing pleasure,
recreated a game show.
So I have objects, we're
gonna play a game called,
"Will it float?"
And the first object, you're going to
predict this through the clicker.
Is I wanna know, if our
little dolphin friend,
is it going to float... okay
sink...
or the third option which is tricky,
you might not know this word, suspend.
And suspends means hang out
kinda in the middle of the water.
So you have three options, alright.
We're gonna vote on
this with the clickers.
Do you have a question
before we do that?
- When you put it to the test,
can I move forward?
- Absolutely, so if you can't see,
you can either stand up or you
can squeeze up into an aisle,
yeah absolutely.
Yes sir.
- Which one is it, A, B , or C?
- Oh I'm gonna tell you
right now, okay.
So we're gonna see
if the dolphin floats,
sinks, or suspends.
And if you can't see when I do it,
we'll count and you
can stand up and watch.
So A is gonna be sink, so do
you think it's gonna sink.
B, answer B will be float.
C will be suspend,
Okay, so sink, float, suspend which means
hang out in the middle of the water.
Okay, so this is an A through C option.
Okay, A sink, B float, or C suspend.
- Well that was fast.
- Yeah, that was really fast.
So let's see... everyone...oooo
84% say that this particular
object is going to sink.
If it sinks, what will you observe?
If it sinks, what will you observe.
- How fast.
- It falling into the water
- Well, he's going to fall into the water
one way or another but
where will he end up?
- On the bottom.
- At the bottom of that okay?
Some of you, one person
said that it's gonna float.
Okay, so raise your hand if
you're the person who thinks
it's gonna float.
Okay, thank you for taking
a risk, that's okay.
You don't know yet right,
it's for fun.
So if its floating,
what will that mean,
what will you observe?
- That's she right.
- When I put this in the water,
what will it look like
when it's floating?
- Like... I don't know
- Will it will be sitting
on the bottom?
- No.
- Where will it be located.
- Floating on the.
- Floating, right on the top, okay.
And then we had, oooooh three
whole people said it would
suspend right in the middle.
Raise your hand if you
think it's gonna suspend.
- Oh yeah!
- Okay.  Leia, why do you think
it's gonna go right in the middle.
- I think it's too light
for it to totally sink,
and I think it's took
heavy for it to float,
so thought it would be
right in the middle.
- Okay, so you're making the
hypothesis it has something
to do with its weight.
Okay, alright so that's one idea.
Too light to stay at the top.
But too heavy would go to the bottom.
Is that what you said?
Okay, yes.
- So does suspend mean
it stays in the middle.
- Yeah, suspend means it
literally hangs out right here.
- Yeah.
- Okay, that's not true.
- Okay, are you guys ready?
- Yes.
- So stand up if you need
to be able to see.
Here's the game show,
there's a little song
that goes with it like,
♫ Will it float, will it float ♫
Okay, there's my game show, you ready?
Alright it's very suspenseful.
Can you see?
- Okay, here it goes.
[kids singing]
- Yes!
- Aww yeah!
[students clapping]
- So, it sank.
So go back and have a seat please.
Now raise your hand if
you have any explanation
for me why that sank.
It did sink, oh no!
We've all been down to
the bottom of the pool.
Why do you think it sank?
- I thought it wasn't flat enough,
or didn't have enough
space enough to float up.
- So now we've got two different ideas
about sinking and foating.
So Leia brought up the
idea of heaviness,
you brought up the
idea of surface area.
See if I were to put something that has
a bigger surface area, is it gonna float?
- No
- Yes
- Maybe, did you tell me
that if it had bigger surface
on top of the water.
Okay, should we try this?
- Yeah!
- It's gonna sink
- Oooh
- Okay, so maybe
- Aaaaw
- It got swamped.
Now it floated for a little while right?
So maybe the shape does have
something to do with it,
and maybe weight has
something to do with it.
Or what it's made out of might
have something to do with it.
So we have all kinds of ideas now
about sinking and floating.
Yes sir,
- Is it because
it's denser than water?
- So here's another idea,
it has something to do
with the density of the object.
- It's denser than water.
- So here's a tough question,
so think about this one.
What is the difference between
how dense something is,
and how heavy something is?
If Leia talked about heaviness,
now we've got density,
and now we've got shape,
and what it's made of and all
these different things so.
I just want to know this one thing.
What's the difference between
the weight of an object
and the density of an object.
This is a really hard
question, take a second.
I want you to rotate
back to your partner,
talk to them about what
you think the difference
between density and weight is.
[Background Chatter]
- Okay, when we talked
about number of particles,
it's later than mass.
- Mass.
- Mass, so the relationship between
mass compared to the object.
Okay.
Okay who spoke last time,
'cause I need a cheddar.
[Background Chatter]
- Oh yeah
- A cheddar who's willing to talk.
Emily, what did you guys come up with?
- So, density is like
how much mass or
how many particles are in the object.
And weight is how much
gravity is pulling down.
- Okay.  So would that
mean that something...