- Okay, so ready to go here?
Okay.
I'd like to take you back
to the fifth century.
To a time when Attila the Hun
was uniting the barbarian tribes
and he was leading his great dark horde
to conquer the lands of
Gaul, or Western Europe,
much to the chagrin of the Roman Empire.
"But where," I hear you ask
"Is Attila the Hun himself?"
Well, I fear he has perished.
He died in a drunken brawl,
would you believe on his wedding night?
And who am I, I hear you ask,
to be telling such a tale?
Why, I am Mrs. Attila the Hun
and it has been left to
me to guide the dark horde
as we continue to conquer
the lands of Gaul.
Javelins, and bows and arrows,
those were very well
and good for tacticians
such as Attila the Hun, but
what do I know about tactics?
- [Josh] Not much.
- So I need something--
- [Teacher] Very little, you are right!
Josh the Hun is right!
So, what I need is to get
some sort of a war machine.
Now, let's first think
about what characteristics
do I need in a weapon that
would help us against--
to help us conquer the lands of Gaul.
What characteristics do
we need in the weapon?
What do we need it to do?
- [Male Student] Hurt people.
- In other words we need to have
some sort of damage at
the end of property or
- [Male Student] Force.
- something else.
So, a force, we need to
have some sort of force.
- Range.
- What else, I'm sorry, Jackie?
- Range, the range would be a good thing,
especially if we can get
beyond bow range, right?
That would help out to get
some of the castle walls destroyed
before we even get far, right?
- Steph.
- [Steph] Efficiency?
Efficiency, can you tell me
more about what you're thinking?
- [Steph] Well, being
able to complete said task
without much power used in maneuvering?
- All right, we need to be
able to move the machine around
to be able to get the job done.
We need to be able to not, perhaps,
use every single Hun for it.
So efficiency in being able to load it
and being able to use it.
Anything else that we need
in a weapon to help us
in our destroying and pillaging
of towns and villages?
Yes, Katie.
- [Katie] Possibly something
that you could use again?
- [Teacher] Oh yes, if we only use it once
that's kind of a problem, isn't it?
We want to be able to use it repeatedly.
Good idea.
Other things we want to think about?
Joe.
- [Joe] Something that's mobile.
- [Teacher] All right, so
maybe wheels might help,
or being able to be something that
could be lifted or carried.
Okay, those are good thoughts.
Jackie.
- [Jackie] Accessibility, like
making sure it's easy to use
and not like difficult to set up?
- [Teacher] So if it
takes a bunch of people
and they're struggling to reset it,
maybe not a good idea.
Something that perhaps a few
people might be able to handle.
All right so we've had a
good deal of ideas so far.
That's really good.
So, I need some sort of a war machine.
Something that would have all
of those properties in it.
Hmmm, why, what is this?
- [Male Student] Message
for you Mrs. The Hun.
- [Teacher] A message, okay, let's see.
Why, it is news of a new siege
engine called a trebuchet.
- [Students] Ooh.
- We have a picture of our new war weapon,
but here's the challenge:
I need to build the best trebuchet,
the best war machine that I can
and I'm not certain what
properties, what characteristics,
what parts of this machine,
I should emphasize.
How big they should be,
how strong they should be.
So I'm going to need you to help me out.
I'm going to make little
groups of Huns in order
to create a model of our trebuchet.
Each group can then test
a different quality.
What sorts of things could we change
to test our trebuchet, to see
what would be the best one?
Caroline.
- [Caroline} The weight on the opposite end?
- [Teacher] All right, the weight,
the counter weight and the load.
Both of those things, and
perhaps the ratio of them,
could be rather important.
Josh.
- [Josh] Like the ratio of the arm
on either side of the axle.
- [Teacher] All right, the
lever arm and how it changes,
that could be an important idea.
Other things that we
might be able to change,
to vary or test?
Anything else we might be thinking of?
Kate.
- On the angle, right there.
- Ah yes, the angle and
the angle of launch has a lot to do with.
There's a little pin that
holds the sling in position
until the lever arm releases it.
So the angle of launch and
changing that could be important.
Anything else we might try?
Anything else we could change?
We've had some really good ideas.
All right, so I'd like to break
you into your small groups
and I'd like you to decide on what exactly
your group is going to test.
We'll come back together in several days
in order to share the
ideas and information.
So I need you to prove
your loyalty me, Huns.
Build this trebuchet and test it
and if Attila the Hun were here right now,
he'd say, "What are you
doing laying your duffs?"
"Get to work, Huns!"
Let's get into our small groups
and see what you can decide
on for your trebuchet.
(students talking and chairs scooting)
And you can choose whatever
it is that interests you.
You can choose something that we did
or something different.
But what you want to remember
is that you have to decide
what to do before any work.
You have to decide "I'm going
to change this part of it"
"and keep everything the
same" until we take data.
(classroom noise drowns out conversation)
Remind me, first of all, what
it was you were changing.
- [Blond Student] Counterweight.
- [Teacher] Counterweight,
so you're leaving
the same object that you're launching?
- [Blond Student] We're
just changing counterweight.
- So, what, is that your weight?
- Yes.
- [Teacher] Okay, so what
challenges did you have, if any,
in building this to
test your counterweight?
- We had problems with
the sling and the pouch.
Like, at first we made it really long,
so like, that didn't really work.
It didn't go anywhere, it
kind of just fell apart
and then the pouch itself, it's
kind of like too long.
So like it--
- So a little engineering before
you could quite get one to work,
but you did then eventually get one
by changing the--
shortening the string
and shortening the sling?
- Yeah.
- All right.
So, at that point then, it
looks like you had some data
and you took several trials.
Was there anything, just off the end,
any pattern you happened to notice,
just as you were taking the data?
- We noticed that if the
counterweight was too heavy,
it would just kind of smack down
and then if it was too
light it would just of like,
it would float and then just kind of fall.
So there is an ideal
weight to counterweight
that would make it ...
- Yeah, like, our data, we
went from light to heavy
and then it went from like not
so far to like, really far,
to like back again.
- What if I wanted to know,
not 600 grams or 650, but 625?
How could you analyze
your data to allow me
to interpolate between your data points
or to go beyond, if I wanted to know
what's going to happen at 775?
- [Female Student] Make
a graph or an equation.
- Yeah.
- [Teacher] Actually,
either of those would work,
coming up with an equation
or coming up with a graph.
To me the graph is a very
visual way of doing it.
You could determine then
whether or not it is a parabola
or whether it's some
other sort of a curve.
All right and that will
allow us to look at
other data points which I
think would be very helpful.
So, your job then,
between now and Wednesday,
is to come up with how
you want to analyze this
so that you can explain
what the results were,
from your trebuchet, without
sharing all of the numbers,
but just by giving the ideas
of what it is you found.
I think this is actually
very fascinating that
you found your limit and
then it comes back down.
I think that's very interesting,
the fact that it's consistent.
So, help everyone else
figure out what would
be the ideal conditions
according to your data.
- [Female Student] Okay.
- All right.
- [Female Student] We can do that.
- [Female Student] Hello!
- [Teacher] Ready to share trebuchet.
- Here's our data.
- Okay, so first remind me what it was
that you were changing or testing.
- [Female Student] We were
looking for the angle.
- [Teacher] The angle, okay,
and when you were trying
to build your trebuchet,
what challenges, if any, did you have
in trying to test this angle?
- Well, when we were doing it,
we tried to make the arm in a way
that it would be really easily changeable.
So it couldn't be like super secure.
It had to be--
we ended up doing it with rubber bands
and like popsicle sticks, so
it was really easy to move.
- [Teacher] Okay.
- [Female Student] It wasn't
a super intense trebuchet,
but it works.
- Yeah, we built the whole
thing out of popcicle sticks.
- Now, I'm not certain they had
popcicle sticks back in the fifth century, but I think . . .
- No, like twigs.
- [Female Student] Twigs!
- We'll do it with twigs,
that's a good idea.
Alright, so, then it looks like you took
some data at different angles,
and you figured out then
the range that it went.
Was there any pattern or
anything that you noticed
while you were taking the data?
It's okay to say no.
- Yeah, we noticed you'd want
to start it like farther back,
like there'd be really no reason for you
to start it at a positive degree angle.
- Right.
- Because then it's--
- Because if it was positive
it wouldn't really go anywhere.
- Starting with angles that made sense,
that you knew would give you
enough energy to start it.
All right, and then what did you discover
about the angles that you did try?
- That the farther back you went,
the greater length that it would go.
- So the very farthest
that you took it back
did get the longest range.
- Yes, that was the negative 45
and that was the largest one.
- Now, what limited you,
or was there a limit?
You stopped at negative 45,
could you have gone negative 50 or--
- No, that was when we hit the ground
because ours was so small.
It wasn't like high up
to go all the way back.
- Ah, okay, all right,
You were commenting on being high up.
When we get together on Wednesday
and we talk about conclusions,
we'll also ask about what
could we try in the future
and that sounds like another something
that you could potentially do.
Where if you took the same model,
- but just lift it up?
- Lifted it up, adapted it,
see if that would matter.
All right that sounds good.
So we've got several angles to comment on.
If I wanted to make a guess as to what
would happen at 35
degrees, or negative 35,
or at negative 50, is there
some way I could interpolate
between data points or extrapolate beyond?
Is there some way that you
could analyze your data
that might allow me to
choose a different angle than
the ones you actually chose?
- Yeah, you could probably
think of an average,
you wouldn't assume that it
would be like 100% accurate,
we wouldn't guarantee that,
but it would give a good idea.
- [Teacher] All right so if
you did some averaging work,
if you did some, been thinking of--
- Actually, not so much averaging.
- You could even set it up like ...
- Like side by side, like triangles.
- Okay, okay.
So, figuring out, maybe the ratios.
- Yeah, that's --
- That you should get here, using your,
when you say your size and dimensions.
All right, and that is an
analysis that is so legitimate.
These are equations you can come up with.
You do have the option
of doing it visually,
that is with a graph.
Where you have your angles one direction,
and your range the other.
Just see what would happen now
with just the three data
points you have so far.
You may find that there isn't enough data
to be for certain of what would happen
but you're certainly
welcome to attempt that
in case there is a direct
linear relationship
or something that's easily recognizable.
So you get to choose however
you want to analyze your data.
When we come together on Wednesday,
I will ask you to come up with
a conclusion if there is one.
Some groups will find that
there's no conclusion that the
(classroom noise covers voice)
So that everyone else could know
what the results were without looking
at actual data numbers.
So that's your job for Wednesday,
and any other potential questions
or things that you might
consider for the future
if you were to do another test.
Also a bonus that we can measure data.
- Okay.
- All right, thank you, good job.
The farthest range.
- It was 650 grams for the counterweight.
- Six five zero?
- [Female Student] Yeah.
- [Teacher] Alrighty, so that's good.
So we did discover that
there was a maximum
and then we have lesser
returns after that.
All right, very good.
Fifth group, tell us about
your data and your trebuchet.
- Okay, our variable was
the angle of launch as well.
- [Teacher] Angle, okay, that's good.
- And we analyzed it visually, basically,
and we found that the larger the angle
or the higher it was,
the larger the range was.
- [Teacher] The larger the angle
equals the larger the range
and did you have any limits to that?
- Not really, it just kind of continues.
- [Teacher] As long as you
continue to increase the angle,
you increase the range.
- So you mean like the angle
of release of the sling?
Or the like, how far back the
arm goes before you let it go?
- [Teacher] How did
you measure your angle?
- Oh we measured the distance from
the counterweight to our platform
and like the farther that we raised it up,
the larger the distance was.
- [Teacher] Okay, so the
larger the angle to platform.
- Like what other angle,
could we have used?
- [Female Student] The back arm.
- [Teacher] Okay and this one
was how far we pulled it back?
- [Female Student] Yeah.
- So isn't that the same angle then?
- [Female Student] Yeah, but
we just measured it inside.
- [Teacher] All right.
All right so slightly
different perspectives
we've all found angles on.
All right, our sixth group.
- We varied the counterweight also.
- [Teacher] Okay, counterweight
and how did you choose
to analyze your data?
- We made a chart and a graph.
- [Teacher] Okay, so you had
a chart and then the graph
and when you graphed, what did you graph?
- We graphed the weight of
the counterweight versus the range.
- [Teacher] That's reasonable.
The counterweight versus ...
range.
All right and as you examined
your chart and the graph data,
what did you come up with as a conclusion?
- The more weight we put on,
the further the range was.
- [Teacher] Was there
an upper limit or not?
- Not from the amount of
weight that we tested.
I mean I would suppose that
if you put more weight
than the trebuchet could handle,
then it would probably
would have bad results.
- [Teacher] So that actually gives us
a place to go in future.
If we were to try to add more to the slab,
that might be something kind
of interesting to find out,
is what is the upper limit
and at what point does the equipment fail?
That might make a difference
with our big trebuchet.
We want the biggest one
that was successful.
Were there any other
questions that came to mind
or any other things that occurred to you
while you were either
taking data or analyzing it
or building your trebuchet?
Josh.
- The angle at which the sling
was released mattered a lot.
- [Teacher] All right and, in fact,
if we were to combine that
with your counterweight,
we have a couple of
variables we might examine
at the same time for the same trebuchet.
Other questions or things
that you thought about
that maybe you would've liked
to have added to or varied? Steph?
- When the sling did release,
we could never really tell where it did,
and we couldn't really
tell if it released it
after the object was launched
or if it released at the
point in time that it's supposed to.
So you could never really tell--