- On a regular basis.
Have you ever thought
about what that causes?
I mean, what causes wind
to blow in the first place?
Whether it be a breeze.
Whether it be a hurricane.
Whether it be a tornado.
Would you take a few
minutes in your notebook,
would you just draw a line
write after what you wrote?
(mumbles)
And I want you to give
your best explanation
of what the heck causes wind?
Just do this on your own first.
What could cause wind to blow?
Take a few moments, just on your own.
(background noise)
Just like always guys,
you don't have to be right here.
I just want to know anything that you think
might contribute to wind blowing.
On a big scale, on a small scale.
Anything that you've got
that we can build on,
anything that you put down.
Alright, when you have this
discussion in a few moments,
share your ideas with each other.
And then remember one person
will be called from the group
to share either what you put down,
or what somebody else did.
Talk to each other.
See what everyone there is thinking.
What ideas do we have?
(class chatter)
- The air pressure and
temperature changes and so
it kind of like shocks,
and it creates wind.
- That's good.
I think wind develops because clouds
carries that air (mumbles).
- I don't really know much.
(class chatter)
- Alright, folks.
When we go, let's use,
let's see who gets to share.
Person two.
We're going to go with person two.
And let me switch this
over here real quick
so I can write down some of your ideas.
Hold on.
Alright, where'd my pen go?
Okay, here we go. Person two.
And we're going to start over here.
Did you guys have any
ideas why wind to blow?
No, table seven. Sorry.
- I don't know, but I
said heat and cold air
rising and falling.
'Cause I know how hang gliding gives us
columns of air rising, heat rising,
how you get in the air.
I'm really not sure so I'm just thinking.
- [Teacher] Okay, so
something about hot air rising
and cool air
falling.
- [Student] And like how they're (mumbles).
- [Teacher] Say that again.
- [Student] And cold and hot
air going over mountains.
(mumbles)
- [Teacher] Different land masses.
Okay, very interesting.
Now she had the toughest job.
From now on every other
person number two that goes
you have to either come up with
a different theory, a different idea,
or you can agree or disagree
with what Miah had to say.
But you cannot say, "I don't know."
Okay?
So you gotta kinda run
with what's been said.
Keisha, we're going to
go back to you first.
What was your thought at your group?
- [Keisha] Well, we agree with Miah
because basically we said the same thing
that like the temperature of the air
can have something to do with the wind.
- [Teacher] Okay.
So I'm just going to add on here temperature.
- [Voiceover] I was going to add pressure.
- [Teacher] Temperature, okay. That may
be something different.
Let's see what we can add to this.
So you're agreeing with Miah
that it may have something to do
with the temperatures of the air.
Yeah? Okay.
Table three, you guys had
a different kind of theory.
- We agree with what she said
except we also thought the
pressure (mumbles)
how the wind blows and stuff.
[Teacher] Okay, so you guys
talked mostly about pressure.
- Yeah.
- Could you pass that up to table two?
So far we have two theories.
One has been agreed to already.
We have temperature, pressure.
- Our group wasn't sure.
But I agree with Kavya in
how the pressure (mumbles).
- [Teacher] You're thinking that it's
something do with pressure.
And, okay there's an agreement here
with temperature as well.
Pass that up to table one.
Prescott, what kind of ideas did you guys have?
- Well, we were talking
and we kinda agree with
A, or hot air rising.
And pressure and air too,
but I was thinking that
currents or air currents
carry the wind, or carry the air, faster.
- [Teacher] Okay, so let me add something
about currents in here.
'Cause that's another kind
of interesting thing.
So are currents separate from these two?
Or the same? Or added on to?
Or they another thing all together?
- Just added on, I guess.
- [Teacher] Okay, so we've
got temperature of the air,
we've got pressure of the air,
and we've got something
to do with currents.
Could you pass that over to Conner?
Conner, what is your thought?
- [Connor] We kind of agreed that
pressure of the air
probably makes the wind.
Like low pressure and high pressure.
- [Teacher] You know
that's an interesting thing
with the low pressure.
What would cause air to
be different pressures?
- [Connor] I thought
maybe the Earth's core
and the gravity pulls down more
in some places than others.
- [Teacher] Okay so, let's see.
So you're agreeing with pressure,
and you're kind of
saying the pressures
have something to do with gravity.
Really interesting. Oops, hang on.
Something to do with gravity
causing different pressures.
Pass that back to David.
David, what did your conversation involve?
- [David] Well, I thought the,
I really didn't know exactly
what makes the wind blow, but
if I had to guess I'd
say it's air masses meeting.
- [Teacher] Let's put
that down. Okay. Hold on.
And you threw out something that says
air masses meeting.
Alright, so when you talk about air masses,
give us more of what you thought of what that is.
What do you mean an air mass?
And when they meet,
how would that produce wind?
- [David] Well, I know that when
warm and moist air mass
collides with a cool, dry air mass
it forms a thunderstorm.
I was thinking of
one warm air mass meets
another warm air mass,
then when they collide
it might produce wind.
I don't know why, that's just my guess.
- [Teacher] No, no that's fine.
So you're thinking when,
you're saying when two different
kinds of air masses meet
it makes a thunderstorm.
But maybe when two of the same meet
it makes wind.
- [David] Yeah.
- [Teacher] So let me put that on.
So air masses meeting.
So since we're talking only
about wind right now,
it's the same kind of air mass meeting.
Alright.
Would you pass that back to...
Ah, Nathan we're going to have you go
since Amber already went today.
Back over to Nathan.
Nathan what did your
conversation revolve around back there?
- [Nathan] Well, we didn't really know,
but based on what everyone said
I agree with Miah,
that it's the hot air rising
and the cooler falling.
But
I also think that David's ideas
are kind of interesting.
I agree with A.
- [Teacher] You're agreeing with A,
that it has something to
do with the temperatures.
- [Teacher] Miah, what's your thought?
- [Miah] I also thought what David said,
'cause I know how
tornadoes are formed.
But then I thought air
masses are way too big.
And I know almost all over the continent
get a lot of wind.
And so I think it might
have something to do with
air meeting together.
I think that has to do
with hot and cold air,
kind of mashing.
- [Teacher] Okay so.
You said with hot air
rising and cool air falling.
And then you said something about
hot and cool air mashing.
So when you talk about them mashing,
are they like coming together and
like swirling together?
What do you mean by mashing?
- [Miah] Mixing, not mashing.
- [Teacher] Mixing.
- [Miah] Yeah, just kind
of colliding together,
but not swirling.
- [Teacher] Okay, so when you're saying
hot air rising, cool air falling,
you're saying that those
two things are mixing,
and it's by the mixing together
that's what's causing the wind?
- [Miah] Yes.
- [Teacher] Okay.
Guys take a second.
I want you to talk, we've
got two more tables to go.
But I want you to take a few moments,
talk about the theories that
have been presented so far
and see if your opinions change so far.
And then any questions
that come up based on it.
Talk to each other.
(class chatter)
Alright guys, about ten seconds.
Everybody time.
And three, two, and one.
Great ideas so far, guys.
Let's go to the last...
Any questions or comments come up in your
discussion that you just had?
Yes.
- [Student] Well, I think that if two
of the same air masses meet it
would just make a larger air mass.
I mean if you're adding water with water,
it's just making more water.
- [Teacher] Huh, so you're saying instead
of wind being created,
you would just have a bigger one.
- [Student] And I also think maybe
it creates a thunderstorm if it's
two of the different air masses,
but maybe I think that
would create wind like
negative and positive magenets refusing
to mix.
- [Teacher] You're bringing
a couple of interesting things.
You're saying when a warm air mass
and a cold air mass meet,
you're saying that those are
kind of like magnets.
Like opposite sides attract?
Am I understanding what you're saying?
- [Student] Sorry, I
mean both of the...
I'm a little confused.
Also, I would kind of agree with David now
because if I'm thinking about magnets
then two of the same magnets would refuse.
- [Teacher] Right.
So would that analogy be a wind refusing?
Or would coming together
be more like the wind?
- [Student] I think
that analogy would work
with the two different
temperatures of air mass,
but there's, the magnets are the same,
the air masses are...
- [Teacher] That's really interesting when you go
and you apply to analogy
like a magnet like that,
which is really cool to bring in.
Let me get the two other theories and
we'll come back to that.
- [Student] How big are air masses?
- [Teacher] Well, let me come back to that.
Let me get the two others and make sure
we get some other theories in.
Richard, what'd you guys
end up talking about?
Did it change as you
saw these ideas?
- [Richard] Yeah, so
originally we were thinking
that it might have something to do with
gravity's movement.
Actually, we thought
it would probably be more something like
a change in air pressure.
- [Teacher] You know, I'm going to,
because I think that's
an interesting theory,
I'm going to put it up here anyway.
You said it had something to do with
gravity and the movement
of the planet itself.
So with gravity
and movement of the Earth.
Okay and then once you
started throughout this round,
you're thinking more it has to do
with changing pressure?
Okay, and you agree with what...
Connor, was it you that was saying
that it was the gravity that was causing
the change in pressure?
- [Connor] Yeah.
- [Teacher] So are you feeling like,
are you taking your idea
and kinda hooking it together?
Or does something else
cause a change in pressure?
(laughter)
Okay, alright.
That's fine.
Where's the mic?
Can you pass it up?
Here, I'll come get it.
Abigail, last theory.
Go.
- [Abigail] Well, at first we weren't sure.
And we were talking about
kind of atoms moving,
like molecules and compounds
moving away from each other and combining.
But then we changed our opinions
and think that
like the pressure of air and
the temperature of the air
and the compounds that make up the air,
moving and changing,
make wind
from the combination.
- [Teacher] So you're really
mashing it all together.
So your theory revolves around molecules
moving away from each other.
That was the first part.
And then,
did that end up causing
pressures did you say?
- [Abigail] No, like and then the
different types of air
kinda combined I guess.
- [Teacher] So then molecules
move away from each other.
When you say different types of air?
- [Abigail] So like warm, hot
and pressure.
- [Teacher] And those combine?
- [Abigail] (mumbles)
- [Teacher] Should I add that to this?
- [Abigail] I don't know.
- [Teacher] Tom. Yeah, Tom.
- [Tom] I have a question.
How would two air masses meet
if they didn't have wind
to bring them?
- [Teacher] Well, now that's
an interesting question.
Do air masses, now that's a
really interesting question.
Are air masses
just these big masses of air?
And then wind blows them around?
- [Student] Because then
it wouldn't make the wind
if it couldn't,
if it couldn't come together,
it couldn't make wind.
- [Teacher] Oh, now that's
a really interesting thing.
So is the wind?
Oh, wow.
Is wind a result of the air masses?
Or do air masses need wind to move?
Well, that's a really good question.
Ben, you had a hand up.
- [Ben] I just thought about it,
and I didn't really want
to share the question.
I just was thinking in my head
and I thought through the question.
- [Teacher] Alright.
Does anybody have any other
theories they'd like to suggest?
Other than are there.
Let's go through them real quick.
So we had the theory that said
it's hot air rising
cool air falling,
and somehow those two
mixing that creates the wind.
We had the theory that said
it's the pressure of air
and that pressure is kind
of dictated by gravity.
We had something with currents.
So it's somehow the currents in the air,
whatever those happen to be,
that's what's causing
the air to move as wind.
There's air masses meeting.
If it's the same, what Dave was saying.
If the same air mass meeting,
that's what causes the wind.
It's gravity in the movement of the Earth,
which Richard and this table suggested.
Although they moved away from it,
I think it's a valid
theory to be suggested.
And then it's molecules
moving away from each other
and then somehow combining with the other things.
So would you take a moment,
and if you had to commit to one of these
as being why you thought wind would blow,
take a moment and talk to each other
and decide which one you
think you'd commit to
as far as which one you think it is.
Talk to each other.
(class chatter)
- I don't really know like
what Matthew brought up,
how they would move...
So... (mumbles)
(class chatter)
- [Teacher] Alright guys, here we go.
Would you grab the voter
that is registered to you.
And when you turn it on,
you should have an A through F option.
And would you choose one of those
to be your theory please?
- [Student] Is this graded?
- [Teacher] No, it's not.
No, we're just theorizing right now.
So just go with the one
that feels best to you.
- [Student] What's the question?
- [Teacher] It is which
one of those theories
do you think it is
that is
what makes wind blow?
(class chatter)
Wait for a few more people to vote.
Oh Mark, we gotta get to voting.
Patrick, you in?
Yep, you're in.
Okay.
Mark, what you want to vote on
is which one of these theories
you think is best.
Votes are on your voter
and fire away.
And he's the last one to vote,
as soon as he goes
we'll see what way we as a class think.
Oh, you got it?
Okay, here we go.
Let's see what you think.
Alright, so B is our best theory so far.
So right now as a group, let me save this.
So right now as a group,
we are thinking that it is
pressure and...
Let me ask you this.
Let me get a quick hand vote for this,
just out of curiosity.
One of the things was that
the pressure is caused by gravity.
How many of you are going to add
pressure would be
caused by gravity then?
Okay, most of the people voted that way
look like they're going--