- ...boys and girls, for the last week,
we have been looking at videos about Dr.
Martin Luther King. We've been reading
books about Dr. Martin Luther King to get
a feel for who he was, why people loved
him so much, why laws were changed because
of things that he said and things that he
did.
So, today, we are going to watch another
clip of Dr. Martin Luther King. This is
probably one of the most famous speeches
he ever gave. It was his "I Have a Dream"
speech. I don't want you to so much listen
to his words today as I want you to think
about what else he does as he speaks or
while he's speaking that makes him such a
great speaker. How does he capture his
audience? How does he get people to want
to listen to him?
Alright. So, I want you to pay close
attention. It's just a short clip. Then
you'll turn to your partners. So, let's
see... Let me go ahead and get this
started.
- [Martin Luther King Video] I have a
dream that one day, down in Alabama with
its vicious racists, with its governor
having his lips dripping with the words of
"interposition" and "nullification," one
day right there in Alabama little black
boys and black girls will be able to join
hands with little white boys and white
girls as sisters and brothers. I have a
dream today.
I have a dream that one day every valley
shall be exalted, and every hill and
mountain shall be made low, the rough
places will be made plain, and the crooked
places will be made straight and the glory
of the Lord shall be revealed and all
flesh shall see it together.
This is our hope. This is our hope and
this is the faith that I go back to the
South with.
With this faith, we will be able to hew
out of the mountain of despair a stone of
hope. With this faith, we will
be able to...
- Okay. I'm going to stop it there. And I
want you to tell me first of all, what are
some things that you notice that he did to
capture his audience? I want you to think
about it for a minute. I see lots of hands
up. What I want you to do is turn to your
share partner first. Talk to your partner
about what you saw.
[cross talk]
Okay. Let me have your attention back up
here. I'm going to write Dr. King in the
middle of this web. What I want you all to
do is to tell me what are some things that
you and your partner discussed about what
you saw that made people want to listen
and to focus and pay attention to what Dr.
King had to say?
Sara?
- He had hand motions.
- But there was no hand motions in that
clip.
- Yeah, there was.
- I'm glad that you all saw that. I almost
said something. You could kind of see this
hand go up, but it was so close. The video
was so close. That's why I picked that
particular segment because I saw his arm
and I thought, "Oh, I hope they get that,"
because I couldn't find a better clip.
Zachary?
- The way he said a few words at a time
[inaudible].
- Okay.
- He said
[inaudible]
words at a time and stopped...
- Very good. He spaced his words, for lack
of something, a better term to use.
Zachary said he would say a few words and
then he would stop so that people could
absorb almost what he was saying and then
he could go on. Annie? Okay. Emma?
- He spoke in a very low voice so it was
really easy to hear him.
- Okay. So, his tone of voice, right?
We'll put tone of voice. So, it was easy
to hear him.
- Yeah. And then he didn't mumble. He
spoke up really loud.
- He spoke loudly. He did not mumble, she
said. He spoke loudly.
- He spoke very serious.
- Yes. He spoke very serious. Jesenya?
- He shook his head.
- He shook his head, didn't he? He nodded.
Very good.
- That was my idea.
He shook his head.
- Or nodded. Dalen?
- He was looking at the audience.
- Very good.
He was looking at the audience. We call
that eye contact. He had notes in front of
him, but he didn't do this, did he?
- No.
- He looked up constantly. He might have
looked down to see where he was in his
speech, but he always looked back at his
audience. Lenare?
- He said nice words that the people knew.
- Okay. The words that he spoke, he had a
good message, didn't he? If you have a
good message, people are willing to listen
to you, too. He was a good, good man. One
more. Kalen?
- He even had a gooder life-- a better
life.
- Very good. And that goes kind of along
with the words that he spoke-- the good
message about having a better life. All
right. So, you guys came up with some
really good points right here.
What I want you to think about when you do
your readers theater, I want you to think
about how you can incorporate what Dr.
Martin Luther King incorporated into his
speeches to get people to listen to him so
that you're believable in your part, that
people can understand what you're saying.
So, what we're going to do is we're going
to create a rubric together that's going
to help you. So, it's called Rubric For
Speaking Out for Justice: Dr. Martin
Luther King Jr., a readers theater play,
grade two because you guys are second
graders.
Now, let's take a look at what I've
written-- listening, speaking viewing.
There's a three, a two and a one. Let's do
listening first, okay? Now, if three is
the highest, how do you think you can get
a three? Sayid?
- By getting a one plus two?
- Okay. But don't think about math right
this moment.
- Oh...
- I want you to think about if I were
grading you, you were grading yourself or
your peers were grading you, how would you
give yourself a three or someone else a
three? Emma?
- We start with listening. You wouldn't be
just fumbling through your pages of your
book and just traveling around. You'd be
listening to the other people because you
have to know when your part is. You have
to be ready.
- Very good. You have to know where your
part is. Part of doing readers theater is
listening to the people that are reading
before you because that is going to give
you your cue of when it's your turn to
speak, okay? So, "I was a good listener."
Let's look at number two. How do you think
you would get a two? How would you score a
two for listening? If the best is that you
were a good listener, what would two be?
Annie?
- Looking at your paper and then like
doing something else.
- Looking at your paper but doing
something else. Maybe looking away, maybe
fidgeting. So maybe you tried to listen
most of the time, but you had difficulty
with it. So, we could say, "I tried to
listen most of the time."
- Most of the time.
- So, what about a one? Kennedy?
- I didn't listen at all.
- Very good.
- Like purposefully not paying attention.
- "I forgot to listen." Yeah, you don't
decide to do that on purpose, Whitney.
Now, the next thing you're going to be
scored on is speaking. So, how could you
get a three for speaking? Sara?
- Don't speak like just normal, like how
the actor would speak.
- Speak how the actor would speak. Good.
Lenore? Let's do a body check, please. I
need you all on the carpet.
- You're supposed to like listen to what
he said
[inaudible].
- Okay. Annie?
- Like speak a little louder. When you
speak loudly, then
[inaudible].
- "I spoke loudly enough for people to
hear."