- [Student]
... tilted towards the Sun,
you're closer to the sun, which is heat,
which means you're going to be warmer.
When you're tilted away from the Sun,
then there's less heat,
because you're farther away from it,
it's going to be colder.
That's what changes the seasons.
- [Student] Once again,
it goes in orbit.
Like you said, the
closer we are to the Sun,
or the father away,
once again it goes back to
being an elliptical orbit.
- [Student] I think that tilt
causes the seasons,
and the closer we are tilted to the Sun,
that means it's like Summer or Spring,
then if we're tilted back,
it's Winter or Fall.
- [Student]
I'm kind of understanding
what you guys are saying.
Because I'm thinking of it as like, say,
like the globe that's sitting right there,
say that Ben was the sun...
- [Teacher] You can
use that if you'd like.
- Say that Ben was the Sun,
the Sun would be shining
at the bottom of the globe,
because the globe's tilted.
So, there wouldn't be much
Sun at the top of the sphere
because that's the most tilted away
from the Sun.
So, it would cause Summer lower
and on the other side
it would cause Winter.
- [Teacher] Why are
you shaking your head?
- [Student] I disagree.
I think the Sun would hit more
on top than it does on the bottom,
because like Antarctica and stuff,
always cold, and it's at the bottom.
So, I think it hits more in the top
and in between,
like by the equator.
Because as you go down South,
it's more warmer, but still,
if you go down, way down to Antarctica,
it's totally freezing,
they don't get no sun.
- [Student] That's not right.
Because...
there is like sunlight
in Antarctica and stuff.
It's just 'cause like,
the latitude and longitude,
and like, because...
Because,
Antarctica's at zero degrees.
So, it's cold down there.
- [Student] I want to know,
when the Sun is going in its orbit,
if it just goes from this to this,
like boom,
or if its turning and its like
facing the Sun like that,
like, I don't understand that.
- [Teacher] Okay.
So, our question is what?
- Like,
when you're going around the Sun,
and its on its axis like this, tilted,
and it goes around,
eventu...
Does it just, like, go like that?
Like real quick?
And then it's like
shifted so the bottom
is getting more light,
and that would put us in Winter?
- [Teacher] What do you think, Kaylie?
You haven't said anything.
Do you think that our,
our tilt's going to just change?
- [Kaylie] No.
I think it's like,
whenever we're rotating, like
it goes around the Sun in the orbit?
- [Student] Can I show...
She's saying that as it's rotating,
it's staying the same, it's
just that it's changing because
you're changing position
from which way the Sun is.
- [Student] Can I show
an example with the globe?
- [Teacher] Yeah, please.
- [Student] Say
the Sun was in the middle.
Say, like the globe, is right here.
Say we're right here,
it's Summertime, really close,
and the Sun's right here.
And as we go around, like
maybe, like we're right
here and this is Fall,
and then we go to Winter.
And as we turn this way for the Spring,
and then we're back to
Summer again because
we're going around the sun, so...
- [Student] But (inaudible),
the only problem with that is
we're still going to be tilted away
when it,
when we go over
towards the Sun.
We're still going to be
tilted away, won't we?
- [Student] Well the
Earth's always tilted.
- [Student] Yeah, but
we'll be tilted away.
In the Summer you're
tilted towards the Sun.
- [Teacher] Let's go back to,
does the tilt change?
Okay, so we're definitely
talking about this tilt,
and I'm guessing there's
a lot of kids that are
a little unsure about the tilt?
Yes?
So, if you think you understand the tilt,
help everybody else understand.
We're not getting this tilt
in what you're talking about.
So, explain it the best way you can,
and help each other, okay so...
"I don't get this tilt."
Does it just flip flop?
What do you think, Anna?
- [Anna] I think it stays the same?
- [Teacher] What about you, Shana?
You haven't said anything yet.
- [Shana] Well, as
the Earth goes around
in its orbit, it shifts,
just like a little bit that way,
you're like closer to the Sun.
And then during the Winter,
we're father away.
- [Teacher] Is that how it is?
We're closer towards the Sun in the Summer
and we're father away in the Winter?
- [Students] Yes.
- [Teacher] Who doesn't think that?
- [Student] Could I try something
with the globe real quick?
- [Teacher] Yes!
- [Student] Could I
borrow Nick, to be my Sun? (laughs)
- [Teacher] Yeah.
Be his Sun, Nick.
- Come on, Sun.
Go out there and stand in the middle.
- [Nick] Pretty dark Sun.
- [Teacher] Yeah, you are.
- Okay,
we're gonna say that this little pin here
is where the Sun is hitting today.
All right?
And we're spinning,
woah, spinning that way.
(laughs)
It's spinning, it's spinning,
it's spinning, it's spinning,
but it never,
it never tilts back towards the Sun.
That's what I don't understand,
does it just go like this?
(laughs)
- [Teacher] This is
a really good question.
This is a really good question.
Now I want, wait,
don't move yet.
I want,
go ahead, be the Sun still.
And I want you to walk around
and explain to people
what you're talking about.
Number one, show us the tilt.
- Okay,
that's the tilt.
- [Teacher] Show everybody the tilt.
- Okay, everyone,
this, Nick move,
you're in the way of people.
- [Teacher] Just duck down, just crouch.
- And this is the way
of the tilt, the way it's tilted
that way.
But as we go around it's still tilted
that way. And this side here
is still far away, so what?
It's going to stay Winter all the time?
Or is it just going to like flip?
And be like,
"Hey guys, look! Now we're Summer,
but we're upside-down."
That's what I don't understand.
- [Teacher] He has a
very good question, okay?
His question is,
why is,
what hemisphere are you talking about?
- The Northern Hemisphere.
- [Teacher] Okay.
So, why is the Northern Hemisphere
always tilted towards the Sun,
how he's walking away?
Because his argument is, that...
- [Student] Oh, I have it right here.
- [Teacher] Go ahead.
- [Student] It says, "Because the Earth's
axis is slightly tilted,
when the North Pole
is laying towards the Sun
and South Pole is
laying away from the Sun.
And when the South Pole
is leading towards the Sun,
the North Pole is leading
away from the Sun."
It says, "As a result,
the number of daylight hours in
the Northern and Southern hemisphere
are not constantly recalled
because the Earth is
divided in two halves
of the hemisphere by the equator,
the hemisphere that leads towards the Sun
has a long day and short nights."
Does that have to do with anything?
- [Student] See, I...
- [Teacher] Wait!
Does that have to do with anything?
That's Sabrina's question.
So summarize,
what you just read to us.
- [Sabrina] Does the tilt have,
like also have to do with like,
the days, and like the
short days and short nights?
- [Teacher] Does the
tilt have to do with
the short days and long nights,
and long days and short nights?
Shawn, you're shaking your head yes.
You think it does have to do with it?
- [Student] Say yes?
- [Shawn] Yes?
- [Teacher] You think it
does have to do with it?
Why?
Who could help him explain,
why would a tilt change
the length of day?
Move over, Lucas.
- [Student] Because,
like it's if,
like it'll be indirect Sun if it's tilted
away from it?
And instead of like... I don't know.
- (laughs)
- I think it is
because I think
another thing in the direct rays because,
the way we're tilted,
it's the number of daylight hours
because of the less Sun,
as much of the Sun because of the tilt,
and how the Sun hits it
when its on its tilt?
I think,
like, see how it tilted that way?
- [Teacher] No, why don't you use it?
Why don't you boys sit down and let...
Pass that globe over to Byers,
and let him explain.
- What I think is...
You know how it's tilted this way?
Maybe it'll tilt the opposite
direction for the Summer.
Like instead of it being
tilted towards this,
it'll tilt the other way for the South.
Instead of the North be showing,
the South would be showing.
That's what I think.
- [Teacher] Where is the Sun?
That's what I'm not understanding.
- The Sun
would usually be in the middle.
- [Student] You need a hand?
- [Byers] Yeah.
- [Teacher] Okay, go ahead,
be the Sun again.
- The Sun's in the middle.
And that's why if it's tilted this way,
we're getting our Sun,
but I thought if it would
tilt the opposite way,
like instead of being tilted
this way, it'd tilt that way,
then the South would get more Sun?
- [Teacher] Okay? So, how...
But what you're asking
is the same question as Lucas.
- Yeah.
- [Teacher] How does that other hemisphere
become tilted towards the Sun?
That's what you're trying to figure out.
Whenever Lucas walked it around,
the whole time,
what hemisphere was
pointing towards the Sun?
- [Student] The Southern Hemisphere
was pointing towards the Sun.
And the Northern Hemisphere
was pointing away from the Sun.
- [Teacher] Ben?
- [Ben] No, I thought it was
the Northern was pointing to the Sun,
and the Southern was pointing
the other way.
- [Teacher] But, it remained constant
the whole orbit.
- [Student] Yes.
That's what I couldn't figure out, like
how did it just like, did it like
flip around and all of the sudden...
- [Byers] Maybe the Sun?
- [Student] ... it changed?
- [Teacher] What do you guys think?
Does the Sun move?
JJ, you haven't been in here yet.
- [JJ] I think like every day,
it moves a little to the other side.
- [Teacher] Wait, what does?
- [JJ] The Earth.
- [Teacher] The Earth moves everyday?
- [JJ] Yeah, it might.
Like it tilts every day.
- [Teacher] It tilts,
the tilt is changing?
Is that what you're saying?
So, the tilt changes?
What were you gonna say?
- I think the...
It...
The...
Earth, like doesn't move,
like when it stays in one spot,
I think it might like flip.
Like kind of like,
just go around, like...
- [Teacher] Can you show us?
Do you wanna show us?
- Sure, I'll try.
- [Student] (inaudible)
...I was gonna say maybe like,
as it's,
as like the Earth turns around,
maybe it like, tilts
forward every so often
and backward.
- [Teacher] So you're telling me
the tilt is changing though
and it flips?
- [Student] Yes.
- [Teacher] Okay, so what are you saying?
- It just goes
around like this,
and eventually it just like, spins around.
- [Teacher] So, it spins
on top of its rotation?
- [Student] Yeah.
- [Teacher] What do you think, Brad?
- [Brad] I think, yeah,
I kind of agree with him.
- [Teacher] Wait, with who?
- [Brad] with David.
While it's like going around its orbit,
it just like tilts.
- [Teacher] So the tilt is changing?
- [Brad] Yeah.
- [Teacher] What do you think, Alec?
You haven't said anything yet.
- [Alec] I don't agree with him.
I think that it spins
while its moving around?
- [Teacher] Don't raise your hand,
you don't have to raise your hand.
- [Byers] Only this,
like what Nick just did,
or maybe every day it goes a little bit,
and tilts like this.
And the Sun hits more of the Southern.
- (inaudible)
- [Byers] It's like, everyday,
goes a little bit, little bit, little bit,
so where the South starts to get more Sun.
Because like when we're in Summer
and Australia has Winter.
So, when we're in Winter,
Australia has Summer.
So...
And it's in the Southern half
and we're in the Northern half.
- [Student] Wait!
- [Teacher] Tiffany,
you were shaking your head.
Do you agree with what he's saying?
- [Tiffany] Sort of, yeah.
Because,
if...
one spot on the hemisphere
gets more sunlight,
the most likely it's gonna
be warmer than the other.
Like he was saying,
when we get more sunlight,
and the temperature's warm up here,
the temperatures in
the Southern Hemisphere
get a little colder
if they don't have as much sunlight,
and not as much warmth.
- You see what I mean?
Like say I'm right here,
the Sun is tilted,
so you see how the Sun's right here?
And then it tilts
a little bit like this.
We're still getting Summer sunlight,
but Australia's getting more sunlight.
- [Student] I have to
agree with what JJ said earlier.
It tilts everyday.
- [Teacher] So the tilt is changing?
You think that the tilt is changing?
Morgan, you think the tilt is changing?
- [Morgan] No,
I don't think it's changing.
I think it's staying
the same, because even,
I think the rotation helps,
because if it goes around the orbit,
even though its rotating it helps.
Like...
Nick, you're the Sun like,
and the axis stays,
and when it rotates, the Earth rotates,
and it's like kind of,
it like helps us.
I don't know,
like indirect sunlight?
I don't know.
Something like that.
- [Student] I can show
what she means, I think.
- [Teacher] Go ahead.
- [Student] I think it's also
about the gravitational pull.
Like, when it goes around farther
there's less gravitational pull.
- [Student] As it goes around farther,
Okay, when you do this, Grace,
please explain to me
what it is.
So, that everybody here that's watching
can try and make sense
of what we're talking about.
- [Grace] I think
what she's saying is like,
say Nick's the Sun again.
Since the Northern is that way,
I think she's saying is,
it doesn't rotate but this is,
but we're kind of going around
kind of like this?
So, then it changes.
So now the Southern is towards the Sun
and the Northern is that way.
So, now it's changed.
- [Teacher] She did something very different
in her orbit.
Did anybody catch that?
- [Students] Yeah, yeah.
- [Student] Like she, it didn't move,
it just went around like,
around the Sun?
- [Teacher] What do
you mean it didn't move?
- [Student] The Earth stayed still
and just
moved at one point.
- [Grace] It didn't do that.
- (laughs)
- [Teacher] Okay,
let's do it again, okay?
And I want you to make sure that,
number one, everybody
sees where you start,
and everybody sees what
happens to the Earth
as she's showing you
how it's going around.
So, explain to us.
What is this?
Where are we starting?
- Okay, we're starting out this way
with the Northern towards the Sun,
and the Southern away from the Sun.
And as we are rotating? I don't know
if all of you guys can see this.
But as we're going around?
- [Teacher] Stop there.
- [Grace] It's not moving?
So, since it's not moving,
now the Northern is
kind of like facing away,
and the Southern is facing
towards the Sun now?
- [Teacher] Keep going.
And then just make sure that the camera
can see what you're talking about
as you go around.
Okay.
So, did everybody see that?
Who doesn't understand that?
Who didn't understand
what she did right there?
Okay.
So...
- [Student] Now, I don't understand,
actually, wouldn't it actually
have to stop rotating
and then it would have
to rotate on its axis,
and then start rotating again?
- [Grace] I'm not sure
what you mean by that.
- Like...
you spun it like this,
- [Grace] All right?
- [Student] But the Earth is going
like this the whole time.
Would that end up stopping,
and then it go like this?
Or is that still happening?
- [Grace]
It's not turning like that.
It's just rotating around the Sun.
- [Teacher] Wait, Sabrina,
you had something to say.
Okay. So,
here's what's happening.
Lucas is a little confused
about your explanation, okay?
So, we just have to go through it again.
What did you have to say, Sabrina?
- [Sabrina] The earth doesn't change its tilt.
It stays like an exact same position,
but when it goes around the Sun,
it gets like different ways,
like the Sun hits it in
different directions
which causes different weathers.
- [Teacher] Okay, wait,
why don't you try to show him?
Maybe it's just a different person.
Maybe it will
help explain it, okay?
So, the more people we can
get information out of,
remember, the more we're gonna understand.
So, start and tell us what's happening.
And just make sure the camera
can see what you're doing.
- [Sabrina] The Northern Hemisphere
is towards the Sun,
and the Southern is facing away.
So, this causes colder weather,
and up here where it's facing the Sun
causes warmer weather.
So, when it goes around
the weathers start to change
and then when you get it around here,
the Southern is facing towards.
- [Teacher] Wait, is the
Southern facing towards?
- [Sabrina] The Southern's facing
towards the Sun.
And the winter is facing away.
Which causes it to be warmer down here
and Winter up here.
- [Teacher] Who can
help her out, because...
- [Lucas] What I don't understand, is...
- [Teacher] Go ahead, go ahead.
- [Lucas] I don't understand it because
it's still changing from day to night,
but then it's shifting so
wouldn't it have to stop spinning
and then shift?
- If it stops spinning we're gonna die.
- (laughs)
- [Student] Not necessarily.
- [Teacher] Okay, wait, Ben,
start from the beginning
and explain what's going on.
Nick is our Sun still.
Put your legs in so he doesn't trip.
Northern Hemisphere is towards the Sun,
Southern's away.
And it's still spinning,
it doesn't change...
- [Teacher] Okay. And so stop there
and what's happening?
- [Ben] The Southern
Hemisphere's towards the Sun
and the Northern's away from it.
- [Teacher] And what happened
to the tilt the whole time?
- [Ben] It didn't change.
- [Teacher] It what?
- [Teacher] It didn't
change, it stayed the same.
- [Lucas] But that made more sense.
Like, I couldn't figure
out why it wasn't spinning,
but now I do.
- [Ben] And then it keeps going.
And then it just goes back.
- [Lucas] Now I understand.
- [Teacher] Okay.
Let's use this model,
and try to figure out,
where are the seasons happening?
So, where do we live, Anna?
- [Anna] We live...
Yeah, where he's pointing.
- [Teacher] What's
that called, somebody?
- [Students] America.
- (laughs)
- [Student] North America.
- [Teacher] North
America, let's get bigger.
- [Byers] Northern Hemisphere?
- [Teacher] What Byers?
- [Byers] The Northern Hemisphere.
- [Teacher] Okay, so we live
in the Northern Hemisphere.
Right now, what's happening?
- [Students] It's Summer.
- [Teacher] It's Summer
in the Northern Hemisphere.
Does everyone see that?
- [Students] Yes.
- [Teacher] Yes.
Anybody not see
it's Summer in the Northern
Hemisphere, see it?
- [Students] Yeah.
- [Teacher] Okay, so...