- [Student] Also causing habitat loss--
- Anyways.
- [Student] Indirectly through
our use of C02 emissions.
- It says that...
It is a naturally occurring greenhouse gas
and we want to keep that, right?
We want to keep it naturally occuring,
we just wanna work on our--
- [Brown sweater] Levels.
- Yeah.
Because our impact is not exactly natural.
- [Student right corner] It's
not like we're trying to stop the
unhuman-related processes.
Just like, what we're
doing to increase it.
Because like, it's been staying at a level
until we started releasing a bunch of CO2,
and then it went up,
so it's kind of obvious
that we're the cause of that.
So, I don't think it's going to go down,
then what it was before, normally.
- [Brown sweater] Yeah, I
think it's highly unlikely
that this would ever happen.
- [White sweatshirt] Yeah,
and 20 to 40 degrees Celsius
is a lot, too.
- I highly doubt this would happen.
If we reduce the CO2 emissions,
in what we're doing, this
is kind of ridiculous.
- [Brown sweater] Give some
more evidence for that.
- [Teacher] Why?
- [Brown sweater] Yeah, why?
Explain why do you feel that way?
- Because carbon dioxide is part
of the natural carbon cycle, yeah?
But we're contributing to make more of it.
- [Black sweatshirt]
There's so many economies
and stuff that are
dependent on it right now,
that are not going to get
rid of it for a long time.
Therefore, there wouldn't
be such a drastic change
in the amounts of carbon dioxide,
that there wouldn't be a drop
of 20 to 40 degrees Celsius.
- [Brown sweater] Because
we don't plan to tamper
with the natural...
Flow of the carbon cycle.
We just want to tamper with our
(speaker's voice distorted)
which will take a long time anyway.
So, we're going to be up
and up and up for a while.
- But we kind of already
did tamper with the CO2,
the natural ones, because
yeah, we're trying to reduce
our own personal emissions,
now that we're doing it now,
but we've already gone
in and tampered with it.
We've already cut down
millions and millions of trees.
We've already, so can we talk about...
I'm trying to touch into
what we've done in the past,
and how if we kind of try and back out now,
then we leave the Earth
in a sticky situation.
Does that make sense?
- [Black sweatshirt] Well,
I do have a question.
I don't remember, does
the greenhouse effect
exist naturally, even as
like a little bit, right?
- [Red hat] Yeah, we just made it bigger.
- So it's like, they're claiming
that without the greenhouse effect,
the Earth's average temperature
would drop drastically,
well obviously because
the greenhouse effect
exists naturally, but we're making so much
of the greenhouse effect that
we're trying to bring it down
to normal levels. We're
not trying to bring it down
below normal levels.
I think they're saying that
this is going to happen
if it's below the normal
level, but the problem is that
we are already above the normal level,
so if we bring it down,
it's not going to make it
a complete effect anyway.
- [Blonde hair] I mean,
they are right saying
that it's going to get significantly
below, as everyone said,
it's not going to be to the
point where life will not exist.
But I mean, the process by
which sun penetrates the earth,
like some of the heat is
retained because of that effect.
And what we're doing is enabling
the Earth to retain more
heat than it normally does.
So by releasing some of
it, by reducing emissions,
we are making the Earth much, much cooler.
- [Black shirt] But we also can't get rid
of the greenhouse gases
already in the atmosphere.
So, those would stay
there, and our temperature
probably wouldn't drop as much,
probably still would drop,
maybe not as extreme.
- [Student] And also, we live in a world
where we use so much carbon dioxide,
there's no way that we're
going to get it to the level
of just the natural processes.
I mean, at least not in a ten year period.
- [Red hat] I was wondering
how long it thought
we were going to slow
so-called global warming.
It doesn't really give us a projection.
- [White sweatshirt] I
don't think we're going to
have another ice age for a long time.
- [Black sweatshirt] I mean,
we're having a mass extinction
as it is, the way we are right now.
I think if anything,
reducing it would help stop
the mass extinction.
- I think we've kind of
talked about all we can
at this point.
- Alright, so, at this point,
if you feel like you have talked a lot,
in an effort to get you to stop,
I'm going to have you actually,
I want you to scoot your chair back
like a foot or two, for the next one,
to give some other
people a chance to talk.
Yeah, I have two, you want
the good ones with lotion?
- The next one, sorry,
is, "Concerns over CO2
emissions are unfounded."
Somebody want to read?
- Okay. "Concerns over CO2
emissions are unfounded.
"Water vapor is a leading greenhouse gas.
"Today, Mythbusters
Daily exclusively reveals
"what climate scientists have
been hiding from the public.
"Water vapor is actually
a much more prevalent
"and potent greenhouse
than carbon dioxide.
"Water vapor concentrations
in the atmosphere
"between 30,000 to 40,000 ppm,
"while maximum estimates
"put CO2 around 370 ppm.
"Due to its abundance, water vapor's
"a much more important greenhouse gas,
"so human inputs of CO2 are negligible.
"We should stop focusing on CO2,
"and refocus research and funding
"on reducing the amount of
water vapor in the atmosphere."
(laughs)
- Would that be parts per million for ppm?
- Yeah, parts per million.
- Water vapor unit, really, really.
Okay. We have a whole water cycle,
I know we have the whole
carbon cycle and everything,
but we have contributed so
much to the carbon cycle.
I mean, and global warming
hasn't really been a problem
until recently, gee, I wonder why?
Maybe because, I don't know, we
are emitting a lot of carbon.
I mean, it's not like we've
been emitting more water,
you can't create more water.
Okay. Yeah, I'm done, I'm sorry.
- [Far right corner] I
think if you explained
what the greenhouse effect actually is
it will disprove the water vapor theory.
Because the way the
greenhouse effect works
is completely unrelated with water vapor.
- [Red hat] How?
- [Far right corner] Well,
because like, isn't the greenhouse
gas a gas that lets in
sunlight, but it prevents the heat
from leaving, or whatever
or something right?
But water doesn't, I don't
think water does that.
- I thought it was a greenhouse gas.
We learned about that in chapter 20.
But...
We did it on the worksheet, maybe,
or the thing that we had
for homework last night.
It's considered a greenhouse gas.
That's all I know.
- [Red hat] You know what effect it had?
- Sorry.
- No, it is a greenhouse gas.
I remember reading that.
But--
- [Teacher] You can grab
a textbook, if you'd like.
- [Sweatshirt with number]
Keep talking, Elizabeth.
- Water vapor has always been there.
It has always been at this level.
Am I wrong?
- [Blonde hair] Well, I
mean, if our CO2 emissions
are increasing, and global
warming is happening,
then you would be
releasing more water vapor.
I mean, heat would cause that to happen.
- But then technically this is an effect,
it's not a cause, then.
- [Teacher] Is it possible to be both?
- Maybe.
- [Red hat] Like a positive feedback loop?
- [Teacher] What do you
know about water vapor?
- [Elizabeth] It's a greenhouse gas.
We know that now.
- Isn't it when water evaporates.
- [Student] Clouds.
(students laugh)
- [Teacher] Nope, that
is an excellent point.
- Hold on, you guys, what do clouds do?
They block sunlight.
(students talking over each other)
- So, if the global temperatures rise,
there would be more water vapor,
because there would be more fluctuations
of creating water vapor?
- [Teacher] Don't look at
me, look at your people.
And people who are on the outside
are not supposed to be talking.
- [Sweatshirt with
numbers] Well, just like--
- [Teacher] Well, she can finish.
- [Sweatshirt with numbers]
Sorry, sorry, no go ahead.
- Go ahead, finish. She said
you could finish.
- Oh, Okay.
Well, when water vapor, think about it,
when you like boil water, it's hot,
and it creates water vapor.
So, increases in global temperature,
there would be a possible connection
between increased temperature
and increased water vapor.
- Hot air rises.
- Which way would it be though?
Because if increasing
temperature causes increase
in water vapor, does that
mean increase in water vapor
causes increase in temperature?
- [Blue scarf] Well, you said
that water vapor is clouds,
so wouldn't, clouds would block sunlight,
so wouldn't that decrease temperature?
But that's kind of like contradictory.
- [Teacher] Can that happen, though?
- [Blue scarf] Like how hot air rises,
and cold air drops,
so maybe, forgot what
that process is called.
- [Black sweatshirt] Well, it's
like sometimes when you're
on like islands, or something
that it's like all cloudy,
but still really hot and humid,
so maybe it can increase the temperature.
(says teacher's name)
- [Blonde hair] I have a question.
At what altitude do clouds form?
- It depends.
I mean they can form at ground level.
That's what's basically fog.
- [Blonde hair] What's
the highest altitude
that clouds are going to reach?
For the most part, like on average?
- I have no idea, that
is an excellent question.
- [Blonde hair] But
like what part of their,
is it under the stratosphere?
- There's a laptop over there
if you guys want to get it.
No one's ever asked me that.
That's a really good question.
I don't know.
I know that they're
throughout the troposphere,
but I'm not sure how high up
in the stratosphere they go.
That's a really good, I don't know.
- [Black hair] Can I read
something really quick?
"Four natural greenhouse
gases in the troposphere
"are water vapor, carbon dioxide, methane,
"and nitrous oxide.
"These gases have been present,
in varying concentrations
"in the troposphere during most
of the Earth's long history.
"Fluctuations in the troposphere,
"concentration of these gases,
especially carbon dioxide
"and methane, plus changes in solar output
"are the major factors causing new changes
"in the average temperature
of the troposphere
"over the past 400,000 years."
And then it just talks about how
from the beginning of the
industrial revolution,
human actions have led
to significant increases
in carbon dioxide, and therefore
it correlates the relation
to the increase in
temperature of the globe.
- I just read another thing.
"Additional clouds can
have a warming effect,
"positively back by
absorbing and releasing heat
"into the troposphere.
"Or a cooling effect, a negative effect,
"by reflecting more
sunlight back into space."
So, they can have a warming effect.
- So, should we be
worried about water vapor
more than carbon dioxide?
- [Students] No.
- Why?
- [Black hair] Because doesn't the CO2
cause the warming, which, never mind.
- [Teacher] No no, keep going.
That was good, keep going.
- [Black hair] That was it.
- [Teacher] Okay.
(laughter)
- Well, based on what she just read,
and based on everything we
know about carbon dioxide,
we know that carbon dioxide
can lead to a lot of effects.
A lot of them bad.
And one of the major
things is that it does lead
to more water vapor, and if
water vapor is such an issue
in terms of global temperature increase,
then you would think their first thought
would be decrease carbon
dioxide emissions.
But, no.
- Can we directly regulate water vapor?
-No.
Can we directly regulate CO2?
- Yeah, we can decrease our emissions.
We can switch to alternative vehicles.
We can find other sources of energy.
I mean there are a lot of
options with water vapor,
we just have a water cycle.
We can't tell the water
vapor to stop rising
into the clouds, like,
"Yeah, can you just pause for a moment?"
No, we can't do that,
because it's a natural cycle.
- [Teacher] Are we done with that one?
- So, what do we have so far, Nida?
- Well, that heat would cause the release
of more water vapor, and clouds
can trap and release heat,
but they can also cool.
And concluded that clouds are
water vapor, first of all.
(laughter)
What we were saying, should
we worry about water vapor
more so than CO2?
Probably not, because we can regulate CO2,
but not water vapor.
And water's a greenhouse gas.
- I call that using science.
(says teacher's name)
- [Blue scarf] I have a question for you.
In nuclear power plants,
how the steam comes
from the cooling tower.
Is that water vapor emission?
- That is considered a
water vapor emission.
- [Blue scarf] Okay, so
maybe we could control
that aspect of it, control the steam.
- One additional thing to
just sort of keep in mind,
and we'll talk about this later,
is what we call residence time.
Does anyone know what that is?
Residence time is how
long a chemical stays
in wherever it is.
And so one of the things
that we're concerned about,
when we look at a chemical,
is its residence time.
So, if we're talking
about a water pollutant,
what's the residence time?
How long is it going to stay in water?
Is it going to break down quickly,
or is it going to be very persistent,
and is it gonna last
for a really long time?
So, when we were looking
at greenhouse gases,
we're also looking at
what's the residence time
in the atmosphere.
How long does an average
molecule stay in the atmosphere?
And water vapor tends to cycle
in and out of the atmosphere
a lot quicker than some of
our other greenhouse gases.
Its cycles are usually
on the order of days,
whereas others are on the
order of months to years,
versus like, do you
guys know what CFCs are?
The ozone-depleting compounds.
Chlorofluorocarbons, we'll
talk more about those as well.
CFCs are also a greenhouse
gas, but their residence time
in the atmosphere is more
like hundreds of years.
Hundreds of years to thousands of years.
That would be something we
would be more concerned about.
- [Blue scarf] So like, the residence time
of something radioactive
could be like its half life?
- Yep.
And then a third factor that
we look at is also how potent
of a greenhouse gas it is.
Some gases have more warming potential,
and some gases have
less warming potential.
So, we also want to look at
what is its potential for heat trapping
versus its concentration?
And we'll talk a little
more about that, too.
Alright, we have two
left. I'd actually like
for you to pick one. I'm thinking maybe
you should do the freezing temps one,
because we already kind of talked
about the cloudy one, but if
you want to do the cloudy one
you can do the cloudy one.
- [Blonde hair] You suggest
the freezing temperature one?
- That's my suggestion,
but I won't be upset
if you overrule me.
- Let's do freezing temperatures.
- Does anybody want to write--