- Love the many questions
that you're asking.
Asking questions is a great way,
especially if you're wondering something.
Feel free to ask it, even if you go
in a little bit different direction.
Also, the more you reference the book,
you can give us some things
going on in "Brave New World"
and the more specific you can be,
the better that helps us understand
somebody actually connected to the book
and maybe how it's connected to them.
So two things to be thinking about.
But if you give examples,
the more specific you can,
of real world examples
also the better off.
You guys are doing a
fantastic job, though.
Talking, having a natural conversation,
letting each other speak and all that.
So, continue with the next question.
- Are we doing that on here?
- What's that?
- Are we doing what we're
supposed to in here?
- Yeah, and my outside
people, ya'll are doing fine
continue with whatever
you want to put on here.
As long as it's related to
the conversation, obviously.
- Ya'll want to talk
about Bernard & John now?
- Yeah.
- Absolutely.
- Alright, how do these characters
show a variety of ideas
about individualism and conformity?
I'll just kind of start out.
Here's my answer, I kind of
said that they were like,
the Russians who wanted their blue jeans.
They knew what they wanted
and they kinda went for it.
And in the end, society
pretty much pushed them back
into their place.
And was like, "No, don't stand
up and rise up against us."
- Well, I would say, I see a similarity
between, like, Bernard and John
because they both had individual ideals
but I definitely that John was
a lot stronger in his beliefs
than Bernard was because I think about how
Bernard had, at first,
he was all individual
and he had these individual
beliefs and then when he,
when they got in trouble,
kind of in a way,
all three of them,
with the uprising and
all that kind of stuff.
He kind of went back
on what he was saying.
And John, he stuck to it,
like he actually did something about it.
When he actually kind of protested
and he was able to go back
to being an individual.
And he went into doing his own
thing, with his own beliefs.
So, I just feel like
John was a lot stronger
in what he believed
throughout it than Bernard,
who was kind of allowing people
to look at him, put on him, worried about
what other people thought about him
and all that kind of stuff.
- That's true.
Cuz like, whenever Bernard was more of
I guess a weirdo, he does
always, like, question society
and why everybody acts the way they do.
But as soon as he started being
popular, he started bragging
to Helmholtz about how,
like right here it says,
"And I had six girls
last week: one on Monday,
"two on Tuesday, two more
on Friday, one on Saturday."
So, as soon as he became
just like everybody else,
he started to like it far more
and it mattered much to him
that people like, people
did what they did,
like not explicit
relationships and everything.
So, you're right, John
was stronger than Bernard.
- I don't think John ever conformed,
he stuck to his beliefs
pretty much the whole time.
- Yeah, he always stayed
an individual like,
he made sure he didn't conform.
- Was Helmholtz conformist
or individualistic?
Because he did a lot of the
same things that, you know,
normal people do
but he also read as an idealism at times.
(background chatter)
- I think he's somebody who
he conformed to what he
had to, just to get by.
But at the same time,
he had his own thoughts
and believed what he believed.
I just don't think he really stood up
for what he believed in.
- So we're (background chatter)
- Yeah, I think so.
It's almost like it's almost
like a fair weather friend.
He did what was best for
him, to keep him going
got hit and suffered trouble.
- I feel like, I don't
know, maybe I'm crazy
but I thought Helmholtz
was like, reminds me of,
this is stereotypical, but
he kind of reminds me of like
an old professor, you know?
He, like, just like goes to work.
Helmholtz has, like,
good thoughts about stuff
but then he didn't like, live the life.
- Wasn't he some sort of,
- He was like a top guy,
- professor.
A psychologist, or something?
- He was a scientist.
(laughing)
- Alright, so kind of
sticking on that topic.
What about the books and how they,
nobody really read how they kind of,
all of the books related to, I guess,
individuality and the whole
world, what life was like before
(bell rings)
was locked up.
- I can say the same, John
was reading Shakespeare
and how Shakespeare is all
about, like, love and tragedy
and there's like sorrow
and there's also, you know,
the aspect of love with "Romeo & Juliet."
And how the people didn't really,
Helmholtz would, his job
was reading it to them
and he started laughing about it
because he was trained not to.
So, I think if people
actually read about it,
you know, the feelings and
how love is supposed to be.
Then people wouldn't go along
with how their relationships
would be because they'd
wanna, maybe wanna experience
falling in love with someone
or having that one person
would cause a lot more
problems with that knowledge
along with seeing how
people, how there's tragedy.
People are becoming sad and
how in the New World people are
always supposed to be happy
and everyone's getting along.
Then in these stories,
there's like love conflict
and everyone is fighting
and it would cause problems
because from that, people could form
their own individual problems
and then they start to have
their own individuality
and form opinions and
start asking questions,
which leads to a lot of things.
- Books are they pretty much written
to express those emotions
in which the whole state is
trying to block up anyways?
That was why they're there.
- So, the book, do you
think that the books
are kind of what drove
Bernard to be a nonconformist
and then as he got away from reading,
and he started conforming
back into society?
- What I think happened,
cuz they were saying,
I think he was like bipolar or something
and everyone else was like
(inaudible speech) something.
He was shorter than everyone else
and, I think, he was already
kind of like put aside
'cause they were saying that
they think he had alcohol
given to him as he was a
baby so that made him weird.
So, all along, he wasn't
like everyone else.
So, he wasn't a, like, no one
accepted him for who he was
but whenever he got famous, or whatever,
people began to accept him.
(inaudible talking)
- Huh?
- He wasn't able to conform,
is that what you're saying?
- Yeah, I don't think
he was able to conform
because no one accepted
him for who he was,
except for Helmholtz.
- I think if someone
else was in his position,
like read, even like saw a book,
they probably wouldn't even
try to read the way he did.
They were so used to not, I
don't know, not having books.
I don't think the same thing
would happen to somebody else.
It kind of reminds me of,
I don't know if you guys
have seen the movie, "The Book of Eli"?
How, the entire time, he's
trying to hide the Bible
because that one guy wants the Bible
because he wants control over everybody.
Because like, if he has,
like everything in the Bible,
he could like tell people certain things
and they would just listen to
him so he could be a master.
Like, in this book, how
everybody, like the Controllers
just want control over everybody
and without books, like,
I think it's just another
type of their control.
- That's a good example.
- Also, if you think
about it, present day,
a lot of people don't
even read books anymore.
They mostly know that they
can (inaudible speech)
and you can watch the movies instead.
There is also technology where
you can learn about something
without even actually
having to read the book.
So, do you think in a
way, that's kind of like
the same way of eliminating,
how they did in the story
and how they eliminate books
and there's more technology
is like a weakness?
Today, you know, we're
all about technology
so we eliminate more books
and there's more movies
and more technology.
- Real quick, I wanna throw in one scene
that I want you guys to think about, also.
You just brought up a point about
if people in the world today
saw these books, would they
even know what to do with them?
What would they think about them?
We do have a point in "Brave
New World" where someone
does see a book that isn't used to seeing
these type of books and responds to it.
When Helmholtz looks at
the Shakespeare that John has.
So, what did you make
of Helmholtz's response
to Shakespeare?
And what do you think that maybe suggests
about people's attitudes
in the World State?
Especially since, the Helmholtz
would represent, I guess,
an enlightened view
point in the World State.
You remember the scene
that I'm talking about?
- Yeah (background chatter).
- Yeah, he started off by
laughing at it and didn't,
later on in the scene,
he kind of hid the fact
that he had read it and that
he knew what was going on?
- I'm just wondering where it all
- It's page 183.
(bell ringing)
- Page 184 says, the second paragraph,
like third or fourth line,
"Helmholtz said listen to the
"scenes of the world first
meeting with a puzzled interest."
I mean, I guess being
the enlightened thinker,
Helmholtz is kinda curious about it,
and wanted to know more.
But at the same time,
he had that conformity
which was kinda scaring him away from it.
Cuz he didn't want to
get in trouble, I guess.
- He doesn't really seem to
understand what's going on in
"Romeo & Juliet" because
at the bottom of page 184,
same page we saw him laughing about it
because he didn't understand
why the mother and father
are trying to force the daughter
on someone she didn't want.
So, I mean, it just kind of
shows how different things were.
- I guess that goes back to
the differences in society
between then and now.
For now and the future.
- Like to do the last
comments about John or Bernard
comparing and contrasting?
- I come up with something that
didn't really get mentioned
John, the reason he's an individual is
'cause he was born, he was
like literally, born
and grew up on the reservation.
Bernard, the reason he's an individual is
because of his physical stature.
So, Bernard is an individual
because of physically,
but John is different
because of who he is.
He was born like that,
so that's what makes,
they're two different people
in individuality standard.
And that's why, I thought
that Bernard was so easy to
go back to conformity,
because the only thing
that made him different
was his height.
And that's why John couldn't
because of who he was.
- I thought Bernard was
the person that John would be
if John had been born and
raised in his World State
where Bernard had.
The only thing that made
John different is that he
spent so much time on the reservation
where everyone's different.
They value individuality.
- You had some good ideas,
just to kind of wrap up
with that last question.
Something to think about also,
you guys kind of hit it on this,
essentially what we have
is two characters in
Bernard and John that both do not fit
into their communities.
Right?
And the world is saying
everything is designed
to fit exactly, and if you don't fit,
then you're removed from that situation.
And, the Savage Reservation, you are
basically shamed out of that group.
Now, that's the way John,
he's trying to interact
but because of his mother
and because of his birth,
he is shamed out of it.
But notice whenever John
goes to the World State,
and Bernard takes him and becomes
a celebrity because of it.
All the sudden, Bernard is very happy
to be part of the World State.
So, once Bernard can actually conform
and gain advantage from
that type of society,
he's more than happy to continue on in it.
John, though, being the way he is,
he's never had the opportunity to
conform to any kind of society
and he still has that
shame culture inside of him
that he continues to
live by the whole time
he's in the World State, right?
So, that's something to think about too,
is not only are they
isolated when they are born
and different.
Then what happens, when all the sudden,
one of them can conform
and can be a valued
member of that society,
which John sort of is,
but it's more for him being
strange and weird and exotic,
then it is him being a person
and being brought into it.
Guys, that was a great first half.
What I need you guys to
do in the center circle is
go ahead and log in to your computers.
Outside circle people,
jot down any last minute
ideas you want on your paper responses.
And then in just a minute, we'll switch.
(quiet talking)
- So, now we're taking notes,
as well as having the
competition on there?
- Correct, and did that
go ok for outside folks?
- Yeah.
- It was ok to do both?
- We can still take notes while we're
on the inner circle, right?
- Oh, sure, absolutely.