- [Teacher] We have been talking about
being a good speaker and a good listener.
And in class, your teacher had you do an
activity in your classroom where you sat
across the way from a student and you read
them a paper that you had written about
dingoes. And then you had to stand up in
front of the class and you had to present
that. Do you remember that? Okay. So we
talked about what it sounds like to be a
good speaker and what it looks like to be
a good listener, and your teacher and I
worked on a rubric, and you got a grade
for some different things about speaking.
Do you remember what any of those things
were that you got a grade on? Do you
remember what she was looking for?
- Posture.
- [Teacher] Posture. What do you mean by
posture?
- Not moving around.
- [Teacher] Okay. So when you're standing
up in front of the class, what would you
look like?
- Standing straight.
- [Teacher] Okay.
- Not leaning against the wall.
- [Teacher] Okay, good. Do you remember what else
we talked about being a good speaker looks like?
- Voice.
- [Teacher] Okay. What about your voice?
What should your voice do?
- Use your presentation voice.
- [Teacher] Yeah, like a presentation
voice. Does it sound like this? What does
a presentation voice sound like?
- Kind of loud, but not like an outside
voice.
- [Teacher] Yeah, kind of loud, but not
screaming, right? I like how you said not
an outside voice. All right. What else for
speaking? Do you remember what else?
One of them, I know, didn't really have to do
with speaking, but it had more to do about
your report. And it was did your report
make sense? Right? Did what you write make
sense? What about if I read my report
really slow? Is that good?
- I can't remember...
- [Teacher] It starts with an "F".
Fl-...
- Fluency.
- [Teacher] Fluency. Good. And what does
that mean?
- You're not reading slow or too fast.
- [Teacher] Good, not too slow, not too
fast, just right. Okay. So we have posture,
voice, makes sense, fluency, do you
remember what the last one was?
You're not doing it right now.
- Eye contact.
- [Teacher] Good. All right. You want to
make eye contact, right. Right. So when
you're reading, you want to be able to do
what?
- See the people.
- [Teacher] Yeah, look at the
audience, right? Kind of look over your
paper and make eye contact with people.
Okay, now, if I'm a good listener, if I'm
the person sitting in the audience, how
can I show my classmates that I'm being a
good listener?
- No distractions.
- [Teacher] Okay. So, don't distract them.
What else?
- Don't be distracted by someone else.
- [Teacher] Okay.
- [inaudible]
- [Teacher] So you want to focus on the
speaker. All right. How can you show them
that you're focused on them. How would
they know?
- Look at them.
- [Teacher] Yeah, look at them. Right?
Okay, look at the speaker. And what else?
What about at the end, when they're done?
- Ask questions.
- [Teacher] Good. Ask questions. Anything
else?
- Sit up straight.
- [Teacher] Okay. Good. Could you tell them,
maybe, how they did? What do we call that?
Like feedback? What they did well
on, or maybe what they could do better?
Right? Okay. Put a star next to the ones
that you think you already do a good job
at. What do you think you do a good job
at? Okay. You're focused on the speaker.
All right, you sit up straight. Okay. You
don't distract others. That's good. Okay.
Now, out of these two, which one do you
think you need to work on? Which one could
you do a better job? That one. Okay. So
maybe you could ask more questions at the
end? Okay. All right. What about speaking?
Which ones do you think you do a good job
at already?
- Posture.
- [Teacher] Okay. You do a good job on
that one.
- Make sense.
- [Teacher] Mm-hmm.
- Eye contact.
- [Teacher] Mm-hmm. Okay, so out of your
voice and fluency, which one do you think
you could do better? Which one could you
work on?
- The voice.
- [Teacher] Voice. All right. So what do
you think you need to do better with your
voice?
- Speak up louder.
- [Teacher] Speak up louder? Maybe a
little bit closer to, like, that
presentation voice. Okay. On your rubric,
it was what, five, four, three, two, one?
Do you remember what you got on your
volume?
- Three.
- [Teacher] A three, okay. So Miss Welch
thought you could do a little better too,
so maybe next time you could get a four or
a five. Okay. So we have been talking
about famous African Americans, and you
had said that Walter Payton was somebody
that you had thought was interesting.
Right? All right. So we are going to look
at some information about Walter Payton,
and then, see if we can maybe do better on
asking questions, and maybe, working on
your volume. Okay?
- Cool.
- [Teacher] Okay. So, Austin,
the other day, you and I met and we did a
videotape of ourselves giving a little
speech about Walter Payton, and the first
one was I was speaking and you were
videotaping me. And then we flipped it,
and I videotaped you. So what I want to do
is have us watch those and see how they
turned out. And then we're going to use
this rubric that you use in your classroom
to kind of grade ourselves and see how we
did and talk about what we can do better
in the future. Okay? So we looked up some
facts about Walter Payton, and let's watch
my speech first. And I want you to be
thinking about while you watch me, how did
I do on eye contact? How did I do on my
volume? How was my fluency? Did it make
sense? And how was my posture? Okay, on a
scale of one to five, five being,
"Woo-hoo, Miss Suzer, you did a great
job," and one meaning, "Miss Suzer, I
didn't even see that at all." Okay? All
right, you ready? All right. Let's see how
I did.
Walter Payton was one of the best running
backs in the NFL. He played for the Bears
after going to college in Mississippi.
Sweetness has over 110 questions. But he
died in 1999 of liver cancer. He's one of
the best football players of all time. I
wish I could have seen him play. He was my
favorite football player.
All right. So let's see. What do you
think? Do you want to use purple or blue?
You want to be purple? Okay. So how do you
think I did on eye contact? What do you
think? You think a four? Okay, why do you
think a four? Did I give much eye contact?
- No.
- [Teacher] No? Oh, you're saying yes? I
only saw myself look up once, so I'm going
to give myself a two. I don't think I did
a very good job. You're too nice. Alright.
How was my volume? Pretty good? Okay. I
think I'll agree with you there. How was
my fluency or my rate? Good? Okay. I think
I'm going to give myself a four because
there were kind of parts where I thought
maybe I could have talked a little faster.
I don't know. All right. Did it make sense
what I said? Yeah? Okay. And how was my
posture? Was I standing up straight,
looking ahead. Okay. I wasn't like swaying
or rocking or anything? All right, so it
looks like, overall, I think I need to do
better on eye contact. And you thought I
could probably do a little better on eye
contact. And I think I could do a little
better on my fluency. I think I could have
maybe spoke a little bit faster. It
sounded like I was kind of in slow motion.
Okay. So now, let's watch how you did. And
then we'll grade you. Okay? All right, so
here you are.
- [inaudible dialogue as they watch video on laptop ].
- [Teacher] Okay. Let's see. All
right. How do you think your eye contact
was? A one? Why did you give yourself a
one?
- Because I didn't really look up.
- [Teacher] You didn't look up at all, did
you? Were you looking at your paper? What
were you concentrating on?
- Paper.
- [Teacher] The paper? Okay. Yeah, I would
say, it would be good, maybe, if you held
your paper down at your belly button,
right, and then you could look up. All
right. How was your volume? Not evident?
Okay. I'm going to give you a two and a
half for your volume because we could kind
of hear you. I think the reason we
couldn't hear you is because you had the
paper in front of your face. I think your
voice might have gone out a little bit
more. All right. How was your fluency, or
your rate? What do you think?
- I didn't hear myself at all.
- [Teacher] Okay. All right. I
thought it wasn't bad at all. I thought it
was pretty good because when I could hear
you, I thought it was probably like a
three and a half or a four. You weren't
reading really fast. You were reading so
that I could understand you. It was just
kind of hard to hear. All right. Do you
think your facts made sense? Why did you
give yourself a two?
- I don't know. I had some [inaudible]
in there and... I don't know.
- [Teacher] All right. Because you could
only hear parts of it? You think if your
volume had been better, you could have
heard more? Okay. All right. I'm going to
give you a four because I think it made
sense. All right. What about your posture?
How was your posture? Man, you're being
hard on yourself. Why did you give
yourself a one?
- Because I wasn't, I was like...
- [Teacher] Wiggling around a
little bit?
- Yeah.
- [Teacher] Okay. Well, I'm not going to
be that hard. I'm going to give you a
three. Okay, so if we were going to do
this again, maybe in front of your class,
or in front of your teacher, or something,
what would you do differently next time?
Now that you've seen yourself, what would
you do differently? Maybe the things you
got ones on, right? Okay. So, maybe
looking up, over your paper. Maybe your
volume. Yep. Maybe working on your fluency
or your rate, maybe a little faster,
right? What about your posture, what would
you do differently?
- Stand straight.
- [Teacher] Okay. Try to stand still. All
right. So, it looks like we have a couple
things we could work on, right, for next
time. Okay. Sounds good.