♪ [music] ♪
- So, we go back, remember this. Do not
breathe at the end of a measure unless you
have a rest. Okay? What's happening is
things are getting not broken up. Another
example of that would be measure 16 to 17.
You would not want to breathe at the end
of 16. Now, I want to go back to 13, and I
want you to do what we did yesterday,
where we changed all counted eighth notes
to sixteenths and we get rid of ties. So
what that does at 13 is it should da, da,
da, da, da, da, da... da, da, da, da, da,
da... da, da, daa, da, da, da, da... da,
da, da, da, da, da, da, da, dum. Okay?
It's kind of funny to do that on the bass
drum, so just play the regular part on the
bass drum, okay?
- I can try to.
- Nah, I'd rather you not, because it's
going to muffle-- it's going to kind of
muddy up what everyone else is doing. Try
it at 13, everybody. Da, da, da, da, da,
da, da. Working on accents. One, two, and
ready, and go.
♪ [music] ♪
Look at measure 15. Da, da, daa, da, da,
da, da. What's happening is some of you
are changing 15 to this. Tell me what's
wrong with this.
♪ [music] ♪
Anybody recognize what's wrong with
that? Adrian?
- [Adrian] You played four.
- Yeah, I played four sixteenth notes, and
then I played a note on beat four. It's
got a one and two, three e and up. Listen
again, here's the correct way. Oops, wrong
finger.
♪ [music] ♪
Listen again.
Try that. Measure 15. One and two and
ready and go.
♪ [music] ♪
Again. More accent. That last note's
really short, and it's really strong. One,
two, 15, and play.
♪ [music] ♪
Now, play it the way it's written, but
feel it the way you just played it. That
will give you the perfect subdivision of
the dotted eighth sixteenth note. One,
two, ready and go, and...
♪ [music] ♪
Okay, see how it places it very crisply.
Let's go back to 13. Play it. Break it down into
the sixteenths. Da, da, da, da, da, da,
da. Ready 13, we're going to go all the
way through 20. One and two and ready and
play, and...
♪ [music] ♪