- [Boy in white] More important, 'cause
their friend Maser-- [sic] something
died the day before, and they
stayed in the village for
that long. They didn't have
to stay, but they decided
to stay. They didn't have to
do that, but they just chose
to do that because they
felt it was more important.
- [Teacher] Well, and it may have been
a choice for safety also,
if they stay with him. If
they run to another village,
they may be, you know, picked off.
- [Girl in striped shirt] Trying to stick
to the customs that they are so used to,
like back in normal life, and
stuff like that. So, trying
to get back in that. But,
the fact that they did wait
kept them from their real life,
like their parents, and stuff.
- [Teacher] But saved their lives.
- [Girl in striped shirt] Yeah.
Okay. Emily and Simon. Simon?
- [Teacher] Emily.
- [Girl in striped shirt] Emily and Spencer, I mean.
- [Boy in yellow] Simon? (laughs)
- [Girl in striped shirt] That's her last name.
- [Boy in white] Do you believe the boys
were right for getting mad
at whatever his name is after
they got to the village,
and blaming him for missing?
- [Girl in blue] I think anyone would get mad.
They need to get it out on someone.
- [Boy in yellow] What do you mean by
being right to get mad?
- [Boy in white] Do they have, like...
- [Boy in yellow] A valid purpose?
- [Boy in white] A valid reason for getting mad.
- [Boy in yellow] I mean, yeah.
- [Girl in blue] They were probably just
mad out of frustration.
- [Boy in yellow] If you would have went in
with them before, like earlier,
before the rebels attacked,
they wouldn't have been able
to see their families. So,
that's what their drive has been
for the past couple
months, or however long
they've been running. It's to
get back to their families.
Even if they would have
died, I mean. That's what he
was saying, is that he was
mad at him, at Dishmrael [sic]
for holding him back, because
he could have seen his family,
- [Boy in white] He would have died.
- [Boy in yellow] But then, later on
when his mind cooled down, he was like,
yeah well, he saved my life,
'cause I would have been killed.
- [Boy in white] It was probably
like an in-the-moment thing.
- [Girl in blue] I think in that
kind of situation, you always look
for someone to blame.
- [Girl in striped shirt] 'Cause there is
no way he could have known soldiers
were gonna attack them, so we
should hurry, and go see them.
He thought they had time
to go and see their family.
Like, let's stop and
rest, and stuff like that.
There's no way he could have
known that was gonna happen,
so they can't really
blame him, but they need
to blame someone.
- [Girl in blue] Yeah.
- [Girl in striped shirt] I'd want
to punch someone too.
- [Girl in blue] I'd be so mad if
that happened to me. I understand
why they would blame him,
but looking back on it...
- [Teacher] And how does his age impact that, also?
- [Girl in blue] Well he's not...
- [Boy in white] He' not really
old enough to really think about it.
- [Girl in blue] All he's thinking about is his family.
- [Girl in dark hoodie] With maturity,
you think before you act,
but as a little kid, you just act,
and don't know the consequences.
- [Teacher] Well, and he has no life
experience to prepare him
for this at all. There's another aspect.
- [Girl in striped shirt] And he used to
follow Junior, and everything he did,
but now that Junior's gone,
he doesn't even have that.
- [Teacher] Right. Exactly. Okay, keep going.
- [Boy in yellow] War is hell.
- [Boy in black] Oh yeah, you can...
Sorry about that.
- [Teacher] It's okay.
- [Boy in black] So, want to go, Kaylee?
- [Kaylee] Okay.
- [Boy in gray] Ask the question.
- [Kaylee] The question: Girda is
a young woman at the time
of the book, and so was
Valentino and Wutuzuwut [sic].
How do they change through
the course of the book,
due to the tragic events in their lives.
- [Boy in black] I think they're
forced to grow up real fast,
because of all the pressures.
At the time, I mean,
Valentino doesn't know
his age, but let's say,
like 15 and 20; and when,
I haven't read the end
of this book, but she
comes home to America,
and so does Valentino,
and they just come over;
and even though they're like
19, they're forced to be
like a 40-year-old. So,
it's kinda weird coming back
to America, and trying to
enjoy all the child pleasures.
- [Boy in gray] Yeah, the whole event
just kinda makes them, you know,
kinda step it up a bit. If
something like this happens
to you, you don't easily
forget it. It becomes more
of a part of you.
It kinda takes out who
you really are inside.
- [Kaylee] Yeah, it shapes you.
- [Boy in gray] Yeah.
- [Teacher] Well, and how did the
stages in their life coincide.
That's a good question, Kaylee.
- [Kaylee] Well, first of all, genocide,
I thought, was basically,
kind of done the same, so it
was usually like they lost
their families, they're
forced to go out on their own,
they're forced to make a
life for themselves. And both
of them kind of think, or know,
that their parents are dead.
And so, they kind of use their
families in a way to keep
them going, and just like
other people in their lives
that have motivated them,
'cause I think Ile [sic], or,
I don't know how to say her
name. She kind of motivated
Girda to kind of stay in the
camp with her, and have maybe
a friend there, where with
Abek's [sic] family, she wouldn't
really have a friend, she'd
just have, like she'd owe it
to their family to do things for them.
And then with Achek [sic], he
had William K. to help him--
- [Boy in gray] Just had a friend to make it through.
- [Kaylee] Yeah.
- [Teacher] So they both had a
strong friend. What kind of life
did they both live before disaster struck?
- [Boy in gray] They both had the
perfect, ideal family life, you know.
They were happy. They were all
together. It was, you know,
like what would happen in a
Disney movie, pretty much.
Everything's kinda perfect.
And then, something happens
in the first. Both, in the
person that happens to meet,
their family ties are cut.
And their survival depends
on whether they can kinda
ban together with the people
around them, and kinda
grow, and become stronger.
- [Kaylee] Yeah. I think...
- [Boy in black] Yeah.
- [Kaylee] No, you go.
- [Boy in black] Okay. They were just,
I mean, they were forced to grow up.
And they just lived, like Ryan
said, like the ideal life,
with their family, or whatever.
But once their parents left,
they had to find a friend,
or someone to group with,
in order to--
- [Teacher] Well, what were they
replacing? What were they replacing,
with William K and Ile [sic]?
- [Kaylee] Yeah. They established a family
without being blood related.
- [Boy in black] They just had
to make it through by that.
It's 'cause if you don't have
motivation, then you're not
going to get through
things, so even though
they didn't know that
their... I mean, they assumed
their parents were dead, but
they didn't know for sure.
'Cause on page 80 of this, I
mean, she said that she never
saw her father again. But,
just to know that their parents
are alive, and they just
want to regroup with them
at the end keeps them motivated and alive.
- [Teacher] Not knowing. They
both have that in common.
- [Boy in black] Right.
- [Teacher] Assuming that they're dead,
but not really knowing for sure.
- [Boy in black] Just to keep them
motivated to survive,
so it's a good tactic.
- [Teacher] So what is a really
simple message that we can take
from that, from both of their stories?
What do you need in your life?
- [Boy in black] Motivation.
- [Kaylee] You need family. You need
some kind of family unit to...
- [Boy in black] Survive. Or friends.
- [Boy in gray] Everyone needs like
someone to kinda like go to,
and they can depend on, no
matter what the situation is.
- [Boy in black] Right, and if you're
going to friends a lot of time,
at least in like a high
school, or whatever;
you go to friends with questions,
instead of your family,
or whatever, sometimes you'll
get the wrong side of view
on things, and it will
change your life drastically.
'Cause your friends determine
how your high school
is gonna be, determines how
the rest of your life...
- [Boy in gray] But also, you
got a different perspective,
'cause your family doesn't
necessarily know what's going on
in your own high school.
- [Boy in black] Yeah, so it's
good to get both, but family
is more important 'cause you
can count on them more usually.
- [Kaylee] And they're older and
wiser. You need that
kind of like wise person, 'cause
my mom knows more than I do
or my friends.
- [Boy in black] Yeah.
- [Teacher] But you need those
relationships as connections, right?
- [Boy in black] Right, to keep motivated.
- [Teacher] Both of those stories show that really,
literally life and death
situations; those connections
with other humans. It is a
human basic need that we have
to make those connections.
Or you cannot survive.
I think both of those
stories... That's a really
good question, in looking
at the stages. It also shows
globally... Globally, what
can we say about families?
At the beginning of the
story... you were talking about,
it's like a Disney movie, right?
- [Boy in gray] Yeah.
- [Teacher] So what can we say about families
literally around the world?
- [Kaylee] They're all usually
together. Nobody ever leaves
their children when their
toddlers to go find where,
like how they're supposed
to live, and like,
what's good and bad. You
usually nurture your kids 'til
they're about nineteen, and
then they go off to college.
I think that's just how it
is everywhere. It may not be
that way in some places, but
you usually have schooling,
and then you go off, and then
you figure out for yourself,
once you've got a base.
- [Boy in black] Yeah, they're
usually pretty perfect or ideal,
until like a third party, like
Nazis or the Arabians come in
and just wipe that out, and
changes a lot drastically
to where they have to depend
on themselves, and I guess
their friends, since
they didn't have family.
- [Teacher] And that family unit
seems to lend to safety,
even if you're living in
Sudan or if you're living
in Poland. The children
both at the beginning
feel very safe in their lives, right?
- [Boy in black] Right.
- [Kaylee] And if nobody knows you,
what makes you... if you die
who would care? That's what I
would think. Like, if nobody
cared about me, or nobody knew who I was.
- [Boy in black] That's, what,
a lot of suicidal thoughts...
- [Kaylee] Yeah.
- [Boys](laughter)
- [Kaylee] I was just thinking.
I don't think that, but I'm
just saying, if I had nobody
to be like I care about you.
You need to stay alive,
or like your parents.
There wouldn't be a reason to live.
- [boy in black] Yeah, but like
in those stories, like they find
symbolic fixtures, or whatever.
I think in both, yeah,
the moon. They look at the moon
and they see, they just see
the moon, and it's like their
kinda friend. But they also
hope that the moon will find
their parents somewhere,
or wherever they are,
'cause they don't know.
- [Boy in gray] Yeah, their parents
are looking at the same thing
that they're seeing, kinda.
- [Boy in black] Yeah, so it's
kinda like, right there,
keeping them together.
- [Teacher] And what's funny,
is that's a main... the moon
is a main symbol in a long way gone.
- [Boy in black] Yeah.
- [Teacher] And he refers to that also.
- [Kaylee] I think 'cause the moon can
be seen anywhere on earth.
It's a connection, I
think, somewhere. Yeah.
- [Boy in black] Yeah, totally.
- [Boy in gray] It's kinda like the
bright light in darkness. You know,
the night, it's a pictch
black, but the moon's shining.
You know, kinda there no matter what.
Good. Okay, keep going.
- [Boy in hoodie] And the German's
are just coming in,
and everything's getting really bad.
And like going back to their
past, and showing it as such
a nice place. What she does,
is she ends up showing how much
darker it is by comparison.
- [Teacher] Okay, what was the question?
- [Boy in black] How does the author
implement setting to contrast,
good and evil? How is it affected?
- [Teacher] Okay.
- [Boy in black] ...purpose. And we just
finished talking about how
it shows the atrocities to be even darker,
because it's happening in this nice place.
- [Girl in yellow] But she's forced
to saying the dark side of things,
'cause she's forced into her
basement, where it's all dark,
and you know, there's mildew
on the wall, and it's flooded,
and it's just really gross
down there. And that's what's
happening outside of the
happy little hometown that she
grew up in. And then, her
childhood is marked with flowers
and the sunny days. You know,
running with her friends,
and chasing butterflies, and
eating sweets. And it's just
really happy, and bright,
and cheery. And so,
there's a major contrast.
- [Teacher] And, as you go into the
book, does that darkness continue?
Or is it broken by light?
How does she portray darkness
and light even when she goes to the camps?
- [Boy in hoodie] There's...
- [Boy in black] Go ahead, but I have an answer.
- [Teacher] OK. (laughs)
- [Boy in hoodie] At least up to the point
where we've read, she's kind of
reached a climax of how bad
things are when her parents
were taken away from her and
everything. Arthur's letters
stopped coming. And that's
kind of the climax from how far
we've gotten, where the
darkness is. So now it's about
finding the good things
that are in that darkness.
- [Girl in glasses] Right. I think she has
little flashes of good things,
and the smallest of things to
us brings such hope to her,
of a bright future. But it
is surrounded by darkness.
- [Teacher] And in the camp, did
she talk about physically
light and dark also?
- [Boy in black] Like the dramas,
and she wrote plays;
And they had fun there.
- [Girl in glasses] The single light
shining in the dark room .
- [Teacher] Do you have anything to add, Abbey?
Can you think of times
when she talked about light?
Physically, light in the
camps? I was trying to think.
And how does she portray it?
'Cause that is an interesting
motif in the book, the light and dark.
And it will continue to play a part.
Which camp is she in at the middle part?
- [Boy in black] She's in the, I can't
pronounce it. It's the first one,
where she's, they're
sewing, they're weaving.
- [Teacher] So they're at the looms, right?
- [Girl in yelow] Yeah, they're at the looms.
- [Boy in hoodie] Did she pass
through Auschwitz?
Or was that the one, she was in jail?
I think she passed
through Volkenheim [sic]?
- [Teacher] Yeah. Does she ever get
outside? That would be a key,
at Volkenheim [sic].
- [Boy in black] Outside of the camp itself?
- [Teacher] Just outside, in the outside.
- [Girl in yellow] Well, here's a
reference to outside. She talks about how
the night was starry and
beautiful. "From Heirgonk [sic] I
could see the hill through a
window. Slowly, the full moon
rose..." So that is like a light
in the darkness, literally.
Because the stars... the
moon and the stars are
the brightest things at night
in the sky, and just, her
finding that comfort in that,
also shows really extreme
light and dark.
- [Teacher] But her comfort comes
at night, in the darkness.
And she has one source of
light. So keep looking for those
motifs of light and dark 'cause
they play a part throughout.
Have any of you gotten
past the halfway point?
- [Girl in glasses] Yeah.
- [Girl in yellow] Yeah, we've gotten
a little bit past.
- [Teacher] In the march, you know
that becomes very important.
Alright, good. Good job.
Alright, you guys! Bell's gonna ring.
Keep your questions for tomorrow