(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Does that include slaves?
- [Student] Yes
- [Teacher] Does that include women?
- [Student] Yes.
- [Teacher] Okay.
- [Student] So how
are we supposed to take
uneducated people's opinions when they
obviously don't know what's gonna happen?
- [Student] Because a lot of people in Russia--
I mean, if the Russian's knew how to read,
they would write a song.
If they knew what was going on,
and they were smart enough,
they would obviously
write a song about it.
- [Teacher] I think
John Locke had one more
thing to say, is that right?
- [Student] Yes, okay, and to answer your question
about the government.
The government was created
to protect people's rights,
it wasn't created for you to abuse power
and just do what you think you need to do,
they are only for them,
and it's not doing what
it needs to do, then yeah,
the people do have the right.
- [Student] People
aren't dead, so obviously
I'm doing what I need to
do, and I'm protecting them.
- [Student] If that's all you care about,
then that would just be easy
not to let people die.
- [Student] Obviously
they're not having problems
where their lives threatened.
We have all these, like...
If you're, wherever you live...
Anyways, wherever you
live, if your king or queen
wasn't doing what they
thought to protect you guys,
and you had all these invaders coming in,
then you could argue being mad at them
because they're not protecting
you and doing their job.
- [Student] That's when
you know they're upset.
- [Student] Plus, you're
saying that your people
aren't educated, but
they're educated enough
to know what their rights are,
and how they should be treated, so...
- [Student] I mean, you can
think you should be treated
in a certain way, but I
could say I think I should
be able to slide on this floor right now,
but I might not know if I
slide on this floor right now,
I'm gonna die.
But because I'm not educated
in that kind of way.
But your king or queen is
educated in that kind of way,
so they're not gonna let
you do stuff like that.
- [Student] We're not
asking for stuff like that,
we're asking for our natural rights.
- [Student] I know that they,
(Background Chatter)
What's the word? The end result?
Conclusion. I know the
conclusion of you guys
getting your natural
rights, and the way that
you guys are acting for them.
In a way, I'm gonna get you guys
what you guys need to get, your conclusion
is gonna be a whole lot
better than what you guys
are hoping.
- [Student] So what's the point of
having your natural rights
if you're going to abuse the law?
- [Student] It doesn't mean you're
going to abuse the law,
it just means that you're
gonna be more cooperative
towards the law.
- [Student] You're attributed to
a beggar if they don't
give you your natural rights.
It's like a two-way type thing.
- If they give it to
you, then you're gonna
be happy about it, and
you're gonna want to
follow them and listen to them.
Instead of trying to
revolt and kick them out
if they're not gonna give it to you.
- [Teacher] Alright, so we say
government is a good thing,
bad thing, or kind of in between.
Let's go around the room real quick.
What would you guys say?
- [Student] I would say government
is a positive thing
because it stopped some starving,
and it keeps everything in place.
- [Teacher] Okay, good.
- [Student] We're in between.
Because it's there to protect your rights,
but if they're not gonna
be there to protect you,
then they shouldn't be there at all.
- [Teacher] Okay, so it has
to be done in the correct way?
- [Student] Government is a good thing.
- [Teacher] Any explanation why?
- [Student] Because if you don't have a government,
then you aren't organized,
and if you're not organized,
then you're, like, chickens
would be in your home.
(Background Chatter)
- [Student] We think that philosophers,
they write what they feel about us,
and they don't do anything about it,
and they don't understand
where we're coming from.
"You philosophers are lucky men.
You write on paper, and paper is patient.
Unfortunate Empress that I am,
I write on the susceptible
skins of living beings."
Meaning that they write on paper because
they can put out they opinion like that,
but we have to be responsible
for all the people
in our country, and we're trying
to do what's best for them.
- [Student] In your opinion.
(Laughter)
- [Teacher] Frederick?
- [Student] We think government is interesting
because we need a
government to be organized.
But government also
does a lot of bad stuff.
- [Student] We think the government
is completely necessary
along with religion, because
it brings unity to the people.
- [Student] And I think the laws and
religion kind of go hand in hand
because...
I wouldn't consider myself a Christian,
but others probably would,
because of certain stuff I write in books,
that's why they consider me as a heretic,
but the bible says, "Thou shall not kill."
Killing someone is also against the law.
Thou shall not steal is
also against the law.
- [Student] I feel the government is good
if it uses the right power,
basically for their rights and things.
As long as--
It should be there, we
feel it should be there,
but it needs to be used appropriately.
- [Student] We believe, sort of,
that the government is a positive.
If you didn't have a
government as a base structure
for your country. If you didn't...
The government perhaps is a positive.
Due to the fact that the government,
helps you if you need it to an extent,
I agree with Catherine
the Great in the fact that
it sort of really helps
with the territory.
I've been interviewed by many people,
and specifically saying, to
many people I've said it,
that I'm capable of
saying whatever I want.
So my country is there, and
(Background Chatter)
I get to do whatever I want
- [Teacher] If you were the king,
you'd do whatever you want to.
Theoretically.
Alright, Voltaire.
- [Student] Pretty much, the
government is an abomination.
I mean, there's way more bad
and nasty leaders
than there are good, lawful public leaders
that do good stuff.
Too many leaders take
advantage of their people
in their kingdoms, so I
think they should just
all go away, start over
with enlightened, total...
(Background Chatter)
- [Student] What about slavery?
- [Teacher] What do you think about slavery?
- [Student] What do you people think about slavery?
- [Teacher] What about slavery.
Anybody have an opinion?
Is slavery good bad or otherwise?
- [Student] I wouldn't say slavery is a negative.
then again, I wouldn't say
that it's a bad thing either.
(Background Chatter)
I guess you could say, mostly
slavery came from Austria
due to the fact that
if you get in trouble,
with another country, and
they sand to the Austria
you're pretty much going to be a slave
for the rest of your life.
You pretty much work for them.
You work for the Pope himself,
and you work for the Roman Emperor.
- [Teacher] Voltaire?
- [Student] I think slavery is a necessary evil.
- [Teacher] A necessary evil?
(Background Chatter)
- [Student] Well, we disagree
with (Background chatter),
because we see everyone
as equals,
and think everyone should
be treated equally,
and it's part of their natural
rights such as freedom.
- [Teacher] Exactly, that would
be considered one of
their natural rights.
(Background Chatter)
-[Teacher] Rousseau?
- [Teacher] Serfs, which were similar
to slaves, very good.
Last comment there,
Thomas Hobbes?
- [Student] I don't think
we really have an opinion
on slavery, but if the
king decided to have
slavery in the country, I
think we should respect that
and do it for the
betterment of the country.
- [Teacher] Respect the authority
of the king?
- [Student] No piling up...
(Background Chatter)
...because that's what
slavery is there for.
- [Teacher] Okay. Very good.
Any last minute comments?
I think we're almost out of
time for our salon discussion.
I heard a lot of good ideas.
Does anybody have any last minute comments
that they want to add?
Yes, Frederick?
- [Student] A lot of
things that we have to say
I didn't get...
Three things of everybody's opinion.
All you guys are really self...
You're not sinners or anything.
For lack of better words.
And I wouldn't read them,
meaning I would probably
do anything to get support from my people,
and I'd do anything for my people.
Like my dad would do anything for me,
he raised me well.
And slavery and natural
rights and all that
mumbo-jumbo shouldn't be from you,
because you're not them.
You're not, just as you're not Voltaire,
and I'm not Thomas.
So you can't overrule
anybody else, it's not right.
- [Teacher] Very good.
Excellent job, ladies and gentlemen.
Thank you for attending
our little salon here.
Hopefully we learned some new ideas,
and got to hear some
other opinions of people
throughout Europe, so
let's give yourselves
a little round of applause.
(Applause)
Alright, you are now done with the salon.
You can take your little parts if you want
and put them up because you are no longer
those people, you are now
you in modern day times.
Back to modern day times.
But I do have some
questions, we are not done
with our discussion, but you
are not longer your person,
you are back to being you.
(Background Chatter)
-[Teacher] We are not done,
and I'm going to ask you
your questions now. Please listen.
What was the purpose of a salon?
We've talked about this
from what you've right here.
What was the purpose of a salon?
- [Student] Exchange ideas.
- [Teacher] Exchange ideas,
any other purposes?
- [Student] Sometimes
like, Joseph did over there,
but to find out what
people thought of you.
- [Teacher] Okay, to find out
different opinions.
Okay, maybe see something from a different
side or viewpoint.
- [Student] It was a devised to discuss music,
who gets painting time...
- [Teacher] Okay, so it has an
artistic point to it as well.
- [Student] It was just
another way for us to learn
about taking notes and stuff.
Like research on our
person and then hearing
what the other people thought.
- [Teacher] But as far as back then,
is what we're thinking about.
- [Student] Oh, back then. Oh.
- [Teacher] Yes, you were right
about what you said.
- [Student] Just to
exchange ideas and go back
until people like it.
- [Teacher] Would you say there
were effective back then?
- [All] Yes.
- [Teacher] We haven't talked about results,
we kind of left off
talking about these people
and how they talked about
things and came to the salon.
Do you think this is
going to be an effective
method of discussing?
- [Student] The
conversations we were having
with them over there,
like how they didn't think
that we were listening to what the people
were saying and how we
were just gonna stay
the way we were and stuff,
but actually they got
to hear our thinking about moving to where
we need to go, it's gonna
take them a little longer
to get there.
- [Teacher] Okay.
Do we have anything like salons today?
Do we have salons today?
- [All] Yes.
- [Teacher] What happens at salons now?
(Background Chatter)
-[Teacher] Right, so it's not so
much political all the time
in exchanging ideas
about government stuff,
but they're still kind of
socialization and gossip
going on.
Is there anything that we have in place,
or anything in our society
today which you can
discuss opinions,
especially about government
or problems that you might have in life?
- [Students] Um...
- [Teacher] Since salons don't
really go with that, but...
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] So if you have a
problem with your country
or with the government or with
something that's going on,
we don't have a salon
to go and meet like this
and talk with people, but
is there anything that
we do that?
Or any other thing?
Another way to voice your
problem, if your dissenting
and you have a different
agreement, or a disagreement
with the government, or
with anybody, anything.
What can you do?
- [Student] Don't we have press conferences?
- [Teacher] What do you mean representatives?
Write letters.
Write letters to who?
- [Student] The government.
- [Teacher] Congress, the government, okay.
- [Student] They also
have environment issues
and worldwide problems.
- [Teacher] Worldwide problems. Okay,
that's kind of similar.
Where different people come and talk about
their issues, their problems,
and maybe how to solve them.
- [Student] You kind
of have different levels
like, if you have a problem with, like,
if it's about the school,
you go to the school board.
- [Teacher] Okay.
- [Student] President,
or people who are trying
to be president, they
have the debates on TV.
- [Teacher] Okay, good.
As far as being an average
citizen, what can you do?
Say there's an issue with the world,
or an issue in our country,
or an issue in our city
that we want to see fixed,
what can we do, you think,
to maybe, go about fixing that,
or trying to get that done?
- [Student] Protest.
- [Teacher] Protest. Is that allowed?
Are we allowed to protest?
- [All] Yes.
- [Teacher] Were you allowed to protest back then?
- [Student] It depends
on where you live at.
- [Teacher] Depends on where you live.
We have a different government now, right?
Back then it was monarchy,
now it's more of a democracy.
So what we're seeing here a little bit,
a little bit different method
and a lot more opportunity.
- [Student] There's a town like...