- ... and your ideas, and we're
learning from each other, right?
Because a lot of times,
who do we learn from?
- You.
- Each other.
- You learn from me but
who else do you learn from?
- Us. - You learn from each other.
Okay, Kelly if you would move the book
away from the projector
so we can see the screen.
We're going to watch
another weather forecast,
and as you're viewing this,
I want you to pay really
close attention to how she...
- Talks.
- How she speaks. Okay.
As a good listener and a viewer,
what are some things that
we need to concentrate on
while we're watching this?
- How she, her face, her expression
and how she moves and looks.
- Okay, and how are you going to find out
if she does those things?
- By watching her?
- You're going to be watching her, okay...
Sarah?
- Watch how her body is
moving because... (inaudible)
Watch her eyes.
- Okay, catch your eye.
And I like that you said watching.
What are you doing while you're watching?
Are you just staring at the screen?
- No. You are looking at them
and you're making eye
contact, and you're looking;
you're watching their mouths
because there are people
who can't really hear, so they
would read people's mouths,
and that's really important to do.
- Anything else that you can
do while you're viewing this?
- Listening.
- Okay, and how are you
going to be listening?
We talked about this a lot.
How are we going to listen?
- With our ears and with
our whole entire bodies.
- With our whole entire bodies.
Why are we going to listen
with our whole entire body?
Naomi.
- Because if we're listening with our ears,
then our hands are up here saying,
"Oh, I've got something to say,"
then you're not really listening,
you're not really listening competently.
- All right, can you go ahead
and hit play for us, please?
Yup, just like you did yesterday.
- Good afternoon, I'm Julie
Wunder with your forecast.
47 today with mostly sunny skies.
A north wind, five to ten miles per hour.
Tonight 28, it's going
to be partly cloudy out,
and we can head to a 7-day forecast.
About a 50 percent chance
of rain transitioning over
to some snow overnight
Saturday and into Sunday.
Temperatures fall next week,
what a cold forecast we have.
Coming up at 5 o'clock,
we'll have the latest on that
possibility of snow.
- Turn and talk to your buddy. We're going
to do two right here, two, two, two...
- I noticed that under one of the clouds
we had snow instead of rain.
(inaudible)
- Turn your face...
- Okay and what kind of
body language did she use?
- She was pointing and ...
(Inaudible)
- So why do you think she
was pointing like that?
(inaudible)
- Okay.
- And because you saw her looking at you,
did that make you listen any differently?
(inaudible)
- Did it help you listen more or less?
- When she looked away,
what was she doing?
(inaudible)
- Alright, so why do you
think she wasn't doing this?
Okay like you say, she
was like. Why is that?
(Inaudible)
- Would you be listening as well
if she were making those faces?
Or would you (inaudible) her face?
- Right, not necessarily
what she was saying
but you were focusing on her expressions.
(inaudible)
- Alright guys let's come
back in three, two, and one.
Okay, you guys had some amazing things
that you saw when you
watched this little clip.
- What kind of things did you notice?
Tell me what you and your
buddy were talking about.
- We used this chart.
If she was just like there...
she was pointing at it
so then it made me understand more
but if she was just like there...
?
- [Teacher] When you
did your presentation,
what did you feel like
you were looking at?
- My poster.
- [Teacher] You looked at
your poster the whole time?
Okay, and the second time
when you did your presentation again,
you said you were really
focusing on your eye contact,
were you able to achieve that goal?
- No - [Teacher] No? Why not?
- Because I was looking
at my poster again.
- [Teacher] You say you were
looking at your poster again.
Okay, why do you think you did that?
Were you nervous?
What do you think you could've done
to ease that nervousness?
- Take a breath. - [Teacher]
Going to take a breath?
What do you guys think?
What could Adrian have done
to maybe be a little less nervous
when he was doing his presentation?
- He could think about
somewhere he was comfortable.
- Okay, think about somewhere
where's he's comfortable.
- Picture everyone else
in their underwear.
- Oh, underwear. Sarah.
- Be himself and just act
like it's just any other day.
(inaudible)
- The information we were presenting
was it a little bit more in depth
than what we usually talk about?
What do you think?
Was the topic you were
sharing a little bit,
you have a little bit
more information than
if you were just sitting
here having a conversation?
- Yeah.
- So that make some of us nervous
that we have a lot of
information trying to remember?
- Yes.
- And then, was anyone able
to get over that nervousness?
- Okay. Sarah, how were you guys able
- I followed my goals and
I just tried to be myself.
I just followed my goals
and I just had fun.
- Okay, do you want to show us part
of your presentation where you did that?
- Mhmm.
- Avril, will you move the
book away from the projector
while she gets the computer ready?
Alright, make sure you get
to a spot where you can see.
Got it?
- My project is about
Legends of the (inaudible)
I'm going to start over with Werewolves
people think that ...
I don't know why because
wolves howl at the moon
This is a werewolf, a full moon
is sometimes called a Wolf's Moon...
since its yellow (inaudible).
This one is my favorite.
It's about (inaudible)
... she calls her brother
Helius to find her sister Herse.
(inaudible)
The study of geography to the
moon is called Selenology.
Okay this is ... (inaudible)
This is vampires, vampires
are said to come out
on every moon except for new moon
I guess because they can see better.
This is a vampire person
trying to get his girlfriend
to become a vampire.
This is people, people
think (inaudible) to people
that are aggressive and
violent... (inaudible)
This is a witch from... (inaudible)
- Okay turn to your buddy for a second.
Do you think she was able; she said
she acted like she was comfortable.
Like it was just any other day.
- Yeah.
- Talk to your buddy about that.
Do you think that she
accomplished that goal?
- Yes. (inaudible)
- Because she's a pretty
funny girl, right?
Alright. Let's come back together.
Let's come back together please.
Alright. So her goal,
she said that she wanted
to be more comfortable.
And she was just going to
act like it was any other ...
- Day.
- Did she accomplish that?
- Yes.
- Okay. How do we know
that she accomplished that?
What do you think Arizona?
- [Arizona] Because she
was really comfortable
with her surroundings and
those people just wanted
to get their talking over with and done
but Sarah actually
talked like we were just
talking face to face
acting like the camera wasn't even there.
- Okay. And as a listener,
how did Sarah's confidence
make you listen better?
Did it make you listen better
or did it not make you
listen better? It did?
Okay. Why did it make
you listen better, Levin?
- Because it was fun.
- Because it was fun? Okay.
And what made it fun?
- She was acting like,
the way she was acting
- The way she was acting? Okay.
What did you think, Dillon?
- Because she's usually funny
and she was being quite funny on this.
- Okay.
- And I like to... (inaudible)
- Yup. Alright, anybody else?
- What were some other
goal that you guys created?
Sit up and join the circle please.
Alright, let's see. Someone
I haven't heard from yet.
Isabelle, what was one of your goals?
- One of my goals was
to stop making really
distracting movements
because I was like
twisting it and twirling it
and I was really nervous.
- Alright so that was the first time
you did your presentation,
you felt you were doing
too many movements.
- Yeah.
- And so your goal was to cut down on that
and why did you choose that as a goal?
- Really, when we watched my first video,
we decided that, (inaudible) she said that
she was kind of watching
that and she couldn't really
have her attention stay
on what I was saying.
- And did you agree with her?
- Mhmm.
- Okay, so what did you do
with your second presentation?
- I really was concentr...