- So can you record two on that?
(indistinct crosstalk)
- It's harder to write two.
- Remember, here, you
can use your number line
if you need it to help you.
Do you want me to turn it?
So there's the two.
Can you try to write it?
- [Girl] I did it.
(indistinct crosstalk)
- Awesome.
That looks like a two.
So was this awesome, all
right, or super bad?
- [Girl] Super bad.
- Super bad.
Why do you think it was super bad?
- [Girl] Because it's not heavy.
- Because it's not heavy.
(speaking indistinctly)
Okay, Julia, what's our second problem?
- Ow.
- [Julia] The styrofoam ball.
- The styrofoam ball.
Can you find the styrofoam ball?
(indistinct crosstalk)
Yes, that one.
We can, first we're gonna make--
(indistinct crosstalk)
This one is bigger.
How does it feel, though?
Is it round?
(indistinct crosstalk)
It does?
We're gonna be answering
questions over here.
Julia, can you let (mumbles)
make his prediction?
(indistinct crosstalk)
Which one did you pick?
- That one.
- You picked all right.
Why did you pick all right?
(indistinct crosstalk)
Because it's little.
How does it feel?
Feel it.
No, it's not heavy.
(indistinct crosstalk)
What do you think?
Is there anything that you're wondering about that?
(indistinct crosstalk)
What's next?
What do you think?
- All right again?
- You think all right, too?
(indistinct crosstalk)
Mark them all right.
You think awesome?
You think it's gonna go 15 or more?
Okay, let's see.
(speaking indistinctly)
Are you ready?
Can you pick up the tape and do it again?
Gonna get the tape.
(indistinct crosstalk)
- You're supposed to do it again.
- Because there's another space?
Yep, we're gonna actually do it again
after we do all of them one time.
Okay.
(speaking indistinctly)
(indistinct crosstalk)
Put it this way. Ivan's gonna put it in, is everyone ready?
Oh wait, you have to keep it
upside down so it can push.
Okay?
Can you try it over?
Ivan, are you ready?
Let's try one more time.
I'm gonna put this cup right in front.
One more time.
(indistinct crosstalk)
(speaking indistinctly)
Well, feel it.
(indistinct crosstalk)
Is it heavy?
That's okay. I'm gonna be right back.
(indistinct crosstalk)
Has anything surprised you so far?
(speaking indistinctly)
What happened?
The orange ball?
So what kind of push was it?
- An awesome.
- [Woman] An awesome push.
So did that surprise you?
You didn't think it was gonna go so far?
- I though it was gonna
go like (whirring noise).
- Is that where the tape went?
So you guys can pick up the tape.
Should we do the green ball?
- The green ball.
Which ball so far...
- [Girl] A zero.
- A zero?
(indistinct crosstalk)
And it didn't move at all?
- Yes.
- Why do you think it didn't move?
- Because it's so tiny.
- It's so tiny.
But does it weigh a lot?
- No.
- No, it didn't.
Do you think that's why it didn't go far?
- And it's so tiny.
And it doesn't have more mass.
- Ahh, I see.
So, should we do this again?
- Yeah.
- The super bad is
actually this one right here.
- Oh, it's so tiny.
- So feel it.
How does it feel?
(indistinct crosstalk)
Let Luka feel it.
How does it feel?
(indistinct crosstalk)
So Jacob, why don't you
make your prediction?
From all right to super bad.
What do you think, Sofia?
What did you put?
Why did you put all right?
(indistinct crosstalk)
So right there.
How far do you think it's gonna go?
(indistinct crosstalk)
What did you put, Sofia?
Sofia picked...
Luka, what do you think?
Which one do you think?
What's it gonna be?
Awesome, all right, or super bad?
Good pick, all right.
So we're gonna do it
down here on this one.
All right.
Are you ready?
Make your prediction.
And then we're gonna put it on the ground.
What do you think?
Awesome, all right, or super bad?
(indistinct crosstalk)
Who picked awesome?
Sofia, right?
(indistinct crosstalk)
Do you guys have anything that you're--
- Remember when we were...
(indistinct crosstalk)
- I do remember when we
were trying to (speaking indistinctly).
What did we find out?
What is it?
(indistinct crosstalk)
What do you think for the second ball?
(speaking indistinctly)
You think a rock is inside?
Maybe.
- If they were rocks, then
they would be so hard.
- That's true, is it really hard?
- A little.
- A little bit hard?
What do you think is inside?
Can we find out?
We can open one of these, probably.
Let's put it down first.
Everybody write it.
Jacob, are you the recorder?
What are you?
The counselor?
Are you the starter?
Okay guys, is everyone ready?
(indistinct crosstalk)
You know what? We're gonna do it one more time
so that it knocks over the cup.
(indistinct crosstalk)
We can move the tape now.
Sofia, we need you to count.
Move the cup over.
How far did it go?
- One, two, three, four, five,
six, seven, eight, nine, 10.
- Will you count again with me?
Ready?
- [Both] One, two, three,
four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, 10.
Jacob, this went 10.
Can you write 10 down?
- No!
(indistinct crosstalk)
- For the super bad, it went 10.
Yep.
- It's super awesome.
- So what do you think?
Where did it go?
Was it awesome, all right, or super bad?
- Awesome.
- All right.
- It was all right.
Why was it all right?
(indistinct crosstalk)
And is 10 more or less than 15?
Less than 15.
So that's why it's all right.
Okay guys, I'm gonna go to the next group.
Now what you're gonna do is trial two.
You're gonna do every ball one more time.
Okay? Yep.
(indistinct crosstalk)
We're gonna do it one more time.
Okay, I will be right back.
(indistinct crosstalk)
(yelling)
How's it going over here?
Has anything surprised you?
(indistinct crosstalk)
What surprised you?
Which ball didn't push it very far?
(indistinct crosstalk)
Wait, how far did it actually push?
So that means that the
cup didn't move at all?
(indistinct crosstalk)
Why do you think the cup didn't move?
Because it's so light?
Which one moved the farthest so far?
Which ball?
(indistinct crosstalk)
The orange one?
Is the orange ball really light?
(indistinct crosstalk)
How does the orange one feel?
Like it has more mass?
Is there anything you guys
are wondering about?
(indistinct crosstalk)
If they're bouncy?
Let's put this ball back.
Does that one bounce?
(indistinct crosstalk)
I wonder why not.
Okay, so what are we
putting next on your sheet?
What should you do?
(indistinct crosstalk)
Are you putting the rubber ball?
Yeah.
Are you guys all putting
that you think it's
gonna be an awesome push?
(indistinct crosstalk)
Ready?
Put tape here.
Alexandra, are you the taper?
(indistinct crosstalk)
(yelling)
- It's on the wrong side.
- No, she got it, she did it.
So move the cup over.
Now Nicholas is gonna count.
- One, two, three, four, five,
six, seven, eight, nine, 10, 11.
(indistinct crosstalk)
- Can you help write in 13?
Yeah, this one right here
has a one and a three.
Can you try writing that?
- It's gonna have one more.
- [Woman] It's gonna have one more?
So if the styrofoam ball went zero,
and the orange ball went 13,
which one is more?
- 13.
- How do you know that?
You just know that?
(indistinct crosstalk)
When you count, does it come higher?
Yes, it does?
Okay, Ivan's ball is next.
We need to do a trial shoot of which one?
(indistinct crosstalk)
Okay.
- You have a red...
- Yeah, mine.
- What do you guys think about this ball?
- It's awesome.
- It's awesome?
Why is it awesome?
- It's awesome because it's red
and it's the Cardinals' color.
(indistinct crosstalk)
(yelling)
- Well, I would love for you to come.
Should we see how far it goes?
All right, let's check it.
(indistinct crosstalk)
(yelling)
It knocked the cup over.
Let's try one more time.
(indistinct crosstalk)
(yelling)
It knocked it over again.
We're gonna put the tape here.
(indistinct crosstalk)
Do you think that was
farther than the rubber ball?
(indistinct crosstalk)
But when the ball goes farther.
Seven, eight, nine, 10, 11.
(indistinct crosstalk)
What?
- Can you find it on the number line?
Where's 11?
Uh huh, that's what it looks like.
Is 11 more or less than 13?
(indistinct crosstalk)
Is it more than 13 or less?
Which one?
(speaking indistinctly)
Is what?
- More than.
- Is more than 11?
If you look on the number line.
11 comes first, and then 12, and then 13.
So you're right, 13 is more.
- Yeah.
Okay, you guys can start
putting the balls away.