- [Group] Three, four, five, six!
- We have six friends at the table!
And let's see, I have one,
uh, leave it there please, Eulet.
- Christmas!
- Two...
- Uh, it's a little bit like
Christmas, you're right.
Three!
Oh, I have three strings to put beads on,
but I have six friends.
(overlapping chatter)
But I, you know, I don't.
I have some beads, but I
don't have any more strings.
What could we do?
- Your colors...
- I think, I think, I think
we could have (inaudible)
- You think what, what
do you think we could do?
- I don't know.
- Okay. Alright, does
anybody have an idea?
We have a problem!
We have more friends than we have strings.
- I want to have that one.
- Okay, well we're talking
about what we're going to do.
Alex, do you know what we could do?
- I don't know.
- You don't know?
Surafel, wait just a minute,
'cause I want everybody
to help string beads.
- Me and me and me and me
are gonna share.
- Oh! What did you say?!
- We're going to share!
- You're gonna share?!
Give me a high five for
that great solution!
Did you hear, she said
she's going to share.
Who are you gonna share with?
- I share a toy!
- I'm going to share,
I'm going to share with,
I'm going to share with...
- Did you forget his name?
- Um, Eulet.
- With Ulet! You're gonna share with Eulet!
That's a great idea!
Are you going to share?
- Not a toy
- What about you, what could you do?
Could you share?
- Yes.
- And take some turns?
- Who can you take turns with?
And what's her name?
- Brianna.
- Brianna. Ask her, Brianna,
will you string beads with me?
- Will you string beads with me?
- Look, can you play?
- Yes.
- Yeah? Yeah, you can?
Good, you can take turns
and share and string beads.
Surafel!
- Huh?
- Can you you take turns with someone?
- Umm...
- Oh! Look at that!
Yeah! This is Alex!
You're going to take
turns with Alex alright?
Well what do we need now?
- We need some more beads!
- We need some more beads.
Alright, well I have
some beads, let's see...
I have some beads.
Oh boy, I've got some great colors!
Let me show you what we're gonna do, okay?
Let's see, whoops, whoops!
Hold on a minute.
Okay, Lily is gonna have yellow and
Eulet is gonna have...
- Blue!
- Purple, okay, who's gonna go first?
- Me.
- Alright, Eulet.
- And I'll go next!
- And you'll go next.
Let's see what happens with the colors
when you take turns.
(overlapping chatter)
Alright, let's see. Eulet is...
Surafel sit down, watch.
Whoops! Here, pull it this way.
Alright, Eulet put his
on, now who's turn is it?
- My turn!
- Who's turn is it?
- Me.
- This is Lily's, Lily's turn!
Okay, so look, Lily's having a turn.
Alex, watch.
- Alex! You...
- Okay, but we're not gonna stack.
Alright, Lily put hers
on, now what do we do?
- Eulet.
- Back to Eulet, that's right!
Eulet, you can say, now it's my turn!
- Now it's my turn.
- Can you put one on?
Surafel, are you watching?
They're putting beads on their string!
- That's nice to share!
- It is! It's nice to
share and to take turns.
- Just like I share toys!
- You share toys?
- And we share animals!
(overlapping chatter)
- Tell her it's your turn.
- My turn.
- I share toys with my sister.
- Oh that's nice!
- And I share animals with my sister!
- And you share animals?
Alright Lily, may I show your friends what
you and Eulet did?
Look! Look at their colors!
When you take turns,
look, you make a pattern!
You go purple, yellow, purple, yellow!
Because you're taking turns,
the colors change each time.
That's called a pattern.
- Yeah!
- Alright, so, it's the purple turn now.
Eulet, that means it's your turn.
Nice working together!
I'm going to give Brianna blue,
and Natalie red.
Okay? Here you go.
Let's see if you guys can take turns.
Oh, and look!
Alex gets blue and Surafel,
what color do you get?
- Blue.
- Orange.
- Oh.
- Orange, let's see, here.
Alright, remember, uh oh!
- Lily's turn.
- Look Brianna, look
Brianna, this was your turn.
Now tell Natalie, say Natalie, your turn!
Surafel, did you get one on?
You did! So now who's turn?
- Umm...
Remember, we're taking turns.
Say, Alex! Give him this part.
Say, put yours on!
Alright! Here, we're gonna leave this on.
Wait for Alex!
Oh good! Now it's your turn, Brianna.
You have to talk to your friend and
tell them when it's their turn.
Nice job Eulet and Natalie.
Brianna, whoops! You're
pulling it the wrong way.
Pull it this way so it goes on.
Okay, now who's turn?
- My turn!
- Who's turn?
- Brianna, look, Natalie
said it's her turn.
Give it to Natalie.
Tell her your turn, and
then your turn is next.
How are we doin' guys?
Uh oh, did they come off?
Let me see, let's see.
Oh, uh oh.
Here, let me come around
and see if I can help you.
Eulet and Lily, you're working so nicely.
Is it your turn again?
Alright. Natalie, tell
Brianna when it's her turn.
(overlapping chatter)
Alright boys, let's see.
Let's get you going again, alright?
Here, let's put these down.
Okay, Alex has blue
and Surafel has orange.
Surafel, can you put yours on?
Okay.
Beautiful, okay, now,
who's turn is it now?
- Now it's my turn.
- Who's turn?
Do you remember me saying? It's Alex.
- Alex!
- Alex! Okay. Give it to Alex.
Here, Alex, you're going to hold this part
and you put your bead on.
Whoops! What's here?
Oh, it's a little bit tangled.
Let me see if I can untangle it.
Okay, that's right,
now we need a red bead.
Surafel, can you sit down now?
It looked like you almost fell.
Alright, Alex, yours is on. Look!
We have orange and blue.
So now what do you do?
- My turn!
- Oh is that right? Surafel's turn!
Oh you guys are great.
- Seven! I have seven beads!
- [Teacher] You have seven beads?
- I'll count how many beads I have.
One, two, three, four, five...
- Very good.
- Six, seven!
- Oh good! You have seven too!
You have the same number.
Okay, now what are we gonna do?
- It was my turn!
- Okay, who's turn is it?
- Alex!
- Okay good, take this,
give it to Alex and
tell him, it's, give him this part,
and say Alex, it's your turn now.
- His turn.
- Oh, very nice.
- Now we can count!
One, two, one, two,
three, four, five, six!
Uh oh, the watch has to (inaudible)
- Uh oh, yours is, Brianna,
you put on a blue one!
Okay, now what happens, Brianna?
- Three, four, five!
- Okay, hold on. Brianna.
- Six, seven, eight!
- Okay, take it, no, wait
a minute, you had a turn.
Can you give it now to
Natalie? Give it to Natalie.
- Six! I've got six!
- Look, give this to Natalie and tell her,
it's your turn now Natalie.
Wow, we are doing some nice work!
Did you give it back
to Surafel for his turn?
Alex, yay!
Alright, there's an orange one.
Surafel, what are you going to do now?
- This is (inaudible) of it all.
- What do you do now?
- [Surafel] Alex!
- Pretty, yay!
- [Teacher] Tell him, Alex your turn!
(Background Chatter)
Uh oh! Did we have a bead get away?
(shushes)
Uh oh! Uh oh!
(laughs)
This bead doesn't want
to go on the string!
- It's five, I have five!
- I like the way you're taking turns.
Okay, you are almost finished!
Eulet, you're working
so nicely with friends.
- And the red has...
- Okay.
- One, two, three, four, five, six...
- Uh oh!
- seven, eight, nine, ten...
That's okay, how did that happen?
We've got two blue ones on there.
Whoops! That's okay.
Now Surafel is having his turn.
- Look what I'm making.
- Oh, one, two, three, four,
five, six, seven, eight, nine, ten.
- Are you finished?
- Yes.
- Okay, show me, what
are you going to do now?
- Four, five, six...
- Oh you did some counting, good.
- [Surafel] I did.
Okay, and you have finished your turn,
so what do you do now?
- You only have two left! One, two!
- Is it your turn?
- Nah.
- Okay, so what do you say?
You say, Alex!
- Alex!
- Your turn!
Okay friends, we're almost done.
Let me see, uh oh, we need a red one!
You know what?
I'm going to make it so that you have
the same number as your friend. Okay?
Your turn! Let's see...
- My turn!
- Here we go, and you have
the same number. Okay!
(children counting and shouting)
- Eulet, can you talk to your partner?
- Your turn!
- What are you going to say?
Oh, okay, she said it's your turn.
Can you say, thank you?
- Thank you.
- Okay and we are almost finished.
Uh oh, we're doing some
different turn taking here,
but that's okay!
Alright, okay, so now who's turn is it?
- Alex!
- Okay, give it to Alex,
say, Alex, your turn!
- Your turn!
- Three, four, five, six, seven, eight,
nine, ten, eleven, twelve, thirteen, fourteen.
- Okay, we're not counting
so much right now,
we're taking turns.
Who's turn is it now?
- My turn.
- Natalie's turn.
- Okay, so you tell her...
- It's Lily's turn, I'm next.
- That's right, tell her,
this is Lily, Lily's turn.
(gasps) Look!
What happened?
Did you finish?
- Yeah!
- Did you string all your beads?
- You did! All of your
beads are on your string.
Let's look! Oh, and you too!
Nice Job!
Look! You did orange and
blue, orange and blue,
orange and lots of blue, orange and blue,
orange and blue.
Beautiful. Okay, I'm
gonna lay it right here.
Let's look at yours, because you finished
and you used all of your beads.
Oh look, you used different colors.
You did blue, can you say it with me?
Red, blue, red, blue, red.
[In Spanish] azul, rojo, azul, rojo
Can you say that, Brianna?
(Continues in Spanish) Azul, rojo, azul, rojo, azul.
You guys did a great job of taking turns!
- We finished! We finished!
- You finished!
Look, you used all of your
beads, your trays are empty.
Let's hold it up and look at the colors,
and the pattern you made.
Can you tell me the pattern?
- [Group] Purple, yellow...
purple, yellow, purple, yellow,
purple, yellow,
purple, yellow, purple,
yellow, purple, yellow,
purple, yellow, purple, yellow!
- Yay! And we know that
you took turns because
the colors changed every time.
- It's clean up time!
- You guys did a great job!
And you're right, it is, we are finished.
We learned how to take
turns with a partner,
and we put beads on a string and
made a color pattern
because we took turns.
Yes! It was all good and I think
(bell rings)
you all get to ring the good job bell!
Good job taking turns, Eulet.
Good job taking...