(background chatter)
- [Teacher] Five, four,
three, two, one, stop.
I'm going to follow
the same norms you are,
so if I want to talk,
I'm going to have to raise my hand.
Does anybody want to start us off?
Sort of an initial response,
or something that's been on your mind,
or a place we can go in the play
to start this conversation?
- [Girl with glasses] In the last act,
when Emilia and Iago,
or Iago's been caught,
and Emilia is piecing
together all of these things
that Iago's done, how it all works,
and she's telling the others
around him what he's done,
he keeps telling her,
"Be quiet, this isn't your place to talk,
"you shouldn't be here."
But, whereas most stereotypical women
would have just kind of
followed what their husband wanted,
and just you know, kind
of been in the background,
Emilia actually stands up
and says what she thinks is right.
- (mumbles)
- [Girl in glasses] Yeah, okay.
- What (mumbles) also talked about
was how Desdemona kind of juxtaposes that
in that she's like the very
stereotypical housewife,
to the point at which
she refuses to even like
blame her husband for killing her,
so we kind of, it's interesting how
those two characters are just...
- [Chloe] To touch on the racism part,
I would have to say it's not,
and at least if it is,
that isn't the main focus
of the play.
I'd say that it's focused more on these
complex characters and their web of lies,
and the plot itself isn't focused on,
if it is, I think (mumbles)
because I don't really think it is.
- [Boy with glasses] I
kind of agree with Chloe.
I don't think that Othello
is a racist or sexist play.
It does have racism and sexism in it,
but that's because it was
written by William Shakespeare
in a time when that was the norm.
You can't really look at
it as a modern person,
because we think of racism and sexism
so differently from the
audience it was intended for.
They thought of it as more of the norm,
so it does seem more normal.
Like it seemed believable
and normal to them,
because that's just how their society was.
- [Blond girl] Then it
also kind of looks at like
how racism sort of caused it,
like Iago hates Othello,
and one reason that he gives is that
he's black and he doesn't
deserve his position,
and he kind of uses race to his advantage
to do bad things.
So it's kind of looking at,
it's not racist, it's looking at racism
and sexism, and saying like how
they can be used and
manipulated, you know?
- [Girl in blue] Yeah, I
kind of agree with you.
I think this play is really about like
taking advantage of
people any way you can.
So like if you have something on them,
like they're a different color,
or if they're a different sex,
then you can use that to your advantage
by like putting that as an
excuse almost, to take advantage.
- [Teacher] Let's return to that.
Raise your hand if Iago was
your favorite character in this class.
Come on.
I mean, this is a, I have to say, I agree.
I would raise my hand to that question,
which I find troubling,
because I certainly agree with
some of the opinions
that I'm hearing here,
that we have this interesting contrast
between Emilia and Desdemona,
as two different ways women
can live with male violence,
and we also have this examination of how
racism and sexism are
used as part of the plot
to take down Othello.
But at the same time,
I have to say, I think that it feels to me
like the play is set up
for us like Iago more.
Iago talks to us, he
lets us into his world,
into his mind in a way
that nobody else does.
So I'd almost feel like
we can't blame ourselves
as the audience for identifying with him,
for secretly making part
of us rooting for him,
or he even made me sort like glorying
in his intelligence and his
capacity for manipulation
and just his power.
And I wonder what we do with that,
because if you walk away
from this play being like,
"I love Iago!"
Then aren't you also kind of saying,
in a way, celebrating what he's done?
Do you agree with me? Disagree with me?
- [Girl with head turned] I
think his ability to like,
his like logic, and how
he like plans things,
like how he like manipulates
a lot of situations,
and how he like schemes
to like use people's
like baggage, I guess, to his advantage,
is kind of like I guess
like the way he uses it
isn't a good way,
but like if you could use
it in a different way,
I guess it like could be
viewed as like a good thing.
So, (mumbles)
- I think there's a
difference between like
celebrating what he's done,
and just appreciating
like the amount of thought
and like intelligence that he
has in using it in a bad way,
because like you can like Iago,
and like him for different reasons than,
"Oh, I like what he's done,
"I like how he destroyed this person."
It can be just, you know, "I realize that
"this is a very smart person,
"and someone I really
would not want to be on
his bad side."
But like you just sort of,
you realize like how much, I guess yeah,
I'll just use the word appreciate again.
You just appreciate like how much,
you understand his mind, and
it's just really interesting,
rather than you love him.
- Yeah, I think it's more like,
sometime's it's fun to like root for like
the evil character.
Because you wouldn't actually do it,
like if you play video
games like Grand Theft Auto,
(students laugh)
Like you kill the hookers, it's not like--
you would have to do that,
it's just that it's fun.
(students laugh)
- [Boy] Oh my God!
(background chatter)
- [Girl with glasses] Well,
it doesn't surprise me
that Iago's the one that most people
come away from the play with being like,
"Yeah, he's so great, he's
so interesting," right?
Because like he's the only character that
you actually get to know.
Everyone else just kind of like dies.
They get drunk and like
stab people, or they cry.
That's pretty much what
everybody else does,
and then Iago's the one
who like lets you in,
lets you know what he's thinking,
when he's bringing specific elements,
like with each person in the play,
he's different from each person,
and you can see that through the play.
- Well, as she was saying,
like how everyone else was
crying and like going crazy,
or like either having an awful
time or having a good time,
like they still trust Iago,
even though he's standing
there not doing that with them.
I mean, just like the way he's able to
still convince them whenever he's not,
he doesn't seem like he's on the,
like he convinced them
that he's on their side,
but he's not actually
doing everything they are,
or he's not really doing
anything to show them
that's he's isn't feeling
what they're feeling. Alex?
- I have a quote, I guess.
It's at (mumbles) around there.
"And their palates both
for sweet and sour,
"as husbands have, what is it they do
"when they change us for others?
"Is it sport? I think it is.
And doth affection breed it?
"I think it doth. Is't frailty
that thus errs? It is so too.
"And have we not affections,
desires for sport, and frailty,
"as men have? Then let them
use us well, else let them know,
"the ills we do, their
ills instruct us so."
So it's kind of like talking about how
the men control the women,
and so I guess like that's
like the sexism of the day,
or like of that era, and like
this is Emilia, she's
talking to Desdemona,
and she's talking about
how like men control them,
and all their thoughts are
kind of implanted by the men,
like Emilia, like she got
the handkerchief because
her husband told her to do
that, and they're all just
really obedient and everything. Chloe?
- [Chloe] I mean, I think
that, yeah it has to do
with the time period, as far
as the sexism in the play
or whatever, but I mean because
that it's just the way it
was, but I think that when
you look at the female characters
in the play, like Emilia,
she turns out to be one of the
most influential characters,
and she's the one that
takes down the bad person.
It's her that takes
down Iago, pretty much,
because she tells him the truth,
and then something that
none of the men could do,
or even question.
Then the other thing I would say is that
the women's loyalty to each other,
especially Desdemona to Emilia,
because it's back earlier in the play,
I don't actually have it, but Emilia,
I mean, Desdemona sings a
song earlier in the play,
something, "Willow, willow, willow,"
some more stuff about the song,
and then when Emilia's
dying, she sings a line
from that exact same song,
and she says, she references,
"my mistress death."
So I think a lot of it shows
how the women stick together.
- It's also kind of like,
I mean, I agree with you,
and I mean it's not
sexist, it looks at sexism,
because I mean you see how Desdemona
is the stereotypical woman of that time,
and she kind of does what
her husband tells her to,
she doesn't rebel against him,
she is completely loyal to him,
regardless of how he treats her.
I mean, he's hit her,
and she just accepts it.
Even when he kills her,
she takes the blame and
doesn't rat him out,
and it just kind of, you
have problems respecting her
because of it.
Like I mean, she's a good character,
but you just can't, it's really hard to
respect someone who just accepts
everything that is done to her like that.
Then you have to juxtapose it with Emilia,
and she was a really
influential character,
and is able to rise above,
and kind of try to take
down her own husband
and go against it.
It's kind of looking at
sexism and saying like,
you know, which is better for you?
Which do you like more?
Look at how the sexism
and the roles of women
has affected Desdemona,
and then how Emilia's been
able to rise above it.
- [Teacher] Can I jump in?
- Yeah.
- I definitely agree with you,
but my thoughts are also going
back to Act I, Scene III,
because I think at the
beginning of the play,
Desdemona is very much
not a stereotypical woman.
She has married the man she
loves, defying her father.
Knowing her dad wouldn't like it,
she ran off and married him anyway.
When Othello's talking
about how he won her heart,
it was by telling the stories of the wars,
and it's actually
(cough)
very interesting, because it says that
Desdemona would seriously (mumbles).
She would be very
interested in these stories,
even to the point where she
wished she had been born a man.
Then, when Othello says,
"I have to go to war,"
and the Duke says, "Let's like Desdemona
"stay at her dad's house,"
Desdemona says, "No, I married this man
"to be with him. Let me
go to the war, also."
So at least at that scene,
I think that she's a model
of a very, very active
woman who wants to go to war
with her husband, she wants to be
with her husband.
When Othello comes out
in Act II, Scene III
to stop the fight between
Cassio and Roderigo,
Desdemona comes out, too, and says,
"What's going on, what's wrong?"
And Othello says, "Come away
sweetie, let's go back to bed."
Right?
I certainly agree that there's a passivity
in Desdemona by the end,
but I don't know if I see
that so much at the beginning.
Go ahead.
- [Girl with scarf] I agree,
I think that like sometimes
Desdemona wants to be
the stereotypical woman,
and then like other times, she wants to be
the like "rebel," kind of,
because like Mr. Proctor said,
like she completely rebels against her dad
at the beginning,
and then also like, she's not
the stereotypical woman,
because like every single man
like in the play has admitted that
she's the most beautiful woman,
that they want her and all this stuff,
and so she has some power over them, too.
But yeah, I just think it's interesting
how like there are scenes where
she's the complete like
stereotypical housewoman,
and then other times, she's
like completely passive.
- Even though it's been brought up
that she defied her
father to marry Othello,
she's still, I feel like she's still
very like part of that time period,
as far as the role of women,
because even though Othello wasn't
her perfect husband in
the eyes of her father,
she still jumped from the control
of one man, her father, to
another man, her husband.
So, Tanya?
- [Tanya] Okay, so about Desdemona,
I think that like even
though she did that stuff,
she still was a stereotypical woman.
Like we said before, those women,
they're supposed to be
obedient to their husbands,
so like whenever she
does kind of like rebel
and do something different from,
or like kind of jump in to the conver-
like Mr. Proctor was
saying, like those examples,
she's doing it for Othello.
She jumps in, like she
goes to war to be with him,
and then she comes in like
whenever he's in trouble.
And then, the thing about Emilia
is she's doing stuff for herself.
Like in Act IV, Scene III,
yeah, that's what we read,
she's talking about how it's just like,
she would cheat on her husband once.
It's just like she says,
"The world's a huge thing,
"it is a great price for a small vice."