♪ [music] ♪
- [instructor] No, I want you to swing the
eighth notes. Okay? We're going to swing
the eighth notes. So, remember when you
swing you just make the first note longer
than the second note. So, go like this...
♪ [music] ♪
- Don't be stuck at the tip of your bells.
Here we go. One, a two, a three and go.
♪ [music] ♪
- Every single person here, please make
sure you're playing F natural. Try it
again. Here we go. One, two and go.
♪ [music] ♪
- Okay. Now, when you guys improvise,
you've got to improvise off of this D
dorian scale. Okay? So, watch this. If I
was soloing, and I was, you know, playing
along with the music, and I played this...
♪ [music] ♪
- All I did was play the D dorian scale,
going up and down. That's all it was. It
sounded a little fancy, didn't it? It
really wasn't. Did it sound difficult?
- [students] Yes.
- It really wasn't. I just did
this, like really changing the rhythm.
♪ [music] ♪
- That's basically all I did. Okay? So,
it's really not that difficult. I'm gonna
play some rhythms. I want you guys to echo
it. Please sit up. Thank you. Nice and
tall. I'm gonna play one measure and
you're going to repeat exactly what I
play. We're playing this one on open D.
Only on open D.
♪ [music] ♪
- Great, now I'm going to do two
measures. Okay? Two measures and you've
got to echo it back to me. This is still
open D. Here we go.
Wait for it, I'll tell you when to go.
♪ [music] ♪
- Excellent. Okay, it goes like this. I'm
going to change it.
♪ [music] ♪
- And go.
- There it is. Okay. It's just four notes
in the second measure. So, try it again.
♪ [music] ♪
- And go.
- Do this for me.
♪ [music] ♪
- And go.
- Try this. I'm playing D and F. So, the
higher pitch that you hear is F natural.
So, play this for me.
♪ [music] ♪
- Great. Fantastic. I'm only going to add
one more note. You want to play D, F, and G.
Okay? With the exception of basses.
So do an open G okay?
So, D, F, and G are your three
notes. All right, get in playing position.
♪ [music] ♪
- Okay. So, basically that's improvising.
I'm giving you a lot of ideas for
improvising. Okay? And you will only use
three notes when you improvise. D, F, and G.
You don't have to use all three but
those are your only musical choices as far
as notes. When you improvise, there are
certain rules to improvising. You can't
just play any note, because if you play
the wrong note it will not be the right
choice. Okay? So, we don't want to play
the wrong note. So, please make sure that
you only play D, F, and G. Do you see that
tune that's on whatever page that's on for
you guys? There should be a page that's
got solos at the top, and then it has solo
two and solo one to the side and then
tune. You'll pick the third one with the
tune. Do you guys see it?
- Yeah.
- Okay. Make sure you're on
the correct side. I'll play the tune for
you so you can hear how it sounds, and
then I'm going to have you guys play it.
Okay? Listen to my tempo.
♪ [music] ♪
- Are you guys following along?
- Okay? Play it for me. Here we go. Watch
your rests. One, two and go.
♪ [music] ♪
- Much better. Now.
- Good. Now, play it again.
One, two and go.
♪ [music] ♪
- Good. I want you to play it one more
time. I'm going to play the piano with you
though. All right. Here we go.
♪ [music] ♪
- Great. Now, I'm going to solo for you
guys, and I want to show you how you can
do this. Okay?
♪ [music] ♪
[applause]
- A couple things that I did in there. All
I did was play a dorian scale up and down
and swung my eighth note.
That's all I did.
It sounds really difficult, didn't it?
- Yeah.
- It was like whoa!
No, I'm just going...
♪ [music] ♪
- I can make it sound fancy and make it
sound really difficult. You can do it,
too. Okay. So, we're going to go around
the room. Each person is going to solo.
Okay? Whatever musical idea you come up
with. Remember, your notes are D, F, and
G. You got it? D, F, and G. Whatever
rhythm you want to play, within the
rhythms I gave you. So don't... [plays
quickly] Okay? Here we go. Here's how
we're going to do it. We're going to start
with maybe two measures. We're going to
start with Tessa and go around. Maybe
after, Helen. Then we go with Tallulah.
Priscilla, listen carefully. After
Tallulah we're going to go around
this way. After Jada, we're going to start
with Sammy and we're going to end with
Zoey. Okay? We're all going
to start with two.
♪ [music] ♪