- Okay, what's in here?
(foreign language) do me a favor.
Go up, and tell me what I'm gonna need.
Put (hums).
(background chatter)
- I put down the...
- If he's right,
say (speaks foreign language).
- (foreign language)
- Okay boys and girls,
because it is raining,
I need my one, two, three--
- [Children] Umbrella.
- What happened to that thing? I like red.
Matches my jacket. Maybe,
because it's raining.
(background chatter)
This...
This protects me from the rain.
So, because it is raining,
I need a one, two, three--
- [Children] Umbrella.
- Umbrella.
- I might put that here.
Maybe I'll need it.
Okay, maybe I'll need it later.
Okay boys and girls, so let's keep going.
Boys and girls, since it is (hums),
I'll need my (hums).
You wanna try it? Come up. Come up.
I don't know, I don't know.
(background chatter)
- Oh so now, ooh...
(children laughing)
- Okay, so nice job.
Because it is one, two, three--
- [Children] Snowing.
- I'll need my--
- [Children] Gloves.
- What type of gloves?
I have these gloves.
(children laughing)
- Are these gloves the
type of gloves I need?
- [Children] No.
- Are these gloves the
type of gloves I need?
- [Children] Yes.
- [Children] No.
- I think, I don't think these will work.
These gloves. Say it with me: gloves.
- [Children] Gloves.
- Now just people in pink. Gloves.
- (laughs) Oh, there's a
lot of people wearing pink.
Okay, just boys.
- [Boys] Gloves.
- Just girls.
- [Girls] Gloves.
- Very nice. Just people from China.
- [Children] Gloves.
- Just people from South America.
- All right. There we go. There we go.
All right, let's keep moving, okay?
Boys and girls, it is (hums),
so I'll need my (hums).
We're right here. What is
this? What's going on here?
- [Children] Windy.
- So windy. So windy. What do I need?
Tina, come on up. Come on up.
I don't know, maybe I'll use this.
(children laughing)
(boy speaks in foreign language)
- Okay, so Tina, Tina. One,
two, three guys. Because it is--
- [Children] Windy.
- Okay, in Chinese it's--
- [Children] (speaking foreign language)
- Okay, I'll need my--
- [Children] Jacket.
(background chatter)
- All right, all right.
Great, great, great, great.
So guys, I just wanna say one thing.
I wanna say that these words I'm using
are cause and effect words.
And we have some examples of clothing here
that you're gonna need, and I want you
to focus for a second with this.
Say it with me: since.
- [Children] Since.
- Because.
- [Children] Because.
- So.
- [Children] So.
- Boys and girls, these are
words you use when speaking,
when you're talking about
cause and effect when speaking.
Because it's snowing,
I need my heavy jacket.
That's cause and effect.
These are words we use with speaking.
These words, let's say them just one time
for a little pronunciation practice.
Thus.
- [Children] Thus.
- Therefore.
- [Children] Therefore.
- Consequence. Three
syllables: Con-se-quence.
- [Children] Consequence.
- All right, good, good. And the fact is.
- [Children] And the fact is.
- These are pretty much words
we're gonna use in writing only.
We don't really speak these
words, not often, very rare.
These we used in speaking:
since, because, and so.
And these are the words
you're gonna be using today.
You're gonna be using them to
write some simple sentences
that show cause and effect relationships.
These are more when
you're writing an essay,
an essay, like maybe for the ELA,
or when you're writing an academic essay.
Okay, so we have one more.
You guys are doing so great.
And I have a lot of stuff here.
I have a one, two, three--
- [Children] Scarf.
- Say it with me: scarf.
- What about that "F" on the end? Scarf.
- [Children] Scarf.
- Scarf.
- Okay, I like this
scarf. It's a nice scarf.
I have a, what is this?
- [Boy] Sweater.
- Sweater or sweatshirt?
- [Children] Sweatshirt.
- No, sweater. Sweater.
- [Children] Sweater.
- Okay, I think when it's,
what is this outside?
- [Children] Sunny.
- Say it with me: sunny.
- It is sunny, so...
I think, you know what's interesting is,
this is the important word: so.
- [Children] So.
- So I'll need...
- [Children] Sunglasses.
- Boys and girls, when it gets
really, really sunny outside,
sometimes the sun hurts my
eyes, so I put on my sunglasses.
Okay, so...
I want you to try it now.
I want you to try it.
(background chatter)
Boys and girls, now you
all have in front of you
two worksheets. You have one worksheet
in front of you, you
have two different ones.
Many of you have this worksheet,
and many of you have this worksheet, okay?
I just gonna do one quick sentence here.
Because it is hot,
I'll need my--
- [Children] Sunglasses. Shirt.
- Someone raise their hand.
Tina. Tina, say that loud.
- [Child] Sunglasses.
- Sunglasses.
- [Children] Sunglasses.
- And, shorts.
Oh, I didn't tell you about my shorts.
I brought those today too.
Say it with me: shorts.
- [Children] Shorts.
- Say it with me: shorts.
- Okay, so it's sunny
and I'm gonna need my
shorts and sunglasses. I got 'em.
I'll need my sunglasses and shorts.
And "because" here, this is
what you call a transition word.
This is what we're working on.
Now, if I have this here, Juan Pablo
you have this worksheet.
We have cause and effect.
If I have this here, we have, let's say,
since it is raining,
I'll need my raincoat.
And that's a coat for rain.
It's on your list there.
So, what is this word here?
Say it with me: since.
- [Children] Since.
- "Since" is a transition word.
In speaking, and then sometimes writing
like this style of writing,
you would use these words.
All the time in speaking,
you show cause and effect.
Since I don't have any money,
I can't buy anything to eat tonight.
Because it's raining, I
think I'll go to the movies.
Cause and effect, boys and girls.
Use it each and every
time you think about,
speak about cause and effect.
Now I want you to try
this with your partner,
and then we're gonna
practice speaking these out.
On three, I want you to
go. Three, two, one, go.
(background chatter)
Use the examples, use the sentences.
And here's some more
additional examples for you.
(background chatter)
Do you see it up top?
Clothing. Right here.
Clothing. How would you
make "clothes" out of that?
Can you see it? Give it a try.
Can you read this to me?
(inaudible)
What do you need when it's hot?
Okay, so you see the list right here?
Which items are for hot?
Which items are for cold?
Can you try to write that for me?
I'm gonna come back.
(background chatter)
- Look at the charts,
they are there to help you.
(background chatter)
You see the chart that I made?
So, let's try something.
I want to try something.
Can you read me, actually
read Hon Lu your first sentence.
And you read her your
first sentence. You first.
Partner A, partner B. Partner A, go.
You first, you're partner A.
- Because it is raining, I
need my umbrella and raincoat.
- Because it's hot, I need my shorts.
- Okay, now you're speaking
to each other, not to me.
Okay, keep going. Go.
- Since it is sunny, I need my sunglasses.
(background conversation
drowns out speaker)
- Can you write that there?
Look right here. That list, for you.
Okay, you see on the...
(background chatter)
(boy speaking in foreign language)
- Look at the
word. Slide through it.
Two syllables.
(background chatter)
Is that one boot? One boot? Or two?
So how, is there...
Yes, yes. Boots. Great.
This is great stuff. I'm proud of you.
So proud of you.
Read this.
You look like you
haven't got started here.
So listen to him, he did
a really nice job here.
And let's work together, okay?
Can you read me your first sentence?
- [Boy] Because it's hot,
so I need
my sunglasses.
- Good, now pause. Now
listen, I want you to try one.
(background conversation
drowns out speaker)
- So I need my (speaks foreign language).
- I'm sorry, did you say the--
- [Boy] Umbrella.
- If it's hot, I need an umbrella?
- No.
- If it's, which one?
Which one?
If I, if it...
Which one do I need an umbrella?