- Now, watch this felt as I
pull this up and down. See those bubbles
in it? Right here, I got the bubbles at
the top that means I gotta pull it down to
get those out. You want this stuff
laying flat. If it doesn't it'll probably
show up underneath the machinery. If I
pull it down too far, it pulls a wrinkle
in the bottom. So you want to make sure
you get it straight and get all the
wrinkles out of it. I've got them out and
I'm just a little bit below my line right
here, but that's okay. It's more important
that this is out right here, that it's on.
Does that make sense?
- Yeah.
- So just make sure. Now you want to come
out here at this point and get you one
right here. Don't forget our nailing
pattern that we discussed. Here, here,
here, here, and here. You can feel right
here where the plywood is. You want to put
a button right here, and your nail line is
going to be right in here on this. You
don't want to nail into the fascia board.
You want to come right across in here and
put them every six inches. And about every
two feet right here, and one occasionally.
Be careful not to step on the felt. Step
on the buttons so you don't end up
sliding. Just be careful anytime that
you're stepping on felt. You never want to
step on loose felt. Okay? All right. Go
ahead and nail that off.
This one right here.
See how you're doing this shingle?
- Yeah.
- We're gonna come back with a starter
right here, turned upside down. This right
here is gonna have to be cut off.
So go ahead and just cut this off even,
that'll be fine right now. This one over
here, don't nail that yet. Hold on just a
second. Come here a minute. You can do it
that way. That's one way that you can run
it down and cut it, or right here I can just take
this soldier, just like this, and I can cut it
off right here. Or I can just lap it up
there and nail it like it is. The other
soldier is coming down to right here. So
just come up here and cut this off. Got
your hook weight on you?
- Yeah
- Take and cut one tab off of the shingle,
flush it up and nail it on and then go
ahead and start your starter tabs up
there.
- It doesn't have to be straight right? I
just cut it?
- Pardon?
- Does it have to be straight? Just
eyeball it?
- No, it doesn't have to be perfectly
straight, just go ahead and hook your hook
blade right here and pull it straight
back. That'll be fine. Hold it down. There
you go. Never cut back on your handle.
These right here we'll be able to use for
the caps on top so don't throw these away.
Tabs always go in on these. So make sure
your tab's in, flush it up, and nail it
off. Once you've done this you need to
pull a layout, and in the classroom we
talked about layout on three tab shingles.
If we're gonna go off the end of the
building what are we gonna pull?
- Thirty, 36.
- We're gonna pull 36 inches, and we're
gonna pull 30 inches. Top and bottom,
topping your lines.
- All right.
- Does that make sense?
- Yeah
- Okay so do that. Once you nail this off
do that, and then run your starters. You
can go ahead and cut that off.
The inches right here you can go ahead
and cut them, come right here and cut it
off right here on the edge of the plywood
and then that will have you ready to put
your shingles on in a minute. You got a
hook blade? Y'all have it? You go ahead
and do that, then you can do the other
side right here.
-[Background Chatter]
- Go ahead and get your lines snapped, put
them on there and mark it and pop your
lines. Either way. You can do it either
way, it doesn't matter, but since we're
gonna go ahead and start these they need
to be on the 30x36 way out anyway. Flush
it up and hang it.
[Background chatter]
- Don't pull that down. If you do that's
just gonna take and break that shingle
off. This right here is establishing the
overhang that we wanted, that inch and a
quarter off the edge of the building; so we
want our finished shingles to come right
here also. When you pull your 30x36 for
your layout on your three tab you want to
go all the way to the edge of the soldier
joist. Go ahead and mark that at the top.
You need to keep them moving, you gotta
have it marked up there. Go ahead and mark
it up there, and mark it right here. Get
these popped and then you can go ahead and
get Darius to get you a shingle and have
it ready to go and y'all will be ready to
put these things on. Put your starter on
it...
- Here? Thirty and 36.
- It's raining buttons. See that button
landed right there? Y'all make sure that
you pick these things up when you're done.
You should be able to reach right here and
nail this plywood on without any problem.
Once they get right here, you can't nail
it move down the line.
[Background Chatter]
*Hammering*
- Talk to him, what do you want him to do?
- Put a nail right there.
- There you go. Brandon is telling you
right. Y'all hold on a minute. What does
putting a nail right there do? I mean
you're about to put it right there--
- It holds it center, because that way no
bubbles or nothing comes up.
- It's gonna hold it right.
- Keeps it straight.
- So really you can start putting buttons
from down there to here, it's not going to
affect anything. Because he's got that
button in. From this point on we can't
put any more buttons in it until he gets
it where he wants it down here.
- He nails it off.
- Right, but you could nail this. Go ahead
and start doing that. Working together as
a group to get the job done is what it's
all about. This is not a one man job, you
can't roll this stuff out and do it by
yourself. It's not a one person job.
- If you want to mark that and pull that
up to where you can get to it there's
nothing wrong with doing that. What you
don't want to do is put your foot on that
felt right in there. Watch about cutting back
towards your hand like that. Just be real careful.
There ya go. Mike, put your hand on that roll
for him.
I got it. That may not be enough to cap
that ridge off. So we can roll it as far
down as it will go and piece it if we need
to. You need a button in it now. He needs
help. Help him right here. Yes, sir?
- Where at?
- Hold on, come on the line right there?
- Yeah, come on right here.
- Is that on right?
- Yeah, next put the felt right here. As
far as starting this next row, you got a
line on...
- Thirty-six inches.
- You got a line on 36 inches, and you've
got a line on 30 inches. We want to make
sure that when you start this next run
that you're not breaking. Let me see a
shingle, right here, I want you to watch.
I've worked on several houses, the whole boxing
fascia boards and
all this is rotten on the house. The
reason for that was this right here. They
put their starter on like you're supposed
to, to allow for the throats of the
shingles. We have no water penetration
down here. But once you start this starter
tabs up, over to your 36 inch line, if I
laid this 36 inch shingle down and nail it
off I have a straight avenue of water to
get down to this felt. This felt will only
hold for so long. It's going to get down
here, it will rot it out and there you're
gonna be. So you wanna make sure that you
start this on your 30 inch line and
then, give me one more shingle. Then
when you butt this shingle up to this one,
now what I have is I got my break right
here in the center of the full tab and I'm
six inches away from it. That's why our nailing
pattern here is important. You want
to nail above every throat, in the far
line, slightly above, in a three tab
shingle. Four nails, 1,2,3,4. Just like we
discussed on the PowerPoint--
- Above the tar line?
- Pardon?
- I can't hear you.
- Above the tar line?
- It can be in or slightly above. Most
people are gonna put them in them or
slightly above them. Your video PowerPoint
was slightly above, but the main
important thing here is that you have it
to where...
If you put them in random, if I put one
right here, or in the middle of these two.
I could possibly have a nail where I got a
shingle breaking. Or I could possibly have
a nail in line with a throat that's gonna
line up on top of the next one. It's
important to go here, here, here and
here. The purpose of this tar line is when
this sun heats it, and it heats up you
have the next shingle on top of here it
helps secure it down so wind don't take
and blow it up and rip the shingle off.
- So it melts down?
- It'll actually seal and melt down to
it. All right, you're doing good, but go
ahead and make sure that you do this with
this hot sun out here today you will wanna
keep these cut. So use a shingle to square
it up or your speed square. Mark your line
and cut it straight down right here. You
can nail it on first, that will be fine.
Or you can go ahead and cut it before you
nail it. You see this shingle right here,
that's got the little slit in it? That is
exactly six inches is what that is. So you
can take this shingle, right here. Put
your speed square up here, take your hook
blade and follow along it and cut that
off. Then you can nail it on if you wanted
to do that. Either way, there's multiple
different ways to do it. The main thing is
don't just take this, put it on the 30
inch line, nail it down, and don't do
anything else to it until you get up
there. Y'all do it as you go. These hot
days like this cool that down and it won't
get it's form back. It'll look bad. So we
want to keep it looking good. All right,
how we doing?
- Good
- Good. What about right here?
[Background Chatter]
- You need to put it along the edge, if
you don't follow along the edge...
- There's three buttons if you started,
one at the top one at the bottom. What's
missing? One in between so let's get them
in there.
Jake you mind getting that one?
- Is that going to be enough to roll all
this?
- If not, we'll get another roll and
finish it out. Just go ahead and run with
what you got. That'll be okay that will
lay down beneath.
Be careful about the top edge of that
felt. Run that, y'all can stand on this.
Get a couple more buttons in between here,
we're a little far apart right here. I
like to see two foot. Go ahead and hop up
here and stand on a button. Get you a
couple more in the middle, and then cap
that off. Lay it right down the center...