- [Teacher] So what about this part?
Is this any different,
or is this part the same as last time?
- [Rileen] It's different because--
- [Chris] Well--
- [Teacher] Let's let Rileen talk, Chris.
- [Rileen] It's different
because it's wider,
and it got right to here and the other one
came up to there.
- [Chris] It's like six more,
it's like ten more
centimeters than last time.
- [Teacher] Okay. So once you guys
finish with your observations,
you guys can start working
on collecting your data
for the canyon and for the delta.
(Background Chatter)
- [Girl in floral] See, this part is completely dry.
- [Elondra] It's pretty much almost half.
- [Girl in floral] Water's above the side.
- [Cameron] Watch that,
watch that, it's gonna fall.
- [Girl in floral] Look at that.
- [Cameron] It's like a boat
going down a waterfall.
- [Girl in floral] That was sand.
- [Cameron] I know.
(Background Chatter)
- [Xander] The water has stopped going.
- [Cameron] One minute's passed.
- [Girl in floral] Thirty?
-[Cameron] Oh.
- [Both] (giggles)
- [Girl in floral] There's a--start to get ready.
It's not done playing.
- [Cameron] It's still not done (Background Chatter).
- [Xander] Well, the water--
- [Girl in floral] Look at this, look at this.
- [Cameron] I know, we're still dry.
- [Xander] There's a pool of water at the end.
- [Elondra] There's a pool of water at the end.
- [Cameron] Look at this, there's
a dent, there's a dent.
- [Xander] Oh, wow.
- [Cameron] Right here's dry.
- [Teacher] Okay, why do you guys think this part
didn't get any water?
- [Cameron] Because it probably went under?
- [Teacher] So Cameron says it went under,
Xander, what were you saying?
- [Xander] It was going too fast
and it didn't--it was probably right here,
so it didn't decide to
go all the way over here,
and it went right here.
- [Cameron] It formed a lake right here.
- [Xander] It went the easiest route.
So it's got eight or nine minutes.
- [Girl in floral] So,
now ten, nine minutes.
- [Teacher] Is water still draining?
- [Cameron] Yeah, the water's still there.
- [Teacher] When are you guys gonna
decide when the end time is?
- [Cameron] When this goes.
- [Girl in Floral] There's
been nine minutes, right?
And the water is dripping.
- [Cameron] Last time we got 15 minutes.
- [Girl in floral] The
water's dripping into basin.
- [Cameron] Last time we got 15 minutes.
- [Teacher] So how does it all compare?
- [Cameron] Because, um, it compares
because it's almost the same,
and look at, it like
poured a pool or something.
- [Teacher] Cameron, you were saying
this one is almost the same?
Like it took the same amount of time?
- [Cameron] No.
- [Elondra] No.
- [Cameron] No, I'm saying it's getting there.
- [Elondra] No, the other one's longer
because it drained a bigger whole.
- [Cameron] Yeah.
- [Teacher] So Elondra, how was the
time different for this one?
- [Cameron] How it was like similar?
- [Teacher] Let's hear what Elondra says.
- [Elondra] This one went faster.
- This one went faster?
- Yeah, way faster.
- So you're saying it's
similar, not too different?
But Elondra's saying it went faster.
Do you agree with her?
- [Cameron] Yeah, and the deposition
it's like way over here.
Way across there.
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] You guys are, I think, pretty much done
with your water draining now.
- [Cameron] Okay, so--
- [Xander] Nine or ten minutes and it's done.
- [Teacher] So you guys want to
record your end time?
- [Cameron] No, no, it's still going.
- [Teacher] It's okay if there's still
a little bit of water left in.
Once it stops draining, you guys can put
the tape over here and you guys can start
taking your measurements.
- [Xander] Where do we get the toothpicks?
- [Elondra] Don't we have to know what time it is?
- [Girl in floral] 10:30, right?
- [Elondra] Was this when the chocolate melts?
- [Cameron] When's the chocolate melt?
Elondra.
- [Elondra] What?
- [Cameron] It looks like chocolate--
- [Teacher] So are you guys ready to
start taking your measurements?
- [Xander] Yeah.
- [Teacher] Why don't you guys open
up your science notebooks
so you have the table in front of you,
and I'll bring by a toothpick
so you can get started
on the writing.
- [Girl in floral] Yeah.
- [Xander] I think the widest part is right here.
- [Girl in floral] Can I do the poking?
- [Xander] Huh?
- [Teacher] You guys have your measuring tape out?
- [Xander] We have to go get the measuring tape.
- [Girl in floral] Tape that back up.
- [Xander] Here, our widest part is right here.
- [Girl in floral] Widest part is that.
- [Xander] No, no, no, you're
not supposed to poke it.
- [Girl in floral] How long is that?
- [Xander] It's about to here.
- [Cameron] Okay, we got what we need.
- [Elondra] Go from centimeters.
- [Girl in floral] Centimeters.
- [Xander] Aw, Cameron.
Cameron, you messed it up.
- [Girl in floral] That's not our longest part.
Our longest part is this.
- [Xander] Okay, we have to redo it.
Wait, where does we start?
- [Cameron] Right here.
- [Xander] Here, you do the poking.
Don't poke it into the thing,
but how deep is it?
Here, grab it.
- [Elondra] (Giggles)
- [Xander] No, you're not supposed to do that.
Remember what she did?
- [Girl in floral] Okay, this right here.
- [Xander] It's about three centimeters.
- [Cameron] Three centimeters.
- [Elondra] So, depth of straight channel
is three centimeters.
- [Elondra] Okay, what do we measure next?
- [Cameron] Okay, time to do the width.
- [Elondra] How much was it?
- [Cameron] Three centimeters.
- [Elondra] Three? Okay.
What's the widest?
- [Girl in floral] Where's the measuring tape?
Around six centimeters.
[Elondra] - How much?
[Xander] - Six.
- [Cameron] Six centimeters.
- [Elondra] Six.
Okay, now we need to do width of soil drop
to end of stream channel.
It's all this, it's all from right here.
- [Xander] It's from here to here.
You guys, we need the tape measure.
- [Girl in floral] Yeah, width, from here to here.
No, it's this long.
I've got it with my fingers.
This long.
- [Xander] It's about 15.
- [Girl in floral] No, it's 14 and a half.
- [Xander] No that's 15.
- [Elondra] Yeah, 15.
- [Girl in floral] Oh yeah, 15.
- [Elondra] Same with the other one.
- [Cameron] 15.
- [Elondra] It goes all the way to the end.
- [Cameron] Yeah, length.
- [Elondra] Okay, 29.
- [Cameron] How many?
- [Xander and Elondra] 29.
- [Girl in floral] Yeah, and depth of soil dripped
at the end of end of the stream channel.
Where's the toothpick?
- [Girl in gray] So right here...
- [Cody] Right there, yeah.
- [Girl in gray] Okay, where's the time?
- [Girl in gray](Background Chatter)
- [Kendra] (Background Chatter)
- [Kendra] (Giggles)
- [Girl in gray] Okay, so, can you hold that there?
(Background Chatter)
- [Jorge] How much is it?
- [Girl in gray] Five centimeters.
- [Kendra] How many?
- [Girl in gray] Five.
- [Kendra] Five c-m.
- [Kendra] Okay, width of the
soil dropped at the end
of the stream channel.
So right here.
- [Cody] We're gonna actually move to here.
- [Kendra] No no, width.
- [Cody] Oh, width?
- [Girl in gray] Looks about...
- [Cody] 11 centimeters, maybe?
- [Kendra] 11 centimeters.
Alright, length of the soil dropped
at the end of the stream channel.
So now we're measuring that.
- [Girl in gray] Here, you can do it.
- [Teacher] So what're you guys
working on measuring now?
- [Girl in gray] Length.
- [Cody] We've got a long length.
- [Girl in gray] 27.
- [Cody] 28.
- [Kendra] 28, yeah.
- [Cody] 28 centimeters.
- [Girl in gray] Jorge, you can measure--
- [Cody] Now what do we measure?
Depth of soil dropped at end of the--
- [Girl in gray] Wait, what was it?
- [Kendra] 28.
- [Cody] Depth of soil dropped at
the end of the stream channel.
- [Kendra] Where's the toothpick?
- [Girl in gray] I'm letting Jorge do it.
- [Cody] Okay.
- [Kendra] Jorge, you can do this one.
- [Cody] So, maybe poke it here.
- [Kendra] Poke it in there.
- [Cody] Now put your finger down.
Put your finger down where it is.
- [Kendra] Slide it down until you feel the dirt.
- [Cody] Good.
- [Girl in gray] Bring it over to Kendra.
- [Cody] So you can kinda see
the dirt right there.
That's not even a centimeter.
- [Kendra] You start here.
- [Cody] Okay.
That's not even a centimeter.
- [Kendra] That's three millimeters.
- [Girl in gray] So we round it down to zero centimeters.
- [Cody] Okay.
- [Kendra] Zero.
Okay, we're all done.
- [Cody] No, we still have to--
- [Kendra] "Work on your bird's-eye
view picture in your notebook."
(Background Chatter)
- [Girl in gray] Up in the big can.
- [Cody] Oh no, they're over there.
- [Girl in gray] Okay. The same bird's-eye
view or a different view?
- [Kendra] That's what I was going to--
(Background Chatter)
- [Kendra] I'm especially gonna draw in here,
because that's really interesting.
- [Girl in gray] Really interesting.
- [Both] (laughs)
- [Girl in gray] Did Cody just go get something?
- [Kendra] Yes, he did.
- [Girl in gray] Oh my gosh, he's so nice.
- [Teacher] So did you guys finish taking your data?
- [Girl in gray] Yeah, we're gonna do
our bird's-eye view.
- [Teacher] Before you guys look
at your bird's-eye view,
I want you to share.
What'd you guys find from your data?
So let's look at your data tables for a minute.
- [Girl in gray] Okay.
- [Cody] It kind of made like a cave.
- [Girl in gray] No, right here.
- [Teacher] Yeah.
- [Girl in gray] So I see the
difference right here.
In the depth of the stream channel,
the basic stream was actually more
than the rushing river.
- [Teacher] What was more?
- [Girl in gray] Like, in centimeters,
so one centimeter off.
- [Teacher] So, Alejandro's looking at the depth
of the stream channel,
and the last time it was
three centimeters deep
and this time it was only
two centimeters deep?
So last time it was actually deeper.
How about which one was wider?
- [Gitl in htsy] The rushing river.
- [Teacher] So the rushing river made
a wider stream channel?
- [Kendra] Yeah.
- [Girl in gray] I think the reason why it was wider
is because more water came in.
- [Kendra] It basically didn't
spend enough time going in,
it basically just went--
- [Girl in gray] Yeah, and it made it
more curved-inish and stuff.
- [Teacher] Okay. Jorge, what'd you notice?
- [Jorge] I noticed that, right here,
it made a little cave,
and I think something like water,
I think there was a
little whirlpool there.
- [Cody] Yeah, there was.
- [Girl in gray] There were a bunch of whirlpools.
- [Cody] Yeah, there were doubles.
- [Girl in gray] There's one right here and here.
- [Jorge] So I think it broke the water
(Background Chatter).
- [Kendra] I saw one little whirlpool right there,
and another one over here.
- [Cody] I saw one here.
- [Teacher] So the water was kinda
doing some different things
in some of these places?
- [Cody] Yeah, I think it's
'cause it curves like that,
so the bubbles keep on spinning
if the water's coming through.
- [Jorge] Yeah, so the water's--
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] So what about the delta?
The deposition?
How is this different than
your first experiment?
- [Girl in gray] Oh my gosh, it was
five centimeters bigger.
- [Teacher] Five centimeters bigger?
What'd you notice, Jorge?
- [Jorge] The biggest part was that
it was only this part right here.
- [Teacher] Okay.
- [Kendra] Yeah, that was the
longest part that was part of it all.
- [Teacher] So Cody, I noticed that, this time,
how deep was your delta?
- [Cody] Our delta, which would
be to get that soil?
- [Teacher] Yeah.
- [Cody] Zero centimeters.
- [Teacher] So does that mean there's no delta?
So how did you guys come up with zero?
- [Cody] 'Cause it was three millimeters,
so we had to round down.
- [Teacher] Okay, so you guys have your data.
- [Girl in gray] And the length of the soil--
- [Teacher] It was a lot wider, wasn't it?
- [Girl in gray] Yeah, the length of the soil
was like four centimeters bigger.
It was from the end right here
and it continued down.
- [Teacher] So you guys, remember,
we're gonna take this data--
- [Jorge] Someday are we gonna put
more of that stuff in here?
- [Teacher] Oh, put more of the earth material in?
- [Jorge] Yeah.
- [Teacher] And see what it would be like
if you added more material?
- [Jorge] (Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Okay, maybe that would be a
question we could investigate.
- [Kendra] Maybe the
delta would be thicker
because there's not
enough room for all of it.
- [Jorge] You know why
I'm asking you that?
Because I think it would be deeper,
because right here it only
makes little ones here,
but the other one would
probably make it bigger
because it has more space.
- [Teacher] Okay. So you think these
channels might be bigger?
- [Jorge] Yeah.
- [Teacher] If there was more earth material?
- [Girl in gray] What
if we made an even bigger hole?
- [Teacher] Oh, so you're wondering if
it was an even bigger flood,
what might happen?
- [Jorge] Maybe that would be
a hole like this big.
- [Teacher] Yeah, you guys are doing
that thing that scientists do
after they do an investigation,
they start asking more questions,
"I wonder, what if we tried this."
So you guys have got your data,
so we'll be ready to put this
in the class data table, right?
Find our averages probably on Thursday?
Right now, you guys are
going to be working on--
you want to make sure you
get the runoff sample,
draw what that looks like today,
we'll see what it looks like
when it settles out later,
and then you guys are going to
work on your bird's eye view,
and think about where's the humus,
where's the gravel, where's the clay,
so you can add that into the picture.
- [Cody] Hey guys, I'm gonna like--
- [Girl in gray] Yeah,
I was thinking the same thing,
like rip this up.
- [Cody] Whoa, there's the biggest--
- [Girl in gray] Oh, that's cool!
- [Kendra] Ms. Maher, it made a big dip.
- [Cody] I'm guessing that
some water's still down there.