- Viewing my art room from the front
corner I have a storage area on the right
hand side. Entry to the art room and paint
storage is right by the door. Uh, a cart
for paint supplies that can be wheeled out
into the room. I have a large white
cabinet for all of my paper and on the
other side storage for student art work. I
have a dry erase board, a digital white
board and a bulletin board for instruction
for students in the front of the room. We
often sit right in the center of the room.
There's also a birthday chair there for
the birthday person to sit in. My tables
are shaped around there in a U-shaped
formation, each labeled by a colorful
paint splot hanging from the ceiling.
Indicating the table there's a red table,
orange, yellow, green, blue and so forth.
Each table has organized supplies in a
painted shoebox and red caddies left on
the tables. In the very back corner is the
teacher desk. Two computers to the left of
that as well as a laptop that's hooked up
to the digital whiteboard. Across the back
of the room I have work space for our
student teacher and also to mount student
art work, and store some ongoing large
artworks. On the back wall I have more
storage: metal cabinets, rolling
cabinets and a light board that we can use
to copy work from. And directly below me
is our class pet this is where Shelly the
turtle lives and she is currently
hibernating.
- Like rabbits and dogs, dinosaurs.
And kitty cats
And puppies
So first thing we are going to do today is
look at pictures. Listen so that we have
time for working. I need everyone to put
in bubble. We are going to look at some
pictures that artists have made long,
long, long ago. The very oldest art in the
whole world. Are horses and bulls inside
of a cave. So the very first artists way
back during cave people they were making
art about animals. About horses and
animals that ran around that they saw in
their environment all around them. Put
hands down, put hands down.
- ...dinosaurs ...yeah
- Well that was after the dinosaurs. But
I'm looking for somebody that would be
able to point out an animal that they
recognize up here. Does anyone recognize
some of those animals?
- Yeah
- Izaiah do you? Izaiah? Izaiah with a
"Z." Do you want to go up and point?
Come up and show us some animals that you
recognize.
- Only animals who... only, only...
- Listen! She's the teacher right now.
What's it?
- Kangaroo
- What else? Let her answer.
- Fish and turtle and, um, crocodile and a
duck.
- Yeah and some kind of a bird. Good job.
Did you notice that these are all made
with dots?
That's how some artists who live in
Australia... Kimberly come right here in
front of me... Turn around so you can
see. That's how some artists in Australia
make animals.
And they kind of show what's inside of
them, don't they? It's really good that
you notice that, Izaiah. Do you have a
comment?
- I know all those animals
- Good so you were naming them right along
with her? Raiden, why is your name up,
your hand up?
- You said last time we have to finish our
[Inaudible].
- Oh we do have to finish those you're
right. We will, don't worry.
Okay. Next.
What kind of animal is that?
- A horse.
- A horse. You know what it says at the
top? It's a horse of a different color.
Because what color is it?
- [Together] Blue.
- Kind of like the "Wizard of Oz?"
[ Background Chatter]
right there. Why, boys and girls? Why is
the horse blue? What do you think? Why is
the horse blue?
- To make the horse beautiful!
- To make it beautiful? Why else would it
be blue?
- Maybe because it... ?
-There's another one.
- It's a unicorn horse isn't it?
What?
[Background Chatter]
-Shhhh... what? I'm curious...
- Izaiah, why would an artist make a horse
blue?
- Because it might be a unicorn.
- Well, it could be. Why?
- Because it might be a different kind of animal.
- Yeah, it might be a different type of animal horse.
- Have you ever drawn a picture and maybe
just used your imagination? And used your
favorite colors in it? How many people do
that sometimes? I know I do. Sometimes I
might make an animal but instead of making
him brown, maybe I'll make him pink and
purple and yellow.
- Ooooooh!
- And make him a little bit more
imaginative.
- Sometimes at my dad's house all by
myself.
- What else do we have?
- Another horse.
- Here's a fancy prancy horse.
Now the other horse was kind of looking
down, but what's this horse doing? What's
this horse doing?
- Jumping.
- Flying.
- He's walking or galloping, isn't he? He
looks... Look how he's standing. Look at
the two horses. If you had to tell me how
this horse is feeling...
- [Together] Sad.
- Why do we think sad? Emma why do you
think sad?
- Because he's looking down.
- He is looking down, isn't he?
- Maybe he's sad because his family just
got killed by another animal.
- Oh, I hope that didn't happen. He could
be sad about something that happened. What
about this horse?
- [Together] Happy!
- Why Melanie why do you think he looks
happy?
- Because he still has a family of his
own.
- Because why?
- Because he still has a family of
his own.
- That's not why! That's not why!
- Izaiah, you might have a different idea
than Melanie. Isn't it okay to have a
different idea?
- Yeah
- So, I need you sitting, Kimberly and
Regan, you both need to be sitting right
here where you can see hun.
Izaiah so it's okay to have... what was
your idea about why he might be happy?
- Because he's walking and his family is
going to get killed by a pack of animals.
- Oh my, but that wouldn't be very happy
would it? You think he looks happy? Are
there any other words you can think of to
describe him?
He's prancing around. Usually if you're in
a bad mood do you walk around like this?
With your head up?
- No.
- I used to do this, too.
- That's not prancing, that's stomping.
But prancing is when you have your head
up, isn't it? Kimberly! Kimberly! Right
here. Come over here by me.
- Maybe... maybe he was doing this because
[inaudible] on his arm. There's
something on his arm.
- Oh, it could be like a bandage, couldn't
it? It might just be the way it's painted
like his knees are a little bit lighter
than the rest of him. Is that what you're
noticing? What are you noticing?
- [Inaudible] but one of my
family died
- Awww. That is sad, isn't it?
- Really really really old.
- [Background Chatter]
- That happens sometimes, I'm sorry.
[Background Chatter]
- ...family died in a fire...
- Guess what? Guess what?
- Shhhh... Kimberly if you want to earn
your star card today you have to come sit
by me. Brandon if you want to earn yours
you have to be sitting on your bottom, not
crawling on the floor.
- You have to color inside of it?
[Background Chatter]
- You might want to draw his shell first
to make it really big.
- Look at mine!
- Can I see?
- Good job! Make these lines really,
really dark.
- Hey, look at my turtle.
- Go back over it like this.
- Boys and girls, if your paper's kind of
[Inaudible]
'cause you're pushing so hard then you're
drawing dark enough. Okay, they should
really be pressing hard with that.
Good, go over it really really dark.
That's dark enough. It looks great.
- Oh Kimberly yes.
- And put your name on the front with the
crayon.
Well look Izaiah, here's two choices for
your shell. You can start with an oval
like that or you can start like this.
Okay. Yeah but I think two different ways
see the top one and the bottom was a half
circle.
Which one do you like? Make it really big.
Perfect! There you go!
[Background Chatter]
- Look at my turtle.
- Boys and girls I want you to darken your
lines and draw for at least five more
minutes before you paint. Okay? Keep
darkening your lines.
Okay, darken those lines.
- We have to go and get our paint.
- Boys and girls, darken every line and
I'm going to come around and as soon as I
see that yours is nice and dark I'll put
the paint on your table. Okay?
This is yours? That's good, that's good.
This is dark enough. What I want you to
trace over is the black parts. And see
these pencil lines? You have to trace over
top of them. Or the paint will cover them
up. So, what color would you like to use
there? What color would you like to trace
these in? Come pick a color. Come sit down.
Tyler start working on your design. No,
start working on your designs in the
middle.
That's perfect. Nice and dark.
Boys and girls, see how dark these lines
are? This is a really good example of how
dark you want your crayon to be. You want
to go back over it and trace it really
dark. That one looks good, too. Nice and
dark. That's awesome!
- Start drawing.
[Background Chatter]
- I need yellow
- Boys and girls, would you put your name
on...
- [Intercom Announcement]Pardon the interruption,
[Inaudible] please
come to the office. [Inaudible]
please come to the office.
- [Teacher]Put your name right here. While you're
getting ready to paint, put your name on
the front in crayon. Nice and dark, write
your name nice and dark with your crayon.
Well, trace over it with the crayon.
- Look at mine.
- As soon as you're sitting down, Caitlin.
I'm coming around to look.
Boys and girls, when you're ready, you may
put your hand up and I'll come around and
check your pictures.
You are ready. Yours looks really nice.
Good!
He made me draw it for you.
Very good!
[Background Chatter]
- Melody, I'm waiting for that hand to go
up.
Isaiah, ah! That looks great! While you're
waiting for your paint, make those darker.
[Background Chatter]
- Shhhh...
Darken these a little bit.
- Izaiah what are you doing?
- Oh, I like your turtle.
[Background Chatter]