- [Teacher] Good, right?
So I was telling you that
these are the piece of bread
and these were a piece of bread
and I could have a
peanut butter and jelly sandwich
on white bread,
or I can have a peanut butter
and jelly on wheat bread.
We're going to keep the
white bread for right now.
Pop push.
Then this made me laugh.
Think about this as the heel of the bread.
- [Student 1] I don't get it.
(Teacher laughing)
- [Teacher] I'm glad to know that
you're like "I don't get it."
There's a piece of bread and
there's a heel of the bread--
- [Students] Oh!
(Teacher laughing)
- [Student 2] The butt of the bread?
- Yeah!
Oh, that's why!
Because you call it the
"butt of the bread".
Oh!
But it's the heel of the bread.
Ok so not so funny.
(Students laughing)
- [Teacher] So we have pop push, step
as our ingredient and then as our
butt of the bread, good
flap step dig, right?
So today we're going to do
pop push, step, good flap, step dig
as a review on the right and on the left.
And then we're going to do pop push, flap,
we're going to add another ingredient,
flap step dig. Okay?
Flap step dig.
Now remember--this--
is important, why?
- [Students] It's the ingredient.
- [Teeacher] barely
comes up, think about it.
- [Student 3] Good flap
because when you step flap
means that it's two sounds to (mumbles).
- [Teacher] Boo ya!
Remember it's two sounds
and that's why you say "Good flap"
and to get it up, she said, real high.
Alright, everybody up,
(claps her hands) spread out.
Pop push.
Pop push again is spank, kick.
It's exactly what we did as warm up
the one across the board.
Put your right heel out.
I need a good pop push.
Ready and (shoes tapping).
I need a good step. (shoes tapping)
As we step, what do we do?
What happens to the body?
- [Students] We swing right.
- [Teacher] We sure did, pick up that foot.
Good flap, (shoes tapping)
step dig. (shoes tapping)
Alright, do it one more time.
Let's do an echo.
Let me do it.
I'll do pop push, step, you do
- [Students] Pop push, step.
- [Teacher] I do good flap, step dig.
You do--
- [Students] Good flap, step dig.
- [Teacher] Right, right.
And I go.
(Teacher's shoes tapping)
(Students' shoes tapping)
Okay, I go.
(Teacher's shoes tapping)
(Students' shoes tapping)
-[Teacher] Better.
(teacher' shoes tapping
and then the students')
- [Teacher] Ok by now our muscle
memory is either going
"I got it! I've worked it out"
or "I don't got it"
and we need to correct it
before it becomes muscle memory.
So here's what I want you to do.
Say "Pop push step".
- [Students] Pop push step.
- [Teacher] Good flap step dig.
- [Students] Good flap step dig.
- [Teacher] Pop push step.
- [Students] Pop push step.
- [Teacher] Good flap step dig.
- [Students] Good flap step dig.
- [Teacher] Pop push step.
- [Students] Pop push step.
- [Teacher] Good flap step dig.
- [Students] Good flap step dig.
- [Teacher] Right foot out.
Six, (hands clapping) here you go.
You take--
- [Everyone] Pop push step
- [Teacher] Good flap step dig.
Good flap step dig.
- [Teacher] You can do a shuffle.
Pop push step
Good flap step dig.
You want to? Okay.
(shoes tapping)
- [Teacher] Not too bad!
Look at y'all keep on going
just like wonderful kids!
Now let me take a dip.
What I need you to do real quick:
bunch up right here.
Bunch up.
Do me a favor and...
bunch up right there.
Do you body roll?
- [Student] Not really.
- [Teacher] Yeah you do. (laughs)
- [Student] No.
- [Teacher] Sure you do.
Ok well I got it wrong.
You don't body roll but you will.
You rock, you rock, knee right.
(Background Chatter)
No? (Giggles)
Come on, right hand.
Flap, step, dig.
See you're doing this
really well. (Giggles)
Alright point your leg, listen.
We're going flap, step, dig.
(Background Chatter)
Flap, step, dig.
Ready?
And right foot, step, flap step dig.
Yes!
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] How is this group doing?
Okay everybody look, everybody look!
Here we go.
Five, six oh you precious thing.
Are you ready?
Deep breaths.
You need your right foot out.
Six, ready, and pop push step.
Good flap step dig.
Almost, left foot.
Pop push step
Left foot, good flap step dig.
Okay, let me tell you why.
You're doing a shuffle.
We do pop push, step, lift your foot up,
good flap step dig, on left foot.
Pop push step.
Good flap, step dig.
These were all two things.
Okay, body roll.
Do a body roll.
Now you can't do a body
roll back here. (Laughs)
Hold my hand.
Here we go.
Pop push.
Step. Shift it over.
Good, flap step dig, right here.
Good flap step dig.
Did you get all this?
Again the right foot.
Flex your toes.
Good flap step dig.
(Background Chatter) bring it in.
Oh, no you gotta body roll!
Bring it in.
Good flap step dig.
That's better.
And since the problem is
your weight distribution
it's back here and it's
hard to do it like this.
So you gotta do like this.
Yeah? Okay.
Alright, let me see the middle group.
Middle group!
Right foot out.
Ready, oh sorry, I got all excited.
You were ready.
Six, ready, and
pop push step.
Yes, okay.
Let's go pop push step,
hold for a second, good flap step dig.
Ready?
Right foot.
And pop push step,
hold for a second,
good flap step dig.
Yes!
Left foot, left, foot, left foot.
Six, ready, and
pop push step,
good flap step dig.
Almost, almost.
I saw it on the right, do
it on the left real quick.
Left foot and...
pop push,
push your heel down.
Base.
(shoes tapping)
Let me hear some base, do it again.
Pop push
step, pick up that foot,
good flap step dig.
Good flap step dig.
Left foot, good flap,
come on baby.
- [Student] With the lift?
- [Teacher] With the lift.
Oh sorry, my bad, my bad, to the right.
Good flap, step dig.
That's it!
(Everyone applauding)
Show some love, very nice!
Alright this group, come on.
Right foot out.
Six, ready, and
pop push step.
Oh I got overachievers I love it!
This time with the hold punched in it.
Now let me see the hold.
Six, ready and
pop push step hold for a second
good flag step dig.
Left foot.
Pop push step, hold for a sec,
good flap step dig.
Love it!
Let's take out the hold.
Pop push step, good flap step dig.
Five, six, right foot ready and
(shoes tapping)
- [Teacher] And ready stop.
You know what?
Not so bad.
Alright this is what we're going to do.
We're going to move on,
we're going to move on.
I want to see pop push FLAP.
Pop push flap on the right foot.
Put your right heel out.
We're gonna go
pop push flap.
Where's my head?
- [Students] Over you.
- [Teacher] Over the front of
the body, that's right.
Five, six, ready and
pop push flap.
Yes, five, six, ready and
Five, six, ready and
pop push flap.
Not bad.
Five, six, last time in
push and freeze.
We're going to take a second
piece of bread, that heel
and go good flap step dig.
It happens with the left foot.
Five, six, ready and
good flap step dig.
You already know that part!
Isn't that fabulous?
So we're going to put together
pop push flap,
flap step good.
Five, six, right foot goes
pop push flap, flap step dig.
Oh!
Wah!
Say it for a second.
- [Everyone] Pop push flap, flap step dig.
Pop push flap, flap step dig.
- [Teacher] Say it!
- [Everyone] Pop push flap, flap step dig.
Pop push flap, flap step dig.
- [Teacher] Let me see the next move.
- [Teacher] In the shower?
(Students laughing)
Be careful you might slip.
That's a hazard, always safety first.
Yes?
Okay, Andra?
- [Andra] In Walmart.
- [Teacher] In Walmart, really?
- [Student] Love it!
- [Teacher] Okay.
- [Student] I do mines in Kroger.
(Laughing)
- [Teacher] Do you find--okay.
- [Student 4] I do mines in the kitchen.
- You do yours in the kitchen.
Does your mom yell at you?
[Student] No.
-[Teacher] Be careful.
- [Jasline] Like when you
sit down on the desk in class
and you just sit there, all year.
- [Teacher] Okay so Jasline, do your
teachers get on to you
when you practice in class?
- [Jasline] No cause I'm quiet.
- [Teacher] Because you're quiet.
(Students Laughing)
- [Teacher] Well number one, I'm super proud of you
for practicing everywhere.
And do you find that
you do it all the time?
In the store, in the school.
So it's not just something that
you're going to do in class.
You see this?
And what you're going to find is odd
a lot of former students
come back and they go:
"Oh, well I continue to do this
"and I'm not even taking tapping.
"I wish I could go find and tap more."
Okay when that's gonna happen,
because it is going to happen to you,
it's like a bug, it's like a virus,
you just get all excited and all that.
Go to Youtube for me,
and on Youtube, there are
lots of how-to videos.
Do you know you could look up
how to do this time-step
on the Youtube video?
Now is it going to be your standard
buck and wing arc, buck times step?
- [Students] No.
- [Teacher] No, it may not be because
remember the sandwiches
it may be a different kind of sandwich,
a different kind of time-step.
So, if you're ever curious
and you want to continue
this through like, because you're gonna.
Do you have to have tap shoes by the way?
- [Students] No.
- [Teacher] No.
What do you have to have?
- [Students] Hard floor.
- [Teacher] Tammy, sit up for me.
You what?
- [Student] A shoe with a hard bottom.
- [Teacher] Yeah. Look, I'm in heels right?
That's all you have to do.
Now one of the things that
I wanted to point out to you
as we're about to evaluate yourselves
and evaluate your peers,
I want you to look at weight distribution.
Say "weight distribution".
- [Students] Weight distribution.
- [Teacher] What is weight distribution?
- [Jasline] Can I use an example?
- [Teacher] Yes.
- [Jasline] Like when we're doing
the good flap ball change,
you have to move your
body up for the good flap
and you move it back
down for the step-beat.
- [Teacher] Okay, so great, Jasline said
that you have to move your
body forward on the good flap
and then back, and sit it
back down, for the step dig.
Anybody had something to add?
- [Student] Shift your weight.
- [Teacher] Yes, you're right you
shift your weight which way?
- [Student] Opposite of
which way you switch your knee.
- [Teacher] Oh, opposite of which
way of whatever foot I'm using
because if I have this foot up
I've got...
(show tapping)
right?
Does my body have to turn?
- [Students] No.
- [Teacher] No, but it kind of does, don't it?
Got some hip action going on right here.
(Students laughing)
Alright anybody else see
any weight distribution?
(shoes tapping)
- [Student] We can do the sink,
you're kind of down a little bit.
- [Teacher] Okay, I was going to say,
I was trying to get to you.
The weight distribution
doesn't necessarily
have to go right to left, right?
Or front to back.
It can go, up and down.
What is the reason we want
out weight distribution
kind of lowered?
- [Student] So we can move.
- [Teacher] Move.
- [Student] To have (Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] to have a better base for what?
- [Students] (Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Okay so we can keep the rhythm.
Because if the rate of speed, speeds up
then our rhythm has to
stay with it, right?
Tell me how different, how
important is weight distribution
as opposed to females and males?
Anybody know the difference?
We covered this one.
Where's the woman's center of gravity?
- [Student] In her glut.
(Students laughing)
- [Teacher] You are absolutely correct.
In her glut, right through here
and that's where women
tend to put on weight
right gravity centers,
her center of gravity
around her belly, the baby belly
and around...
- [Studnet 10] Idk.
- [Teacher] Oh Idk, alright you don't know?
So where is the men's center of gravity?
Where do they tend to...
- [Students] Torso.
- [Teacher] Torso.
Right, their diaphragm
and that's where we get
that spare tire from.
A man's center of gravity,
and this is what it means,
are we here?
There we are.
Here's what it means.
As the woman's center of gravity
if your body can be forward
and your bottom is still back
and you're fine and dandy.
A man, if this is him, he's going forward.
He's going to fall.
He's not going to be
able to keep his weight.
So it makes a difference
in your body posture
and your weight distribution.
Yes?
Let's look really quickly...
Oh, how many of you have
taught your significant adult?
You taught a significant adult
and you taught the time-step.
What did you see, anybody?
- [Student] Sometimes
your parents got the rhythm
(Background Chatter) has lost.
If your parents are a little older
than most average parents,
let's say like 40s to 50s.
- [Teacher] Good, good.
- [Jasline] Their
rhythm has kind lost it.
It takes a longer time to teach them.
They have to be concentrated
because they're like
"Uh uh do that again, do that again!".
- [Teacher] Okay, Jasline, that is awesome
I'm going to put you on hold for a minute
because I have heard
from you several times.
Let me hear from somebody new.
Come on, Audrey.
- [Audrey] I found that I really
got my skills from my mom.
My fast-learning skills.
- [Teacher] You got your fast learning
skills from your mom, awesome!
- [Audrey] She learned real fast.
- [Teacher] She picked it up good.
Alright who else?
- [Student] Instead of
teaching a significant adult
I taught my whole family to tap.
- [Teacher] You taught your whole family?
Rock on!
- [Student] I found out
that my youngest brother
learned faster than even my mother.
- [Teacher] So why do you think
your youngest brother
learned faster than your mom?
- [Student 12] I think she
slowed down over the years.
- [Teacher] Over the years, okay.
Okay let me hear from somebody up here
because I haven't heard
anything from up here.
- [Student] While I was teaching my
mama, my daddy got excited
and he wanted to,
so I taught both of them
and they decided upon themselves
who was going to learn
it the quickest and--
- [Teacher] Right, competition--
- [Student] And my mama, she
actually learned it faster
but although it took my daddy more time,
once he got it, he could
do it over and over again.
He actually got pretty
good, like speed-wise.
- [Teacher] See?
Tap is for all ages guys.
It'll keep you in good health,
it's something fun, it'll keep you active.
You don't have to learn a certain...
you know we learned a step
and I hate to teach a step
but that's the beautiful
thing about tapping,
it's you can come up
with all kinds of stuff.
And you know-- Hey, look here,
I want you to hear.
How many of you like step, step dancing?
Oh, all around the room.
Oh, we love the step dancing right?
Step and tap are similar,
do you see the correlations?
You're making rhythms, there
are prescribed movements.
So we need to
really think about the
ways that they intersect
and it may become the next big thing.
You just never know.
You might have tap groups all around.
Let's go ahead and do some
peer evaluation real quick.
I want you to watch the screen.
Now what I want you to watch--