[Background Chatter]
- [Instructor] So, who can tell me, in
this group, who can remind me, what is our
objective? What are we discovering today
in science? I'd like to see a lot of
volunteers. Lindsey?
- [Lindsey] We're seeing what soil holds
water better and...
- We're seeing which soil holds water
better. What's the term for that? Holds
water? Chris.
- [Chris] It's absorbing the water.
- What's absorbing the water?
- The clay and the sand absorb the water.
- Very good. So we're trying to figure out
which absorbs more water. Clay or sand,
today? Very good. Who can tell me what was
the first step that you did in this
project? Cameron.
- [Cameron] First, we poured in the sand.
- What did you pour the sand into?
- We poured it into a funnel.
- Okay. What's that thing on the funnel?
- It's a coffee filter.
- It's a coffee filter. Why do we need a
coffee filter on the funnel?
- Because when it's on the funnel it makes
it so that the sand doesn't run through
the funnel.
- Okay. All right. What's the second step?
Can somebody tell me what the second step
is? Cameron said you dump the soil sample,
whether it was clay or sand, into your
funnel. What's the second step? Caleb.
- [Caleb] The second second step is to
pour in the water.
- The second step was to pour in the
water. Who can tell me what the third step
is? What's the third step? Chris.
- You record how long it took for it to
drip every last drop into the cup of
water.
- What's it?
- The water.
- The water. Good. You're recording how
long it took for all of the
water... what's that word called? What
did that water do to get from here to the
surface to the bottom of the cup? Cameron?
- It drained.
- It drained. Very good. What are you
measuring in? Are you measuring in
seconds? Are you measuring in minutes? In
hours? Lindsey?
- Measuring in minutes with the seconds.
- You're measuring in minutes with
seconds. Okay. Can you tell me how long
your clay is up to for draining out the
water?
- Two minutes and a half.
- Two and a half minutes. Good. Can you
tell me, Cameron, how long it took for
your water to drain through your sand?
- It took 28 seconds.
- Twenty-eight seconds. Good job. Keep up
the good work. I really like all the
diagrams that I'm seeing. Lindsey, you did
an excellent job at paying very close
attention and following the steps, in
step-by-step order. You can give yourself
a point for science. Good job.
[Soft Background Chatter]
Ladies, can you tell me did your sand hold
water?
- [Luana] Yes.
- It did hold water. How did you know
that?
- Because it absorbs some of the water. I
poured it in here and it had
29... there's 29 left and I did 42
into the water, so the sand holds 11
milliliters of water.
- Good. So you're saying that the sand
held 11 milliliters of water. You said
that when you poured the water in through
the sand then you dumped something in this
graduated cylinder. What did you dump in
this graduated cylinder?
- [Student] We dumped all the water that
was in there.
- What's there?
- In the cup.
- So you dumped all the water that was in
the cup after what? What did the water do
in order to get in the cup?
- It drained through the funnel, through
the sand, down into the cup.
- So it drained through the funnel,
through the sand, down into the cup. So
then you took your water and you poured it
in your graduated cylinder. Luana, you
said you did 40 minus 29 to get 11
milliliters? Why did you do 40 minus 29?
- Because that's how you find out how much
the sand is holding.
- That's how you find out how much the
sand is holding? How did you know to start
with 40?
- Because we poured 40 milliliters of
water in the cup to start.
- Oh. To start, you poured 40 milliliters
of water in. You took the water that you
had to start and took away the amount that
was left, which you got 11 milliliters.
Very good. Excellent.
Gentlemen, what are you noticing about
sand and water?
- [Student] We're noticing, about the
sand, this time it took us two minutes and
eight seconds for it to stop dripping. We
started out with 40 milliliters and...
- What did you do with that 40 milliliters
of water?
- We poured it into the strainer to drain
it down into the cup and when we poured
into the cylinder we had 28 and a half
milliliters.
- Very good. How do you figure out how
much water is in the sand. What
subtraction sentence would you do?
- Forty minus 30.
- So you're rounding up. You said you had
29 and a half. Are you going to round that
to 30?
- Yes.
- That's a very good choice.
You're going to do 40 minus 30 so that
tells you how much water is in the sand,
which is?
- One, 10.
- Ten what?
- Milliliters.
- Ten milliliters. Very good. Do you think
some of that water's still in the funnel?
Because this funnel is still dry. This
funnel feels wet. Do you think some of
that 10 milliliters of water is in
this... not funnel, in this filter?
- Yes.
- Do you think so? Why do you think that?
- Because it's soaked and some of the
water might have stopped in there because
it was so thick and sandy.
- And now it's a little bit thinner? Keep
up the great work.
[Soft Background Chatter]
Sam and Madison, what are you noticing
about water with your sand and water with
your clay?
- [Sam] The sand drains the water faster
than the clay.
- The sand drains the water faster than
the clay. Have you figured out yet which
one holds more water?
- Clay.
- The clay holds more water. If you were a
gardener and if you were planting a
garden, what would you rather garden with?
Would you rather garden with sand or would
you rather garden with clay?
- Sand.
- Why's that?
- Because it drains water better and the
drainage would get to the plants faster.
- Okay. So the drainage would get to the
plants faster. Where do the plants need
the water?
- Roots.
- At the roots. What do you think,
Madison?
- [Madison] I would do a mixture of sand,
clay, and humus because mixed together
it's loamy and loamy soil is good for the
plants.
- Great observation. That's wonderful. So
you said you'd mix all of them together
because that would make a loamy mixture
which would allow the gardeners to get the
best soil for the plants to grow. Very
good. Nice job. What are you three
noticing about water and sand and water
and clay?
- [Student] Water and sand, it can absorb
through the sand, the water. And through
the clay it soaks and [inaudible] at four
minutes.
- You're almost at four minutes for your
clay. Wow. What do you think this shows
you about what happens on a rainy day
whether it's outside in our soccer field?
Or what happens on a rainy day in your
backyard? Does anybody want to tell me
what happens?
- The clay, it gets very muddy because the
water is pouring down on it. It might make
a puddle because some of the soil on the
ground can't hold itself so it might make
a puddle.
- Good. So Matthew, when you poured your
water into your clay, did you have a
puddle at the top of your clay?
- [Matthew] Yeah, we had a puddle at the
top of our clay because it was leaking
little drops and it stayed on top of the
clay. We had to wait a long time till we
could pour more water.
- What stayed for a long time on top of
the clay?
- The water did because it didn't have
small particle sizes so it was hard for
the water to get through.
- Oh, so the clay has small particle sizes
so it's hard for the water to get through.
Wow. Good job. What does that mean about
the particle size for the sand?
- It means that the particle for sand is
bigger and it has more space for the water
to drain through.
- Good. Excellent. Did any of you draw
diagrams of what your experiment set-up
looked like?
- What it looked like?
- I think you have a diagram on the
previous page. Did you draw a diagram?
- Yes.
- Okay. What did your diagram show?
- My diagram, for sand, shows that the
water is going right through the funnel
and it's pouring to the bottom. And for my
clay it's little drops because the clay is
stuck together once it has water.
- Good. I can easily tell, in your
diagram, which one's sand and which one's
clay. One suggestion that I can make to
you, though, is I would like a few more
labels. If I were to never see this
experiment before, how would I know that
this is sand and that this is clay? So if you
could label those for me and tell me what
these drops are. I don't know if they're
water, or [inaudible] or milk. If you
could do a little bit more labelling for
me, that would be excellent. Good job.
Nice work. Very impressive.
[Soft Background Chatter]
How long are you guys up to for your water
being through your filter, through your
clay?
- [Xavier] Five minutes and 45 seconds.
- Five minutes and 45 seconds. I can tell
that both of you are working very hard.
And Xavier, you're doing excellent job at
staying in your seat the whole time. You
can give yourself a point right now for
being on task. Nice job. Good.
What are you noticing about sand, clay and
water?
- [Student] I noticed that the clay held
less water than the sand and I was really
surprised by that because I thought that
water can go through sand fast.
- So you were really surprised because you
didn't think water would go through sand
that fast? And how much water did your
sand hold?
- Our sand held 11 milliliters.
- Eleven milliliters. Good. And how much
did your clay hold, do you know?
- [Kendall] Five.
- Held five milliliters. Wow. What number
sentence did you do in order to figure out
how many milliliters were in the clay and
how many milliliters were in the sand?
- We did 40 minus however the milliliters
were left in the cup.
- Okay. And why did you do that?
- Because we had 40 to begin with and we
needed to find out how many were left
and... I forgot.
- You forgot? Kendall, can you help her
out?
- We got 29 in this and it began
with 40. So we had to do 40 minus 29.
Forty minus 29 is 11 millimeters.
- Milliliters.
Good. Remember millimeters is when we're
using rulers and milliliters is when we're
measuring water. Okay? Excellent job.
Which soil would you rather garden with?
Would you rather garden with sand or would
you rather garden with clay?
- I would garden with both of them so I could get a
loamy soil and loamy soils are better for the flowers.
- Okay. So you would mix them together so
that you could get a loamy mixture. What
about you, Kendall?
- I would do sand because water can get
through it easily.
- So water can get through it easily? Why
would that matter?
- Because the soil and everything else,
and the grass and everything, needs water
but if you use clay it just stays on top
and it can't get water.
- Very good. Excellent. Looks like you
girls are ready to move on to your
graphing. What are we going to graph? What
are we graphing today?
- How much water is in the...