- [Instructor] That's what we're going to
do today, is you all are going to learn
how to draw blood. You're going to learn
how to actually stick the fake arms that
we have or the phlebotomy learning aids is
actually what they're called. And each one
of you have gotten to a certain point in
either phlebotomy or medical assisting
where you're ready to start drawing blood.
And I know that Wanda has gotten a little
further but it never hurts to refresh on
the procedures because, guys, when you get
out there in the clinical area, a lot of
people don't follow a lot of the steps
that you need to do as far as blood draws.
Guys that are medical assisting, you are
not going to have to do as many
venipunctures and the phlebotomy students
but you may be responsible for drawing
blood in a doctor's office. When you're
there in the doctor's office it's just you
and the person. So you quickly develop
really good phlebotomy skills because if
you don't get it then you have to send
them to outpatient hospital to be able to
get that blood drawn. The first things I
want to talk about is your vein choice.
And I printed off your veins. And the
median cubital is your vein of choice and
the median cubital runs
right here in the middle.
- [Female] You can see this one better.
- Yeah, you see that one better. Your
median cubital runs right in the middle
and then your basilic is the one you want
to stay away from. That's the one that
runs little finger side. And then your
cephalic is on the thumb side. So this
little finger side toward the inside of
the elbow is the one you really want to
stay away from. And the reason that this
is your last choice vein is there's quite
a few nerves that are right underneath it.
So if you go too deep or you move the
needle around too much you can actually
cause nerve damage. And I will leave this
on the table as y'all are practicing
with your phlebotomy arms so that you can
look at your vein choice. Nerve damage is
a very real possibility and some nerve
damage is permanent so be very careful
when you're choosing your vein. You can
only advance or withdraw the needle only.
You cannot go sideways. I know those of
you who's already been in the clinical site,
you've seen them go sideways, you've seen
them come out and go back in. And guys,
that could be a liability for you, and
you're the only one that can protect your
patient and you. I've got the materials
set up. Whenever we repeat this, you all
will set your materials up so take notice
of what we've got here because you'll need
this every time you practice on the
phlebotomy arms. When you go to clean your
arm, you're going to clean in a circular
motion. So I'm going to go ahead and get
started. First thing you're going to do, I
don't need your gloves, just the two
hands. First thing you're
going to do is put on your gloves. I just
washed my hands but I'm going to put on my
gloves. And why do I want to do that? Jim.
- [Jim] So I don't get infected.
- Yeah, I don't want to come into contact
with someone's blood. Now, who could
protect me from coming into contact with
someone's blood?
- Yourself.
- I'm the only one that can do that. And I
can tell you, from having my blood drawn,
people have drawn my blood without gloves on
though they didn't know me from Adam. And
one person in particular got quite a bit
of my blood on them. So I am the only one
that can protect me. If I see you
practicing without your gloves on, it is
an automatic grade ding for that practice
day. If I see you drawing in the clinical
area without gloves on, then we're going
to have a big talk, okay?
Because you've got to protect you.
- [Cathy] I have a question.
With some people that you draw blood on,
do you have to wear a mask?
Like an eyeshield-type thing.
- If they are on precautions then yes, you
would. And you've seen, at the hospital,
on the doors where they have contact and
respiratory isolation. If you were to go
into one of those rooms, yes you would. In
the ER, when you draw blood, you usually
have on that splash mask. Now usually,
with a venipuncture, you're not going to
have that much pressure. It's not going to
shoot the blood back out at you like an
arterial would, but still, it's better to
err on the side of safety. But also, if
there's nothing wrong with me except I
need a CBC to have a surgery and you come
at me with a mask and a shield, I'm going
to think, "Oh my gosh. Why is she doing
that?" You know? So make sure that it's
appropriate. If you're in a trauma area
then yes, definitely. If you're in an
outpatient clinic, unless that patient
tells you, "My veins squirt blood really
bad." A patient will tell you. One time I
was doing a finger stick and it squirted
and I had on my glasses but I turned my
head. It hit me in the hair. So sometimes
the venous flow will do that. Good
question, Cathy. All right, so got my
gloves on, first I'm going to do is I'm
going to put the tourniquet on. And guys,
the tourniquet can be kind of tricky the
first time or two you do it. And you're
going to put it underneath the arm. You
need to make sure it's tight so your vein
will pop up but not so tight you're going
to cut off the blood flow and not so tight
you're going to cause petechiae, which is
little red patches on the arm. I'm going
to cross my hands over. What I do is I put
my left hand in position, I take my right
hand, get ahold of the tail of this, pull
it, and then I stick it underneath with my
little finger. You always want your tails
up toward the top so they're not in your
area where you're going to clean and draw.
When I'm going to clean... well, let me
show you how to feel first.
Well, it's not going to cooperate today.
- You can use my arm. That way
they can see better.
- Can you move the Sharps container?
- I'm going to stick it underneath there.
And now it should stay on there. Now to
locate a vein, I'm going to take my index
finger and I'm going to feel back and
forth. And guys, you all can do this on
each other. Jim's excellent to feel veins
on and he's a real good volunteer. Bounce
back and forth. It feels like a gummy worm
or something soft underneath there. If it
feels really hard, like I have one that
I'll let you all feel that is very
sclerotic or hard, you're not going to get
blood out of it. It's got to be... it's got
to bounce. So when you go across and you
find it, then you're going to find which
way it travels. So you're going to go up
it and down it so you know which way to
put your needle in. Some veins will go off
to the side and some remain very straight.
So I found my vein. Now the tourniquet can
only stay on for one minute. Has my
tourniquet been on about a minute?
Probably so, so I need to take the
tourniquet off, give this patient's arm a
rest, and then I can talk to them about
the weather, I can go ahead and line up my
tubes at that time, and then I'm ready to
draw blood now. So I come in here, I put
my tourniquet on, and guys, when you put
this tourniquet on you got to be ready to
go because you only have one minute. And
I'm going to clean. I'm going to clean in
a circular motion and then, if you're
having trouble with the alcohol, you're
not able to fan it, you can't blow on it,
and you can take one very clean 2 by 2,
go straight down, dry it off, and
then... many of you already did that. This
part of the needle, this part with the
rubber on it has the needle on it. You
screw that in, take the end off, this is a
safety needle. You anchor and then you
stick in the bevel of the needle, that is
the pointy part, the bevel goes up and
then the pointy part goes into the skin. I
pull my thumb away as I'm going in. I take
one of these Vacutainer tubes, thank you,
Jim, and I push it in. And guys, when I
push in with my thumb I'm pulling back
with my fingers. And you're not able to
see but there is... and I don't do this in
the clinical side, but there is blood
coming in there. You let it fill until it
stops. Now it's stopped flowing. I'm going
to wrap my fingers around it and push
because the more still you keep the
needle, the less it's going to hurt the
patient. Pop my tourniquet and I'm going
to take a different 2 by 2 than what I
cleaned with. Fold it, lay it on the arm,
and guys, I'm just going to kind of hover
there until I bring the needle out and
push down. If I push down while the needle
is in the arm, it hurts really bad. And
I'm going to hold here and I'm going to
hold until it quits bleeding. And you can
peek. Now if the blood... oh, sticky needle
engaged. It's hard to talk and do stuff at
the same time, isn't it? Sharps. And you
toss that in the sharps. Now, if this
patient is on blood thinners, I've got to
hold longer. A lot of clinics will just
put a 2 by 2 or a cotton ball on there,
put a CoBand on them and send them on
their way. If they bleed out outside of
the lab, you're liable. And again, you're
the only one that can protect you. So I
make sure that they've stopped bleeding.
And now how hard is that going to be when
there is a lobby full?
You guys have been observing.
- Can we ask them to hold it?
- Well, you can. But what if they don't
hold it tight enough? What if there's a
whole lobby full? Jim, what have you seen
them do in the past?
- [inaudible] and check.
- Yeah. You need to check it. If there's a
whole lobby full sitting out there then
you'll get to them when you get to them,
because you've got to protect your
phlebotomy certificate. You're the only
that can do that. A lot of places, they
will put a 2 by 2 or a cotton ball on
there, tell the patient to hold their arm
up. That breaks platelets, that's going to
make a huge bruise, and it doesn't really
help with the clotting that much, just
kind of bruises. So we're going to look
here. Okay, this patient has quit
bleeding, so I am good to go here. Now,
another lesson I will teach you about writing
on the vials, the blood draw vials and
what information needs to be on there. So
before you all draw, let me ask you a few
questions. What's your first choice vein?
- Median.
- Median. Okay. And why do we avoid the
basilic? Nicole.
- [Nicole] Nerves and tendons.
- Nerves. Okay. What can happen if
I... powder on the shirt. What can happen
if I dig around in there and I do injure
somebody? What can they do?
- They can bleed or they can have their
nerve damage.
- Right. And they can come and say, "This
phlebotomist drew here." And then, guys,
if you're ever in a setting where you have
to go to court, they're going to call
somebody that's a phlebotomist like you
are and they're going to ask them, "What's
your first choice vein?" And they're going
to say, "The median, " and they're going
to say, "What's your next choice? What's
your last choice?" So you're going to have
somebody there that knows. You really
don't want to draw from that one unless it
is your last choice. Okay, what can happen
if the patient's on blood thinners?
Cassie, what's the most important thing to
remember about the patient
that's on blood thinners?
- [Cassie] To keep pressure.
- To keep pressure. Okay. How do you clean
your site, Martika?
- [Martika] In a circular outward motion.
- Circular, you don't ever go back over.
And how long do you leave
the tourniquet on, Faye?
- [Faye] One minute.
- One minute. Good job. Okay. You all get
your... First thing you do is what?
- Gloves.
- Get your gloves on. So you all are
going to draw.
- With drawing blood, are you supposed to
record where you drew at and everything
just like a nurse is supposed to?
- I would if I were you, because that just
protects you. So you can write median. You
can write an MC, median cubital, and that
way you may... actually you could put it on
where you put your initials where you draw.
And that way they know that you
drew from the median. That you didn't draw
from basilic.
- I need another needle.
- Okay.
Anybody else need another needle?
- Thank you.
- You're welcome. I'm going to send
tourniquets home with you all and you can
practice on everybody. Feel their veins,
feel all the different types of veins.
Some people have garden hoses is what I
call them. Some people have very large
veins. And feel for your vein.
- The tourniquet pinched my thumb.
- The gloves are hard to... you trading
them out? It's this arm, Jim, I think
because I had trouble getting it.
- When I was doing it, too.
- Okay. Just make it a little
tighter with your...
- Oh.
- Did you stick yourself?
- Mm-mm.
- Okay.
- I screwed the wrong part.
- I think she's bleeding and I haven't
even done anything yet.
- Oh, yeah hand me another one.
- There it goes again.
- Okay, Casey. Let me see what I can do
for you. Good job, Martika.
- Want to just chill, how's the weather,
blah, blah, blah, blah.
- Is it not come undone now? You might
want to pull your tail, just pull it in
there with one of the smaller tails.
It'll stay down.
- Okay.
- It's moving again.
- You're kidding.
- See?
- Okay. Just keep going.
- Okay.
- Just keep going. It's easier on a
person. That's my stomach, Jim.
It's hungry. Sorry.
- [inaudible] Yeah, this one...
Jim knows which ones stay better. Okay,
you got to anchor your vein with your
non-dominant... with your non-dominant hand
you anchor your vein.
I have to stand. I can't... see, you take
your thumb and you pull down here.
Anchor your vein. There you go. Casey,
are you left-handed, too?
- Mm-mm. I thought you said non-dominant
hand.
- Non-dominant hand to anchor. Back it
out. Put it in this hand.
Are you right-handed?
- Mm-hmm.
- Put non-dominant hand thumb there,
anchor.
- Okay.
- Now, did you clean it?
- Yep.
- Okay. Then go in.
- Uh-oh.
- It's okay.
[Background Chatter]
- Well, that's okay. Put that on.
- Start over.
- A lot of this is hand movement. A lot of
this is prac--