- Keep the rhythm sync. Soft. As we do our
solos, here if you would take your
pencils, and when you hear the soloists
play, on these notes on the side of this
changing. I want you to put a mark beside
that change where you are. Put a count on
it. Each rotation will be different.
Sometimes they may play from the middle
scale to the middle or the whole thing.
Wherever you think that happens. I will be
documenting it over here, too. All right.
Today's volunteers are, beginning with the
vibe player, and then we'll just go
through the trumpets, the trombones, and
saxes and those others who are assigned to
play today. Here we go everybody got
pencils ready?
And one, one, two, three, four.
[xylophone solo]
Here we go Rockville. On my mark. One,
two, ready. . .
[trumpet solo]
One, two, and one, two ready play.
[trombone solo]