- Okay. So if you're having trouble seeing
it, you can go back in with a regular
pencil brush. Visible enough for you? You
can go back in and make it lighter. But
right now, the mark makings you're doing
is really good. As you want to turn, if
you're having trouble making curved lines,
you can turn--
- Oh, okay. All right, that helps.
- Instead of turning the tool, turn the
plate and keep pulling towards you.
- Okay.
- It might make it a little bit easier to
make those curves.
- Yeah, they're really tough to do.
Other than that, it's been fine.
- Good.
- Is that working now that you, what we
talked about yesterday with this little...
- Yeah.
- ...shadow?
- I thought it was kind of--
- Okay. And the same thing that I just
told Kim, if you're having trouble with
the curved lines, you can turn your plate
and keep pulling towards you instead of
using the tool to curve. All right, but so
far what you're doing is good. You're
adding all these different values.
Continue with that type of texture on the
edges because that's working.
- I'm just going--
- That's okay. Be patient. Have you
decided yet how you're gonna treat this
area in here?
- No, I'm probably gonna do what you
initially told me treating the light areas
from start from this bottom half
and doing--
- Okay, so adding a different texture. Are
you leaving the text?
- I never... I forgot to reprint it so
if I do decide...
- You'll just have to reverse the text.
- Yeah, I know, and I'll,
right, add it in.
- That's fine.
- I think I'll just decide it later.
- Yeah, finish your whole overall design
first.
- Yes, exactly.
- And then if you want the text in it, as
long as it's reversed so you print it the
right way.
- Yeah.
- You can just reprint it. Okay, sounds
good.
- Awesome.
- Yeah.
- So you're just... [Background Chatter]
- [together] Yeah.
- All right, the way you're doing the
crosshatching here is really strong so
continue that to make sure that it's
consistent.
- Do I have to make it identical?
- No. Well, what do you think?
Are these identical persons?
- It's like supposed to be but I know I'm
not gonna be able to get the exact family
on the other side but I think it would
look fine if it was different. I kinda
want it to look a little messy.
- You want there to be a little bit of a
different expressive line on each one. I
don't think there's anything wrong with
making them separate. I know that they're
trying to be echoing each other
symmetrically.
- Yeah.
- But all of the textures can be
different...
- Okay.
- ...to add some interest to it.
- I think it would be difficult to try to
get the exact same thing on the other
side.
- Right. Don't you think that it might be
more expressive to add different types of
textures anyway?
- Yeah, definitely.
- That's good. How did you decide that
you're going to treat the inside of the
mouth area? Are you gonna leave that dark
or do you want it to be light?
- Well, there's supposed to be some tongue
over here, but over here I'm gonna make it
like... I'm gonna try to go solid black
in some parts. Like I tried to do that
inside the mouth.
- Yeah! That's good. That's good.
- I want mine to seem [inaudible].
- So then all of those areas then
will stay dark?
- Yeah.
- It'll create a nice shadow. Excellent,
that's really good. Are you gonna go off
the edge?
- Yeah.
- Nice, that's really good. Keep it up.
And Emily, how's yours coming? Yeah, the
same thing. All those little dark areas
that you're working on inside in between
teeth, now that you've carved out all that
area, it's gonna create a darkened tone.
And as I mentioned before, all the
different stippling areas, that's really
good. It's adding some more dimension and
more depth to the figure. If you're
finding that it's easier for you to pull
it off of your initial drawing, if you
wanna get a white piece of paper to put
underneath or use a separate sheet, it
might be a little bit easier to see than
using the table.
- Okay.
- Good, good. This is good.
- I'm getting confused of where I'm going
because if I did the backgrounds, this is
the negative space that
I do the crosshatching.
Then it would have to
continue down here.
- So you want to decide all the different
types of textures that you're using in
between all of it.
- Yeah.
- All right, so you've got a little bit
of the crosshatching here, okay, and
you're using illustrative lines over here.
So you wanna try and find something in
between that's a little bit different.
Right?
- Uh-huh.
- Well, you haven't done any stippling
texture yet.
- I was working on...
- In here? Okay, so in here's gonna be
stippling. So right, then this can't be
the stippling because it's gonna be next
to it.
- I was thinking of here, kind of, moving
this pattern down and then maybe just,
sort of...
- Okay, I think that would be a good
solution to that.
- It's like this area in the background.
- Okay. Now what if you decided to leave
it for now by following just some of the
shadows that are there and creating
textures just where these shadows are and
then leaving that solid? And then you can
make a test print to see if you like the
way that looks keeping it solid. Then if
you really feel that it needs to have more
texture, you can go back
into it and add it again.
- Okay.
- Okay, so in here, like you said,
follow the movement of these
objects. Okay, this is all the chain
inside the bike. So following that
movement with your line would make a nice
gesture. And then in here just because you
have all this texture in here, you might
not need to put anything else there.
- Okay.
- What's your instinct as far as feeling
how busy it is now to add extra?
- Yeah, it's hard to tell because
I'm not sure how it's gonna look
when it's printed but I think that might
be good. Because it would get kind of
crazy. I think it might
be nice to have--
- And you wanna still have it have a focal
point. So if you go crazy with other
textures in here, you might be taking away
from the focal point of your art work.
- Okay.
- I'm having a hard time
seeing it so you--
- I might need to get one of those blue
sheets.
- Okay. The blue sheets are working? I
think, you know what? Emily's been using
the table. So maybe that helps her to see
her white lines. That has been helping. So
if you don't wanna use one of those blue
sheets, you can do what she's doing and
use the table.
- Yeah, I'll do that.
- I think I wanna lift
it off of the book.
- So you can keep it taped to this and
then flip the book out from underneath to
use it or get a darker sheet of paper to
help you see all your lines.
- Okay.
- Okay. You're still working on your
design right?
- Yeah.
- I think you might be ready to go on to
the plexiglass soon.
- Yeah.
- Because once you figure out what's going
on over here...
- Yeah, I just have to...
- Yeah and all of this positive and
negative space is really strong. So what
are you deciding to do with all of the
other areas? Are you gonna fill them in,
too?
- Yeah, I think so.
- Okay, then did you decide what kind of
texture that you wanna put in there when
you start etching it, engraving it?
- I don't know. I don't know if I should
do really fine crosshatching.
- Mm-hmm.
- But then should I put a new texture on
these?
- What do you think? Do you want it to be
solid or do you want to have the texture
when you make the print?
- Because I think if I texture both of
them, it'll be a little confusing so maybe
these should be plain and not have
texture.
- Okay, so you can texture crosshatching
in the background and then if you make a
test print first, you can decide. If
they're too solid, then
you can go back in with
a different texture.
- Okay.
- Okay. So finish up the regular part of
your design first and start working on the
engraving part and then you can do a test
print and decide if you want to add more
later.
- Okay.