- [Teacher] We haven't talked about
some things that we do
when we are what?
- [Kendrel] Sad.
- [Nick] Sad.
- [Teacher] Not sad. He's ma. . .
- [Kendrel, Nick] Mad!
- [Teacher] Mad.
He is really, really mad.
He's got that mad face going Rrrr.
- [Kendrel] He is so ugly!
He is so ugly.
- [Teacher] He is mad!
And it says, "sometimes I get mad."
Is it okay if we're mad?
- [Kendrel] Yeah.
- [Nick] Yeah.
- [Kendrel] What is (Background Chatter)
- [Jakiah] No.
- [Kendrell] If somebody eat people.
I bet that way too.
That must have been (Background Chatter)
- [Jakiah] Ow, Ow, Ow.
-[Teacher] If someone's biting they
probably would get in trouble.
because we don't want to hurt our friends.
- [Jakiah] Ow.
- [Nick] No!
- [Teacher] No we don't want to hurt our friends.
- [Jakiah] Ow, Ow, Ow.
- [Kendrel]or push them
out of the chair.
- [Teacher] Or push them out of
the chair, you're right.
that would hurt our friends too--
- [Nick] That's a man.
-[Teacher] --And we don't want to do
that, yes sir look up there.
Alright, what are some things
that make you mad, Nick?
- [Nick] When somebody hurt on fingers.
- [Teacher] When someone hurt your fingers,
that makes you mad?
That can make me mad too.
Jakiah, what's something
that makes you mad?
- [Jakiah] People bite me.
- [Teacher] If someone bit you,
who bit you?
- (Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Deion? Your brother?
I'd be mad too, 'cause that
hurts our friends, doesn't it?
-Kendrel, what's something
that makes you mad?
- [Kendrel] My sister beat me
off the chair and
my sister threw my toys.
- [Teacher] When she kicked your
chair and threw your toys?
- [Kendrel] And broke my TV.
- [Teacher] And broke your TV?
Oh, I'd be mad about that too.
Alright, this page--
- [Jakiah] You don't got a sister.
- [Teacher] Yes, he has a sister.
this says--
- [Nick] I do.
- [Teacher] when I get
mad sometimes I--
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] I hit, I. . .
- [Kendrel] Throw those toys.
- [Teacher] ...throw our toys.
I . . .
- [Kendrel] Bite somebody.
- [Teacher] I may bite.
or I may--
- [Kendrel] Yell.
- [Nick] Yell.
- [Teacher] Are those good things to do?
- [All] No!
- [Teacher] Why not?
- [Nick] Someone might cry.
-[Kendrel] In trouble!
- [Teacher] because, Nick said some
might cry, maybe it would hurt them.
- [Kendrel] And get in trouble!
- [Teacher] They would, but we don't
want to hurt our friends, do we?
- [Jakiah] And pull our hair.
- [Teacher] or if someone, yeah
we don't want to pull
our friends hair either cause
the would hurt our friends.
- [Kendrel] Or pull somebody's braids.
- [Teacher] Or pull somebodies
braids that would hurt
and that is not a good not a
(Background Chatter) is it?
- [Kendrel] My uncle had braids.
- [Teacher] Did he?
- [Jakiah] I do.
- [Teacher] This said, "this
is not a good idea,"
that is a--those are what?
those green choices or red choices?
- [All kids] Red choices.
- [Teacher] Those are red choices.
Things we do not want to do.
Alright, let's see
what our next page says.
It says, "When I am mad
it is a good idea too. . ."
who remembers something that we can do?
(Background Chatter)
-[Teacher] who remembers something
we can do
when we're mad that's okay to do.
- [Jakiah] I know.
- [Kendrel] I know.
- [Teacher] What?
- [Kendrel] If somebody get mad...
- [Teacher] Then what can you do?
- [Kendrel] Kick somebody,
and punch somebody in the face.
- [Teacher] Is that a green
choice or a red choice?
- [Kendrel] Red choice.
- [Teacher] Punching someone
would be a red choice.
What's a green choice we could make?
Do you remember one?
- [Kendrel] Yeah, that be good!
- [Teacher] What is a good choice?
- [Kendrel] That maybe share with toys.
- [Teacher] Maybe we could
share our toys,
that would be a good choice here.
Criss-cross please.
- [Jakiah] I'm by myself.
- [Teacher] criss-cross please.
Kendrel said maybe
we can share our toys.
- [Kendrel] Yeah!
- [Teacher] Alright last time we
talked about some other things.
We can do what?
- [Nick] Talk to some buddies
- [Teacher] Talk to our friends, good Nick,
and what do we tell our friends?
- [Kendrel] Um...
- [Teacher] If they took a toy from
us, what could we tell them?
- [Jakiah] Sorry.
- [Kendrel] Sorry!
- [Teacher] No, not sorry.
If we took a toy from our
friends, we could tell them sorry,
but if they took a toy from you
and you got really, really
mad what words could you use?
- [Kendrel] Say, "give it back to me"
- [Teacher] You could say, "give it back"
If they were doing something
that you didn't like,
what could you say?
- [Kendrel] Give it back to me.
- [Teacher] You could tell them to
- [Kendrel] Sorry.
- [Teacher] To st. . .
To stop.
If they're bothering you
or doing something you don't like,
you can tell them to stop,
or leave me alone.
We can talk to who?
- [Kendrel] To our friends.
- [Teacher] To the. . .
- [Nick] Teacher.
- [Teacher] Teacher!
And what could you tell me?
-[Kendrel] To give back our toys.
- [Teacher] Maybe that
someone took my toy and
I want it back, and
they wont give it to me.
- [Jakiah] (Background Chatter) Toys.
- [Teacher] You're absolutely
right, good for you Jakiah
-[Kendrel] Because you want your toys.
- [Teacher] Yep, or we talked
about this one too,
what is that?
- [Kendrel] Cupped push on hands
- [Teacher] Take those hands, arrrrr.
Sometime when we get mad it's
okay if we squeeze our hands.
That might help makes us feel better.
Make us calm down a little bit.
Alright, I have some of our pancakes.
- [Kendrel] Yeah!
- [Nick] Yay, pancakes!
- [Teacher] The Pancake Game.
- [Teacher] Alright.
- [Nick] Yeah, pancake games.
- [Teacher] and on some of my
pancakes are things that are--
- [Kendrel] Coo-coo games
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] --red choices, things
that we don't want to do
when we're mad, and some of
my things are green choices,
and if it's a green choice,
we're gonna add it to our book.
If it's a red choice, we're
gonna put it on our plate.
Okay?
Alright, so, Jakiah you want to go first?
- [Jakiah] Yes.
- [Teacher] Alright, are you ready?
Alright, here you go, ma'am.
- [Jakiah] I want the pink one.
- [Kendrel] Flip it.
- [Teacher] Oh, that went
way high past my head.
What is that boy doing?
- [Jakiah, Kendrel] (Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Not your thing.
What is he doing?
- [Jakiah] Bite
- [Teacher] He's biting.
Is he biting himself or his friends?
- [Jakiah] His friend.
- [Nick] His friend.
- [Teacher] His friend.
Is that something we want
to do when we're mad?
- [Nick] Yeah.
- [Teacher] Should we hurt our friends?
- [Kendrel] No!
- [Teacher] That is not
something we want to do
- [Kendrel] We need to be good.
- [Teacher] So, Jakiah does that
go on our red choice plate, or
is that a green choice
that goes in our book?
- [Jakiah] It's the red choice.
- [Teacher] It is a red choice
plate, you are right.
All of our red choices go on our plate.
You were right that was a red choice.
Put is right on top.
Nice thank you, high five.
Good job!
Scoot back, sit down.
Alright, Nicholas are you ready?
Flip that thing.
I caught it.
What are they doing on there?
- [Nick](Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] They are smelling that
flower, and blowing out the candle.
Can you show me how to do that?
Smell your flowers. Now
put the hand on top.
Do it one more time for me.
Sometimes we need to stop
and take a deep breath
to calm ourselves down.
Nick, is that a red
choice or a green choice?
- [Nick] Green choice.
- [Teacher] It absolutely is a green choice.
Here's your sticky stuff.
I'm gonna put it right there.
Can you stick that picture
right on top please?
Our sticky tack
- [Kendrel] Sticky tack
- [Teacher] Put it on top, please.
- [Jakiah] Sticky tack
- [Teacher] Good job.
- [Kendrel, Jakiah] Sticky tack
-[Teacher] Nice thinking.
Okay. High five.
Okay.
High five.
Nice work! Have a seat.
Alright, Kendrel Lowel, are you ready?
- [Kendrel] Yeah.
- [Teacher] What about...
this one?
- [Jakiah] Woah.
- [Teacher] Woah!
- [Kendrel] Somebody push
somebody off the chair!
- [Teacher] Somebody pushed someone
else off that chair.
- [Kendrel] Somebody broke that head off.
Right there.
- [Teacher] It doesn't look like
he has a neck, does it?
You're right.
- [Kendrel] Woah.
- [Teacher] That's just weird.
Try and see me--
Criss-cross applesauce.
Jakiah show me criss-cross, please.
Thank you.
Alright, Kendrel, is that a
green choice or a red choice?
- [Kendrel] Red choice.
- [Teacher] Absolutely, why is
that a red choice?
- [Kendrel] because that is very bad.
Don't know when to snack, or
probably our friends at the playground.
- [Teacher] Why is that a red choice?
- [Kendrel] Because they gonna get left.
- [Nick] (Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Because it hurts their...
friends
- [Kendrel] Friends!
-[Teacher] It hurts their friends.
- [Kendrel](Background Chatter) that
pushed somebody off the chair.
- [Teacher] Yep, Alright, Jakiah, Jakiah.
Kendrel where does that one go?
- [Kendrel] On the red.
- [Teacher] On the red choice plate.
You're absolutely right.
Alright, miss Jakiah, flip that pancake.
- [Jakiah] Boom!
- [Teacher] What is he doing?
- [Nick] Numbers!
- [Teacher] Numbers. They are?
- [Jakiah] One, two, three.
- [Teacher] And what are they
doing, they're...?
Counting.
Can you help me count to ten?
- [All] One, two, three,
four, five, six,
seven, eight, nine,
ten.
- [Teacher] If we get really
mad at our friends,
can we stop what we're doing,
take a deep breath and count to ten
to help calm ourselves down?
- [Jakiah] Yes
- [Teacher] Would that be a green
choice or a red choice?
- [Nick] Green choice!
- [Teacher] Absolutely,
it is a green choice.
Jakiah, is that a green
choice or a red choice?
- [Kendrel] Red choice
- [Jakiah] A red choice.
- [Teacher] Is it a red choice to count?
- [Kendrel] No.
- [Teacher] Does that hurt our friends
if we stop and count?
- [All] No.
- ]Teacher] So, that's a green choice.
Something we can add to our book.
- [Jakiah] Though it's the red choice.
- [Teacher] That's a green choice.
We can stop and count.
Our red choices are--
- [Jakiah] That's a green
- [Teacher] --things that may hurt ourselves--
- [Jakiah] choice and a green
--or our friends.
- [Jakiah] choice.
[Teacher] It is a green choice.
Can you put it right there on
our sticky tack in our book?
- [Jakiah] Sticky tack
- [Teacher] Put the picture on top please
- (Background Chatter)
- [Kendrel] I know sticky's cake
- [Teacher] Alright, you ready, Mr. Nick?
- [Nick] Yeah.
- [Kendrel] Sticky.
- [Teacher] Okay let's do one more.
Lets see what else--
- [Jakiah] You're sticky.
-[Teacher] --we can do.
We could, can we do this one?
-[All] Oh.
- [Nick](laughing)
- [Teacher] What are they doing?
- [Jakiah] Walking
- [Nick] Walking.
- [Teacher] They're taking a walk.
If we get really mad and we
just need to get away from
our friends for a minute, is it okay if
you come ask me to take a walk?
- [Nick] Yeah.
- [Teacher] Yep.
We could walk around the hallways.
So is that a green
choice or a red choice?
- [Nick] Green choice.
- [Teacher] It absolutely is.
There's your sticky stuff.
- [Kendrel] Sticky stuff (Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Your sticky tack.
Sticky tack.
- [Nick] It make stick (Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Put it on quick please.
Or on the book please.
Good job.
- [Kendrel] Let me see
- [Teacher] Okay, stick it on there.
Nice job.
Alright, so let's look at some
of the things that we have
that we can do.
Can you scoot way over here
so your friends can see?
Alright, you guys, help me read this.
If we get mad, it's a good idea to . . .
- [Nick] Talk to people.
- [Teacher] Talk to our friends.
We can tell our friends to. . .
- [Nick] Give it back (Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] to give it back or to. . .
- [Kendrel] Give us back the toys.
- [Teacher] or to...
- [Kendrel] Stop.
- [Teacher] Stop.
We can talk to who?
Jakiah, who else can we talk to?
- [Jakiah] Our teacher.
- Our teacher, and what
can we tell our teachers?
- [Kendrel] To give us back our toys.
- [Teacher] We could say someone
took my toy and
they will not give it back,
or someone hit me--
- [Jakiah] Give it back!
Teachers.
- [Teacher] Alright,
we could stop and do what?
- [Nick] That guy.
- [Teacher] What can we do?
Good Kendrel.
- [Nick] This one.
This guy.
- [Teacher] What could we do, Nick?
- [Nick] Smell that flower and
then blow that candle away.
- [Teacher] We can stop and take a deep breath.
Smell that flower,
blow out that candle.
Deep breath. Smell that flower.
We could...
- [Kendrel] Push the hands!
- [Teacher] Push those hands, how
hard can you squeeze them?
Jakiah, can you show me?
Nick's squeezing, Kendrel's squeezing.
Alright we could ask our teachers to what?
- [Kendrel] They get a walk!
- [Teacher] To take a walk.
Sometimes we may just need to
to get out of our classroom and that is okay.
- [Jakiah] You're loud.
- [Teacher] That was loud, You're right.
- [Jakiah] You screamed.
-[Teacher] But you know what, I like how you
used your words and told him.
You told him that you were screaming and
that hurt my ears.
Alright, using your words--
- [Nick] I did.
- [Teacher] You did too.
Alright what's our last one, we can. . .
- [Kendrel] One, two...
- [Nick] Numbers!
- [Teacher] We can stop and...
- [Kendrel] Count!
- [Teacher] Count.
We count to ten.
- [All but Jakiah] One, two, three,
four, five, six,
seven, eight, nine,
ten.
- [Teacher] It makes my teachers happy when
I am calm and not mad.