- [Instructor] The eighth note or the
quarter note? Raise your hand if you know.
Maddox, what does Holly's song start with?
- [Maddox] Eighth note.
- The eighth note and is that ti ti or
ta, Mason? Is this ti ti or ta? Ti ti,
very good. One, two everybody now.
- [Together] Ti, ti, ti, ti, ta, ti,
ti, ta, ta, ti, ti, ta.
- Very good. Let's move on and let's,
oops, no talking. Let's open up Griffin's.
His song is called "Jaws." What does this
start with? Raise your hand if you can
tell me. What does this start with, Bear?
A quarter note or an eighth note? A
quarter note very good. One, two everybody
play.
- [Together] Ta, ti, ti, ta, ti, ti,
ti, ti, ta, ti, ti, ta.
- Now this one's tricky because we went
ti, ti, ti, ti. So let's try that
again. One, two ready go.
- [Together] Ta, ti, ti, ta, ti, ti,
ti, ti, ta, ti, ti, ta.
- Raise your hand if you can tell me how
many beats does the quarter note get?
Chandler, how many beats? How many
heartbeats does a quarter note get?
- [Chandler] Two, one
- [Student] One.
- One heartbeat, good. How many heartbeats
do the eighth notes get?
- Two.
- Lilly?
- [Lilly] One.
- One, very good. They both just get one.
All right, let's try it again fixing
the ti, ti, ti, ti. Going from here to
here. One, two ready go.
- [Together] Ta, ti, ti, ta, ti, ti,
ti, ti, ta, ti, ti, ta.
- That was much better, good job. Okay
let's move on to somebody else's song.
That was "Jaws" by Griffin. Let's go to
Lilly Dee's song.
Her song is "Pink Butterflies." One, two
everybody play.
- [Together] Ta, ta, ti, ti, ta, ti,
ti, ta, ta, ti, ti.
- Excellent job. Let's go move on to
somebody else's. Let's see Bear's song.
It's called "Boom Boom Bam."
- Bam.
- Boom Boom Bam--
- That's a funny name.
- One, two everybody play.
- [Together] Ta, ti, ti, ta, ti, ti,
ti, ti, ta, ta, ti, ti.
- Let's try to make that a little cleaner
okay. One, two watch the board.
- [Together] Ta, ti, ti, ta, ti, ti,
ti, ti, ta, ta, ti, ti.
- Very good.