- What were you saying, Joe?
- I said young people
definitely benefit our society
overall more than old
people in the country.
- Why?
- Just because they can--
- Progress.
- Contribute more. Yeah.
Like they can work and they
can help our industry grow
and provide opportunities for more people.
- Yeah, they're a lot more active
compared to old people more,
who just is gonna basically sit at home.
- I mean if we look at like
the current political situation
in countries that are rebelling,
the rebellion is completely
composed of the youth.
- Yeah.
- If we look at the political
situation in America,
like Obama's election, was pretty much
the 18 to 21 year-old vote.
It's just like clearly,
they're like better
at affecting social change.
- In this time period
that we're discussing,
why would you want the youth to come?
- Well because this is like the start
of all social change in the union,
and I want young people to
bring a youthful energy,
and determination, and some sort of hope
about the country that they're moving to,
and that all, my union in here.
- [Matt] They're gonna progress,
they're gonna like technology,
and they're gonna invent stuff.
- So you're onboard with the--
- I'm just saying we
still need more money.
They're going to be working
and they're going to be
taking money out of our economy
because they're gonna want to pledge.
How much are they gonna spend?
Like we need old people to spend a lot,
like rich people to spend.
- [Girl in brown] But we need workers.
- Yeah, no, so it's like--
- We need workers,
old people cannot work.
- [Matt] We need a combination.
If only get young people--
- If we look at this list of people
that we can bring into the country
that we were supposed to
look at to begin with,
the old people on this
list aren't that rich.
- Yeah, but there's
- [Girl in brown] The bottom line is
- Gonna be more than just
the old people there.
the old people other countries--
- But right now we're focusing on that.
- they're going to be
moving and they're rich,
who would move here?
Why would they move to
the "Land of Opportunity,"
if they don't need opportunities?
I didn't mean to say that!
(group laughs)
- That's honesty! Okay.
- Yeah but, I mean, I see that.
- It seems like the majority,
did the majority rule on that?
Because I guess, who was against having
younger people come in?
I know Matt was.
Was Matt the only one who
wanted older people to come in?
Ok, and you were--
- [Girl in brown] Also--
- [Matt] I'm a loner.
- You just went with the consensus?
- Yeah.
- Okay, good. - [Girl in brown]
Another point, another point!
Also, old people coming
from another country
just to spend the rest of their life,
aren't necessarily going to be
all that interested in America
- Okay.
- as a country.
- And wait, and also--
- They're not going to vote,
they're not going to, you know,
try to participate in the country itself
so they're just here to die in comfort?
(girl laughs)
- Okay, go ahead Darvel.
- On the way, it's already tough enough
to come across the sea to
get to the United States,
because so many people died
on the way getting there,
so they might die on
the way getting there.
- So don't even consider
them to begin with?
- Right.
- Or if they're sick,
they can't come into the country, anyway.
Like, we're not going to let people
who have cholera into our country,
because then it'll start
spreading here, so ...
- You said "colema" or "column?"
- [Matt] Isn't that more in--
- Cholera.
- [Matt] That's like--
- Okay, I was like, what?
- What else did you
guys have on your cards?
What about religion? Does religion matter?
- [Matt] No.
- I don't think it did.
- No, no.
- That's one thing we, I
think we all could agree on.
- Yeah.
- Oh, everybody--
- What about the nativists?
Darvel, you were okay
with the religious freedom
happening in this group?
Well, I mean, it's kind of like
on the edge of the--
- He's conformed.
- But I (inaudible)
because most of the time,
it's Christianity in
the United States, so...
- Also, majority rule.
- Yeah, majority rules.
- USA! USA!
(teacher laughs)
- Okay, so who did you guys decide to,
wait, was that the end
of your criteria, or?
- No, we had-- - [Girl in brown]
There's still reasons for coming,
race, and knowledge of
English, previous jobs, and--
- Oh, what'd you guys say for English?
What'd you guys say?
- They have to know English.
- Yeah, we said they had to know.
- Basic English, at least.
- At least a little bit.
They have to know some of it.
- Or--
- Enough to, you know,
find out where the bathroom is.
- Really?
- Or enough to like communicate--
- Or have the ability to learn it.
- With other people who may
not know English that well.
- And Boss, you were okay?
- I mean I feel like I'm
one of the only ones
who disagreed with that,
because like being a boss,
like I have connections like
in every part of my city,
and every community,
and communities are often
like separated by race, so--
- By race and?
- [Teacher] And language.
- Mm-hmm.
- So, maybe different communities
wouldn't have trouble communicating
if they only knew one language.
- Mm-hmm.
- But being a boss, with my connections,
I could definitely like,
I could make it so that
they could communicate,
and I can get them what
they need, help them out.
- Okay.
- I don't think now
English is a necessity.
- Well you wouldn't--
- I think it's pretty,
I mean how are people
supposed to communicate?
And it's just going to make life miserable
for the people who are trying to make it.
Because I mean, overall the
majority speaks English.
- But we do have immigrants
in this country right now
that speak different
languages, so they could just--
- They're getting by, though.
- Right, right.
- I don't know if (inaudible)
- You should know them,
working in factories,
you should know a lot of these people.
- Yeah, but-- - [Girl in brown]
You might even know someone--
- When I think of like
different languages,
I think of like the
Tower of Bavel, or Babel,
it's like in the Bible story,
where like everybody
spoke different languages,
and then the tower collapsed.
So like, if everybody
speaks different languages,
we can't get work done productively,
because we don't know
what each other want.
Like if we say, "Yo, go make this type,"
I don't know, just, "Do this job,"
and then they do something else,
you need communication.
- Darvel, what do you think about
the language piece?
- Well, I think that speaking
English is basically,
it's a necessity.
I mean, obviously, you would
want workers to come in,
because he just wants money.
He doesn't really think
communication is that important,
but as a nativist, I believe that it is.
- Why? What will happen
if we let a lot of people
come into the country
with different languages,
maybe be different races,
different ethnicities?
What will happen to the country
if we let those people in?
- I mean, that could create like conflict
between the work, because like Matt said,
they really wouldn't know what to do
while they're working.
Also, that could change
the patriotism of the country, as well.
- But will they know why they're working?
- Not really.
- So people who don't speak English
don't know why they're
doing a specific job?
- Well, probably, yeah.
I mean, they know that they're doing a job
to get money.
- Right, so does English really matter?
I'm just asking.
- I mean, they're not gonna really--
- X, you wouldn't care
if they spoke English,
because if they didn't speak English,
it might make it easier to exploit them.
- I somewhat care.
Because they have to
collaborate with the people
they're working with to get the job done.
- The way I see it is,
they can come into the country with a,
you know, as long as
they have the mindset of,
"I should probably learn English
to succeed in this country,"
then I think it's a good idea.
Because if you're going to
be immersed in a language,
you're going to be able
to learn it eventually,
so I mean as long as they
try to learn English,
or try to know basic English,
I think they should (inaudible)
- I mean, I think I agree to Darvel.
Like if I was a nativist,
I'm not saying I am,
but if I was a nativist, I wouldn't want
hoards of people who don't
speak English coming,
because I mean it's like,
America's pure, we've got
everybody speaks English,
like we don't want--
- But does everybody really
speak English right now?
- Not now, I'm saying--
- No, not right now in 2011,
but in our age that we're discussing--
- [Matt] If I was a nativist in my--
- Even then, right?
- In my like Ideal world,
you would want everybody
to like speak English.
- Okay.
- The whole world should speak English!
- Oh, goodness! Yeah, that's
what a nativist would say.
- I went with the English speakers,
because like to properly
rebel and have a voice,
communication is vital,
and I think that people
who aren't speaking English
won't be interested in what I have to say,
can't even understand
what I'm saying, so--
- Okay, well you guys decide,
and talk about who
you guys are letting into the
country specifically, okay?
- Yeah.
- All right, thanks guys.
- Oh, we already did.
- [Boy in green] Education's
not really that important
to me, though.
- I think it's really important.
- Dude, it's saying that
a lot of these people
going into this country
aren't educated to begin with.
- Well, education like-- - [Girl in
blue] You would want educated people.
- As a non-union worker, like
I don't care about education.
I just want to keep my job,
and I want like union workers
to get out of the country.
- And as a union worker, I
want educated immigrants,
because then they would
stand up for themselves,
and like change factory conditions.
- Me, being a tycoon, I just
want people to work for me.
I mean, they can come to this country,
they can live the American way,
I'll supply them with a job--
- What's the American way?
- American way is to--
- Well but you're not
giving them any money.
- Wait, wait, wait,
what's the American way?
- [Boy in green] 2.5 kids--
- We are, actually.
- 2.5 kids, white picket fence.
- [Boy in green] Dog!
- Well that's the American,
is that the American way now or then?
We're talking about then.
- [Girl in blue] Labrador!
- Basically, the American way is
- I want them to be doing better than
the country they were previously in.
- Okay.
- That's my concern.
- Well, but they came
here to like succeed,
and you're giving them
like two cents an hour.
- I mean, for me with education though,
it's not that big of a deal,
because then again, if
they're coming to America,
they're going to have to
learn our customs and our way,
and with them being uneducated,
that's easier for us to
mold them into society,
and opposed to like we
can mold their thoughts
into like correct candidates to vote for,
and stuff like that!
- But this is supposed to
be like a free country,
and they came over here
because we like grant that,
and we're just like manipulating them.
- Yeah, but like basically,
the only people I want in the country
are like people that are
going to give me jobs.
Like people who are kind of like--
- Who are those people?
- Kind of like sketchy people,
kind of, because like--
- You want sketchy people
to come into your country?
- Well, sketchy people
are about to give me jobs,
because like sketchy
people are about to like--
- What do you mean by sketchy?
What does sketchy mean?
- When you're saying sketchy,
do you mean poor, or like--
- Nah, I mean like people
that are like rich and stuff,
and they'll like have a business
and whatever, but like--
- They're corrupt a little?
- Yeah, they're a little corrupt,
so they won't like hire union workers,
and they'll keep their people ununionized
so I can come in and take
the work, make that cash.
Know what I'm saying?
- Oh, okay. So you want it
that people will have money
when they come into the country,
but not be on the side of unions--
- Exactly.
- So that they will--
- They'll give me jobs.
- They will, okay, they'll
hire non-union workers.
- They're not people that are going to be
entering the workforce,
they're people that are going to be like
already kind of upper,
you know what I mean?
- Okay, so you want people
with money coming into the country?
- Yeah, exactly.
- Okay. Did you guys decide
on a criteria already--
- Yup.
- Or are you discussing a criteria?
- We have a criteria.
- This is our criteria, pretty much.
- Okay, what's your criteria?
- We said non-educated, which
some of us don't agree with.
- Who didn't agree with it?
- I don't agree with that.
- [Teacher] Why?
- Because--
- [Girl in blue] I did not agree with it.
- America is the land of education.
Everybody needs an education.
You can't come here--
- Well, but at this time,
remember education is
not like going to school.
It's more of knowing a skill or a trade.
- It's like street smarts, almost.
- Well, if they don't know anything,
then they can work.
- [Girl in blue] Yeah.
- Okay.
- And we decided on that--
- Do people really need
to know a lot, though,
to work in these factories?
- No, but like--
- [Boy in blue] No, my business is
to teach them how to use these machines.
- [Girl in blue] We don't want them
to be taken advantage of.
- I mean, but at the same time,
I don't really see the
importance of education
if they don't come with like money
or some type of,
like I don't know, some
type of prior knowledge
with like succeeding in America.
Because you may know,
you know how to read 100 books,
but that doesn't help you like
start a business or something like that.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, but not like
that kind of education.
Like, education enough
where they know like
that two cents an hour is not okay.
Like so they can stand up for themselves,
and like be able to like
negotiate with you.
- Why is that not okay?
I mean, everyone has to get paid.
Everyone gets paid that same amount.
- Yeah, but they're living
in like cramped shacks
and like poor conditions.
- I mean, that's in your opinion.
A house is a house.
- Yeah, and then look at
where they're coming from.
They're coming from religious persecution,
they're coming from these
governments that are collapsing,
these war-stricken countries--
- Exactly, and the government--
- I think it's better
to work in a factory,
earn some wage--
- Yeah, but how much are you
earning compared to them?
- Eat or have necessities in life.
- I mean, but there's also
government support, too.
That's where I come in. I set
them up with a place to stay,
stuff like that, you know.
That's what government's here for
is support of people that come in here.
So it's best when they're not educated,
it's best when they don't have money,
because that makes it
easier for them to get help,
and that's what we're here
to do is to help people.
- But then they're relying on you
and they don't know what
to do with themselves,
like when you--
- They're relying on him,
but then he lets them rely on themselves,
so they come in, rely on him,
and then he kind of sends them, like--
- How?
- Helps them out.
- How does he keep people
from relying on him?
- Because then, all right,
so I can help them decide
for who to vote for
in some type of election
that can help them
with their lives.
Like if there's a politician
voting for labor laws,
I can help them. If I'm
with that politician,
I can, "Yo, this is the
guy you want to vote for,"
"This is the guy that will help you."
- That's like brainwashing, though,
they like have a right
to think for themselves.
- Honey, this is America.
- Exactly.
- Exactly! Exactly!
- So you're saying that
nobody should campaign, ever?
You're saying campaigning is brainwashing?
- No, you could campaign, but you don't--
- Exactly, he's just campaigning!
- Can I just say something?
- No, but he's like getting
them all to agree with him.
- Okay, if you think about it this way,
you can really have people from
all spectrums of money-wise,
like from all kinds of
economic backgrounds.
You can have the more rich people come in,
sorry, the education backgrounds.
The more educated people
are going to come in.
No matter what, they're
going to help our country
more than hurt it.
Then for me, I can supply the people
who have gotten a lesser education,
and I can give them a job,
I can start them off in life,
and maybe they can go to the library
and learn themselves.
- Why don't you better their
working conditions, then,
if you like are "helping" them?
- Because I mean, still,
this is much better.
- No, because they like
die in those factories.
- It's better than being killed
by their previous governments.
- [Teacher] Wait, have we decided--
- No, it's not!
It's not the same thing.
- Have you guys already
decided on this piece already?
- Yeah, we have like our set laws,
we just have disagreements about that.
- You guys have disagreements?
So you guys were able
to a consensus on them?
- Yeah, well we kind of voted on it.
We decided that they
have to be non-educated,
come with some sort of money.
Their religion and race doesn't matter.
Come with a family--