(children chatter)
- About 33.
- 33, so 150 plus 33?
- 180.
- What'd you get?
- 180, so is that...
Did we double?
- Went a little higher.
So you guys made a good
prediction, didn't you?
All right, keep doing
your trials, nice work.
Heads up, Madison.
Heads up. Ah!
- Can you stop it?
- No, you're good.
All right, so what have
you guys found out so far?
- We've been increasing,
but then we just...
It increased a little,
but I think we're gonna
increase a little more.
- Okay, so you're measuring...
You've all, you've raised your ramp to 10?
- Yes.
- All right.
(children chatter)
Now, what was your prediction?
It would go farther based on height?
- Because, like, from all the other
experiments that we've done...
- Uh-huh.
- It's gone farther, so...
And it has more force
if the ramp is higher.
- Okay.
Man, that ambulance, that thing moves.
All right, what did you guys get, Mary Robin,
when you measured?
- We got 179.
- 179, okay.
- What was weird is that...
Like, what's weird is
that on the first trial,
we got 130, and then we went to,
like, the, like 50s and things.
- Okay.
- And then we went back
to like the 80s and 90s.
- Yeah.
All right, so now we need to go ahead
and do what?
You've done your three
trials, what's the next?
- Average.
- All right, let's see.
We got 182, 172, and 179.
(children chatter)
- 533.
- 533, and then
what are you going to do?
- Divide it by three.
- Okay, divide by three.
- 177.666667.
- So we can round that up to?
- To 178.
- 178.
Is that pretty close?
So you got...
Your trials are pretty
close together. 182--
- 172 and 179.
- So you predicted that it would increase
by raising the ramp.
Was that true?
- Yes.
- So your prediction came true.
Let's turn over the back side,
and let's finish the
rest of that lab part.
- So were there any trials
that your team did not record?
We only did it...
We didn't do that one
because it flipped off.
- It, like, hit this chip card
and it just, like, went whoo!
- It went like...
- All right, that's a
good one not to include.
Let's write that down.
We didn't include one
because it hit a chip hard.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, that's good.
- It just
like flew off to the side
and it went all the way, like...
- Did it really?
- Yeah, it just...
- That's crazy.
- It was funny because...
It was also funny because
it was going straight,
but then it just...
- That's weird.
- Turned.
- That's weird that it hit that...
That that caused it to,
you know, make such a turn.
- But then, like,
(mumbles).
The whole time it's been
going to the, the right side.
- Oh, okay.
So it's been curving?
- Yeah, it kind of like tilted, and...
- That's a good idea.
Yeah, that's a real good idea.
- Okay, so, question two.
What was the average
distance the Jeep rolled
with the five-centimeter height?
So the five-centimeter height.
- On the back side of that.
- We got an average of 30, 93.
- 93, all right, so
write that one down, 93.
Did that surprise you, it would go 93?
- Yeah.
- Is that farther,
that's what you thought?
- I never thought
we'd actually get to the end of it.
- Yeah, that's a--
- But then we actually did
with those little toy cars.
- Yeah.
- And this is actually
an older-looking toy car.
- Yeah.
- Because
whenever I roll one wheel,
the other wheel rolls just a little.
- Oh, yeah. Okay.
So you thought maybe the wheels would have
something to do with it?
- Yeah.
- Okay.
- But I never thought
it would actually go that far.
- Okay.
So you're now on number three, right?
- What was the average
distance the Jeep rolled
(mumbles) 10-centimeter height?
That was 178.
- Okay.
So, 178.
It looks like the next question is,
did the Jeep roll shorter
or longer distance?
- Longer.
Can we figure out how much farther?
- Yes.
- What would we have to do?
- The 10-centimeter average
minus the 5-centimeter average,
and then your answer would be how...
Like, the distance between.
- Well, why don't you do that?
Why don't you pull that up?
The 178...
(boy mumbles)
You know, it's always better
when you can incorporate
those into your answers.
You know, it increased by one...
Or it was 85 higher.
It's always better when you
can show your answer with data.
When you can increase that
it makes your answer
seem more valid, right?
All right, so maybe can include that,
and then move on to
that number five there.
Okay? All right.
You guys are doing a great job.
Hey, have you guys gone through
everything you needed
to do on the front side?
Did you read all these first?
You gotta read this whole
section of your lab first, okay?
Yeah, so I would read this part first
and then move on, okay?
All right.
(children chatter)
All right, how you guys doing?
- Good.
- All right,
so you guys have done
your first trial on this one.
Now, did you do this one here?
- I don't...
- Let's look at our directions.
It says change the ramp back
to five centimeters high.
Did you do that?
- No, sir.
- Okay, let's do that.
All right.
- Sandpaper?
- And then I think it...
Doesn't it say...
- It says tile floor.
- It says tile floor,
so we're going to measure on the tile.
(girl mumbles)
- I get to race it.
- All right, are we ready?
Now I'm going to move over here.
Now, what vehicle we got here?
- You should move over there because
it always goes over here.
- Oh, it always moves over here?
- Yeah.
- It has a curve?
- How about if I move back over here?
Will that work?
All right, you ready?
- Right here?
- Yeah, that's good.
Oh, you're right.
Good thing I moved.
- I'll hold it down. Hold that down.
- Now, in your first experiment, Annie,
while they're doing this,
what did it?
When you increased the height of the ramp,
did it increase?
- Yeah, it went faster.
- It went what?
- It went faster because
it had more force.
- Okay, so it had more force.
(children chatter)
So why do you guys think
by increasing the height
of the ramp on the first
lab, it had more force?
All right.
- It's more steeper.
- Okay.
- And the more steeper it is, the more,
less friction it would
cause, so it could go faster.
- Okay.
What was the force that was
bringing it down the ramp?
- Gravity.
So you can you conclude
from your model experiment
that when you increase
the steepness of the ramp,
the pull of gravity is greater?
- Yeah, because it's going more (mumbles).
- Okay, all right.
- It's going down, going faster.
- Okay.
- And then when it gets,
if it gets down safely,
it'll just go farther
because it has more speed.
- Okay. Great.
All right, so we're on
trial two, aren't we?
- Yes.
- Let's do it.
- Go!
- You do have that, it
does have that curved roll.
- Oh, it landed on the--
- On the back of it.
- There's like a cargo of
some sort in the back of it.
- Is it, is there a--
- There's cargo in the...
- 113.
- Wait, wait, hold on.
Let's double check.
What I would do, maybe,
is bring your Jeep over.
- Yeah, but then it's--
- 106.
- No, but then it's...
- Oh, you're on the...
Are you going to the front?
- Yeah.
- Okay, 113, yeah, you're right.
- No, but then you're going at an angle.
- And you don't let it go.
- Yeah, I mean, either way, I
think you're going to get a...
As long as you--
- That's the way we're doing it from here.
- Well, you know, as long as you do
the same thing every time,
then you should be consistent, right?
- Yeah.
- All right, one more roll, right?
- One more.
- And then we have it, yeah.
- One more roll, Jordan.
Here we go.
- Then we have to add them all up.
- Dun, dun, dun,
dun, dun, dun,
dun, dun, dun, dun, dun!
Dun, dun,
dun, dun, dun.
- The only thing is that...
Is that farther?
Don't you think it's farther?
Are we ready?
- Maybe it's because of me.
- Do you think you have
anything to do with it?
- Yeah.
- You do, huh?
- Go!
- Fire!
(children chatter)
- 117.
- How far?
- 117, all right.
- 117.
- So now, wait.
Now Thiago, the math whiz,
has to do his math.
- All right, so how do you
find the average again?
- We do...
We do...
We add them all up, and then we divide it
by the number of times you rolled it.
- Okay, let's do it.
- So we
rolled it three times.
- You ready?
Let's find our average.
- Pencil, please!
- Oh, you guys aren't
even using a calculator.
- No, we haven't been.
- We only use it for the division.
- Oh, you only use it for the division.
Hey, I like that.
- Sometimes, sometimes.
Sometimes we still need it.
- What do you guys got?
- 10.
- That's zero.
- To zero, add up the...
- Four, and three.
- So 340.
- So you're going to take 340,
and then you're going to divide it.
- Divided by three.
- And Thiago can usually do that.
- You get 113.3333333.
- All right, well, check
it out on a calculator,
just to make sure.
- Okay.
- How can you do that in your
head without a calculator?
- I don't know.
- Yeah, but how do you do that?
What did you say the number was, Thiago?
- It was 113.33333.
- All right, here we go.
- It's 113, come on, Thiago.
(children chatter)
- 113.333333333.
He got it.
All right, nice job, man.
All right, so 113.
Is that pretty consistent, though?
- Yeah.
- Yeah, because we had a 113.
- Yeah, you did.
And that was your middle score, wasn't it?
- Yeah.
- And really, if you take the thing--
- And then we gotta do this one.
- No, never mind.
I think if you take four
here and you put it here...
- Yeah, if you take
three here, put it here,
then you have one more here.
- Yep. All right.
So now what we're going to do,
it says to add sandpaper
to the bottom of the ramp.
- Which we did.
- And predict whether it's going to go.
We'll have to redo those, won't we?
- Yeah.
- So let's erase those,
because you had the ramp at how high?
- 10 centimeters.
- 10, and we needed to...
We need to have an equal trial.
We need to have it at
the same distance, right?
- Yeah.
- So the question is...
Sit up for me, Jordan.
I know we got a lot of space here.
What are we going to...
Do you think it's gonna go shorter
or a farther distance?
- It's gonna go shorter.
- Why?
- Because there's more friction.
Sandpaper's rough, so it
creates more friction.
- Okay.
- Slow down the thing.
- Okay, what do you think?
- When it slows it down,
it may slow it down and then it says,
the car starts to turn, just because...
Just because it's our car, goes out to the side,
so it goes more to the side.
- All right.
- Than it usually does.
- What do you guys think?
Farther or shorter?
- I think it'll go shorter because...
The gravity may be pulling it down,
but the sandpaper is really
rough like Thiago said,
and it would, like, stop it
to make it not move anymore.
It would, like barely get off the paper.
- Okay, can you guys, like...
Say you're riding your bike.
And you ride your bike on smooth pavement,
and then you ride it on a rough surface.
Is it easier to ride on
the smooth or the rough?
- Smooth.
- The smooth, right?
So can we use that to help
us make our prediction?
- It actually could be
faster on the bumps more,
because if you hit a bump...
If you're going fast enough
and you hit a big enough bump,
you could actually go in the air.
- Okay, maybe.
All right, let's go and
test this thing out,
and see if you guys are right.
Annie, while we're setting up this lab,
can you go ahead and
write your prediction?
And it looks like you need to
grab your sandpaper there.
Now, I can't sit here, can I?
This is the bad seat.
I gotta move.
- Well, I say you sit--
- It doesn't go very far
anymore on the sandpaper.
- All right, well, let's set it up there.
That one there, right?
And that one there?
- Four centimeters more.
- All right, let's look.
We went 113.
With the sandpaper, how far
do you think it's gonna go?
Let's make a prediction.
- I think
it'll go maybe half that,
or even less than half that.
- Okay, so what would half of 113 be?
What's that close to?
- I don't know.
I think that would be maybe...
500 and...
- 500?
- 500 and...
- No, you want half of it.
- Oh, five, okay.
Half of it.
- 50.
- I think, there you go, 50, yeah.
- All right.
- 52...
- 51 point (mumbles).
- 50 point, like...
50.5 or something.
- Okay.
All right, are we ready
for the first roll?
Let's do it.
Let's get our first trial.
Here we go. We're ready.
- Wait, who hasn't rolled?
- Has Emma not rolled?
Okay, all right, good.
I like the way your group's
working together there.
- All right.
- Here we go.
Oh.
Should we use that trial,
or should we try a different one?
- Try again.
- Let's try one more.
Maybe we can get that--
- Well, scoot it right over here.
- And we could even scoot
the sandpaper, like, there.
- Yeah.
- All right, you ready?
All right, there it is.
- It didn't even
move off the sandpaper.
- Let's give it...
- Can someone hold that down?
Can someone hold that down, please?
- Here we go.
This is our test.
Is the prediction right?
- The sandpaper's hard.
- It is, it's rough, isn't it?
- Yeah.
- 49.
- Now, aren't you on the front?
- Yeah, which would be a 49.
- Yeah, but you mean...
Or maybe you're (mumbles) about 50?
- Yeah, about 50.
- You guys were pretty close
in your prediction, weren't you?
Half.
- It was like 50.
- Yeah, Jordan said 50 1/2.
- All right, you guys got
two more trials, right?
- I said 51 1/2.
You said 51 1/2.
- All right, ready?
- Yeah.
Oh, man.
- Really?
- Let's like keep it down.
- Or maybe we'll hold
it down next time, yeah.
- Yeah, I think that's the problem.
It's scooting back.
- That was 50...
- 47.
- Yeah, 47.
- Okay.
- Almost in half.
- All right, I'll hold it on this side.
Are we ready?
Here we go.