- ... the fact that he couldn't do it
because he didn't have enough money to do
it. What would you do in that situation?
Would you try to get money?
- Isn't this kind of different because
we're all girls?
- Yeah, but...
- If it was a boy, and he was the one who
didn't have money...
- Do you feel like the chapters that we
read, do you feel like you could tell what
Pip was going to be doing?
- Kind of. You could tell that he was
becoming more stuck-up; wants to change himself
and not be around the poor people.
- Are you doing the discussion director?
Did you do any questions in regards to
his-- did you have any direct questions
with regards to the text?
- Yeah. One of them was like how did Pip
change from the beginning of the book to
where he's at now, like his character and
basically how he acted.
- What was the question I missed, Brianna,
where you said about the girls? I didn't
hear the question. I just heard your
response.
- His was, in Chapter 29, when he is
becoming part of her marriage, he was just
like, how would you feel or whatever. None
of us really had an answer because the
situation is different, like it's
different for the guys... She's the one
who's like the rich girl.
- Who's the recording one?
- So, on page 128, paragraph two, that's
where Herbert tells Miss Havisham's story.
That's important because it kind of
explains why she is the way that she is.
He explains that you meet Miss Pocket, and
then she's kind of like- he kind of
explains why she's kind of crazy.
- All right. Chapter 8 was interesting
because he was home from war and in the
camp. He started to treat people. He
treated them like they were all heroes.
- And he shared the cigarettes with him
one time.
- He shared the cigarettes with them and
was even
[Inaudible].
- When he was amongst the Russians, he
didn't care. They were struggling to
survive. He felt sorry for them, which as
a connector, I've connected it to- I
don't know if you guys have seen "Tears of
the Sun."
- I have.
- And "Avatar." In "Tears of the Sun," he
wanted to go and try to rescue people, but
he got stuck behind enemy lines
[Inaudible],
like they're struggling people too trying
to gain their freedom. And then same thing
in "Avatar." Paul kind of reminded me of
how he was behind and he was with the
Russians, but he thought that they weren't
as bad as he- the military was the only
bad part about them. Civilians, he felt
sorry for them, that they had to go
through all this. They were being killed.
Their people were being killed. And they
were actually just regular people trying
to make it.
Everybody was dying because they used all
this stuff in the military and they
weren't caring about the civilians.
[cross talk]
- The prisoners?
- They were [Inaudible].
- They had to trade whatever they had to
get like a couple supplies to the
refugees.
- He started to wonder like why are people
higher up, people he'd never met forcing
them
[Inaudible].
- Yeah.
[cross talk]
- So, then this whole section made me
think about that. So, I thought that could
be like the controversial part to talk
about. This whole section...
- Which whole section?
- The one you were just talking about.
- They're talking about magic.
- Yeah. They're talking about the magic
and being invisible and then he
[Inaudible]
and scares them away.
- It really showed a struggle between
Antonio internally with religions.
- Yeah.
- In one he had keys and then in the other
one it was totally crazy.
- Yeah.
- That's my next section, is that dream. I
think it's page 119. That whole dream is
really important because it's like, it
kind of highlights what I just said about
how he might be the next
[Inaudible] person or whatever.
He goes to this dream and it's kind of the
same thing he's been facing through the
whole book- his mom's side versus his
dad's side. And Ultima kind of
comes out and is like, "Well, you are
both. You have to find a happy medium."
It's all within the world of his dreams.
And then page 139...
- One part that I thought was really,
really important was his brother at the
brothel.
- These two chapters, I think they're kind
of jam-packed. I just kind of picked stuff
that would be good to talk about. And then
page 139, paragraph three, they're talking
about how the group can be buried in the
casket of time. I just felt that was
informative and something that we should
look at. Just pretty much the whole
funeral.
- The funeral was good styling.
- Like, I don't know, these
four chapters...
- There was no part where you didn't
[Inaudible].
- It's like, read these four chapters.
- Exactly.
- After I read the chapter, I wrote some
questions down. The first one is what did
the contrast between the golden carp and
the black bass- how the golden carp made
the black bass jump. And his missing of
the bass symbolizes maybe like a win for
Abel...
- The golden carp story was just very
interesting.
- The whole controversy is that he's
Catholic, but part of him really wants to
believe in this whole...
- It's not like he wasn't interested in
it, but he still didn't believe. But then
he still respected the story itself and
the respect of the carp.
- It made me feel like the golden carp
would bring it up. Could Antonio...
[cross talk]
- It made me feel that Antonio's struggle
between his mother's beliefs and his
father's, how his father was like, on the
corpse-strewn shore.
- I remember there was something like when
you're in the ocean, it's the same
water-
- It's like Ultima came in.
- She was like, "You don't pick one.
You're both. That's it."
- You can't just choose one path.
- You should be a priest cowboy.
- I think the way it was portrayed was
like because of the way he was brought up,
it was kind of showing the negative.
[cross talk]
- She's brought up. She's not there, but
she's brought up too much.
- I feel like she's a goal though, to be
like be some kind of spirit type thing.
- He hopes that she's like someone who's
not fake.
- So, I guess he's trying to like make
things work with everyone else and see,
like, what his relationship with other
people and to finally be able to call a
[Inaudible].
- I feel like he compares all of his
relationships to her. He has that
standard.
- Didn't he point out like all the flaws
of her?
[cross talk]
- That was just creepy. I was just like,
"Poor guy," to have all of these weird,
awkward dreams.
- I'm going to say foreshadowing. I'm
sticking by that and saying Ultima's going
to die and he's going to be the new...
I'm sticking by that, and that's
foreshadowing.
- Look at you go.
- All of those things are foreshadowing or
are they just predicting something that
happened in the past?
- Most of them. Well, I think the one
where, remember where he went into a
brothel in the one dream? Right. Exactly.
So, I think that most of the dreams are
foreshadowing.
- They're not showing directly what
happens, but hints.
- Basically I'm a beast.
- We don't even have to read the rest of
the book because I just gave it to you.
- Because we know what's happening.
- I said also, in chapter 14, the bad
dream, what do you make of it? Is he
seeing the sinners as deserters that all
witches are being spun out and that he
needs to step forward? Or does the golden
carp have like stronger power? What do you
think it symbolizes?
- I think there are good witches and there
are bad witches. The bad witches are the
ones that should be, like...
[cross talk]
- That's Antonio's issue as well. I think
he's kind of figured out that there's
something different about Ultima. I think
he's kind of figured out that- he's kind
of just like, "Oh, they're evil and she's
good. If she's a witch, then she's evil."
So, it's kind of this contrast of can a
witch be good? It's kind of like the
question of what he wants to believe
versus...
- It kind of relates to the Civil War and
the Africans and their personal stuff. It
kind of relates to that.
The white people, they didn't want to
believe that they're intelligent and
they're friends. He doesn't want to
believe that a witch can be good because
he's been told otherwise.
- And he's a Catholic and witches are
evil.
- I think that the golden carp symbolizes
perhaps the rebirth.
- I think the two most important themes,
symbol figures are the owl and the carp.
[cross talk]