- This one is probably medium.
So this one is mine.
- So this has to be a medium.
- And this one has to be a large because...
My medium is half way up to here.
So it has to be a large.
- So you make a prediction
about how many small rocks
it takes to make a big.
- I think it's gonna be 12 small rocks.
- That's a good idea.
Put our small rocks we have here
so we make it, draw two little blocks
and if we have 12.
- Draw a rectangle and just put,
put your line through right here.
- What do you think how many small rocks?
(children talking over each other)
- I think that there is going to be eight.
We have eight rocks.
So I think that there's going to be
15 small rocks.
What about you?
- I have 10, 11, 12.
- Boys and girls I had a good question.
If you've got more
rocks than you do boxes,
you know that we've got how many boxes?
How many boxes?
- Ten.
- There's ten.
So at the top you can write,
since we've been working with
place value with tens and ones
you can put ten. We know
that's how many boxes we have.
You could put plus six
if you have which number?
- 16.
If you all had 11 what could you do?
You got ten so you
would write plus one.
If you had 12 you would write,
you've got 10 so what
would you write above it?
Plus two.
So you can do it that way.
Good question.
- Now what about you
make a prediction of five
then you ask us how
many baby rocks we think
that ten makes.
(children talking over each other)
- I think that there is going to be...
- These can be large.
And there's one, two
three, four, four larges.
(children talking over each other)
- He's already told you
how many mediums there are.
(children talking over each other)
- However you think.
Very good.
So you've got yours sorted by size
or you could see if there's another way
you can sort your rocks?
- We just did size first
so we could do our work.
- Very smart.
Very smart.
Tell me about looking at the graph
how many small you had Diana.
How many small rocks were there?
- Five.
- Alright how many
medium rocks did you have?
- 11.
- And how many large?
- Four.
- Good, good and you sorted them.
Oh, you got some nice rocks.
Oooh.
Nice rock there, it's pretty.
- Neat.
(children talking over each other)
- Now this looks
much better, much better.
- Medium, there's one, two, three, four,
five, six, seven, eight, nine,
10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15.
(children talking over each other)
- Three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, 10.
10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15.
(children talking over each other)
- Wait, wait. One, two, three, four, five...
- Now we need five more to make 15.
(children talking over each other)
- One, two, three,
four, five, six, seven, eight, nine,
10, 11, 12, 13, 14.
(children talking over each other)
- Four, five, six, seven, eight, nine,
10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15.
- I counted 14.
(children talking over each other)
- Put them together.
- One, two, three, four.
(children talking over each other)
- I'd say like maybe
it goes with the white.
- Okay, what about this one?
- That goes with the white right?
(children talking over each other)
- What about this one?
- Hmm, I'd say like, what
does it have the most of?
I'd say probably white.
- What about this one?
- This one goes for tan.
- This one is,
this one goes.
This one goes too.
- This goes with the gray too.
- This one goes to the--
- I think it goes.
- It goes with the white.
(children talking over each other)
- Now let's see.
I think it's a pretty rock.
Wait, oh.
- That one goes there.
- I know it.
They all do.
Wait, these go with the green.
No this one, this one is gray.
- It's still got sand in it.
- This one is green and
at least it looks a little bit greenish.
I'd say like maybe green too.
We'll have all yes.
Okay, now this rock.
Okay Diana, Cam and Gaelin.
What I want you to do is
you'll probably,
how about you just take the rocks.
Because I can't remember.
- What's going on?
- We're sorting them a different way.
- You're sorting
them a different way.
And what way would that be?
How did you all decide to sort rocks?
- I thought we'd sort them by color
and now we're gonna do it by cut.
- Tell me that again because I don't,
I don't know that part.
(children talking over each other)
- Now since we did the color,
we're going to do is,
we're going to do by texture.
- What's texture?
- It's by how it feels.
- Oh, well can you teach me?
- Find out the texture
from these two rocks,
I see how it feels.
And since this one feels very
smooth I'll put it by itself.
- Well, can I feel it?
- Pretty smooth.
- Pretty smooth. Have you felt it?
Feel it.
How you think it feels?
- Smooth.
- It does feel pretty smooth.
- And it looks like a piece of meat.
- It looks like a piece a meat?
- Yes.
- Better not eat a rock should I?
Okay, where does this one need to go?
- It needs to go.
- Over here?
- We haven't finished quite yet so...
- Okay.
- And this one is like
I'll say pretty rough.
- Pretty rough, can I feel this one?
Oh gosh.
Whoo.
Yeah.
It does feel a little rough.
It does feel like it's
got some sand on it.
You know a word that I can think of
that makes me think of that?
- Rough.
- Rough or gritty.
You know sand is gritty feeling.
Well, that's kind of gritty.
It does feel a little rough.
- It can stand up.
- It stands up?
- I'm gonna do it, put it by itself.
- Okay.
- And we're going to keep on doing it.
Until all of them are sorted.
- Okay, this is a pretty cool rock,
how does it feel?
- I'll say pretty bumpy kind of rock.
- Pretty bumpy, pretty rough.
Oh, this one's very rough.
- So rough I can hardly stand myself.
- Look at the shell on it.
(gasp)
- It does have a shell in it.
- On the other side, look.
On the other side turn it like right here,
it has another shell.
- It does, so what kind
of rock would this be?
- A two fossil rock.
- A fossil rock.
And what kind are they,
what's it called?
If it has a fossil imprint in it?
- Fossil.
- If it settled
and got a fossil?
- Sedimentary.
- It would be a sedimentary rock.
Very cool.
I'm so proud of you.
That was definitely very rough.
Have you felt it?
- This is.
- What do you think?
- On, the back is kind of squishy.
- It is rough.
Okay, you all keep working,
you're doing a good job.
I'm proud of you.
- Okay.
Now you can put it with the rough, the super rough.
I think this one is, I can tell.
I say medium, a little
rough, a little smooth.
This one goes in the middle.
- This one is smooth.
- This is super rough.
Let me feel.
- Smooth.
- I'm gonna put it in the middle
because I think--
(children talking over each other)
- Very good
Arianna, I like the way you--
(children talking over each other)
- One more medium rock than large.
Because we have eight medium
and seven large.
- Because you can see...
- A smooth side and a rough side.
(children talking over each other)
- Because if you add two more together
it make 12.
Medium is
seven and large is
eight.
- And I have an idea, when you do your rock
what about you trace it?