- [Boy in gray] I think we need the policeman,
because he's the only one with a weapon.
He's the only one with a weapon though.
- [Student in red] What if he goes crazy?
He's the only one with a gun.
- [Boy in gray] Exactly, that's a good thing, though.
- [Teacher] Wait a sec,
why is that a good thing?
- [Girl in floral] Are you saying he'd shoot us?
- [Boy in gray] I didn't say it's a good
thing if someone could shoot us.
- [Teacher] No, I didn't say that.
You said it's a good thing.
Explain why you think it's a good thing.
- [Boy in gray] It's a good thing
because we could stock the food, Drake.
- [Teacher] OK, so he said two things.
- [Student in floral] But he might
shoot us because we might be starving
and he might start to shoot us.
(Heavy Background Chatter)
- [Boy in orange] We could take him,
he wouldn't shoot us.
- [Teacher] Where you at, Riley, it
looks like you're sweating.
- [Riley] I'm trying to
think between you two.
- [Teacher] So you write down
what you said you'd do,
and you worry about everybody here.
Who do you think is the most important?
Eileen says the policeman, does everybody
agree with that or not?
- [Girl in gray] Yeah.
- [Boy in orange] Why?
- [Teacher] (Listens to Eileen) Because
if someone gets hurt--(Background Chatter)
He can respond to medical stuff?
yeah, they're First Responders.
It's a good idea.
Anybody else?
Can you write down reasons
why you should keep somebody?
Would anybody that you know
that works here already?
That's good, he's too old,
his life would be long.
So, the old sir will be able
to be productive to society.
Think about that.
Anything else about the male professor
that you maybe thought about?
- [Background Chatter]
[Teacher] --in support of communism. Do you
want that in your society or not?
- [Girl in gray] No.
- [Teacher] Why not?
- [Girl in gray] Because-- (Background Chatter)
00:02:40,150
- [Teacher] Okay, so freedoms
are important to you.
- [Loudspeaker] Mr. Malls?
- [Teacher] Yes, ma'am?
- [Loudspeaker] Send Kyle
to the office for a minute, please?
- [Teacher] He's in Miss Crane's room, right now.
- [Loudspeaker] What core are y'all in?
Because I told Mr. Wayward
where he was supposed to be,
and he said he was with you.
- [Teacher] Uh, he, we're actually in
2nd, he's with Miss Crane.
- [Loudspeaker] All right, thank you.
- [Teacher] OK, you can resume.
Folks, we're about, I don't know,
15 minutes until the end.
- [Girl in gray] Hey, why should we keep
the male professor?
- [Teacher] What's the issue you have?
- (Heavy Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] OK, now this is just a question, guys,
If someone's not fit, does that mean they
have no potential to
be helpful to society?
- [Girlin yellow] Nah,
they could be really smart.
- [Teacher] OK, they could be really smart.
(Background Chatter)
- [Boy in gray] But she's nine--
- [Teacher] She's nine?
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] She's nine, so,
are you looking for right now
or are you looking for the long run?
- [Boy in crimson] We're talking
about the long run.
- [Teacher] The long run, so you got time.
So just consider all aspects, just because
maybe just because she has...
does she have anything to offer?
Let the group decide, it sounds like some
people are really for and
some maybe are against it.
(Background Chatter)
- [Student in crimson] If you
want a male farmer, say aye.
- [Male Students] Aye.
- [Boy in crimson] If you want the male
professional, say aye.
- [Only boy in crimson] Aye.
(Laughter)
- [Boy in crimson] If you want the female
scientist, say aye.
- [Boy in Green, Girl in floral] Aye.
[Boy in crimson] If you want the
male preacher, say aye.
[Girl in floral, Boy in gray] Aye.
- [Boy in crimson] Definitely female nurse.
- [Gir in yellow] We already have a nurse.
- [Boy in green] We already have a nurse!
- [Boy in crimson] Who cares?
- [Student in gray] I do.
- [Boy in crimson] In case he dies--
(Background Chatter)
- [Girl in yellow] But the female med
student's only in second year,
she hasn't even been to the hospital.
- [Boy in crimson] It might go for four years.
- [Girl in yellow] Exactly.
- [Boy in crimson] We got the scientist
and the nurse to help her.
- [Boy in green] Plus she'd be off breeding.
- [Girl in yellow] Excuse me?
- [Boy in green] No offence.
(Background Chatter)
- [Girl in floral] You know we only got
like thirty minutes.
- [Girl in yellow] We only have fifteen, so...
- [Teacher] Hey, we're about 5 or 10 more minutes,
and then I'm gonna stop you
in groups and you'll listen.
If you have not managed to
already make your decisions,
here's the key point,
here's the key point...
Still got a group talking,
you need to listen.
About five or ten more minutes, you need
to come down to your five, you need
to have the reasons
why you chose the five,
and we're gonna share
those, and reasons why
you did not choose the
five you didn't choose.
Keep in mind, Edna, keep
in mind that five are going
with you to start this new civilization
that's gonna hopefully
flourish, and I hope you're
all taking people with, uh,
that you know will make it.
But there's also, you gotta keep in mind,
there's five people you're leaving behind,
that most likely is not gonna make it.
But you, you're
concentrating on who you need
to start this new productive society, OK?
OK, start closing up in the
next five or ten minutes,
about who you're choosing,
who you're not choosing.
Those radiation levels are
getting high, very high.
Over here especially.
- [Girl in floral] I know, really!
- [Boy in crimson] I kinda changed
my mind about that.
Because she's cute.
(Background Chatter)
- [Boy in crimson] You can't change times and down.
- [Girl in floral] I'm agreeing with that.
- [Boy in crimson] Say aye again,
if you want-- (Background Chatter).
- [Most students] Aye.
- [Boy in crimson] Finally...
- [Boy in white] They wanna take
cripple girl and I'm saying...
- [Student] He's still overruled.
- [Teacher] I posed this question
just a minute ago.
So, this is, so we can look at mass...
So we can look at it two
ways, one you're looking at:
"She can't do anything,
she's gonna be hard to keep,
because someone will have to do it,
second way of looking at it, she...
And she doesn't have her doctor.
Uh, is that true?
Once she had a doctor.
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] OK, and then what else?
- [Teacher] Have you ever heard anything about...
- [Students] Yup.
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] So what if this person could
be maybe a scientist or a...
- [Boy in white] It didn't say that.
- [Teacher] But again you're not
saying that she is...
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] ...you can combine that.
OK, continue on.
You need to start choosing,
maybe 3 or 4 of your 5.
And why you're gonna take or
why you're not gonna take 'em.
(Heavy Background Chatter)
- [Girl in floral] OK, male professor, too old.
(Students disagreeing or agreeing at once)
- [Girl in floral] He's too old!
- (Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Five minutes!
I'm giving you five minutes!
Start making decisions.
(Background Chatter)
- [Boy in white] But why do we need a
policeman if we got a lot of money?
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Hey, I wanna share some of the tips
that some of you were talking about...
And one person said, "well,
she has the potential to become
"any of these things here, she has
"the potential to be any of those,"
so it might something to consider.
(Background Chatter)
- [Student in white] We need
extra little kids, and she
won't help us with no extra little kids.
(Heavy Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Somebody's
ready to go, just about,
so you need to make sure
you get your five choices.
(Heavy Background Chatter)