- Okay Dylan what song will
you be playing?
- Playing B A and G.
Okay and line number?
- Four.
- Four, okay. Let's get your left hand on
top. Okay and whenever you're ready as
soon as you start on the note B.
♪ [recorder playing] ♪
Give him a hand, nice job. [clapping].
You can have a seat Dylan, thank you.
Okay Christopher.
- I'm doing number four
playing the note A.
- Playing the note A number four okay.
♪ [recorder playing] ♪
Left hand on top Christopher.
- That's all.
- Okay let's give him a hand. [clapping]
- Number four playing the note A.
Great!
♪ [recorder playing] ♪
Let's give him a hand. [clapping]
Elise.
- Number B playing number one.
- Playing B number one, okay great. Make
sure your left hand is on the top. Okay that's
your left hand and your right hand goes
along alright whenever you're ready.
♪ [recorder playing] ♪
Let's give Elise a hand. [clapping]
- Playing the note B1.
Okay.
♪ [recorder playing] ♪
Let's give Jessica a hand. [clapping]