So we remember our unit of measurement.
The top is 140
41, 140... okay
Ruth flip over and let Maddie do the question. We're going
to write it out and then you can do this question next, okay.
Compare and record the results of all three patterns you
have been observing -absorption- observations.
So lay out your data sheet right here in the middle, where
you can all look at all three.
Okay, um I would say... I would say...
It's because like the peanut butter moves 9 and its grown
What do you mean its grown?
Its like expanding, it expands
What was it that expanded into that paper towel?
The fat. The oil.
The oil from the peanut butter?
- Yeah, the oil.
Okay, so we discussed that one. So Maddie is going to write
down about the peanut butter.
What the observation was. At the first observation it was 9
centimetres.
And it has grown. In Joshua's words, it has grown.
Good. And you're gonna do that for all three of them.
- Okay, um, The peanut butter,
- No, we just did the peanut butter
Oh no, I mean the banana, it's... it's...
It's grown like 4 inches taller
Its like 1, 1 and a half inch taller.
- Its like one and  half inches.
- Okay what is that? Look. Its like 9 and a half.
- 10 and a half - 9, 10 and 12. That's 1, 2, 3
- We're looking at the bananas, yeah
... wait that's half an inch
Alright, so did you get that? Were the Cheetos
recorded? Okay, good.
Alright, so now we've got... let's look here. Josh go
ahead and read number 9.
Compare and record the results from all three fat
absorb- absorption- observations.
Observations
Observations, okay, so we're going to look at all three
here we've got our data laid out here. Look at your Cheetos.
Um the first time Cheetos was eight and a half inches,
the second time it was 10 and a half inches, and the
last time it was 12. 12 centimeters.
So what does that mean? Joseph what do you see when
you see those numbers going like that?
Um its like growing because every time you check one its
like
a little bit bigger and it gets a little more inches on
and it gets a little bit more big.
So basically the longer that the Cheetos sat on the
paper towel,
the more fat and oil is absorbed into the paper towel,
right? Okay?
So um Josh, if you'll just go ahead and write that down
about the Cheetos.
And Hailey, what did you notice about the next food?
The apples?
Um, two times it stayed the same and one time it got
a little bit smaller.
- Just got a little bit?
- Yeah
Okay, it says two are the same and one is just a little
bit different.
And that could have been just, um where is our centimeters?
It could have been just human error where we just sort
of measured a little bit off.
Okay? Um, 'cause if you look at this apple sample here,
there isn't really any coming out of the green
circle, is there?
So nothing was absorbed from the apple.
Did you see that? Okay, alright?
So if you'll add that to our list
that we've noticed, we observed.
Shemaire you look at those potato chips.
I'm going to leave that one here.
Tell us what the overall pattern was with the potato chips.
The potato chips
Talk real loud for me.
Um ok, the potato chips, they, like, changed each time.
Like, the first time, it was 5, the second time it was
eight and a half and this time it was 7.
And what are those that you are talking about?
what units of measure?
Centimeters
- Centimeters, okay. So we want to make sure we get
centimeters written in on there okay?
-[Student] uh-huh
Alright, so what does that tell you about potato chips?
Um, that its not like that fat, it doesn't got that much
grease in it 'cause, pretty much it showed like,
it was lower and then it got a little bigger
then it just got a little bigger.
Okay, so comparing the three here, what do you notice?
Pretty much that this one has more fat than these two.
It looks like with this observation, just this one here
in class today,
and later we're gonna do- we'll look at the food labels of
potato chips and Cheetos.
But right now, just on our observations, it does look
like the Cheetos have more fat right now, okay?
- But when we start reading, its gonna be potato chips?
- Oh that leads us in
- [Shemaire] It's gonna be Cheetos!
So go ahead, so um let's look at number 10,
read that for us Josh.
What can you conclude from the observations and recorded
data?
Which snack has the most, or least amount of fat?
So you all will come and discuss that together and then
you can answer that question right there.
Put most and least. Fine, okay?
I'd say the apples have the least amount of fat.
And the potato chips have the least...
... the apples have the least amount of fat, then the
potato chips second and the Cheetos is last.
And why do you think that might be? Why do you
think the banana has expanded the most?
Because its... - I don't think its because
of the fat in the bananas and getting in...
Talk loud
I don't think its because of fat with the bananas that's
getting oil on the paper towel,
because bananas are pretty healthy and they don't really
normally have fat in them.
Yeah, yeah
Okay, so that's your background knowledge. You are aware
of that. What were you gonna say?
- It's like, its not fat or oil, its like its just water
- Maybe water
[Student] absorbed in it...
What prediction would you make, if we were to let this sit
over night, to where like, the water would have time to dry up.
What would you predict this paper towel would look like
tomorrow? Let me go with Tray?
It would be all wet and soggy.
- So you think it would actually be more wet?
- Yeah.
-[Teacher] Okay, Emily what do you think?
Well I would think that the way it is now, that the paper
towels are gonna end up like that
and the bananas would get all... and more disgusting and...
Okay, does anybody think that the banana might-
that the wet, watery part might dry up? Maybe
I think it would expand a little bit more and then
start drying until the water is out of the banana
and then the banana starts to dry out too.
Okay, well alright. We'll actually leave that one
out and see, and we'll check on it tomorrow.
And see what it's doing. And we'll kind of answer
our own question there, okay?
Okay, wait we're not finished,
what do we say about the banana?
You have to talk louder though
The banana I guess - the banana, like expands
the wetness.
It expands a couple centimeters, like a half a centimeter.
Good use of centimeters. I like how you're using
the actual mathematical term there.
The centimeter is good.
Okay while she is writing that, I'm going to let Tray
go ahead and read that next question,
Well, if you can see it.
Maddie, will you let him read that so we can kinda
be thinking while your finishing up there?
Um, what can you conclude from the observ-
observation and recorded data?
What snack has the most most and least amount of fat?
Well, um, as my opinion, I would think that, the
banana has more fat than the peanut butter
and the least amount of fat would be the fudge.
Okay, Josh?
Well, I would think that the fudge has the least amount,
'cause it has the least amount of absorbed
like, grease and fat. But the banana has like
... all this oil, water and all that, like, sinking into it.
Okay, Maddie?
I think that the peanut butter has the most
amount of fat because um
like I said earlier, the bananas are more healthy
than the peanut butter and
it's probably just water and this is like oils and
salt and stuff,
making it more greasy and that's probably more
fat absorbing into the paper and
then the fudge hasn't had very much at all so
I would say it has the least amount of fat.
I would agree with like most of y'all because the banana
and the peanut butter is like,
has like, a lot of wetness in it. And the fudge
has like, a little bit of wetness.
- Like a centimeter
- Yeah, about a centimeter.
But also the bananas could have the least amount of fat
because they are healthier and that's probably just water.
Compare the results to the original group hypothesis.
Our hypothesis is that the potato chips will
have the most fat.
-[Teacher] Talk loud
Our Hypothesis is that the potato chips will
have the most fat.
Our group decided this after discussing Cheetos
versus potato chips deep fried and
adding salt and Cheetos are made out of cheese so
cheese is made out of milk from cows, which is healthy.
Oh, wow, lots of thought went into that.
Okay, so read that question again, how do we compare
our original hypothesis to what we've discovered
now in our research?
- We were wrong.
- Say that again.
-[Shemaire] We were wrong.
Okay, so according to our data, what did you find?
Why do you say we were wrong?
- Because, like the Cheetos, they had like
a bunch of fat, grease and stuff.
- [Teacher] Talk louder
And the potato chips, they like barely have any.
They had some, but it wasn't quite what you were
thinking, right?
- What were you gonna say Josh, we're gonna
come right back to you.
- [Josh] No
- Yes Joseph?
- She thought it was the Cheetos,
which we thought it was that and afterwards now since
we found out that it was probably the cheese [mumbles]...
- Talk loud
- When it gets stuck on you fingers, it's all wet and
oily and everything.
- [Teacher] Okay
- No, she's the one that said cheese was healthy.
- Okay well think about it, some cheeses are healthy,
this is more of a dehydrated powdered cheese
added to the Cheetos, right?
Go ahead, Josh, what were you gonna say?
- She said that maybe the salt from the potato chips
could've dried up the grease, maybe.
- [Teacher] Okay, Hailey?
Pretty much what Josh said. It's the same.
Okay, so you just agree with that?  So Josh, maybe
you could all just write down some of what you all discussed.
About the change from what our prediction or our
hypothesis was to what we found now? Okay?
And Hailey if you want to go ahead and start some
of our discussion questions. Okay?
Based on our discoveries from today,
what snack has less fat? Joseph?
- Um apples
- Claire?
- [Claire] Definitely apples.
- Josh?
- Apples
- Yeah, apples.
When you go home today, what snack would you choose
based on the data collected today and why? Joseph?
I'd probably do the apples because it pretty much has
no fat which we learned, and
I'd probably want to eat no more Cheetos
since I found out how many fat was in them now.
- Never again?
- [Joseph] Never
- Oh, you wouldn't live would you?
- Very good Hailey, say that again?
- [Hailey] I wouldn't eat Cheetos very often
You wouldn't eat Cheetos as much, but in
limited quantities, right?
Okay, very good. Shemaire which snack would
you choose?
I'd probably have to say apples too because
they are healthy either way and
I love Granny Smith apples, they're my favorite.
Oh good, good, healthy snack eater!
I'm going to have to say now since we found out Cheetos,
how much fat it has.
Then we start thinking about how much fat is
actually in there,
we probably don't know how much fat is in there.
Right. Well we're going to look at those food labels
closer now that we've investigated these and see
which one really does have more fat,
the potato chips or the Cheetos.