- Where do I have more potential energy,
at position A, or position B, Matt?
- [Matt] Position A.
- Why?
- [Matt] Because it's fully
stopped before it's there,
it's already moving a little bit.
- What else?
Why does this point here, point A,
have more potential energy than point B?
So this is A, this is B.
Does everyone agree that
position A has more potential energy?
Raise your hand if you agree with that.
Okay.
Now who can tell me why, why does position A
have more potential
energy than position B?
- [Voiceover] It has
more potential to do work.
- Why, has potential to do work, yes, why?
- [Voiceover] It has a greater height.
- It has a greater height.
Who mentioned gravitational
potential energy
at the beginning of the class?
- [Voiceover] I did.
- Okay, so going back to GPE.
When you have a pendulum
swinging back and forth,
types of energy that are
involved are kinetic energy,
and potential energy,
specifically. We can say that
the potential energy is
representing gravitational
potential energy.
If you
focus your attention here.
What is that?
- [Voiceover] A pendulum?
- [Teacher] A pendulum.
Similar to what you have here.
Actually, you guys within the next week,
you'll actually be working
with the simulation,
it's effect simulation, they're online.
They're free for you to use and they're
nice because they allow you to play.
I know you like to a play a lot.
- [Voiceover] I like to play.
- [Teacher] Yes, Matt. (laughs)
You will be working with
this, but I just wanted
to show you another application of this,
just in a different format.
When we swing the pendulum
what's going to happen?
- [Voiceover] It's gonna move.
- [Teacher] It's going to move and at
point
here.
And here, let's say A and B,
what type of energy is being represented?
- Potential.
- [Teacher] Potential energy.
Who can tell me where kinetic energy
is going to be represented?
You wanna come up?
- [Voiceover] Sure.
Between A and B.
- So every place along
the path between A and B.
Does everyone agree with Ali?
- [Class] Yes.
- Yes, okay.
Where is
gravitational potential energy at its max?
Wanna go up and point?
- At points A and B.
- Right, so everyone
agree on the two ends?
Where would kinetic energy be at its max?
Where is kinetic energy at its max?
- Right here.
- Why?
- Because it's lowest.
- What else?
So we said here, let's label this point C,
we already used A and B.
Why is kinetic energy at its maximum value
at this point here?
- [Voiceover] That's when the potential
energy is at its lowest.
- Great, that's where potential energy,
the gravitational potential
energy, is at its lowest.
And if you remember or can
recall the kinetic energy
formula, what does the formula state?
What variables involved in the kinetic
energy formula, Matt?
- [Matt] Mass and velocity.
- Mass and velocity.
What can you infer about
the velocity of the pendulum
as it's swinging along
its path back and forth,
from A to B?
What can we infer about
the kinetic energy?
- [Student] It's terminal
velocity is (mumbling).
- Well, we're not gonna
say terminal velocity,
the object isn't falling, it's attached.
What can we conclude about the velocity
at point C, any thoughts?
Garrett?
- [Garrett] Greatest.
- [Teacher] It's at its greatest.
When the pendulum is at this point,
it stops at each point A
and B, our two end points,
it stops for a split second
because it has to do what?
Maddy, did you say it?
- [Maddy] Turn around.
- It has to turn around.
When it swings back down,
what's happening to the velocity?
Is it increasing or decreasing?
Increasing, so if the
velocity is increasing,
what's gonna happen to
the kinetic energy value?
It's also going to increase.
Now, if
I show you
a graphical representation.
Who can describe the
graphical representation?
- [Student] Like a downward (mumbling).
- Okay.
Ali?
- As it moves I guess it
swings back and forth,
the kinetic energy when it
reaches the middle point,
it's the highest and then
when it reaches points A and B
the potential energy gets highest.
- So does this
simulation validate the thoughts and ideas
you just came up with?
- [Students] Yes.
- Yes and we see that
through the representation
of the graphical information
of your potential
energy and kinetic energy.
I can stop it at certain areas.
Sometimes it comes out better than others.
It is somewhat on its way back,
but just note that the kinetic energy is
lower than the potential energy.
And if I'm really good I can maybe try
and get it in the middle.
Close enough, it's hard to
stop it right in the center.
But you notice that the
potential energy does what?
(several students speaking)
Decreases and your kinetic energy will?
- [Students] Increase.
- Increase rather.
And you said that the
kinetic energy will be
at its max at point C.
One other factor that's involved here.
There is one other type of
energy or form of energy
that's involved, can anyone think of it?
Celini?
- [Voiceover] Thermal.
- Thermal energy.
- [Voiceover] Mechanical?
- Mechanical.
- [Voiceover] Thermal.
- [Teacher] Thermal.
Garrett, you had your hand up.
- [Garrett] Thermal.
- [Teacher] Thermal.
Who agrees with thermal? Raise your hand.
- [Student] Wait, actually no.
- Is there thermal energy involved
in the motion of a pendulum?
- [Voiceover] No.
- That's mechanical.
Thermal.
If you're saying thermal
energy, what form of
thermal energy is represented
here with the pendulum?
What is the pendulum doing right now?
It's moving through the?
- Air.
When objects move through the air,
what can occur?
Or what is present?
Air resistance, which is a form of?
- [Student] Friction.
- [Teacher] Friction.
Is or is not friction an
example of heat energy?
- [Student] Is.
- Or thermal energy?
Yes, so is it possible for us to have
some thermal energy present?
- [Students] Yes.
- [Teacher] Yes.
Now how come it's not
showing up on the graph?
- [Student] There's no friction.
- There's no friction.
So what I like about
this, and like I said,
you guys will be using the simulation.
And one of the options you have is to
change the value for friction.
Right now I have no friction so it's not
showing up on the grid.
So if I increase the friction you're going
to see how the value for
thermal energy will change.
Also, when you apply or
work with the simulation,
you can actually change
the mass of the ball,
or the pendulum in the length
of the pendulum itself.
And those are factors
that you will investigate
and collect data on in the upcoming days.
So let's add some friction.
Let's go about halfway.
What's happening to the friction?
- [Voiceover] It's increasing.
- [Student] It's
increasing on every swing.
- It's increasing with every swing.
- [Voiceover] And the
pendulum is not reaching
points A and B anymore.
- And the what?
- [Voiceover] It's not
reaching points A and B anymore.
- Why, what's happening
here, we have all these
types of forms of
energy, what's happening?
- [Voiceover] The air
resistance slowing it down.
- The air resistance
could be slowing it down.
Want a little more?
- [Voiceover] Falls away.
- Lots of friction, and
what's gonna happen?
Ali?
- [Ali] Losing particles?
- It's not losing particles,
I'm not losing any mass.
We're not changing the mass, we're not
changing the particles
if there's a great deal of friction.
- [Voiceover] It's losing energy.
- It slows down.
Does it lose energy?
(students talking)
How many of you think it loses energy?
Raise your hand.
How many of you think otherwise?
What happens to the
energy that was present?
We had colorful bars,
Matt said it's colorful.
We had colorful bars
representing kinetic energy
and potential energy.
Now we have these great big red bars,
representing thermal
energy and the total energy
is thermal right now. What
happened in this simulation?
Ali?
- I don't know that, but
because in the definition of
thermal energy that's the
total potential or kinetic
energy in an object.
- So there is potential and
kinetic energy involved, yes.
Steven, you wanna try and help him out?
- [Steven] The energy gets
transferred to thermal?
- Exactly, the energy gets
transferred to thermal energy.
What does the word transfer mean?
Or transform, what does that mean?
You know the movie Transformers?
You guys are not too young for that right?
I had a Transformer.
I did.
Jessica.
- [Jessica] It changes?
- [Teacher] It changes.
If we were to come up
with a new concept today
explaining what happened, what
could we say that we learned
about the energies involved?
What would be the main concept,
the thing you just learned
which Steven and Jessica proceeded?
What happened to the energies,
who can restate what
they just stated, Matt?
Or maybe give a definition.
Energy is?
- [Matt] Transferred, but not lost.
- Okay, energy can be
transferred or transformed
and energy is not lost.
So what you learned right
now is that energy can be
transformed into other forms of energy.
Would you agree with that statement?
Raise your hand if you agree.
And what does the word transform mean?
- Bella?
- [Bella] Change.
- [Teacher] Good, change.
So you changed.
We began with what kind of
energy at this position?
Elaine.
- [Elaine] Potential.
- [Teacher] Potential.
Ailsa, it changed to?
- [Ailsa] Kinetic.
- [Teacher] Kinetic,
it changed to?
- [Voiceover] Potential.
- [Teacher] Potential.
Changed back to?
- Kinetic.
- Kinetic, and we also have
some thermal energy involved.
Is everyone clear on that concept?
What you're going to do with your group,
get out a sheet of paper,
a piece of scrap paper.
Or you could use the back
of your packet is fine,
there's a blank spot on there.
One paper.
- [Voiceover] Per group?
- [Teacher] Per group.
(students talking over each other)
Okay, what you're going to do.
I'm showing you two
objects, I brought in props
for you guys today.
Real life, this is my toaster from home.
- [Class] Aw.
- [Voiceover] Is it a
brave little toaster?
(laughter)
- What I want you to do,
you have two examples.
Stand and look at the fan because
it is plugged in, it is turned on,
the blades are moving.
What I want you to do
to these two objects,
I want you to write
down the forms of energy
that you think are involved
with these appliances or objects,
but what I want you to do
is take it a step further.
I want you to tell me or place in order,
what type of energy do
you begin with and then
maybe with one to two
types of energy or forms
of energy that are transformed.
So you begin with, you
might have a thought,
what type of energy do
I begin with in order
for the toaster to work?
What type of energy
did the fan begin with in
order for it to turn on?
And I want you to list the
types of forms of energy
involved and then put them in
the order of transformation.
You're gonna get about two
to three minutes to do this.
I would like every person
in the group to participate.
You all should be able to
share your ideas freely.
Respect what other people are saying,
and then come to a consensus
and write down your idea
and your energies.
Any questions before you begin?
Any questions?
Okay.
(students talking with one another)
- See, it like stops here (mumbling).
Like that's potential energy and (mumbling).
(students talking all at once)
- Well, if you look at the fan,
I purposely turned it on.
So the blades are doing what?
They're moving. Are they doing work?
Yes.
Base your forms or types of energy
on what you see.
The blades are moving,
it is turning, okay?
If you want to list the
energy you begin with,
put an arrow, put the next
form of energy, put an arrow.
Put the next form of energy
to show the consecutive
transformations of your
energy that's involved
with the two objects.
Is it turning right now?
Do you all agree on that?
I would spend a little time
sharing some ideas about that.
- Wait, wait, wouldn't they both be
nuclear energy?
- Nuclear energy?
- Yes, because it's (mumbling).
- Think about your
definition of (mumbling).
- [Voiceover] Here you put
the energy for toaster.
(students talking all at once)
I would write it down.
Sucked in.
I don't have the jolt in that, look.
I don't have the toaster plugged in.
(background chatter)
Don't burn yourself.
But let's look and observe.
Three of you, do you feel anything?
- Yes, do you see all those
little black pointy things,
when you put something in
there and you turn it on?
I don't know what you call
those things, but they like...
- The coil?
- Yeah, the coil, yeah.
- (mumbling)
- Yes, they do!
That's how you generate the heat.
- If you had the toast it would turn on.
- How about in the oven, coils inside,
what colors do they turn?
- Orange.
They turn orange, the same thing.
- They turn orange?
So do you think that there's a
form of energy involved here?
- [Girls] Yeah.
- Magnetic.
That's right?
- Oh!
- But you discovered it on your own.