- [Voiceover] What you just said.
They're going to go back together.
- Well, I've glued them
down so they can't.
The green and the red charts
are locked down in place.
They can't get back, but I've
taken up the orange field.
- [Voiceover] Wouldn't
it generate a new field?
- They're going to make a new field
and that new field will be?
- [Voiceover] (mumbles)
- Say it again.
Oh, like the earlier drawing?
- [Voiceover] (mumbles)
- We can actually say a little more than that.
In this vicinity here?
- [Voiceover] (mumbles)
- They'll be trying to pull
each other back together.
So, we're going to end up with a field
that's exactly opposite (mumbles).
What we did was they move around.
(laughs)
- [Voiceover] As long
as it's still running.
- They move apart until the field
is basically nullified.
- [Voiceover] Let's look at one more example.
- [Voiceover] Do you have one
more potato shape in there?
- [Voiceover] Most people.
- [Voiceover] Most people, right.
So, let's start for this last one,
let's look at this shape and say
that I observe
fields coming out like that.
Write down a couple of observations
before you make your prediction.
Based on what you're seeing in there,
what can you say about what you see?
(class chatting)
- Are those lines all
supposed to be straight?
- [Voiceover] Yeah.
To the best of my drawing
ability they're horizontal,
parallel lines.
My drawing was perfect.
- Mr. Shields, what (mumbles)?
- [Voiceover] They're
going in two directions.
- [Voiceover] The orange?
- [Voiceover] Yeah, the orange one.
- [Voiceover] Like a very large plate.
(class chatting)
- [Voiceover] It could
be just a potato in there
and that's (mumbles).
(class chatting)
- [Voiceover] The thing in your hand.
- [Voiceover] This one?
- [Voiceover] Yep.
(class chatting)
- [Voiceover] Okay, let's take a look.
Chris, can I get you to shut the door
to keep the noise down?
We'll give you a break in
about 10 minutes or so.
It's nice to have the extra period here.
First thing before we
talk about this new one,
I failed to address Hannah's question
and good insight earlier.
Yes, (mumbles).
The orange lines in here will
be drawn into the negative
and they're going to bend and
will be coming outward
from the positive end.
So, you're definitely going
to see this sort of pattern.
I think people saw a little
bit of that in the simulations.
Anytime you've got a
conducting material...
Anytime you've got a conducting material
the field lines always
intersect exactly perpendicular
with (mumbles).
It's a conductor.
So, it definitely makes a
difference when you call it
a conductor and look at
what happened in the field.
Let's talk about this new one.
There's a couple of observations.
Ian give me one observation
and Claire give me the second observation.
- Besides the fact that
the lines are straight.
- [Voiceover] No, that's a good one.
The lines are straight.
Very important.
Claire?
- They're going in opposite directions.
- [Voiceover] Exactly opposite directions.
Okay, Hakim give me another one.
- Well, the lines are coming out of it.
- [Voiceover] Okay, they're
coming outward not inward.
Good.
- To indicate that the (mumbles).
- [Voiceover] Okay, so
that one we know from
the very first piece here.
The net charge is positive.
The fact that they're horizontal.
- They indicate like a plate or something.
- Yeah, is it like two parallel plates?
(mumbles)
- [Voiceover] Two parallel plates?
So, where would you draw them?
Above and below?
- There are two on top.
- [Voiceover] So, like
above and below like this?
- [Voiceover] Four plates.
Let's make it 16.
(class chatting)
- But if you had a plate
and the thing is neutral
or no net charge and
then they would just...
- But what if you had one positive plate
straight up and down the middle,
then it would push away on both sides.
- Two positive plates (mumbles).
- Two plates sounds twice as good as one,
but I'm not sure that it is.
Four plates sounds even more appealing.
An infinite number of
plates sounds fantastic.
I'm hearing good ideas here.
I want you guys to think
about what it would look like
in different scenarios.
So, two positive plates.
Okay, two positive plates
and I'm looking at the
vicinity in the middle here,
is that right?
And do I want my two positive
plates to be on the sides?
- [Voiceover] Negative plates.
- [Voiceover] Well, negative plates, okay.
Two negative plates on the sides like this
so the field would look like what?
- Bend.
- [Voiceover] Okay,
we're getting a bending
because if I draw it here--
- But you still have to compare (mumbles).
- [Voiceover] It'd be like
this kind of a picture?
- It'd still be bent.
Greater than the distance.
- [Voiceover] Okay, so you've got...
So, based on that you've got some things
going on above and below
that should be penetrating
into that shape.
- What about two infinitely long?
- [Voiceover] Two infinitely long plates.
Both negative?
What would the field look like?
Forge the potato shape.
What would the field look like
in the vicinity of two infinitely long,
evenly charged negative plates?
- Wouldn't they go (mumbles)?
- [Voiceover] If I take a
single positive test charge and
release it right in the middle,
what would it do?
- [Class] (mumbles)
- [Voiceover] What if I
release it a little bit
to the left side?
- [Class] (mumbles)
- [Voiceover] An infinitely long plate.
We derived this one before, a single one.
Remember the equation for the field
or the general shape of the field
from an infinite plane?
- [Voiceover] It's constant.
- [Voiceover] It's a
constant, exactly right.
Brittany didn't even
have to look at her notes
on that one.
But you remember, what was our analogy
to an infinitely large plate?
- [Voiceover] (mumbles)
- [Voiceover] Yeah,
gravity on the earth here,
you know, big flat earth.
I don't care how far
above the ground I am,
it's the same number, it
doesn't change at all.
That's exactly right.
So, an infinite plate,
the field is some number,
another identical infinite plate,
it nullifies it.
So, in the same charge, okay?
Well, that isn't going to work.
- [Voiceover] Infinitely far.
- Infinitely far away from each other.
(laughs)
When Brittney says it's a constant,
even if you go to infinity,
I guess it'd still be a constant,
either that or you go to zero.
- It would be two sets,
one set like that except that
they are horizontal and vertical
and they're infinitely far away
where (mumbles).
- Two horizontal plates like this?
- Yeah, because (mumbles).
(mumbles)
- I don't think that's
going to work either.
Ben, you're getting agitated back there.
And what are you saying?
- We were just talking.
- You're saying there's
no way in the world
they can be infinite.
Is that what you're saying?
- Yeah.
(laughs)
- [Voiceover] (mumbles)
- You can't have an
infinite plane anything
because you're defining the shape?
- [Voiceover] So, that's a good question.
When I've got the shape here,
do we require that the
thing that I'm talking about
fit inside of the shape?
- [Voiceover] No.
- [Voiceover] I'm going to say no.
Okay, so does that change your answer?
Okay.
I think we can and will look at situations
where the surface...
And remember this is all leading up
to that Gaussian surface idea
we mentioned on Friday.
Where the Gaussian surface does not fully
enclose an object.
Like an infinite plane, we
need to be able to study those
even though I can't
fit it inside of a box.
So, we have to expand a little bit
to the possibility that whatever it is
is inside of there.
- An infinitely long positive plate
right in the middle.
- [Voiceover] Right in the middle.
Is that what you said
about seven minutes ago?
- Yeah.
- [Voiceover] I tried to ignore him
because I didn't want you
guys to get the answer
too quick.
But I do want to acknowledge him (laughs).
Yeah, tell me if this makes sense and why?
Somebody besides John and Ian.
It doesn't make sense
that I've got a plate
and this is slicing my potato in half
and it's a positive plate.
- [Voiceover] Would it
have to be infinitely long?
- [Voiceover] Much longer (mumbles).
(mumbles)
- If I don't...
Now, I'm not very good at drawing in 3D
so is the potato lines,
are they diverging this way at all?
I can't tell.
They're uniform this way,
parallel lines this way,
so we know that it has
to be infinite this way.
And not have divergence
this way (mumbles).
- [Voiceover] (mumbles)
- Well, I didn't draw any lines
coming out of the (mumbles).
Do they have to be parallel to the ones
that are on the board
or would they be diverging?
That's going to change
the answer that you give.
If I draw another red line
that's coming like this,
that's clearly diverging
from this red line.
So, I'm going to assume that every line,
for this problem, every line that I draw
is parallel and then
we'll get a new (mumbles).
- [Voiceover] Perpendicular
with the plate.
- [Voiceover] Yeah, perpendicular
to the board.
And then all positive
coming out both sides.
Very good.
Alright, I've got one
more drawing on there
I want to hit and then we'll just say
some fantastic summary words
and then I'll give you guys a break.
The last one here,
instead of the three dimensional shape,
now all I've got is a
single sheet of paper.
And this sheet of paper I've got,
I noticed...
(mumbles)
I noticed parallel lines,
arrows, coming straight out of that shape.
Write down a couple of
observations on it quick
and then see if you can predict,
based on what you observed here,
what and where, if you want to,
what the source of the field lines is.
What can we learn from
the electric field lines?
- [Voiceover] They're
all coming out parallel
in one direction.
- [Voiceover] Yes,
parallel in one direction.
(class chatting)
One direction.
They're parallel this way
and they're parallel this way also.
So, they're normal to
the surface everywhere.
- Are they coming from the other side?
- [Voiceover] All I see is
lines penetrating this way,
so I could actually draw them like this
and that's fine.
- Do you know anything about
the other side of the plate,
like is there anything there?
- [Voiceover] It's a two
dimensional structure
and the arrows penetrate.
- Oh, okay.
- [Voiceover] Yeah, they're
not diverging at all.
Yeah, uniform, orthogonal,
all that good stuff.
(class chatting)
- [Voiceover] Into the paper?
- So, they're coming out of here?
- [Voiceover] They're going
into here and coming out here.
- Oh, okay.
- To the differences,
that's a closed shape.
This is a two dimensional surface.
If I had wrapped it around like this
it would make a difference, right?
(mumbles)
(class chatting)
- Okay guys, let's see what we've got here.
I'm going to ask Paul first,
Emily second, and then
we'll see if Michael
can go for the trifecta.
- Oh no.
- [Voiceover] No pressure.
You can be wrong, it's alright.
Paul, what is, based on your observations,
what is the thing that
you think is the source
of the electric field here?
Where is it coming from
that it makes this pattern
in this object, on this sheet?
- I think this is like the second
or the third example we did
when it was passing through.
- [Voiceover] Where they're
just passing through?
- Yeah.
- [Voiceover] So, then where
do you think it's coming from?
What does that tell you about the source
of the electric field?
- I'm not sure.
- [Voiceover] You have more to say?
- No.
- [Voiceover] Emily, give it a try.
- Since it's positive on this side?
- [Voiceover] Yup.
- You can see that there might be
a positive charge (mumbles).
- [Voiceover] Okay, so if
I had a positive charge
on this side, I would
get electric field lines
going like this?
That's correct, okay.
- Or if you had a
negative charge (mumbles).
- Ah okay, so you're answering two things,
which is pretty
overachieving, but I like it
that you're saying that instead
of a positive back here,
it could be a negative over here.
Okay, now there's something incomplete
about what you're saying.
The positive here versus there
could be a negative here,
that's a great insight that
it could be one or the other,
but Michael's going to help us out
because you're a little incomplete
on what you're telling us.
- They have to be infinite.
- [Voiceover] Infinite.
Infinitely strong charge.
- Infinitely long, whatever, a plane.
- A plane, yeah.
A plane back here that's infinitely large,
distributive charge that's positive.
That's the only way to
get a uniform field here.
Can it work with what
Emily was saying about
it could be a negative over here?
It could be an infinitely long thing here?
There's one more option.
Does anybody (mumbles)?
- It could be intro (mumbles).
- [Voiceover] That this
piece of paper here
is neutral?
- And you could just put
a new positive charge.
- [Voiceover] But be careful.
Any positive charge, if I start off with
the very first drawing,
and I look at what happens
when I put a sheet here,
the field lines are like this.
(mumbles)
(laughs)
They're diverging.
I'm not having divergence here at all.
So, it can't come from
any old point source.
We are going to assume that
this thing is neutral though.
Okay, that itself is not...
It's just capturing the story
of what's going on.
Hannah?
- Could there be both a positive
and negative along the plate?
- [Voiceover] Yeah, you can have both.
You bet.
- [Voiceover] That seems like
a little bit of overkill,
but as long as you're making
your sheet infinite in size,
you might as well make two infinite's.
- You have all your infinite (mumbles).
- [Voiceover] That's right.
And two parallel plates,
two plates that are
parallel to each other,
one positive, one negative,
is a very common thing.
So common in fact that
it's on my tie today.
Oh yeah, there it is.
See that?
(laughs)
Hakim, do you have a question?
- Okay, so it's the positive plane
that's standing or negative plane?
- [Voiceover] Yeah, the infinite plane.
- The infinite plane.
I was about to say that.
That it would be infinite.
- [Voiceover] Yeah, I
think Michael was saying
that it would probably be.
Not the charge distribution, the sigma,
how much charge per unit area
will be some number,
but it would just keep on going on.
Chris?
- (mumbles)
- [Voiceover] Yeah, you know,
that would be a lot.
- (mumbles)
- [Voiceover] Reasonably
speaking, if something goes
to infinity, all of your homework is easy.
So, there's no purpose for me doing that.
What is the answer?
Infinity or zero.
It's got to be one.
Infinitely large in size
with a uniform charge distribution
does add up to an infinite charge,
but it's distributed infinitely far away.
So that's okay.
Now, remember the goal of this
as we were getting into this today,
is to figure out what can we learn
from an electric field?
And here's the thing.
In the first three or four examples
or five I guess for some people,
if I take a closed
surface I can learn a lot.
Not everything necessarily,
but I can learn about
what's inside of that.
Infinitively, is the first one positive?
- [Class] Yes.
- [Voiceover] Yes.
The next one that I drew
was negative, absolutely.
This most recent closed surface,
it had to be a positive
plate shoved in there.
This last one with just a
two dimensional structure
to measure with, to
gauge what's happening,
I don't know everything.
We've got a lot of ambiguity.
And this is why with Gauss' law
we need to use this closed surface.
We need to look at it from all sides.
We need to be fully
envelop in what's going on
or else we might miss something.
We'll go back again.
The equation that I showed you last week,
we'll put that on the
board in a few minutes
when we come back from a break
as well as looking at
a couple of scenarios,
just conceptually how
we can draw these things
to capture all that field.
Go ahead and take a break
and be back in five minutes.