- What do you think it
is going to be this time?
I think it's going to
be like negative 57, 59.
- Maybe like 54 or something.
- Colder or hotter.
You don't need to touch...
- You don't need to touch it.
You and your temperature.
(multiple voices talking at once)
- [Voiceover] I got a (mumbles) playing
with your (mumbles).
- Go down.
- [Voiceover] The temperature
is going to go down with the ice.
- It was 22.
- [Voiceover] 22, no not 22.
- [Voiceover] You think
(mumbles) ice the temperature is
going to go down?
(multiple voices talking at once)
- The water went up.
- It's your choice how much
of anything you put in.
(multiple voices talking at once)
- Should we put a lot?
- A little more.
- Why don't you dump it into (mumbles)?
- Not the whole thing.
- Yeah.
Oh!
(multiple voices talking at once)
- [Voiceover] Don't put
it all in like that. There's hardly any room.
- Ready?
- Go.
(multiple voices talking at once)
- Science is kind of messy, isn't it?
It's okay.
Just put it back in
there and work together.
- Tell me when to go.
- Ready?
- Ready and start.
- What do you think?
I think it's going to be
like maybe 20 degrees.
- Or maybe negative 10.
- We'll just have to see.
(multiple voices talking at once)
- 40, Jacob, 40.
- [Voiceover] No, it's 50. 40.
- 50 degrees, it's almost.
- It's 50 degrees, Jake.
It's 50 degrees.
It's 50 degrees, Jake.
What's he doing.
- [Voiceover] So where's the line?
Try to put one in.
- Oh, so now you get it?
- Where's the line?
- [Voiceover] And it's 40.
- 40, comes out like 44.
- [Voiceover] What's the temperature?
- It changed.
- 44. It says 40.
- [Voiceover] No, it's 44.
- Jacob, it doesn't matter.
- [Voiceover] What are you
having a dispute about here.
(mumbles) get out now.
- It was right here.
- So it's on.
- It's not even gone down.
- And now it went up to what?
Well, a little higher than that.
Yours went up, so what did,
how do you know, Jacob, by looking at the
thermometer, how it went up or down?
Explain to me.
- I know how it went up because I see,
because if you turn your
head away and then you look
at it, it went up.
- You think so?
How do you read this, though?
(multiple voices talking at once)
- Are they?
There's five lines right, let's see,
but how do you break it
up so you can read it
to get from 70 to 80?
How do you break that
up, Jacob, do you know?
- Um.
- Right, you count by twos.
Okay, you guys get busy, I'm interrupting
your experimental time,
you're scientists here.
(multiple voices talking at once)
- [Voiceover] Down, all the way down.
- [Voiceover] Just color it up to 50.
- [Voiceover] Down 30.
I wonder what was in it.
- I think it's salt.
- I don't think it's salt.
- Last time I used, last time I used it
it went down, and then
it went down even more.
(multiple voices talking at once)
- That's what I told you.
- It's floating.
- I'm breathing in good water.
Water.
- What happened?
(multiple voices talking at once)
- Use the thermometer.
Ready, set, go.
(mumbles) one more.
(multiple voices talking at once)
- I think it's going to
get colder, and (mumbles).
I think it's going to get (mumbles).
- I think it's going to get negative 10.
- What do you think, Emily?
- [Voiceover] Zero degrees.
(multiple voices talking at once)
- [Voiceover] Maybe negative zero.
- I'm not sure there is a negative zero.
- It's like frost all over it.
- Cold.
- Frost right here.
- Whatever was in it makes it go down.
- Temperature go down, makes frost.
(multiple voices talking at once)
- Mystery (mumbles) is salt.
The mystery grain is salt.
The mystery grain is salt,
it's melting the ice.
- [Voiceover] And it's
condensing on the outside.
- [Voiceover] Ready guys?
- [Voiceover] Five, four.
- [Voiceover] What do
you guys think it is?
What do you think the
temperature's going to be
this time?
- I don't know.
55.
- Lower than 50.
- 555 degrees?
- That would be toasty.
Got to be lower.
- [Voiceover] One, two, three, four, five.
I see that most of you have
finished your experiment.
I would like to call and see.
I'm going to get some questions.
- Take it out.
- Okay, eight.
I have questions.
Teagan, your group needs
to come to me, please.
Thank you, very good.
Jacob, what did you notice between
the base temperature
and the first time when
you put the water in, what happened?
- I noticed that when
the base temperature,
when we put in the base
temperature, it was only
71 degrees, and then when we put in the
water, it only changed by one degree.
- [Voiceover] It only
changed by one degree.
Very good.
Number nine, who's number nine?
Kayla, Kayla.
What did you guys notice
about the temperature?
- We...
- [Voiceover] What happened to it,
what happened to the temperature?
- It went down.
- [Voiceover] It went down.
What happened to your can, who knows?
Think about that, take a
minute with your group,
I want you to talk about what's happening
to your can, and why.
(multiple voices talking at once)
- [Voiceover] So maybe it
got frost for (mumbles).
- They get more frost on it.
When I put, and it got yellow.
The water was clear and
then it got yellow
when we put salt in.
- [Voiceover] It got dirty.
_ [Voiceover] It looks like lemonade.
- It's all mushy.
- The (mumbles) stuff is
looking to the ice that--
- And making it squishy.
- [Voiceover] Okay, one,
two, three, four, five,
come back to me for a minute.
I pulled number five.
Number five, what is
happening to your can?
- It's getting frost on it.
- [Voiceover] It's getting frost on it.
Why do you think it's getting frost?
What did your group think that it
was getting frost on it from?
- The ice and the mystery ingredient.
- [Voiceover] The mystery ingredient and
the ice are making the can frosty.
What did we learn about, with the weather
cycle, we talked about that,
what's really happening?
Talk in your group, is it the
can making the water come
on in and make the frost?
Talk in your group and
figure out if you guys
know what's coming that's
making the stuff on the
outside of the can.
(multiple voices talking at once)
- There is water on the side of the can.
- Maybe the mystery thing...
- [Voiceover] Making
condensation on the can?
And because I learned a lot about that--
- I think the mystery one
and the ice did it together.
- That could be.
- Yeah, that could be.
- And combined and then
it created frost on the
outside of the can.
- [Voiceover] I think that
the water, the mystery
ingredient, (mumbles).
- [Voiceover] Okay, one,
two, three, four, five.
Number three, what is making
your can get the frost
or the wet stuff, what's
that wet stuff called?
Ella.
- Condensation.
- [Voiceover] It's called condensation.
What do you, why is that
happening to your can?
Number three, that's you right Luke?
Okay, what's happening?
- Because it's like evaporating, and when
it touches the cold can,
then it turns back into
cold water.
- [Voiceover] What's evaporating?
Stop, don't answer that.
Think in your group, what,
he said it's evaporating,
and then it's touching the can.
What's touching the
can? Talk in your group,
figure out if you can
figure out what's coming to
touch your can.
- So well really it (mumbles) can.
- Yeah, it's kind of
melting, so the water is
on the can...
- So it's the mushy, icky...
- I know whatever mystery stuff.
- [Voiceover] Now I'll take it.
It makes me, and then it
makes water, water, water.
Everything, you know, water.
- [Voiceover] How will
Eve's last question?
- [Voiceover] Nope, we're
just asking questions
right this second.
You guys need to wait,
then we're gonna (mumbles).
One, two, three, four, five, come back
to me.
Number 19, who's 19?
- Ella.
- [Voiceover] Okay, Ella.
What is happening to make
that can wet on the outside?
- The water and the
ice, well the water tries
to evaporate, but since
there's ice at the top, it hits
the ice, and then it comes back down.
But then it gets on the can.
- [Voiceover] So the
water, you think the water,
in the, the can itself
is coming and making that
water come back on and
catch that, hit the ice.
Good thought, let's
keep going, let's see if
we can get some more.
Who is number 12?
- [Voiceover] Hayden.
- [Voiceover] Hayden's
not here, so let's move on
and let's find number nine.
Who's number nine?
- Kayla.
Kayla, what's happening to your can,
what's happening to it and why?
- It frosting.
- [Voiceover] It's frosting.