- Work of art in front of the class using
the smart board.
- We have to--
- Continue working please.
- We have to finish the whole thing today?
- You should have enough time if y'all
aren't drawing on the artwork that much.
But y'all been working hard and a little
bit of playing, but working pretty well.
After you get finished with the analysis,
go ahead and flip over and start on your
interpretation. What you think is going on
or what the artist is trying to portray in
the work of art. All right, so y'all are
on interpretation?
- Yeah.
- What do y'all think of the work of art?
Kaitlin, what do you think of the work of
art?
- Well, it makes us feel like calm.
- It made me feel calm.
- It made y'all feel calm?
- No, it made me feel calm.
- It made me feel calm.
- Okay. Now have any of y'all been out
west?
- Huh?
- Out west like Colorado, Wyoming, places
like that?
- Yeah. Yeah.
- Well, sometimes in the mountains, they
have places where the snow has melted and
there are actually small lakes or ponds up
inside the mountains. So you could
actually either be looking at a lake where
you could drive up to or something that's
hidden in the mountains. So if you're
calm, that's a pretty good idea. All
right, guys, what are y'all working on
now.
- We're on judging the building. I keep
working on one.
- Okay. Can you tell me what you have
about interpretation?
- I think of this art as a rainy day. The
sky is a dull gray.
- I like the bright colors on the doors.
- It's like a mixture of happiness and
boredom. Since it looks like it's raining,
the dark clouds at the top of the painting
when it goes from white to dark.
- Like from light and it's going to dark,
that's when you can tell it's about to
rain.
- Okay, gotcha, gotcha. Sounds good.
- That, sir, is my interpretation.
- Okay, and with judgment, what are y'all
think about the work of art right now?
- My judgment of the art is that it's
kind of a boring day. It's slightly dull
but you don't know what's about to happen.
- Sounds good so far. Keep working. Y'all
doing all right over here?
- Yeah, we're doing...
- I wrote my opinion. Now he's gonna write
his opinion.
- Yeah.
- And then Brody will write his opinion?
Sounds great.
- All right. Y'all on interpretation. What
y'all had? Oh, y'all are each doing
interpretation?
- Yes, sir. We were going to do that for
judgment and interpretation.
- Sounds great. And what are y'all looking
at now for interpretation with the subway
painting?
- We're doing what it makes you feel.
- Okay, what do you have so far?
- Well, he wrote most of them.
- Okay, so he can read it?
- Okay, actually it makes me feel like
traveling...
- Okay.
- ...since they're on a train. And that's
pretty much it.
- All right. Who would like to tell me
what they are thinking of for
interpretation on valley flowers?
- I don't know. I mean, it's a good
painting but it's not really my favorite.
- Okay.
- It's not very exciting.
- So that would be for judgment? You don't
find it exciting? Okay, kind of boring.
What do you think of the work of art?
- I think it's a bit dull because there's
not really any colors or anything like
that, and it's got the same colors where
each... Right here is green, and right
here is orange, and blues back there.
- You know, if I was using my imagination,
I would think of maybe The Incredibles in
where the mole men came up at the end and
were taking over the Earth. So these could
be tunnel boring machines.