- They're coming around. They're coming
around. When you have it, "You're a Grand Old
Flag" goes under your seats. "What Do the
Stars Do?" Put them in your hands.
William, why don't you come
sit next to Victoria?
Do you mind? Because then you're
a little closer.
Just move a little closer to Jeffrey.
Stand. Reach. Stand up. Stand up.
Big breath. Oh my goodness. Relax. Put
your hands here. Get a diaphragm breath
instead of that kind of a breath. Here we
go, big diaphragm breath. Ready?
Breathe in. Remember the beginning of the
year when you were doing [breathing]
Ready? Breathe in. Here we go.[Breathing]
Let it all out. Breathe in,
diaphragm breath.
Put your hand here. Breathe.
Again. [breathing]
Hiss it all out
[breathing]
Breath in.
And you're going to go
[breathing]
Ahhhhhhh ready? Here we go. Breathe in.
Start up. Breathe in. Good low diaphragm.
Relax your shoulders and ahhhhhhh. Breathe
in. Do you see what you're gonna do?
Instead of hissing out, you're gonna go
ahhhhhh and let it nice and open and tall.
Ready? Breathe in. Ahhhhhhh.
Big low breath.
Ready? Ready? Here we go.
♪ [singing] ♪
Okay. That's far too sweet. We need it to
get ugly. Let it get ugly, and I want a
slide. I need to hear every single pitch.
Ready? Really try and let that sound
vibrate in your forehead. Sing it like...
I want you to zero that sound right at me,
like you really mean it. I know you do.
Ready?
♪ [singing] ♪
Much better. Again.
Get a big breath. Again, I want to hear
every pitch on the [singing].
One, two, ready, go.
♪ [singing] ♪
I love it. Do it here.
Whoo. Sit down.
Take out "What Do the Stars Do?"
Please my friends, look at part one.
Big breath. This is tricky because we
start on a low so.
It's what do the stars [singing],
Very, very high. Make sure you're sitting
up with good posture.
♪ [What Do the Stars Do?] ♪
Here we go. ♪ [What do the stars do
up in the sky.] ♪
I am so impressed that you
remember so much of that.
That was beautiful.
We're gonna do it again.
We want a really round ooh, and I need
a little more emotion on.
♪ [What do the stars do?] ♪ Do you feel
it? Think about it. You're singing to the
stars. How cool is that? Right? Here we
go. Not like celebrities either, like the
actual stars in the sky. Here we go.
♪ [What do the stars do up in the sky?] ♪
Love what  I'm hearing. Is the word "do"
interesting? Or do we just kind of seem
to hold it forever and it's kind of
boring? Speak really loudly.
Christopher, what was your idea?
- We could crescendo.
- We could crescendo. I think that's a
great idea. I think it needs some kind of
motion. So let's put a little crescendo
on the word "do."
Ryan, what's your question? A sforzando?
We'll try that in a second. Let's see.
We'll choose which one we like better.
Let's try just a crescendo on "do," just
to keep it interesting. So it's
♪ [What do the stars do up in the sky?] ♪
Try and do it in one breath.
If you have to breathe. Don't breathe
at the same time as your neighbor.
Stagger. Ready? Here we go.
♪ [What do the stars do up in the sky?] ♪
I love the crescendo. We have to get it
together for up. Right?
Let's try Ryan's idea. You want to do a
sforzando on "do?" Okay. Let's try it.
Ready? So it's
♪ [What do the starts do?] ♪
That was your idea too, Maria? Let's try
that. Ready? Here we go.
♪ [What do the stars do up in the sky?] ♪
You like that? You like it?
Raise a hand for crescendo.
Quiet. A quick quiet hand. Raise that
quiet hand for crescendo. Raise a quiet
hand for sforzando. Okay. Sforzando wins.
That's what we're gonna do on the word
"do. " Love it. It's really,
really pretty.
Make sure the word "do", You keep it
really nice and open. Claire, are you
sitting on a chair? Or are you sitting
between Rose and Garrety. Just go grab a
chair. You don't have to squish like that.
Ready? Here we go.
It's okay.
I know she came in a little late.
So that's why she's... You looked a little
too close for comfort over there.
♪ [Here we go, beautifully, nice and up.
Check your posture.] ♪
Yeah, very strong.
Yes. Ready? Just Lauren,
move in a little bit.
♪ [Ready? Here we go.] ♪
♪ [What do the stars do
up in the sky?] ♪
[piano music]
♪ [What do the stars do
up in the sky] ♪
What happens there? What happens there on
that one? It goes one up higher.
Thank you, Rachel.
♪ [Up in the sky] ♪
Right? Can we start right before 11? Pick
ups to 11. Ready? Here we go.
♪ [What do the stars do
up in the sky?] ♪
What comes next? Where are we?
♪ [Where the clouds,
where the clouds can fly] ♪
That's how far we want to get today on
that. Look at where the clouds,
where the clouds can fly.
Notice part three does
♪ [Higher than the winds can climb.
Then you come in] ♪
Is your pitch after the word
higher, lower, or the same as the
pitch in part three? Higher, lower, or the
same as the pitch as "below?"
Are you sure?
We start on the same. So that's how you're
gonna know to
♪ [Higher than the winds can blow
or the clouds can go.] ♪
Yeah. Is this gonna be beautiful?
This is gonna be... Sorry. I think this is
gonna be really beautiful, like which one
we just did. Yeah. It has a lot of the
same kind of qualities, but there's some
really rich harmonies and some really
rich, beautiful opportunities for
crescendo and decrescendo
and all that kind of stuff.
Yes. The whole song isn't a cappella. It's
a cappella in parts. Yeah. It starts out a
cappella, which means no piano. Jeffrey,
sit up. It's a cappella for a little
while, and then the piano comes in.
Then it's a cappella again, and then the
piano comes in, and then it ends a
cappella. So it kind of goes back and
forth. What we want to get from this, for
today, from this piece, is I want to hear
your expression. I want to hear that
crescendo, that decrescendo. Same thing on
the word "clouds." What do we think? What
should... It's another one of those
long notes. So we need to do something
with it. What should we do with it?
Decrescendo? Put a crescendo in it?
Energize it a little bit?
Should we try each? Should we try a
decrescendo and try a crescendo and see
which one we like better?
So the long "cloud"
♪ [Where the clouds,
where the clouds can fly.] ♪
Two of them. We have two of them. So let's
energize them, and then
we'll try backing off. Let's see. Ready?
I believe that's our pitch.
Ready? Here we go. One. Two.
♪ [Where the clouds,
where the clouds can fly.] ♪
Do we like that? Just energize it a little
bit? That was crescendo.
Do we want to try backing off?
♪ [Where the clouds,
where the clouds can fly] ♪
Which one do we like better, you guys?
Let's try the decrescendo. Ryan, question?
Oh, one of each. That's what you're
thinking, Rose? So make one crescendo, one
decrescendo? So maybe which one?
So first one grow,
second one decrescendo.
Yeah, kind of pulling back a little.
Posture. First one is gonna grow. Ready?
♪ [Where the clouds,
where the clouds can fly.] ♪
I love it. I love it. Let's do from the
beginning of that piece. All right? Think
about your expression. Singing about
stars. One, two, three, one.
♪ [What do the stars do
up in the sky?] ♪
Beginning. So it's
♪ [up in the sky] ♪
and our "do." What were we gonna do with
it? I know it's hard when I'm by the
piano. I won't be. Ready? Here we go.
♪ [What do the stars do
up in the sky?] ♪
♪ [Higher than the winds can blow
or where the clouds can fly] ♪
Beautiful. Beautiful. I think that piece
is gonna be gorgeous. I can't believe it's
only your second day on it. Yeah. You know
what? The clouds or the clouds can fly had
a really beautiful crescendo, lovely
expression.
Put that one under your chair
and take out "You're a Grand Old Flag".