- Some of you are ready to print, so I
wanted to go through the actual printing
press process today. Some of you might
even be ready to try that today. If you're
not ready to try it right after I do the
demonstration, you can go back to your
etching or engraving, and then by
tomorrow, you'll be able to run it through
the press. Before I do that, I wanted to
share something with you that's a little
exciting, and the fact that I actually
have a relative who was a professional
engraver. My grandfather was an engraver.
He started in the 1930s and '40s. After
World War II, he was part of something
called the GI Bill. Does anybody know what
that is?
- Oh, I do.
- Yeah, what is it?
- They pay people to go to college.
- Yes, exactly. Yeah. After the World War
II veterans came back from war, the
government paid for them to go to college.
And he went to a college called The Art
Students League, which I was just talking
with Alex about, and he had an extensive
education in figure drawing and he chose
the trade of an engraver. I'm going to
pass some of these around. These are his
actual engraved plates that he lent to me
to show you. You can take some of those.
So you can see that the tradition of
engraving as we talked about yesterday
goes back a long time. A hundred
years at least or even more. But this is
from the early '30s and '40s, these
engravings. And these were actual etchings
done with the acid bath that I explained
that we don't do here because of the
safety. You're doing a plexiglass
engraving instead without the use of the
acid. So I'm going to demonstrate how to
do all that inking and you can get to see
the difference between the copper plates
that I'm passing around now and then the
plexiglass plates that we're working with
today. And it's kind of cool my
grandfather gave those to me and asked if
one of you would ink it up and print one
for him while we were printing all of
this. So I'm going to let one of you use
his actual etched plates and then print it
for him. All right, so the materials that
we have out here include all the different
colors of print-making ink. So for the
most part, we're going to start with black
today, but you can choose any color that
you want. So you can see some of the
examples that I put up here from past
students. One student decided, instead of
putting black ink on the white ground, he
used white ink on black ground. So that's
another method that you might choose to do
after learning the basic process. So all
the steps that we're going to go over are
up here to remind you during the class
period during the rest of the week. It's
going to remind you of all the steps. So
the first step after you've beveled all
the edges in your plate that I
demonstrated yesterday is to get yourself
some print-making ink. And all of these
materials will be out for you in front of
the room and take it to your desk when
you're ready. You'll take a little bit of
print-making ink and put it on the plate
like this.
[thud]
- Just like that. And you'll use a tool
called a brayer. And the brayer will hold
your ink and it gives you a nice flat
surface to apply the ink onto your plate.
So once your brayer is filled with
the ink, you'll apply it to the plate.
And I'm actually using my grandfather's
plate from several years ago. All right,
so you'll gently apply the ink over the
entire plate.
[shuffling]
- Okay, just take a seat
and I'll hand it out.
[shuffling]
- All right. And after you have the entire
plate inked, you'll check and make sure
that you didn't miss any spots. All right,
notice that I missed a spot there so I'm
going to have to bring it back to the
plate to get all of the areas covered.
Once you have all the areas covered... And
this is just in interest of time, I'll
just show you the next step. Once the
entire plate is covered, you'll take a
small piece of mat board.
[shuffling]
- I'll just use this instead. Okay, I have
little pieces of mat boards for you. Okay,
so you're going to take a little piece of
mat board or you can use a piece of the
wood that I have cut up here. After you
apply the entire ground with ink, you have
to remove it so you have the clean surface
with everything except all the ink that's
going to be on your inside lines. This has
a dual purpose. It removes some of the ink
for you plus it also pushes the ink down
into the surface of the plate. This has
been prepared for you to take off the
excess ink when you're done. This will
push all the ink in the surface. Okay, and
then once you get most of it removed, then
you can take the cheesecloth. I found one
of my mat boards. Here we go. All right,
so you can use the mat board here to get
off most of the ink. And then you can take
a piece of cheesecloth like this and you
want to wad the cheesecloth into your hand
like this so you have a nice solid piece
of it in front. This will lift the ink off
pretty easily. And after you do this
process... This is the messy process, so
you should take a paper towel and wash
your hands after you're done with this
before we move to the printing press. I'll
show you how to do that. Sometimes a
circular motion with this will help. So
I'm going to show so you can all see.
Circular motion to get off all of the ink
from the surface. I'm showing you this
quickly, all the steps, but I have one
prepared for us to print with. Just like a
cooking show, so it's ready to go. All
right, so you're going to use... Flat on
the table. I'm showing you this so you can
see it, but you're going to do all of this
flat at your desk. Get all of the ink off
with the cheesecloth. If you run out of
space, you could fold it over to a cleaner
side and start again. Then the last step
before you clean your edges... At this
point, if you want to go clean your hands
so you don't get it on anything again, you
could go clean your hands as well. We'll
take a piece of newsprint, a flat piece of
newsprint and just buff the top of it
again to make sure any last-minute or
leftover fingerprints are taken off of it
with this piece of paper. The newsprint
works the best, so I have cut-up piece of
newsprints for you also to make a nice,
smooth surface. And before you're ready to
print, you could take a Q-tip, dip it in
some water, and then clean your edges. So
the beveled edge that you
made of your printing plates,
you should take the Q-tip to clean
any ink off of that bevel because the idea
is to make sure the bevel around your
image is clean. So this print was left up
here for a reason. It doesn't have a clean
edge. I wanted you to see the difference
between a student that cleaned their edge
and a student that didn't clean their
edge. Okay, this has a nice, clean edge.
This has a little bit of ink left on the
edge. So when you pull a perfect print,
you want to make sure you have a clean
edge. And the way you guarantee that is
cleaning it off--