- You're totally fine.
So you guys will be using,
I'm assuming a meter tape?
- Yeah.
- For measurements?
And then can you take a minute to explain
the balance thing again so we're good?
- Strength versus strength
qualifies ten times.
- Ok so I like that you're
making everyone go clockwise,
everyone's doing ten, alright.
- And then see how long they can balance
on their most dominant foot.
- Ok.
- There's a max of 60 seconds
and no shoes on.
- No shoes on, ok perfect.
You guys are good.
Ok so wingspan,
what are your units you
guys are measuring in?
Centimeters and you're
going tip to tip right?
And then what was the ability again?
- They'll take their shoes off,
try to touch their toes.
And then we'll measure the distance
from their finger tip to
the top of their foot.
- Ok, good.
In what units?
- Centimeters.
Did you say take shoes off or no?
- Yeah.
- Ok, cool.
You guys can start collecting data.
I'll come back to you.
Ok what do you guys got?
- [Voiceover] Same thing we got yesterday.
- Recap me.
- Hair color,
- You were hair color.
Why the hell don't you
have something else?
- [Voiceover] I don't know.
- Ok, so here's my question.
Cause I was thinking
about this last night.
You're gonna be asked to
make a scatter plot graph
of this data.
How would one go about
making a scatter plot
with hair color?
Ok, so you're gonna assign numbers,
numeric data to shades?
- [Voiceover] Zero to ten.
Or one to ten.
- One to ten.
- Yeah.
- One being the,
- lightest.
- [Voiceover] The lightest (laughing)
We should probably get
this straightened out
before we do it, right?
And then ten being the darkest.
Ok, before you start collecting it
can you just give me a
really quick specturm.
Draw a line out so I
could see where you're
getting your number data.
And then what is your characteristic?
That was your characteristic.
What is your ability?
- How many steps does it take you
to walk backwards seven feet?
- Ok, so we'll probably
do that in the hallway?
Does that sound fine?
Meter tapes are up there.
- [Voiceover] That's a lot of guys.
- So give me a real quick scale
then you guys can start.
- Ok.
(people talking over each other)
One and ten.
So that's blonde and really blonde.
And like really dark brown.
- So where would red fall in?
- Like me?
Like right there.
- So you're gonna make blonde one end.
The low end, are we all
in agreeance on that?
- [Voiceover] Yeah and
mine is like in the middle.
- [Voiceover] Ok, and
then the other far end's
gonna be the darkest brown?
- [Voiceover] Yeah.
- [Voiceover] Or black.
- Or black.
Are you gonna have everyone
taking data on that?
Or maybe one or two people
just consistently doing the hair color?
You know what I mean
so there's not a ton of variation?
(laughing)
- Measure their hand from first crease
to their middle finger.
And then hopping on one foot, right?
On your tiptoe?
Or no, balance, balance.
And then once your heel touch
into the ground, it's done.
And your hands can do whatever you want.
- [Voiceover] Ok, are
we shoe on, shoe off?
- Shoe off.
- [Voiceover] Shoe off and
is it right or left foot?
Right foot for everybody?
Ok.
Right foot shoe off on tiptoe
- Max two minutes.
- Max two minutes so the deciding factor
when to stop the stopwatch
is when their heel hits the ground.
- Or their other foot.
- [Voiceover] Or their other foot.
So it could be either or.
Okeydoke.
So just a kind of a
flashback to remind us.
This has been a couple daytime span here.
Our goal behind this is try to determine
what we can learn from a fossil.
So as we work through this unit
we're gonna start building
together pieces of information
that help us come up with
ideas about the past.
We've been specifically,
as I've said before
looking at one specific fossil,
foot fossil length, right?
The idea behind this is that
scientists put the pieces
of the puzzle together, we
start to get a clear image
of what's going on.
Again, our goal was to determine
if there's a relationship
between the characteristic you chose,
the ability you chose, and
a person's foot fossil.
I asked you last night
to plot up your data
for both characteristic and ability
and then if possible
draw a line of best fit.
That could be an indirect relationship,
a direct one, a trend, or no relationship.
What I'm gonna ask you to do for a minute,
talk to your neighbors.
Compare your data.
Make sure we're on the same page
in determining a relationship.
And then I'd like you to
come up and post your data.
It's gonna be a pretty simple
process to post your data.
So for example, if group one,
what was your characteristic?
- [Voiceover] For fossil length.
- Hand spans.
We're gonna put characteristic
on the left side
so they're gonna right hand span for us.
And then what type of relationship
did you guys see for that?
- [Voiceover] Direct.
- Direct, so all you're
gonna do is do this.
That's all we need to report.
Ok, in your lab packet,
you are going to find some little graphs.
You're gonna be asked to
record everyone's data.
I've also given you a supplementary sheet
cause you're gonna need more graphs.
I messed up and didn't tell you.
So what's gonna wind up happening
is all the graphs would appear on here.
You will also copy down into your packet
because as a whole you'll be
looking at everyone's data
and drawing conclusions, ok?
So take a minute to talk to your groups.
I'll come around and
give you some markers.
Determine what your
characteristic and ability
relationships are.
Post them on the board
and then we'll talk.
(students chattering)
- No
- Can you determine it?
- No.
- Cause they're not.
They're just kind of clustered.
It was like more not clustered.
- Ok, so we're gonna have a trend
fall in between where?
- I guess the trend
really is between 15 and
- What are we lacking?
- You know what, it was 12:30 last night,
Fossil, foot length, stride length.
- Ok, so we're having a
trend falling between,
what's our lowest?
- Our lowest is 12 and our highest is 23
but like the trend is between these ones.
(mumbling)
- Ok, I think that works.
So you're gonna give a horizontal line
on your graph up there.
Need help?
Ok, whatcha got?
- [Voiceover] Would you draw a line
for a trend?
- Yeah it would either
be vertical or horizontal
just like we did in the beginning.
So this person's kinda
like an outlier right
so let's just for argument's
sake take them out.
Does that help clear the data up at all?
You could say no, it's ok.
- They're all kind of
in the same foot length
but they all have different times.
- Ok, so we've got a pretty
wide range here, right?
For trend, we tend to see
more of a skinnier range.
So if you look at our options,
it's definitely not a direct
or indirect I would say
based on what you showed me, right?
Trend-wise,
it's kind of a wide range.
So what would we determine,
what's our other option?
- No relationship.
- Yeah, I would probably go.
So up there instead of drawing a line
just write no relation, ok?
Here's your marker.
- With this one,
cause it's kind of like a trend
or kind of just focused in this area.
But then there's also the increase
- Ok, so here's my question.
That's a good question.
When I look at this data, right?
If I had a pick, excluding this line,
if I had to pick where
someone with a foot fossil
over here would fall,
where would you pick?
Up here?
Why?
Yeah, it appears to be going this way.
So that would indicate
that you have a direct relationship.
It's kind of the easiest
way to look at it.
Ok group number one.
Hand span versus foot fossil
length and then jump height.
What kind of relationship
are we seeing here?
Direct, so the bigger the foot fossil,
the bigger the hand span.
So just to clarify hand span,
we're talking tip of
thumb to tip of finger.
Correct?
Why do we see that?
So I asked you guys last night
to jot down some ideas
in the conclusion section.
so you might want to turn
to that page, everyone,
cause you wanna gather some ideas here.
Why are we seeing this?
Why do you think we're
seeing that relationship?
What did you guys say?
- Because your hands and
feet are usually proportional
in size.
You're not gonna have a very large foot
and have very small hands.
Usually.
- [Voiceover] Ok.
So I have a question
for everyone in class.
I bought some new shoes and I like them.
Do you like them?
- [Voiceover] They're so big on you.
(clomping)
- They're a little loud.
Don't worry I won't wear
them on testing days.
They look good?
(students chattering)
What's the problem here?
They're like way too big,
like twenty sizes too big.
How do you know?
Why do you know that
my foot's not this big?
Yeah, it doesn't look
proportional to my body.
And exactly what Megan said,
bodies in general are proportional.
Now we go through some stages in our lives
where we have long, really lanky arms.
Or you might know someone
that has extremely long legs.
They're kind of fitting
outside that pattern.
But in general, bodies
are proportionate, right?
And so we can probably
makes some connections
to certain body characteristics
based on other body
characteristics, right?
Because of this idea
that we are proportioned.
You're not gonna see Shaquille O Neal
wearing a size three shoe.
He'll fall over.
He wouldn't be able to
support his own body.
Common sense applies here.
That's a good one.
Jump height.
So you said pretty much
everyone kind of fell
into one kind of area
but there's no indirect
or direct relationship.
Why do you think we saw that?
- Jump height is an ability versus,
- Ok, jump height is an ability,
you are correct.
- [Voiceover] It depends on muscles
versus structure.
- Ok, so it's depending more on muscle
as opposed to structure of your foot.
- I remember the class
like could already reach
so that played to our height
and the proportions of our body
and then in turn determined
how high I could jump in itself
so I guess with your foot,
depending on what size shoe you have,
that in turn kinda determines your height
because of the proportions of your body.
- By having them reach, guys.
What was your point?
When you set up your lab?
Cause I remember distinctly
talking to you guys
you said you're gonna
have them make a mark
and then they're gonna jump.
- [Voiceover] Well it's
so that the taller people
didn't just automatically jump higher
than everybody who was shorter than them.
Cause then it's already the distance,
like how high they can
actuall jump as part of
how tall they are.
- Ok.
So you're saying that
by measuring the height,
you factored that idea in.
So Mr. Bieber isn't totally outjumping
say Adrian who's a little bit shorter.
So you already kind of factored that in.
Why did we not see a connection though?
Megan said
jump height deals with
more muscle mass maybe?
opposed to foot.
- [Voiceover] Cause everybody
kind of jumped the same.
There wasn't any variation.
So it didn't really matter
what foot size you have.
- Ok.
So when you say jump the same you mean
achieve the same scores roughly?
They found the same general area
in that same general pattern?
- [Voiceover] That's why theres a trend.
It was all in just one spot.
- So in general when
we're looking at fossils,
would jump height be one
that we could solely predict then
based on the length of the foot fossil?
- [Voiceover] No.
- Probably not.
Which kind of makes sense anyway.
Group two.
Group two didn't get their data plotted
but let's take a peek.
They did foot fossil length and height.
If you were to make an assumption,
if there was a relationship,
what would you all assume
would be the relationship?
Direct, why direct?
- [Voiceover] Cause it's proportional.
- Bingo, bodies are proportional.
You're gonna see that pattern
as we work through this.
Proportional, ok?
Average stride.
- [Voiceover] We didn't really get a graph
but it didn't look very direct.
It was a little more indirect.
- More indirect?
- [Voiceover] I think so.
- Like this?
So you're saying longer?
- No, no.
Like there wasn't really a pattern.
- Oh so your'e saying no relationship?
- Yeah.
- Does that make sense?
Alana says no.
I saw this.
Why?
- Well just based on
the proportional idea,
if your height and hand
span is proportional
to your foot length
then your legs then,
the length of your legs
are also proportional to your foot lenghts
and the length of your stride
based on the length of your legs.
- So you're arguing that
you think we should see
what kind of relationship?
- [Voiceover] I think, a direct.
- You would say direct.
Claire and then Barrett.
- Well, cause we had the same thing
but a little bit different.
And, well, backwards.
It couldn't really be that accurate
because it wasn't a very long distance.
and people had different ideas of walking.
Some people were trying
to take larger steps
or being more careful or walking slower.
It wasn't just like an average.
- So you are saying based on the idea
of body proportions
that we should see a direct.
- But you're saying, you agree
that we should see direct
- [Voiceover] No we
should see an indirect.
- An indirect?
Longer leg, shorter strides?
Direct.
Longer legs, longer strides.
But you're arguing that the way maybe
that the experiment was set up
didn't lend itself to collect proper data?
- [Voiceover] Yeah.
- Ok, good point.
- I think it was also just,
I was asked just to
walk like I normally do
and I don't take very long strides.
I kind of walk really slow
so my strides are very small
when I just normally walk.
- Ok so you almost felt
it was kinda awkward
like how am I supposed to walk.
So maybe we could have captured it
in a different manner.
We could have designed the experiment
if you're already walking
and then you walk past the line
and maybe keep carrying
through that stride.
- I think no relationship is accurate
because my stride length I would assume
is based on how long my legs are.
I have very long legs
but everybody knows I have a small foot.
I mean I'm still proportional
like I'm normal sized
but my legs are just a lot
longer than anything else.
- Ok so you're kinda arguing that maybe
you're not always going to fall
into every part of your body
being specifically proportional.
- There was a lot where some people
with kinda smaller feet had
relatively longer strides
and some people with big
feet had smaller strides.
It was kind of just all over the place.
- Ok.
So what are we labeling this?
Direct, question mark,
no relationship, question mark.
- [Voiceover] If we're basing
it on the data that they had,
I'd say no relationship.
- Ok, if we're basing it on the data,
even though we didn't plot it.
Looking at their actual data,
we would say no relationship.
Could there be a point
where we could argue
that we might potentially
see a direct relationship?
Yes.
So for our data collection,
we'll leave no relationship.
But keeping in mind that very valid point
that if' you're gonna have longer feet,
more than likely you have longer legs.
More than likely you're
gonna take longer strides.
But inherent as Claire said
in the kind of setup of the experiment,
that maybe that didn't shine through.
Group three.
Hair color versus foot fossil length.
No relationship.
Is this shocking to anyone?
- Yes.
Even though they had
a great numeric scale?
Why?
Why no relationship Bubs?
- [Voiceover] I didn't have
anything to do with it.
- [Voiceover] It's like a gene base.
- Hair color is determined by
- Your DNA.
- Does your DNA determine
your foot length?
- [Voiceover] Yes it does.
- [Voiceover] But not the same gene.
- Ok but not the same gene.
Ok, now you're getting very technical,
I appreciate that.
Yes sir.
- I think its partially
because (murmuring)
- Would you think that
there would be a connection?
Like smaller foot, lighter hair?
- [Voiceover] Well go on
for like racial background
like your ethnicity,
Some ethnic groups are generally taller
and have bigger feet than the others.
- Ok so maybe you're
arguing the sample size?
The idea that we were to survey globally,
maybe we could see
certain ethnic backgrounds
that tend to be taller,
would have different,
I could see that.
Yeah.
- Well, I think it has
nothing to do with it
because I'm six feet tall
and Franco's under five feet
and we both have dark hair.
So obviously.
- [Voiceover] Yeah it's
got nothing to do with it.
- Ok so on face value,
looking at hair color.
Would we say that foot fossil length
would be a good indicator of hair color?
- [students] No.
- Ok, I would agree.
There's no connection there.
No connection.
My question though, is.
There are organisms
that lived in the past.
And we have very, I would say.
We have certain ideas about
what their coloring was like.
How would we come up with that, then?
How would scientists
come up with that idea?
Of the coloring of certain organisms?
Caroline.
- Well if you say that lizards would be,
or dinosaurs would be green,
it would help them blend
into their environment
so you would assume it would be good then
to be green but you don't know for sure.
- So you're thinking
evolutionary connection.
It'll be beneficial for
them to be able to blend
in their environment,
- [Voiceover] Yeah.
- Yes Claire.
- I think you also said a few days ago.
About how you're supposed to assume
everything in the past
works how it does now.
So if you see some type
of reptile in the past
it probably looks something
like a reptile now.
- Ok, so again you're doing
that evolutionary connection
to modern day relatives saying
well if they appear to be this color,
possibly due to some benefit,
we can assume in the past.
Good, nice job.