- That they need to make
some sort of a change.
- [Male Student] Like the turning point?
- Like there's a turning point.
There's some kind of
change that needs to occur.
Do you guys think that most people
take that opportunity and then change?
- [Students] No.
- I think some no.
In Fahrenheit 451, how some people
were assuming that Mildred already knew,
but she just didn't want to not like accept it
but not be part of it.
She didn't want to be part of the change,
she just wanted to be
in tune with society.
- She never gave herself an opportunity
to have any kind of turning point.
[students chuckling]
- Even when she had the
opportunity, she didn't.
- Right.
- [Male Student] I think emotion plays
a big role in that, too, because Faber
let fear get in the way
of him doing something,
so he basically created
that little earpiece thing,
so that somebody else could do it for him,
and he could watch over somebody
that's actually doing it.
- [Male Student] Another
person who's carrying
the shoes to go through the
turning point is Beatty,
because although he had
all of the knowledge,
much more knowledge than Montag had
about society and everything,
he chose not to go against it
because he believed that if he does it,
then what's the point, if he's not going
to gain anything out of it.
- [Female Student] Do you think also
because he has all that knowledge,
he wants to use it to have power?
Since he knows all that,
he wants to manipulate,
keep them in control, keep
them in check and stuff.
- [Male Student] No, I don't think it's
that he wants power, I
mean, it's that he's seen
the bad side of things,
and, like all humans,
you don't like to go through something
when it has lots of negativity in it.
With education, he knows it's good
because it helps you
think outside of the box,
and everything,
but it's bad also because then you have
two countering opinions on everything.
Then you realize that there's genocides,
there's slavery, there's wars,
there's too much negativity.
- [Female Student] The
government also doesn't want
that because it probably gives
them ideas of where to go.
The more information they know,
the more possible ways they
can use it against them.
- [Male Student] I like what you said
about the government
doing that kind of stuff,
because I guess they see it as a way
of knowledge makes people--
- [Female Student] Vulnerable.
- [Male Student] Vulnerable.
It's like if the people
were the government's subordinates,
so it's not the government's
people who they're protecting,
it's pretty much who
they're in control of.
- [Female Student] I kind
of want to share my opinion
on the turning point
thing, like in Harrison,
and bridge around again.
You get to see the emotion, or what George
has to go through, but
yet he doesn't do anything
about it; Harrison does.
It says right here, "His
thoughts fled and panicked
like bandits from a burglar alarm."
It's showing you what he has to go through
for his thoughts to be
taken out of his head, or whatever
but Harrison is the one doing the actions.
He's the one that wants to
go against the government,
and George isn't.
- [Male Student] So, do you
think their relationship
and the correlation of George and Harrison
is just like Montag and Faber's,
where Faber doesn't want to do anything,
because he didn't want to
go to jail in the South?
George doesn't want to go to jail
because he doesn't want
to lighten his own way
because he would get,
what was it, seven years?
- [Female Student] Yeah.
- For each sled that he takes out.
And Harrison is actually doing stuff.
And Montag isn't doing stuff.
So, do you think that
you need that person,
the one behind the scenes doing the stuff,
and then a person that's
actually doing it,
or do you just mean people that actually
already in action to a bill?
- I think that you need
people who are (inaudible)
I think that you need
but I think that it's
easier to (inaudible)
so I think that way is better.
So you don't get in trouble (inaudible)
(students laughing)
- (male student) I think
the people that have
(inaudibleble), the people in the
front lines are always useful.
They are easier to camoflauge (inaudible)
They are the ones with the real plans.
These people in the
front don't usually come
up with them.
- Yeah, but you have the plans and then you
don't do it.
but what does it matter
that you have the plan
and you don't know how to use it?
- Well, not every body's that brave.
(students talking)
- That's why you need to...
- (male student) I think
people need the support system,
like Faber was Montag's support system.
- He had a plan (inaudible)
(inaudible)
(students laughing)
- (female student) Don't
let him tell you he sees,
walk away, walk away.
(students laughing)
- (teacher) I guess, here's my question.
So, in looking at our essay question
for our final exam tomorrow,
I want you to think... our question is,
to what extent should citizens comply
with unfair laws, right,
created by government?
I know I'm asking you to
respond with to what extent,
should citizens comply
with these unfair laws?
But we're also talking about
so who should act, right?
So who should be the one to act out,
to lead, to go against the government?
Because we're looking at characters who
possess the capacity to act out.
We're looking at people
who have knowledge,
who have strength, who are talented.
But they're not leaders.
And we're also looking
at people who may not
have those qualities,
they have the potential
to have those qualities,
but need a little bit
of encouragement and a
little bit of a push.
So when we say to what extent
should citizens comply,
do you guys think that
citizens applies to everybody?
Or is it limited to a
group of people who are
willing to make those sacrifices?
Do you even think that's
fair that it's a small
group of people who make
the sacrifice for the whole?
I want you to think about
any types of current
or historical events where
we've seen a group of people,
whether it is a whole group,
or just a couple of people
who take charge, who
lead and impact change.
Are there any examples that
you can connect to that?
Do you think that that's
even fair for everyone
to benefit from the sacrifice
of a small group of people?
- (male student) I see it as
a way... every time there's
a change, or a law, or
something that affects
a certain group of people,
it's never really based on
the whole group of people.
Like all citizens. It's more of a target,
and when a certain group
is attacked or targeted,
it makes others not really...
I don't want to say care,
but it doesn't really matter
to them because they're
not the ones that are experiencing
the negativity of that.
Or, yeah... it's just basically
it's that group of people
who have to, I guess,
express their ideas and
it may be scary for some
people to go along with it
and actually carry out
what they think is right,
but I think it's necessary for a unit.
You probably need that one person who
spreads the message, and then
I think it is very important
for other groups of
people to go along with it
because you never know when
it's going to be your turn.
- (teacher) So, here's my
question because on your
AP exam, on your final
exam, for your argumentative
essays, you have to be able
to generate your own examples.
So, I know Omar you've
got a very clear idea,
but does any body have
a historical reference
or a current event that
we can tie that idea
to something specific, and
that's what you can discuss.
Let's see if we have any
ideas here about historical
or current events that we
could really provide as really
concrete examples that we could look at
because you want to get specific.
You want to say, "hey, let's
look at this specific example,
where this actually happened."
Any thoughts on that?
- (male student) Anything with slavery,
with Frederick Douglass and
the abolitionists in the north.
They really felt the need that slavery was
needing to be abolished
and I guess that's where
civil disobedience comes from,
is the abolishment of slavery.
Well, the need to abolish slavery.
That it really wasn't
really blacks or Africans,
or whatever you called them back then.
Wanting to be set free
was people that weren't
even affected by slavery that
wanted them to be set free.
And I think that's more
important, and more
appeals to your emotion
because these people
have no tie to slavery.
They're not benefiting,
they're not getting negative from it,
so it's like you really
think that it's wrong
when someone else is not
affected by the situation.
It's saying that it's wrong.
- (male student) I want to
connect to what you just said
about to the idea of the
mental slavery that's going
on right now
because I guess maybe not
a lot of you are aware,
but there's... I don't know
if you guys heard something
about the green eye? That
recently... that's in the past.
And I think that's very
important because that affects me
in a way because many
people wanna go to college
but I guess the idea of going to college
and getting your degree,
but then not excelling in
what you are supposed to be excelling in.
That kind of stops them
and discourages them
from... to keep going.
So I guess that idea is... I don't know,
it's kind of opressive
because they're trying
to maintain you in that little...
it's just marginalizing you and yeah,
I think it needs more support.
- (teacher) So I want you
to think about that example
because there were a
lot of protests, right?
People were really protesting that,
and there were a lot of
these laws that people
were standing against, right?
And when we look at the questions,
to what extent should we
comply with unfair laws?
If that is an unfair piece of legislation,
to what extent do you
then choose to protest?
How far would you be willing to take it?
Because we talked about this,
this line between pushing your protest
and your form of rebellion.
Like look at Harrison, right?
Dancing on stage as a ballerina.
Doesn't really seem all that tough, right?
But, for him, he was
taking a big stance, right?
Not about borderline violence, right?
I want you to look at what Thoreau did.
He didn't pay his taxes.
He wanted to go to jail.
He was happy there.
He was like, "don't bail me out."
Had nothing to do with violence, right?
You hear a lot of people
protesting, you know.
Issues regarding the DREAM Act,
but to what extent should
they comply with the laws?
Do you use violence?
Do you even take it there?
Do you use more creative
forms of protesting?
I want you to consider
how far do you take it?
How far do you show your protest?
What is acceptable, and
where do you draw the line?
(students answer together)
Good reaction, lots of reaction.
Let's hear from people
we haven't heard from.
I want you to go back and think about your
goals that you set.
I'm hoping those of you
that are a little bit
quieter in our discussions,
chose goals that
might push you to speak up.
So let's hear from a few
folks that we haven't
heard from yet and share the air time.
Any volunteer? Jesus, what do you think?
- (Jesus) Like Omar
said, like the DREAM Act,
has an ill affect on a lot of people.
It doesn't really affect
me, but I know a lot
of friends that it is affecting.
It's not really fair that
it really didn't pass,
but when we want to try to push something,
like Julian said for
slavery, it didn't really
take... it took such a long
time for them to really
get the rights. There was the abolishment,
there was Frederick
Douglass during that time.
But as time went, then
came Martin Luther King,
who was the center person who started the
really big move for African Americans
to realize their own rights.
He lead the protests,
marches... if you gather
groups of people over time...
if you speak up with your
voice people will hear.
Even people like African
Americans, they came
and rallied to listen to the
idea that everyone being equal.
There should be rights and everyone...
no matter what color you are.
So for Latinos like us,
for the (inaudible),
it's such a short time because we just
started also trying to pass our rights,
but the dream that was once dead,
but even though it didn't pass,
people should not be put down,
like, "Aw, it didn't pass."
So they'll just forget you
got to stand back right up
and get more people and
to continue to pass on
for your rights, cause
if we stay together,
anything can happen...
If we stay together as
one, something will happen.
- (teacher) I am hearing
two things and we'll get
back to Stephanie really
quickly I think she's just
itching to get in this conversation.
I'm hearing two things.
One, that it takes a
collective group effort.
It's not just one person,
but it needs to be many people involved.
As many people involved
And I'm also hearing that
it takes a lot of time.
So those are a couple of
factors that play in to
going against unfair laws.
- (male student) That's
kind of like right now,
that it's kind of more
modern because (inaudible).
- (teacher) You think so?
- (students) no, no, no.
- (teacher) I want you take
this idea that Omar brought,
this idea of mental slavery of oppression,
of our intellect, our intelligence.
Is that something that
you think is just recent?
Is that something that's
been happening over time?
I want you to think about that and see...
we might isolate one part of the problem,
but I want you to think
on a broader scale.
Is it really just one isolated event,
or is this one in a stream of events?
Stephanie, you had
something that you were...
- (Stephanie) Yeah, all of
them were in the governement,
and I was thinking of the movie, "Milk".
How they have to fight for
the rights for equality
for homosexuals and what he does is
he runs for office in California,
and to be heard, which is kind of like
civil disobedience in a way.
But he does it in a bigger
way for them to be heard.
One part in the movie
that I'll always remember,
is when a guy in a wheelchair
calls him to tell him
that he's gay and all of that.
But he just hangs up, but
yet he does it for him,
most likely because he wants
people like that to be heard.
And that's kind of what my connection is.
- (female student) I think
another historical event
besides the slavery and what
you just said
is the nine eleven.
I think it's the short-term one.
It took actually really quick...
(inaudible)
the terrorists going up there.
It just took one simple idea to tell them,
"Oh, let's just go..."