- Spanish, and you would know if,
I mean, you would know what they're saying
because you learn English, and you talk,
you learn English and you
know how to talk Spanish.
- [Girl with headband] I
agree with you, because like,
because like if they
when you said that they had
to read, write, and speak English,
like they put something that,
they put something that's
English on your paper,
you'd probably understand it more,
so that's why I agree with you.
- [Boy] But when they
fill out the application,
what if the application didn't (mumbles)
- Well,
- [Girl with headband] The application is
about like where you're from,
why are you coming here for,
like they want to know a lot
of information about you.
- [Boy] I think we should,
I think we should keep it at one,
because if you fill out the application,
you'll know more about people,
and their birthday and stuff,
like and then they usually
bring them a present, (mumbles)
- Okay, so it's important
to know about somebody.
Now, the citizenship board might not go
to their birthday party,
but it is important to know
when their birthday is, right?
Okay, what were you saying, Ariel?
- I think he must fill
out an application,
because...
- [Girl with glasses] I think you should
fill out an application
so you can, so if you come to America,
you can...
If you come to America,
they'll know when your birthday,
where did you come from and stuff.
- [Teacher] Yeah, it's important to have
that information.
Why do you think we need to
know where they came from?
- [Girl with headband]
Because I think they wanted
to know where they came from,
because like if they came from a bad city,
and they want to come to
like a good city, and--
- A city or a country?
- A country.
- A country, okay.
- If they came from a bad country,
and they wanted to join a good country,
then you want to see like,
they want to see like if
they got like (mumbles)
- [Teacher] If they were bad,
like where they came from, that would be,
yeah, they'd have to know that.
- I think I would be (mumbles) because
like when they,
like different countries
have different holidays,
so when they be out,
like they be out celebrating,
then nobody won't think nothing's
wrong with it, because
they're celebrating,
and they don't know that on this day,
that's when they're
celebrating their country.
- I didn't even think about that.
We need to know about their culture,
so that we can let them celebrate.
That's important, too.
Great conversation.
So we're gonna keep that one
or get rid of it?
- We're gonna keep it.
- Okay.
So let's move onto the next step
and see what you think about the next one.
- That you have to live
in the US, United States,
for five years.
- [Girl with headband]
I don't believe that you
have to live in the United
States for five years,
because like if you're like,
I'm (mumbles) five years,
if you're married, you're going to have
to live for three years,
but then like the reason why
you should live in it five years,
because like you could get used
to the country and everything,
that's what I think.
- [Girl with glasses] I
think that you should live
in America for five years
if you come from somewhere else,
because like some people,
they come here,
and they see that they don't like it,
and they try to move back
to where they came from,
and when they try to move back,
somebody already took
their house or something,
and if they go, they ain't gonna have
no money to come back
because they're just
gonna be outside homeless.
- I think there will be some changes
to live in the US.
Two years, because if you're real old,
if you're old,
then they say that you
might die in a couple years,
then if you're staying here,
if you have to stay
here to become a citizen
for five years,
then it takes longer,
then you wouldn't get the chances
to make choices before you die.
- [Girl with braids] I
think you should change,
you have to live in the US, United States,
for five years, because what if
if the house is dirty, and it's not clean?
Like if it's like the tub
still got stains in it
(mumbles)
- [Teacher] Explain that
a little bit more to me.
So you said that you would change it
to how many years?
- [Girl with braids] To one year.
- To one year,
becase if you got in a house
that was dirty, you might want to do what?
- [Girl with braids]
If the walls was still
had stains on it--
- Well what would you want to do then?
- Move.
- Okay, where would you move?
Still in the United States,
or back to your country?
- [Girl with braids] Still
in the United States.
- Okay, so you would still be there,
so would you want to just stay,
even though you
move from place to place--
- [Girl with braids] I will--
- Do you think you would
change the number of years
they're gonna be in the United States,
or just not make them
stay in the same place?
- Not make them stay in the same place.
- Okay, so we need to make
sure that Ariel knows,
do we have to stay in the
same place for all five years?
- No, not really.
- No, okay.
- [Girl with glasses] I think that if they
I think that they should
give them at least one year
to figure out if they
want to stay in that home
or go back to where they used to live.
So I mean,
if they don't like it on the first day,
so they won't have to go back again,
come back to see,
or come back, somebody else at your house.
At your old house.
- [Girl with headband]
I disagree with you,
and I agree with you.
The reason why I disagree with you,
because they said still living three years
just like if you're married,
and I agree with you, because like
when you said that they
come from the first place,
I mean, the first day
they may not like it,
and they could probably go
back where they came from,
that's why I disagree and agree with you.
- [Boy] Okay, I think we should change it
so if they look at their choice
to go back to their home country
for like two months,
because then they'll miss
their family members,
then like when a couple
days in their country,
and nobody was doing it in America,
then they could just go
back to their country
for like a month or something.
- [Teacher] So maybe
you guys need to discuss
how many years they should
stay here in America,
and maybe if they could,
how long they could go
to visit their relatives
in other countries.
Although I think those
are all good
things to keep discussing.
So maybe make that
decision on how many years,
and then move onto the next one
and I'll come back and see you.
- [Girl with white beads] Here, but you
you trying to become a citizen here,
but you like want to,
like you're trying to vote,
like say if you lived in Germany,
you're trying to go back to Germany.
You can't, that's not being loyal
to the US, because you're
trying to become a citizen
to the US, and you're trying to go back,
if you was living in Germany,
you're trying to go back to Germany.
What do you think, guys?
- Well, (mumbles) because they have
to want to say that, A, if you don't,
then they won't have to send you back,
because you have to be community and jobs
so they can get you jobs
and what to do and--
- [Brittany] I think that
we should keep the rule,
because say if your old country
got in a war,
you would say you tried to take up them,
and you're already trying to become
a citizen of the USA,
and you take up for your old country,
that makes you not become a citizen.
- That don't mean if you're born
in your like regular country,
that don't mean like you can go back,
go back and forth and take up for them,
and then when we're having a war,
you want to take up for us,
you can't do that.
You can't like,
if you grew up in Germany,
you can't take up for Germany,
because you'e trying to be
a citizen in the US now.
You can't take up for Germany,
even though you were born there.
You got to take up for the US.
- [Teacher] Do you think that's
hard for someone who
came to the United States
to forget about their old country?
Woudl that be difficult?
- [Girl with white beads] Yeah.
In my opinion, I think
that'd be difficullt
because like with me,
I can make a connection because
when I went, when I had,
when I used to live with my grandma,
me and my momma, we used to live
with my grandma,
and I couldn't forget about the things
that I did at my grandma's house,
so my grandma and my cousins,
but we still were around,
but I couldn't stop,
I couldn't forget about
what the fun things
that we did.
- [Teacher] Yeah, (mumbles)
- [Adune] So what should we put here?
- [Girl with white beads]
Well, I think we should
keep it, because like
you can't go back to your like
regular country to do like,
like you can't fight for the army,
the army, they're trying to stay here
to protect us, and you're already trying
to become a citizen for the US.
You can't like go back to Germany.
- [Adune] Then we should
keep that, because then
so we should
learn how to be nice?
I don't know.
- [Girl with white beads]
Like, we could put,
so that if like you grew up in Germany,
you can't fight for Germany.
So we're gonna put that.
- [Adune] Okay.
- [Teacher] You have to be true to the US.
- Be true to the US.
- [Teacher] How about the next one
that says, "Have good moral character."
Is that one that you would keep
or get rid of?
- [Girl with white beads] Get rid of.
In my opinion, I'd get rid of that,
because people,
like that's like,
that's like having like you
gotta be like nice to people.
Some people, they can't take it.
Like, they can't take that,
they can't like,
people, like I can make
a connection because
my cousin, she got like ups and downs,
because when people, they just like
irritate her, and they be aggravating her,
she can't take it no more, she just like,
she just gotta get mad and stuff.
Like people, they can't take having
a moral character.
Like my cousin, she can't do that
because people, they be
like bullying her and stuff,
and she can't like keep like,
she can't keep on standing right there
and people keep on bullying her.
- [Adune] Brittany, do you think
we should keep it or leave it?
- [Brittany] I think we should,
I think we should get rid of it.
When I was in the suburbs
with my godmother,
she said that my godbrother
was getting picked on
in school by a bully,
and he just felt like beating him up.
What do you think, Adune?
- Well, keep it, because like,
why would you let some (mumbles)
people get away with most of that stuff?
You're just gonna let them
keep doing the same thing?
And without the rule?
Without that rule, everybody,
people would just keep
getting beat (mumbles)
- [Teacher] So what I
hear all of you saying
is that you don't want
people to get beaten,
but you also said that
sometimes it's hard to control your anger,
so you can't, you're not always
a good person all the time.
Sometimes you make bad choices.
Do you think we could maybe
change that rule so that
everybody would be happy with it?
- [Girl with white beads]
Yes, I think we should
change it to like, like,
when you're like around like older people,
like elder, like older people,
and like they're real old,
you can like,
like you can show like good
moral character around them,
but then when they like go and stuff,
like when they're not gone,
like when we was talking about immigrants
on the, like they was on the boats,
you don't know what type
of people is on the boats.
It can be like elder
people, you never know.
Like you can have good
moral character around them,
but like when you like,
when you're like around your mother,
don't she want you to respect you?
Don't she want you to respect her?
- [Adune] But, we should change the rule
to like sometimes people can just like
have a chance to get some people back
that really did something
really bad to them,
or caused them to get hurt or something,
so we should change the rule
to like, it's kind of
like hard for a name,
but we should think about it.
- [Girl with white beads] I think,
I have a cause and effect
for a good moral character.
That's why they have like,
if you have to fill out an application,
that's why they're trying to like,
that's why they're trying to
like fill out an application
to see if you got good moral character,
or if you're cra--