- What I'm going to do is
we are going to use these projects
to help students at our school.
Mrs. Ess's class is not the only class
that has had problems with students
accidentally plagiarizing.
And that was the original reason that you
guys came here today: because somebody in
another class had plagiarized
something accidentally
in Mrs. Ess's class.
Your projects today are going to be used
in other classrooms.
So we're going to have a contest.
We're going to pick
the 5 best Powerpoints,
and we're going to send
them out to other classrooms
to help students learn why
they shouldn't plagiarize.
Now some of you are already
experts at Powerpoint.
We're not learning how to
do Powerpoint right now.
A lot of you already know how to summarize
because you learned to
summarize in Mrs. Ess's class.
So you have that experience.
There was a disconnect where you didn't
put the two together.
So what we're doing right
now is we're saying,
okay, I know how to summarize;
now I know how to avoid plagiarism.
So let's start working right now.
You have your rubric.
Look at your rubric.
If you have a question, raise your hand
and I'll come and explain it.
And we're going to start
right this very second.
So go ahead and get into
Powerpoint, and do your powerpoint.
If you're going to be
doing something different,
like making a newspaper, a
brochure, or maybe a podcast
then you're going to
start working on that.
And I am just going to
walk around you guys.
Our focus is plagiarism, and
the way we avoid plagiarism
is through focusing on summarizing.
So you can refer back to your notes.
Remember you used your Cornell notes
the other day when you were here
and we went online, and you
took a summarization quiz
and tutoring session? I'll
be right there in a second.
Yes?
I'm sorry?
(inaudible whispering)
Okay, David?
Yes, yes absolutely.
(inaudible whispering)
I'm sorry, I'll be back
to you in a moment.
Yes?
- (inaudible question)
- I think that would be a great idea.
We're focusing on
plagiarism and we've learned
about how summarization is
one of the ways to avoid it.
Right?
Okay. I'm sorry.
Sure. Very good.
Oh, great, you're back up.
Okay, tissues are behind the globe.
Can you go get one for me?
Okay, have you been helped?
You have to know how to spell it.
Right over there on the board.
(inaudible speaking)
How's it going Cathy?
- Pretty much.
- Take off the S.
I like that though. It was good.
You need some help Mr. Phillip?
- No thank you.
- You're fine?
What you're doing is looking through here
at all the requirements.
So when you use your creativity
to put this together,
And I, yes?
- what does this word mean?
- Okay. So, multimedia
basically means that
it could be either
Powerpoint or a podcast.
So you need all of these
to get the highest grade.
So if you come up with
something additional,
you're going to get a higher grade.
This part you did here is basically
your method of memorization
which would be number 3.
How is it going?
- Pretty good.
- Now remember if you're
taking a definition
of plagiarism from a website,
then you really need to
say where you got that.
There's a way of doing that.
You're going to state where you got that,
and when it was, yes?
- (inaudible question)
- That's okay. You're going
to use your own words.
It's interesting how
different all of these look.
Yes, you can. You definitely can.
I also have some books
available. They're hiding.
You could, Eric, use this book too.
I've got you marked right here.
Would anyone else like a dictionary?
You can get an online definition too.
Okay I've got them marked. You
can find it easily that way.
- Can we use our paper to take notes?
- Yes, of course you can.
If that would help you, Cathy.
Have you gotten to Powerpoint yet?
No?
Do you know how to do that?
Oh, good.
Okay, David. I'm sorry.
I've got it in this book too.
(inaudible mumbling)
Is that your second slide
or your first slide?
- My first.
- Okay.
Okay, like I said before,
the purpose of doing
this is to try to help
other students in our school.
And a lot of you already know ways
of avoiding plagiarism.
Maybe you were even aware
that you were plagiarizing.
And we've been focusing on summarizing.
Of course, there's
another way you can do it.
Paraphrasing is a little bit harder,
but we're focusing on summarizing.
And besides summarizing,
another thing that you can do,
with summarizing, is still giving credit
to where it came from.
Yes?
Hang on.