(No Audio)
- [Teacher] How old are you?
- [Blake] Five years old! (speaks with
noticeable speech impairment)
- [Teacher] Five years old!
Blake, is this a bear?
- [Blake] Yes
- [Teacher] Yes
Is this a bear?
- [Blake] Yeah
- [Teacher] Yes
Is this a bear?
- [Blake] No
- [Teacher] No, very nice!
Is this a fire truck?
- [Blake] No
- [Teacher] No
Is this a penguin?
- [Blake] Yes
- [Teacher] Yes
What's your name?
- [Blake] Blake Walker
- [Teacher] Blake Walker
Give me eyes.
Awesome!
Where's your eyes?
Where's Blake's eyes?
- [Blake] Here's the eyes
- [Teacher] Eyes. Good job. Eyes.
Where's eyes?
- [Blake] Eyes
- [Teacher] Very good. Eyes.
Where's Blake's eyes?
- [Blake] That's the eyes.
- [Teacher] Eyes, very good.
How old are you?
- [Blake] Five years old.
- [Teacher] Five years old.
Do you want the elephant?
- [Blake] No
- [Teacher] You want the ball?
- [Teacher] You want the book?
- [Blake] No
- [Teacher] Want the fire truck?
- [Blake] Yes! Vroom! Vroom!
(timer beeps)
- [Teacher] Oh, my turn fire truck.
Excuse me.
(recording of "Old
MacDonald" plays briefly)
(Teacher revs toy train's wheels)
- [Blake] I train please?
I play train please? I play train?
I play train please?
- [Teacher] Train!
My turn train. Thank you.
(Blake makes verbal noises to himself)
(sounds of the Teacher
rolling the train on the shelf)
- [Blake] I play train.
- [Teacher] Choo-choo!
(toy train makes noises)
(Blake makes excited noises)
- [Blake] I play with train please?
- [Teacher] Train.
- [Blake] Choo-choo!
(women quietly discuss between themselves)
(toy train noises in the background)
- [Teacher] My turn train. Thank you.
(Blake contentedly mumbles to himself)
(toy train noises in the background)
- [Blake] I play train please?
I play train please?
- [Teacher] Train.
(Blake quietly talks to himself
while playing with train)
- [Brunette Woman] My turn!
(Blake mumbles disappointedly)
- I play train please?
- [Teacher] Blake!
(Teacher makes knocking noise on table)
- [Blake] I play train. All mine.
- [Blake] I play please? I play?
I play train? I play train please?
- [Brunette Woman] Train!
(Blake talks to himself
animatedly while playing)
[Brunette Woman] He's
traveling with the whole thing.
- [Brunette Woman] He is at least waiting
until he gets closer before he starts.
- [Teacher] Uh-huh.
He's not repeating.
(Blake continues to happily
make noises while playing)
- [Brunette Woman] My turn.
(Blake mumbles disappointedly)
- [Blake] I fire truck? I play
with fire truck please?
I play fire? I fire.
I play with fire truck please?
- [Brunette Woman] Fire truck!
(toy fire truck makes
alarm and siren noises)
- [Brunette Woman] My turn!
- I fifth please? I fifth please?
I play the please?
- [Teacher] Fish?
- [Blake] Fish please?
- [Teacher] Fish.
Uh-oh!
Fish broken. Bye-bye, fish.
- [Teacher] Let me see.
(Teacher turns something on with a click)
Now see.
Alright!
See I knew they worked.
- [Brunette Woman] All done fish!
- [Blake] Bye fish.
- [Brunette Woman] Right,
bye fish. All done fish.
(Blakes makes excited noises)
- [Blake] I fish please?
I play. I play (mumbles).
- [Teacher] Fish.
- [Blake] Please? Fish.
- [Teacher] All done fish.
All done fish.
- [Blake] Bye fish!
(Blake makes excited noises)
- [Blake] I play. I play fish please?
- [Teacher] Yellow fish.
Orange fish.
All done fish.
Done fish. Bye-bye fish.
(Blake makes excited noises)
- [Blake] I play. I play with fish?
I play with fish?
I play fish please?
- [Teacher] Fish.
(Blake talks animatedly to himself)
- [Teacher] Can you count fish?
- [Blake and Teacher
together] one, two, three, four
- [Teacher] Fish all done.
Bye fish.
(Blake makes excited noises)
(toy train makes noise)
- [Blake] I play fish.