- Okay. What objects or pictures do you
see?
- I see a flag.
- A flag.
- [together] A sign.
- The sun.
- And the letters.
- A sign. Yeah.
- And the birds.
- There are birds over here.
- People carrying bags.
- Okay, people carrying bags.
- There's a ship.
- A ship.
- The ladies all have hats.
- Okay. The ladies all have hats on. They
look like they're dressed to go somewhere,
right?
- [together] Yeah.
- Good. All right.
- Do you want us to write it in here?
- You can copy it. I have the words
spelled up here. We have Uncle Sam. We
have a boat.
- Do you want us to write it?
- I'm going to have it up here. Yeah.
- Oh.
- We have a flag.
- We have this thing. What does this thing
look like?
- Kind of like a witch.
- No. No.
- Yeah. It looks kind of like a witch.
Something scary anyway, right?
- [together] Yeah.
- Broccoli.
- It looks like broccoli? Okay. Yeah, it
does. It's kind of fluffy on top. I agree.
- All right.
- There are people.
- We've got people. We've got birds.
- [inaudible]
- Mm-hmm. So here are our objects. Uncle
Sam, boat, American flag. I wrote scary
devil-looking thing. If you want to put
witch-looking thing, that's fine.
- I'm gonna put both.
- Traveling people and birds.
- [inaudible]
- I put enough blanks for a few objects,
but feel free to add more than the number
of lines I wrote.
All right. Okay. Which of the objects--
whoops. Okay. Which of the objects do you
see could be symbols?
- [together] The flag.
- All right. This is what I want you to
do. Stop. Turn to the person beside you.
Beside you, beside you, beside you. See if
you can think of-- you already said flag.
That's a perfect example. It is one of
them. I think four of these are symbols.
Not every object is going to be a symbol.
So turn and see if you and your partner
can come up with any more.
[Background Chatter]
- [inaudible]
- Each pair can be that.
- Two different. Yeah.
- Oh.
[Background Chatter]
- All right. What did we come up with?
- We came up with the top of his hat
thing. It's the same as the flag.
- It looks exactly like the flag, okay? So
what could Uncle Sam be a symbol of?
- [together] U.S.
- Of the United States. Good.
- Did you come up with one?
- The traveling people.
- The traveling people? What do you think
they symbolize?
- They're from other countries.
- Yeah. They symbolize people from other
countries. Good. Did you come up with one?
- The scary devil-looking thing.
- Okay. What is that?
- It's clouds in the sky?
- Okay. It looks like clouds, but why did
the artist draw the clouds as a
scary-looking thing?
- To get them out?
- To scare them?
- Or maybe it's the rain. They're scared
of storms.
- Okay. Who is the devil-looking thing?
Who is he going after?
- [together] The people.
- The people. What are the people running
away from?
- From their other countries.
- From their other countries. So what
could the cloud be a symbol of?
- Bad things.
- Immigrants?
- Yeah. They're the immigrants. What is
the cloud?
- [inaudible]
- Yeah. Their governments from their own
countries.
- Oh.
- Is coming back after them or trying to
scare them, anyway. All right? Here we go.
We have these four. Uncle Sam, the boat,
the American flag, and the devil-looking
thing. I didn't do one for the travelers,
but you're right. They can symbolize
immigrants. Uncle Sam symbolizes America.
This is one you didn't say.
- I told you.
- The ark, this boat here symbolizes what?
- [together] The Bible.
- The ark from the bible. Okay. Is anybody
familiar with the story of the ark in the
bible?
- [together] Yeah.
- What did the ark do?
- It saved.
- It saved Noah, his family, and who else?
- Animals.
- And the animals.
- Oh yeah. Now I remember.
- So what do you think this boat's purpose
in this picture is? What's the boat going
to do?
- Save them.
- Save. Okay. So knowing that, knowing
that this is an ark and knowing that this
is America, what do you think? Are these
people being stopped or welcomed?
- [together] Welcomed.
- Welcomed. And how do we know that?
- He's letting them in. He's like, come
on, let's go.
- But how do we know that he's welcoming
them and not telling them to stop?
- Because it's the ark.
- Because it says ark, okay? And we're
connecting what we know about the ark to
this picture. That is called an allusion.
In English class, you talked about
allusion. Allusion is when you refer to
something that is famous. Some famous
piece of literature. Okay? The flag stands
for freedom. The scary devil-looking thing
is governments from other countries. Take
a second and copy that down.
Okay. I'll go on to the next question. How
are the words-- How do the words in the
cartoon tell you what the symbols mean?
Okay? We talked about this already. The U.
S. Ark of Refuge are some of the words in
the cartoon and they tell us that the boat
is a symbol of the United States. Okay?
Identify the cartoon's caption. All right.
In this cartoon, there is no caption.
There is no title at the top or at the
bottom, but there are some words that help
us understand and that's this sign. The
sign says no oppressive taxes, no
expensive kings, no compulsory military
service. So this is the promise of the
United States to the immigrants. To the
traveling people. Words or phrases used in
the cartoon to identify objects or people
in the cartoon. Okay? What words or
phrases here can be used to identify?
- I was going to say the ark.
- Yeah. The Ark of Refuge. And what does
it identify?
- [inaudible]
- The ark.
- It identifies the ark as what in this
cartoon? What is the ark?
- The boat.
- But what is it a symbol of?
- Welcoming.
- Yeah. A symbol of welcoming people,
right? Or a symbol of America itself,
because once you're in, you're in America.
What words or phrases in the cartoon
appear to be the most significant?
All right? Calling the U.S. a refuge tells
us people come here for safety.
- [inaudible]
- We'll come back to it. And here, the
sign says no taxes or oppressive kings.
Tell us why people left their countries.
- To get good jobs.
- Yeah. To get jobs.
- To have a better life.
- Right. What were they running away from?
- From paying taxes.
- From paying taxes. From kings. Now, any
guesses about what time period people
would have been running away from taxes
and kings?
- 1900s.
- 19th Century.
- The 19th Century, which would be the
1800s, or the 1900s. Both of those time
periods were very big. Kings were a
problem in some places in the world. No
oppressing taxes. Even as far back as the
revolutions in the 1700s, people were
dealing with this, okay? So you can use
clues in a cartoon to figure out when the
cartoon was written and sometimes things
like these signs can help you figure that
out. All right? List adjectives in the
cartoon and what they mean? What
adjectives are in the cartoon? It's on
this sign for one thing.
- Oh. The kings.
- Okay. What did they call the kings?
- Wealthy?
- What did they call kings? What kind of
kings did they have? It's kind of hard to
read there. Okay. Here we go. We'll do it
this way.
- Controlling.
- Yeah.
- More powerful than others.
- Expensive [inaudible] can't see...
- I know, I know. So oppressive means it's
controlling. Expensive means they spend
too much money.
- [together] Yeah.
- Compulsory means that you have to do
something. Compulsory military service
means everybody has to join the army. So
some people might be running away from
that because not everyone wants to be in
the army.
- [inaudible]
- The army's a fantastic place, but not
everybody wants to be there. You do
understand, right?
- Yes.
- Okay. Anybody not want to be in the
army?
- I want to serve my country.
- Yeah. Would you want to live in a
country where everybody had to do it?
- [together] No.
- I want to have a choice.
- You want to have a choice. I want my
army to have chosen to be there. Right?
Because I don't want a bunch of people
there twiddling their thumbs and not
wanting to be there, okay? Okay. Describe
the action in the cartoon.
- Action?
- I can't cover those.
- I forgot to put the space bar. Okay, so
what's happening in the cartoon? We've
already said this.
- Everybody's coming to Uncle Sam.
- And what's happening?
- The cloud is trying to get them away
from Uncle Sam.
- Right. All right. What is the message of
the cartoon?
- It's that we have to welcome the
immigrants.
- Correct. The message of the cartoon is
that the U.S. is welcoming immigrants who
are trying to get away from places they
don't like. What special interest
groups-- now this one I remembered to put
the extra thing in there so you all have
to think about it. What special interest
groups would agree or disagree with this
cartoon? Stop and take a second. Turn to
your partner. See if you can think of
somebody that would like this cartoon and
somebody that would not like this cartoon.
Talk to you partner.
- What is it?
- Okay. A special interest group. Go
ahead, keep talking. A special interest
group is a group that talks to the
government to try to get them to make laws
for them, okay? So what kind of group
would agree with the cartoon and what kind
of group would not agree?