- Yeah. Why don't we list that up here?
[inaudible]
Okay. Here is what you're going to do. Go
ahead and put your pencils back inside
that basket for me really quick. Put those
pencils away in ten, nine, eight, seven,
six, five, four, three, two, one and just
to make sure you haven't
[inaudible].
Now, you have identified, you have taken
this work of art, you've seen what it is
and you've taken out all those elements of
art and you listed them and you told me
how they were being used. Now, we need to
figure out what is that artist trying to
tell you with those elements. What kind of
thought, feeling is this artist
communicating to you with these elements,
with this subject?
So, who can raise their hand and tell us
first what is one element that you found?
What's one?
- Shapes.
- Shapes. What's another one?
- Color.
- Shape lines.
- Value.
- Value. Texture.
You guys, with those elements, they're
telling you something. So, here's what
we're going to. We're going to put on our
thinking, pairing, and sharing hats. So,
whatever I do that
[inaudible]
so you guys can pair and share together,
will you take your material with you so
that you can use them for reference? Thank
you.
All right. First question--ready? The
first question is how does this man feel?
Now, think for 30 seconds by yourself how
does this man feel? No talking. Think to
yourself. Think. Shh... You've got to
tell me why, too. Don't just think about
feeling. Tell me why. Two people look like
they're pairing already. Don't pair yet.
Now, tell your neighbors what you think
this man is thinking, is feeling is
feeling.
[cross talk]
All right. Now we're ready to share with
the whole group. So, I'm going to start
with, right here with Jermaine's group and
we're going to go around and each person
is going to get a turn, or each pair is
going to get a turn. So, first, what was
your group thinking? How did he feel?
- Sad.
- Why?
- Because the color blue is a sad color.
And he looked down
[inaudible].
- So he had two reasons-- he had the body
position, because he's kind of looking
down like this and he also he had a
connection with what you learned in
kindergarten, good job, he said that sad
and the color blue go together. What do
you guys think? How does he feel?
- I think he feels happy. He's smiling and
he's playing the guitar.
- Okay, because he's creating music. Maybe
that's what makes him happy. I heard Miss
Webster had a disagreement when they were
pairing. Miss Webster, what is your take?
What do you think he's feeling? Tell me
what you think he is? Sit up, tell me what
you think he is.
- I think he's sad because...
- Okay. Because why?
[Inaudible]
- He looks what? Say it again, honey.
Don't be embarrassed. It's okay to have a
different opinion.
- I think he is lonely because he doesn't
have any friends.
- There's nobody else in that picture. He
is by himself in the picture. Maybe he's
lonely. We don't know. Okay. So, we had a
difference of opinion. That's okay.
Next pair.
- I think he's sad because he's looking
down. If he was happy he'd be
[inaudible].
- Whoa. Wait a minute. She just said this
man doesn't have anything to eat. Why do
you think he doesn't have any?
- Because his shirt is torn, he don't have
no pants and he don't have no socks.
- So, you're telling me he looks what? Is
he rich or is he poor?
- No. He's poor.
- Okay. That is very good insight on not
only the details, but also just what those
details are telling us, okay? Do you have
something else to add? What would you say?
- I said I think he was happy to sit
alone. I think he's happy because he just
[inaudible]
- Okay. So, you think the guitar
looks-- even though his clothing looks
torn, his guitar looks nice, right? Maybe
he just puts a lot of value on keeping it
nice. Maybe he puts a lot of value on
keeping his guitar nice rather than his
clothes. Maybe not. Last pair, tell me
what you think he's feeling.
- I think he's--
- One at a time.
- I think he's
[inaudible].
...It looks like he's playing a sad
song. He's playing a sad song and he's
playing--
- Why do you think it looks like he's
playing a sad song?
- Because he's bowing his head down and
his face don't look very happy.
- Okay. You guys, next question-- I can see
everyone sitting nice and tall in your
seat. Did you have something different
than that? Okay. Go ahead.
- I think he's sad because he looks like
he's homeless.
- Oh, maybe he's homeless. Now, why do you
think he's homeless?
- Because his shirt's torn on the side.
- Are there any other clues besides his
clothing? We already had Miss Marshall
tell us about his clothing. What other
clues do we have that makes us think he's
homeless?
- [Inaudible]
- ...without talking and making noise.
Jermaine, do you have a clue why he might
be homeless? Why?
- Because he's outside by his self.
- He looks like me might be outside. This
might be a step that he's sitting on. Next
question... Next question--what do you
think the artist is trying to tell us?
What is the important message-- put your
hands down. Think. What is the message?
Why is the artist painting this picture of
this man? I have one person, she's got
herself in the thinking posture. She's
thinking. Think please. Think, think,
think. I've got a good thinker at this
table.
I hope you're thinking, honey. Okay. Now,
pair up. Ready? Pair and share with your
table mate. Get paired up.
[cross-talk]
Thirty more seconds to share. I hear some
good talking so I'm giving you 30 more
seconds. Why don't you share this time
because you shared last time? Okay. So,
you're going to share this time. Let's see
you sitting up nice and tall. We're going
to share with the entire group. We all
learn from each other. You guys, we're
going to start with the opposite way. I'm
going to go this way. Can you tell me what
the artist is trying to tell us, by
painting this picture-- I'm sorry, just a
second. Could you wait until your
classmates are showing you the respect you
deserve? You guys, when you're listening
to what he's saying, he's trying to tell
you what he thinks, what his table mate
thinks.
So, you need to turn your body, make eye
contact and really listen to what he's
saying, okay? Okay. Go again.
- I think the artist did this picture
because he wanted kids to know how alone
he is and how he's homeless. He doesn't
have any money. He doesn't have any value.
- Okay. When you mean value, do you mean
value like art value or what kind of value
do you mean?
- Like he seems very sad.
- Okay. So, you're talking about the
color, right? Okay. Next group.
- I think that the artist is trying to
persuade him--
- Wait a minute. Say that word again. He's
trying to what?
- Persuade.
- Persuade us what? Persuade us to think
what?
- Persuade us
[inaudible]
He feels real mad or trying to do music or
something.
- Okay. Is that what your team came up
with? You came up with something different
than your team. You had a disagreement,
right?
- I think that I was not
[inaudible].
- Do you think the artist wants you to be
like him?
- No.
- What do you think the artist wants you
to learn from him?
- He won't have nothing to work...
[Inaudible].
- You can have a better life, right? Okay.
This group-- could you put your feet down?
It's your turn. You're going to share with
us what your team came up with? You can
share. Come on. You can talk to us.
Remember that there's no wrong answer.
It's just what you think.