- [Voiceover] Who came up with
the definition for radiation?
Peter, you had a good definition,
could you repeat that, remind us?
- I don't remember it
exactly, but it was something
along the lines of anything
with waves that move,
waves that are radiated, I mean.
- [Girl in purple] Didn't
you say it was waves
that are spread?
- Yeah, waves that are
spread by something,
and they usually have energy with them.
Like, the sun sends its
radiation to the earth,
in the form of light, heat, UVA, UVB rays.
- [Voiceover] Okay, so
with that understanding,
would you guys say that
all radiation is harmful?
- [Voiceover] Not all.
- Yes.
To a degree, all of radiation is harmful.
But just, it depends on how harmful.
- But so then, what is
like, when it's not harmful?
- It's very, very, very.
- Not, almost?
- It's almost negligible.
- [Voiceover] What types
of waves that radiate,
or what types of radiation
do you associate with
being not harmful?
- [Peter] Radio waves.
(students agreeing)
- [Voiceover] Any others, Jordan?
- Microwaves?
- [Voiceover] Visible light.
- Yeah, visible light
isn't really that harmful.
- [Voiceover] What about
microwaves, that's a good one.
What do you guys think about microwaves?
- I thought they were dangerous,
but somebody told me that they weren't.
- They're not really
that harmful are they?
I mean--
(cross-talk)
- [Voiceover] You probably
shouldn't stand in front of it.
- Saying they're not that harmful?
- They're not.
I mean, I think probably
like extended exposure
to them would be bad,
but I think that could be
the same with a lot of things.
- [Jordan] The door shuts when
you use the microwave too.
- [Voiceover] What about
then, where do they fall on
the spectrum, what makes you
think they're not dangerous?
Or that they are?
- [Voiceover] Because they
are longer than light waves.
- They've got longer wavelengths.
- [Voiceover] Which what does that mean?
- They have lower frequencies.
They don't carry as much energy with them.
Lower frequencies.
- [Claire] Let me consult my chart.
- [Voiceover] Okay, good idea.
Or can anyone help her?
What was your question Claire?
- Oh, I didn't have a question.
- [Voiceover] Oh, okay.
- What was the question?
Why is she looking at her chart?
- Nope, same (mumbles).
- We think they're not
dangerous because they
have a longer wavelength and a
smaller frequency than light.
Light is (mumbles).
- [Voiceover] Okay good, so
I think this is a good segue
to the next question,
which is, why are some
electromagnetic waves
considered dangerous to humans,
while others aren't?
- Do you know what a segue is?
- [Voiceover] Okay.
Which ones have more energy than others?
- Gamma rays and X-rays, and UVH rays?
- [Voiceover] Okay good,
Peter did you have something
you wanted to add?
- To what he just said?
- [Voiceover] Mm-hmm.
Okay, good, and,
can you repeat that, Sam?
- Some electromagnetic
waves are more dangerous
because they have much more energy.
- [Voiceover] Okay, good.
So ultimately, what is that energy doing?
Why is that harmful to us?
- Can stimulate cell growth (mumbles).
- The more energy it has the more like,
materials it can penetrate.
Like visible light wouldn't
really cut through you,
but gamma rays could,
like travel through skin.
And X-rays can.
- [Voiceover] What did you guys learn about
perhaps in biology?
Cancer (mumbles).
- Well that it's, when cells grow too fast,
the abnormal growth of
cells keep reproducing and...
- There's a mistake in
the coding of the DNA,
and then everything just goes haywire and,
the cells, like what Caleb
said, grow at abnormally
fast rates, and they just
take over that area and spread.
- Well yeah, they stop
functioning as normal cells,
and their sole function is to reproduce,
and to continue growing and then
they eat portions of other cells.
- [Voiceover] Okay, so what
do electromagnetic waves
have to do with this extra energy?
This dangerous energy?
- Well wouldn't like, Cho
said they would like stimulate
the growth and, or is that not?
- Why do they stimulate growth?
- [Cho] Because they have energy.
- What does the energy do to stimulate it?
- [Voiceover] What were
you going to say, Ronnie?
- Well, I just said that they trigger,
they don't like stimulate, I
mean cell growth to an extent
is necessary (mumbles).
But they can trigger something dangerous,
like with (mumbles).
I don't really have like
the percent (mumbles)
or anything but...
- [Voiceover] What else
might control cell growth?
- DNA?
- [Voiceover] Okay good, yeah.
- Lots of energy can.
Can energy alter DNA?
I feel like it can't.
- Well, isn't that what it's doing if it's
triggering abnormal cell growth?
- I don't know.
- [Voiceover] Is anyone
in here, have you taken,
or are you taking (mumbles) biology?
- I took it last year.
I kind of remember what we
talked about with cancer.
- [Voiceover] It's okay,
and you guys have actually
come to a good conclusion,
that it does lie in the DNA,
and that, you know, certain
types of radiation can
cause mutations in DNA
that affect the cell cycle.
So, when we think about
cancer a lot of times,
in light, or electromagnetic waves,
a lot of times we
think about skin cancer.
And we talked a bit about that yesterday.
We also probably notice
skin variations among
different people from
different regions of the world.
So, how does skin color
variation, how do you think
it relates to the amount of UV radiation
that a particular population receives?
- [Caleb] You mean based on their race?
- [Voiceover] Just based on
their geologic background.
Geographic background, not geologic.
- Well I mean, people with
darker skin tend to not get
sunburned as much as somebody
with really, really pale skin.
- I don't think that's
true, I think it's just that
it doesn't show up as much,
like you can definitely
still get sun damage--
- No, of course you can
still get sunburned,
but I don't think it's like--
- [Sam] It's harder?
- I think so.
- [Voiceover] I think
it's just less noticeable.
- Yeah, I think it's just less noticeable,
I really don't think it
has anything to do with--
(cross-talk)
- [Voiceover] Okay, so you're
getting the same amount,
good, you're getting the same
amount of radiation, sure.
- [Sam] Is sunburning caused
by like the amount of light
we absorb, our skin absorbs?
- It's actually, it's in their,
Grace and Lana's video.
About how (mumbles).
- What did we do?
- On your presentation about sunburn.
How sunburn works.
I don't remember (mumbles).
- [Voiceover] Okay, so ultimately I guess,
I'll restate the question.
So, how does skin color relate to
the amount of UV radiation a
certain population may receive?
We see a lot of variation, so
a lot of people often times
say, "Oh, why do people in,
"in countries that are near the equator,
"Why are they darker, wouldn't
that make them hotter?"
Because we tend to think
of dark colors as absorbing
a lot of different wavelengths of light.
Is that true, is that what's happening?
It seems kind of...
- Wouldn't that make you sweat more then?
Which would be good if it was hot.
- I guess sweat (mumbles).
- [Cho] Sweat is just to
release the heat on your body.
- No, but that's what I'm saying,
like if you get hotter quicker,
then you would start sweating earlier,
which cools you down.
- [Voiceover] What is the pigment in skin
that causes color variations?
- [Students] Melanin.
- [Voiceover] Okay, good, alright.
So, people who have darker skin,
do they have more or less?
- They have more.
- It's in eyes, too, right?
It's what causes eye color differences?
Maybe I'm making that up, but...
- [Voiceover] What do
you think the purpose
of the melanin is?
Is it to absorb, Grace offered one theory,
what's another theory too there?
There are several different reasons.
What does it do to UV light?
What's different about people that live
say, in the equator regions,
like the (mumbles) and
people who live up north?
- They don't get sunburned
if they live there.  I mean...
- There's like nothing to (mumbles).
- Yeah, exactly.
People who live in northern climates are
much more likely to get sunburned,
because they're not
exposed to that much sun,
or their relatives weren't.
And as they adapted they
just passed on that trait
of having fair skin.
But, I don't know why.
Do you know, Miss Roseborough?
- [Voiceover] Yeah, I have
an understanding, yes.
And when I think about
it, I kind of think about
the actual pigment itself,
and what it's doing,
and where it's located on the body.
What it may be serving to do.
- [Cho] Doesn't it
synthesize vitamin D for us?
- That would make sense.
- Yeah that's, vitamin D from sunlight,
I guess that's why.
- [Voiceover] Okay, so
people who have more melanin
have, live in the sun,
you know they have more
exposure to the sun.
Why do they need that extra melanin?
- [Girl in bandana] To protect them.
- [Voiceover] Okay yeah,
so let's go with that,
to protect them.
From what?
- From the radiation like,
I guess if you're out in the sun more,
you need more protection, so like,
it's kind of like a built-in sunblock.
- [Voiceover] What would it protect?
So, it's on the surface, right?
- Protects the inner skin?
It protects the outer layer, right?
- [Claire] Epidermis.
- [Voiceover] Yeah, I
feel like Ewan brought up
something like this yesterday
when we were talking.
- Is that why they, you
have lighter on your hands?
- Oh, I think that's the thing about like,
gamma rays, for example, being more,
like that was one of
the (mumbles) question,
because they have more ability
to penetrate through skin,
and (mumbles).
- [Voiceover] Okay, so
really what's happening is
the melanin actually absorbs
the wavelengths of light
that would normally penetrate the skin.
- How does it do that?
- [Voiceover] It just doesn't,
the energy is just sort of
dissipated as heat, and so...
- You get the heat but not the radiation?
- [Voiceover] Right,
exactly, so it doesn't go
further into your body.
- So, darker people get less sunburned
than fairer people,
because of that?
- Well, does it necessarily
have to do with sunburn?
- And they're less likely
to get skin cancer?
- [Voiceover] Yeah, I'd say
they're less likely to get
skin cancer.
- When you get tan, are
you getting more melanin
in your skin?
- [Voiceover] Yeah, what's
happening when you get tan?
- So, shouldn't tanning
make your skin stronger?
- Well--
- If it increases melanin?
- I don't think it's
necessarily increasing it.
- [Girl in bandana]
Because the tan goes away.
- Oh.
- So, it's like you have whatever
your natural skin color is,
then that is determined, how much.
- Okay.
- [Voiceover] Okay, so next misconception,
that a lot of people have,
or just something that
I've always wondered about.
I don't know if it's a
misconception or not,
but I'm thinking about
colors that we associate
with certain, just everyday things.
So, when I go into the bathroom,
when I go into the kitchen,
I see red and
that indicates the faucet that I turn
for hot water, and blue for cold water.
Why do you think those
colors were chosen and
is that always true?
- [Students] Because fire is red.
- Water and ice is blue.
It's not really blue, it's more clear.
- White and blue flames are
much hotter than red flames.
- [Voiceover] Yeah, explain that.
- [Caleb] I don't know, I guess back,
a long time ago before they knew that--
- The hottest part of
the fire is at the top,
and if you think about
a flame, usually you see a
little blue or white part at the bottom,
and then it's the red orange at the top.
- Which is where it would be the hottest.
- It's hottest at the top.
- But there's, at the top it
would be starting to cool off
as it gets away from--
- At the peak it's the hottest.
But then the bunsen burner,
the hottest part is like...
- Yeah, the hottest part
of the flame is the top.
- You get a marshmallow,
you put it at the bottom?
- No, sir!
- [Voiceover] What color
is at the top, guys?
- [Students] Red.
- [Girl in bandana] White.
- Or orange.
(cross-talk)
- Blue and white at the bottom.
- It's an experiment, Miss Rose,
let's do experiments on fire.
- [Voiceover] That's a good idea,
I think we should at this point.
- Do you have bunsen burners in here?
- [Voiceover] No, I
don't have a gas source.
So, let's just go back,
I even broke it down,
and I was thinking about well,
where did this come from?
I was thinking, what wavelengths of light
are being absorbed by the color red,
and what are being
reflected by the color red?
And so is the color red actually hotter?
How could I relate that to temperature?
How do you even relate
a color to temperature?
So, just the color red,
what's it reflecting?
What's it absorbing?
- What color does it reflect?
It reflects red.
- And it absorbs green and blue.
Or cyan.
- [Voiceover] Right, so,
going back to the, what
makes it that color,
its natural frequency,
what types of waves are causing it
to change in temperature?
What's happening as a result of
different white light say, striking it,
and its actual reflection and absorption
of different waves of light?
Would red or blue actually be hotter?
As a pigment?
- Blue should be hotter,
because it has more energy,
it has the shorter wavelength
and greater frequency.
- Yeah, Sam's right.
- [Voiceover] So, with a pigment?
Think about a pigment first.
- What about it, just think about it?
- [Voiceover] Yeah, so
certain wavelengths of light
are being absorbed, and certain,
wavelengths of light are being reflected.
What does it mean when a pigment
absorbs wavelengths of light?
What happens to the energy
that is being absorbed?
- It transfers to the medium?
- [Voiceover] Okay, good.
- I was going to say the pigment has the same
frequency as those wavelengths, so...
- [Peter] Probably right.
- [Voiceover] Okay good, so it absorbs,
so let's think about blue again.
How could you apply that?
What wavelengths of light does it absorb?
- [Peter] Shorter wavelengths than red.
- Well no, blue absorbs red and green,
so this would be,
longer wavelengths and lower frequencies.
- So, red would absorb the blue.
Therefore it would absorb
the higher frequency,
had more energy, which means
it would be hotter, right?
- [Voiceover] What do you guys think?
Can you restate that?
- Sorry, because red absorbs blue,
and blue has a higher frequency,
the red would be absorbing
the higher frequency,
which means it would
be getting more energy
from the higher frequency.
So, red would be the hottest.
- The man has a point.
I agree with Peter.
- I agree with it, too.
- I agree with Peter.
- [Voiceover] Yeah, that's sort
of the conclusion I came to, the only conclusion.
Then I started thinking more, I was like,
well how does this apply to stars?
So, if I see a star that gives off a...