- [Instructor] Dylan what are you playing?
- [Dylan] Hot cross buns.
- Okay go ahead whenever you're ready.
♪ [Hot Cross Buns] ♪
Let's give Dylan a hand. [Clapping]
Christopher what are you playing?
- [Christopher] Hot cross buns.
- Okay.
♪ [Hot Cross Buns] ♪
Okay Christopher try it one more time
pressing your holes a little tighter.
From the beginning.
♪ [Hot Cross Buns] ♪
Thank you Christopher, nice job, [Clapping]
give Christopher a hand. Okay Drexel, so what
are you playing?
- [Drexel] Hot cross buns.
- Okay.
♪ [Hot Cross Buns] ♪
Let's give Drexel a hand, [clapping] nice job.
Okay now Elise what are you playing?
- [Elise] Hot cross buns.
- Okay, whenever you're ready.
♪ [Hot Cross Buns] ♪
Let's give Elise a hand, [clapping] nice job.
- [Jessica] Hot cross buns.
- Okay Jessica.
♪ [Hot Cross Buns] ♪
Okay Jessica try it one more time pressing
your holes tighter and
blowing really soft.
♪ [Hot Cross Buns] ♪
Yeah that middle part is where it gets
tricky, Jessica. Let's try it one more
time going from just the middle of the
song and the four G's press tight and
blow really gently.
♪ [Hot Cross Buns] ♪
There it is, give her a hand. [Clapping]
Thank you everybody.