- Okay. So, what's going on with this
group? You go ahead since you did it.
- We made like a T chart.
- Oh, fantastic. Graphic organizing. Love
it.
- We put the ones that we're going to
delete over here and then keep over here.
- Now we're discussing why we deleted these
or chose them.
- Was it pretty easy to choose the
keepers?
- It was.
- Yeah, we agreed on most of them.
- What about the delete? Have there been
some discussions?
- We had to think about the smart and the
healthy and religious.
- Yeah.
- Okay. Good.
- Oh and stay in school. They don't have
to stay in school.
- So, there were some that you had to
discuss a little more?
- Yeah.
- Tell me some of your thoughts. Which was
the most difficult?
- Probably the religious.
- And also smart.
- Tell me a little bit about the
discussion you had with religion.
- Well, first of all we thought that it
wouldn't be, but then we thought some
people had different religions and other
people...
- My dad has a friend--my dad has a friend
that isn't a Christian, but he's still a
really good person.
- It's just like as you grow up being a
Christian, that's just what you think. But
then as you think about it, that's not how
you're a good person.
- Okay. So, you stepped back from what you
knew and you looked around. Were you able
to come up with some examples, like was it
your uncle?
- No, it was just a friend.
- A friend. So, were you able to come up
with some examples of people that were not
religious people.
- Yeah.
- Can you tell me some qualities on the
list that they have even though they are
not the Christian?
- My uncle, he's not religious, but he's a
teacher. So, he's helping kids and stuff
and he's really nice.
- My neighbor, she's really nice. You
can't even tell that she's not religious.
You always think she is. She's kind and
friendly. She's respectful. I don't know,
just really nice.
- Okay. So, when we first put up our list,
that was one of the qualities that were on
lots of list--boom, boom, boom, then just
religious. So, we had to step back from it
to really stop and think about that.
- Or they could be not doing their best in
school but they could be a really great
friend or person.
- Very good. There's more than one kind of
smart.
- Yeah.
- Do you think that having good qualities
and keeping yourself with those qualities
is another kind of smart?
- Yes.
- And you're right. I know some mentally
challenged friends, people, that are some
of the most kind-hearted people. Good
discussion. Good going. Okay. Why
did you do happy?
- Because whenever you're sad then you
just have that gloomy feeling hanging over
you all the time.
- Yeah. And also if you're not happy all
the time, you don't have it all the time,
every minute--you can't just be depressed
all the time. And then...
- Stay in school.
- Yeah. Why did we go into stay in school?
- Thank you, Lexi. Come on over here,
Veronica. Okay, ladies, what is your
question?
- We're going two ways. I kind of think
that you need to be religious.
Because if you go to church it helps you
become a good person. But then at the same
time, there's like people in the world
that are really great people but they're
un-relgious.
- They can't be religious.
- Like countries?
- And they're still a good person even
though they can't.
- Also, we were thinking people that do go
to church aren't always taking what they
learn and using it in their lives.
- So, you have found some examples of
religious that are not exhibiting other
qualities and then people who are not
religious who show a lot of these
qualities.
- Yeah.
- Okay. So, that kind of goes both ways.
- I think we should delete.
- I don't know. I can go both ways.
- So, you can see both sides.
- Yeah.
- You don't have to be religious to be a
good person.
- Okay. So, can you set aside what your
own religious beliefs are that if you
believe this way, if you don't believe
this way, something bad will happen to
you? Can you set that aside and just look
at the person's qualities?
- My sister has a friend that goes to
college with her and she doesn't hang out
with her that much, but she doesn't
believe in God. And that's her religion.
But I guess that would be their religion.
So, really, everybody has a religion kind
of, but they can't express their religion
or go to church and stuff like that.
- Okay. So, which one's our leader?
Jordan, you're our leader. So, do you want
to take another vote and see where it
stands? Okay.
You're changing in a way? Okay. So, where
do you stand now?
- Those are all qualities that make up a
good person, but again, we all had to make
a decision on it. But again, other groups
can have different opinions about that or
different opinions on how to make a good
person. So, we can think that you need to
be religious but then another group can
say you don't have to be religious.
- Right. It's all about what this group
decides.
- I was also thinking about the Ten
Commandments, that it has a choice. If you
want to be religious, that's also putting
that in mind.
- Okay. So, are you leaning towards
deleting or keeping?
- We're just talking
[inaudible].
- How about you, Grace?
- I kind of think it's... I don't know.
I think we should keep and then I think
that we maybe should delete because you
don't have to go to church to be a good
person.
- Does anybody have a personal experience
in their own family of somebody who's not
religious that is a really great person?
- Well, like they don't go to church or
they're just not like... ?
- Okay. That is a great statement that
Jordan made that will give us pause to
think. What does "religious" mean to each
one of you? So maybe that's another place
to start. What does that word mean? And
then that might help you decide whether to
delete it or keep it.
- Because going to church doesn't
necessarily make you religious.
- You can just walk into the church and
listen to your pastor's sermon.
It doesn't mean that you're a good person.
- So discuss that for just a moment. Okay.
- What does religious mean to you?
- I think it means being saved and saying
sorry for our sins and asking for
forgiveness. So, that's like the main
writing.
- In my opinion of being religious, I
think that you take what you learn in a
church's sermon and you use it in your
world. You know what I mean?
- Yes.
- If it's a very touching sermon and it's
what you believe, you can take it back and
you can use it to help you go through
problems or whatever and then I think also
religious is that you're willing to share
with other people.
- Yeah. You're not embarrassed.
- You're not just holding back and keeping
it to yourself.
- No matter if people aren't religious and
they'll come up to you and make fun of you
here at school. You're just willing to put
it aside. I used to go to a different
school. I don't remember now. But he was a
very, very, very good student. And for
some reason, they did want to
[inaudible].
I don't know why. I didn't figure it out.
The pastor got fired because it was just a
job to him. He did something very, very
inappropriate that a pastor could do with
another person within church. And he left
because he was so embarrassed.
- Why would he have been embarrassed? I
would have felt bad, not just embarrassed.
- And he was married. You know what I said
about you have to be willing to share?
Well, there was this one pastor...
- Let me turn the camera on you. Hold on.
- So, there would kind of be a way of
saying that it doesn't really work out.
So, if both sides are
[inaudible].
- Okay. All right. Regan, let's hear again
what you said about the deleting, why
would you thought you would delete it.
- Oh, I'm not the one who said delete.
- Oh, okay.
- I said delete it because I know people
that are not atheist who are not--
- Yes ma'am. I will tell her. Thank you.
Scarlet, Vicki is not here today. Thank
you, ladies, for getting quiet when the
intercom rang. Now, discuss, continue.
- They're still Christian but they're
still just as good as any other person
would be. That's why I think we should
delete it. But I don't know.
- Okay.
- Maybe it's the way she put it because
she said it changes you inside, but being
Christian, it does kind of change you
inside.
- Okay. So, you have a person in your life
that you consider to have some qualities
that make them a really great person but
they are not religious?
- Yeah. They're not atheist but they're
not Christian.
- Okay Do you have anybody in your life
that's not religious that you find a lot
of good qualities?
- My grandpa. He's not saved, but he still
believes.
- I guess it just depends on how the
person acts.
- Okay? How about you? Do you have anybody
in your life?
- Yeah.
[Inaudible]
named Delaney, she's an older person. But
she really, really likes
[inaudible]
her house and stuff.
- And would you consider her to have
qualities that make a really great person?
- Yes.
- But you would not consider her
religious?
- Oh no. But she is not really atheist,
but she doesn't believe in anything. But
she doesn't believe in being atheist.
- So, we're kind of on the fence on this
one in that some people think it needs to
be deleted and others think no, it makes a
difference. Do you know anybody who says
that they are religious and they don't
have qualities of a great person?
- Yes. Some people, as soon as they get
out of church, they'll go out and do stuff
that wouldn't be religious.
- Yeah. It's kind of like they don't have
a Christian background.
- They'll sit in the church room and they
say, "I'm a Christian because I'm here at
church," but really you go do this at
other places.
- So, then I guess it all boils down to
what do you believe or what do you think
that religious means. A lot of people
would say, "Oh, I'm religious," but then
like you said, spend the rest of the week
doing things.
- Yes. But they're kind of being truthful
if they say they're not religious and
they're not really religious. So, it's
kind of two things--so truthful, but
they're not religious.
- Or maybe being a fake Christian, like
sitting in church. They'll watch a
football game just waiting for church to
end.
- But maybe that's kind of worse than
saying, "I'm not a Christian," but also
be a good person.
- Okay. So, you're the leader in this
group.
Why don't you poll each other again and
see if they want to now delete other
people.
- Okay.
- So, go ahead and ask.
- Okay. So, I put I'm not sure yet.
- We're still not sure. That's fine.
That's fine. If we're not sure yet, we
don't have to put it in one side or the
other yet if we're not done discussing it.
This may be one that the group can't agree
on.
- I think it's a good thing to have, but
you don't have to have it to be a good
person.
- Yeah.
- I think we can just delete it. It is
good to have, but people can be really
good people and not be religious.
- Everybody agree with that? If you're
still thinking, "No, I don't want to say
that," this is the safe place to say
that. Nobody's going to kick you.
- Because even religious people
can also be...