- [teacher] Plug in two. You got it?
- [together] We got it.
- All right. First question is... Once
energy is used up, it's gone for good.
Talk to your partner, no! Let's try that
one more time folks, eyes up here. What
was the rule on the darts?
- The rule is don't do anything until you
say so.
- Thank you. Don't act until I say so. Go!
[Background Chatter]
- Yeah.
- There could be a little bit left of
potential. Is that what you mean?
- Yeah. Well, [Background Chatter].
[Background Chatter]
- All right. On three. I'm going to need
eyes up here, please. One, two, th-- Don't
flip your card until I tell you to. I
shouldn't be able to tell what your card
is. It should be much more secret. They're
colored, guys, I can tell what they are.
Okay! Here we go, on three, hold up your
card please. One, two, three! Okay. We've
got mostly disagrees. And then we have
very one confident... Oh, we disagree. So
here's what we're going to do. Put your
cards down. I'm calling on Mark first. So
where should we be looking?
- [together] Mark.
- At Mark.
- Okay. Okay. So I strongly disagree,
because say... So you know you... when
you... You know how you eat food, you get
fuel in your body and you have energy and
you go out running. And then you're out of
energy, you're tired, you go to bed, you
wake up the next morning, it comes back.
You eat more food and it comes back.
- Okay. So you're getting it from a
different source.
- Yeah.
- Okay, but that energy you have
originally. So that initial energy that
you have, and then you ran. Does it go
away? Yeah, you have plenty more, but does
that original energy go away?
- No.
- Where does it go? Because you still
don't have it, right? You have to eat more
food. This is supposed to be challenging.
Great job. Who has another idea? Or who
can tell me where does it go? It's awfully
quiet. Awfully quiet. What do you got?
- I don't think it literally... Well, I
don't think it goes anywhere. You just...
It just keeps making more.
- It makes more. So the energy I burnt,
right? So I'm running, and I'm running,
and I'm running. Where does it go?
- Out.
- Out where?
- To the air.
- To the air, in what form?
- Breath.
- Now this is tricky. This is where it
gets tricky. Breath is made of what?
- Vapor.
- Carbon dioxide.
- Water and carbon dioxide. And we call
that matter. We call that stuff. Is stuff
and energy the same thing?
- [together] No.
- No, and this is really a tricky idea in
Science. So we're going to keep working with
you on that. So where does the energy go?
- Out into sweat.
- Out into... Now, okay, sweat is?
- Stuff.
- It's stuff, right? But where... So where
does the energy go? Does anybody want to
change their answer? And say, once it's
used up, it's used up for good? Anybody?
Some people I think... Now Tatum what do
you think?
- I think that when you run, it's... Some
of the energy go into the ground.
- How many people agree with Tatum? That
some of that energy is going to go to the
ground?
- Oh yeah.
- [together] Yeah.
- Okay. In what form does it go to the
ground?
- In static stuff.
- What's that?
I think you said static stuff. Is that
what you say?
- Yeah.
- Okay, so static stuff is... Now this
gets really tricky because now we're
getting into electrons. But you're
thinking about the rubbing, kind of
thinking. Is that what you're thinking?
How it rubs? And then you shock people?
Okay. So that can happen. That's a little
more complicated so I'm going to put that
on hold for now. But what... So if I'm
running, and that energy's going into the
ground, somebody said that. Who said that?
- [together] Tatum.
- Tatum. Okay. So Tatum said the energy is
going into the ground. In what form is it
going into the ground? Yeah.
- Energy transfer.
- It is an energy transfer, right? This is
going from my foot to the ground. What
form is it in? Do you guys know what I
mean when I say form?
- [together] Yeah.
- Yeah. We talked about kinetic, and
potential, and heat, and what else we
talked about? Elastic, and--
- Light.
- Gravitational, and light, and chemical.
- Sound.
- Heat, sound. Ooh, there's just hey, is
any of that sound energy?
- No.
- No?
- Maybe it could be sound energy.
- Yes! Sound! Because you're... You're
stepping hard. You're...
- Okay, so if I'm running, I'm probably
going to produce some sound. Anything else
that could go in there? Jason?
- Huh?
- Okay, I think that as you step on...
You'll actually transform some potential
energy to the ground because once you step
on, you all react to gravity to the
ground.
- So gravity's pushing down--, now remember
what gravitational energy is, is how far
it is away from the ground, right? So how
much room it has to fall basically. So
would there be... If I go like this, would
there be any gravitational energy there?
- Wouldn't there be if you raise your
foot?
- Now it's got gravitational.
- Here's what we need, I'm really doing
something to say... But here's what I want
you to think about this one... Actually,
let's do this one more time. I want you to
re-vote on this. Once energy is used
up, it's gone for good. Talk to each other
for 10 seconds.
[Background Chatter]
- You're thinking it's
going someplace else.
- I don't know where but I don't think it
just disappears for good. I think it's
going somewhere.
- That it's somewhere but just not sure
where.
- Yeah.
- All right folks, we're going to re-vote
on three. One, two, three. All right, put
your cards down for just a second. Here's
what Henry just said, and I want you to
raise your hand if you agree with Henry.
And we're going to talk about, again guys,
we're not getting answers to all these
questions today, we will at some point. I
promise. We're going to do it in the
formal labs but not before I'm through
telling you. Henry, tell me what you just
said.
- I think that it's not gone for good. I'm
not sure where it goes but I think it
doesn't just leave. It's still somewhere
but I don't know where.
- How many of you agree with Henry? That
you think that it's somewhere but you're
just not sure where?
- I don't know where though.
- All right. Do you know what form?
- No.
- No. Anybody else? Know where?
- But wait. Doesn't it just transform?
- It can transform into something else but
then my question for you would be...
- [together] What?
- What kind of energy is it? All right,
but here's what we're going to do, we're
going to move on to the next one. If a
person is pushing a box, the person has
energy, but the box does not otherwise it
would help out. Ready, set, go.
[Background Chatter]
- What's the evidence that the box has
energy? What form of energy is that,
that's moving?
- I don't know.
- Well, it's kineck, kineck...
- One more try.
- Kinetic.
- Okay. [Background Chatter]
- Because it's currently in motion.
- Yeah.
- Okay. All right. So now here's what I
want... We're going do a challenge
question. What about the person? What kind
of energy does the person have, who's
pushing it?
- That... I don't know.
- You guys all have it? Okay, here we go!
Eyes over here please. Are we a little bit
on balancing in agreement? All right, here
we go. A person is pushing a box, the
person has energy but the box does not,
otherwise, it would help out. On three,
hold up your cards, please. One, two,
three. So what you're saying then is you
all think the box does have energy, am I
correct?
- [together] Yeah.
- Okay. Chloe tell me why... What is your
evidence, that the box has energy?
- I think it has energy because when
you're pushing it, it has a friction with
whatever you're pushing it.
- How many of you agree that there's
friction there? Because it's rubbing
against what?
- [together] The ground.
- It's rubbing against the ground. There
could be some rubbing against you, but most likely
it's going to be rubbing against ground.
But here's my question, what is your
evidence that it has energy? It does have
friction, and now it gives you some sort
of indication that it's doing what?
- [together] Moving.
- It's moving. What do we call that,
something's moving? What kind of energy
does that? Just shout it.
- [together] Kinetic.
- Kinetic. So it has kinetic energy. So
here's my next question, so does anybody
disagree? The box does not have kinetic
energy? Tate?
- I didn't believe it. I thought it was
transferred. I thought that it was energy
transfer.
- [together] Yeah.
- Okay. So you think energy's being
transferred from the person to the box.
- Yeah.
- Okay, but the question is still, does
the box have energy? Even if I'm
transferring it there? Does it have energy
while it's moving?
- Yeah.
- Well, do you mean before the person?
- I mean while I'm moving it. I'm in the
process of pushing the box. Does the
box have energy?
- Yeah, but don't you think part of it,
would be from you, and part of it--
- I think all of it is from you.
- Oh.
- But does it still have energy?
- Yeah.
- Yeah, it does. So what's your proof?
Chloe just said it. What's your proof that
the box has energy?
- [together] Friction.
- It's moving.
- That it's moving. Okay, now the friction
is proof that's it's moving, perhaps. But
you also see it moving, that would be the proof
that it's moving. Okay, so here's my other
question, I'm going to make this point,
this is too easy for you. We're going to
make this more challenging. What about the
person pushing the box? So here is me,
this is how I push a box. So if I'm
pushing the box, what kind of energy do I
have? Think about it. Jack, what do you
think?
- Kinetic.
- How many of you agree with Jack, that I
have kinetic energy? How many of you think
there's something else going on there as
well?
- No.
- So I have... I can only have kinetic
energy, right? Because I am... ?
- [together] Moving. Pushing.
- Because I am moving and I'm pushing.
Okay. What other kind of energy must I
have?
- I have to say something else, like it's
kind of helping to [inaudible] and what
disagrees. Yesterday, you told us the
classic pool...
- You're talking about energy transfer?
You guys know what she's talking
about? We're talking about the pool and
handle.
- Yeah. I think of it kind of the same
thing only the pool hall has some of the
[inaudible] because you have the stick in
your hand, and you have the energy,
potential energy and then you start moving
it, and then it's kinetic and it goes
through the stick, and through the ball,
and it moves.
- So you're saying that I have some form
of potential energy as well?
- Yeah, before you start. And then
[inaudible].
- In what form is that potential energy?
Because I think Emily was about to say
this, too. Think about this guys. Where am
I getting my energy from? Is it
gravitational?
- [together] No.
- Muscles.
- Okay, so I've got my muscles, I've got
my body. But where's that energy coming
from?
- Food.
- Which is a form of what, Marcus?
- Fuel.
- Which is a form of what?
- Potential!
- Time out. We're asking Marcus. Marcus,
what form of potential energy is fuel?
- Um.
- This is hard. Did you want a lifeline?
- Yeah.
- Anika, can you help him out.
- Chemical.
- Chemical, right? Make sense?
- [together] Yes.
- Okay. All right, we're going on to
the next slide. Are you ready?
- [together] Yeah.
- Woo hoo hoo. Okay, here we go. Now,
goodness, gracious. Okay, this is a
hard one. Cold moves faster than heat.
Ready, set, go.
[Background Chatter]
- And but also I remember my mom on hot
days, she's like, "Don't go upstairs
because it's hotter." Heat rises.
- So is it, is it move... So your
evidence that it's moving faster is that
it goes up.
- Yeah, and also when you put it
in hot, hot water, it's looser
because...
- Okay, so you're saying if cold moved
faster it would go up as well?
- [together] Yeah.
- Faster than heat? Okay. How about moving
in other directions other than up? Is there...
Do you have any... ?
- Wind!
- Okay, so that would... So does one move
faster than the other? [Background Chatter]
Tatum, what do you think? All right. Think about it.
[Background Chatter]
All right, here we go.
Okay, here we go. So on three, hold up
your answers please. One, two, three.
We've got strongly agrees. We've got an in
between. We've got an ooh, we've got a
strongly agree. And we've got a couple
in-betweens. All right. We're mostly in
orange land, we've got one green. So here
we go? You ready?
- [together] Yeah.
- And stand together, you're going to back
them up.
- Yeah. So, okay, so we agree that. . .
- Are you sure?
- No. Just kidding.
- Because I think the answer you just gave
me was certain. So you're a strongly
disagree. Okay.
- Well, I read it wrong. I thought it said
heat... Yeah, I thought it said heat moves
faster than cold.
- Okay, so tell me why you strongly
disagree then, Tim?
- Well, because there's just as
[inaudible] heat rises. So it has to be
lighter to move.
- And so it must be moving faster?
- Yeah.
- How many of you agreed with this... How
many of you thought about this whole heat
rising thing? Interesting. And how many of
you... Nope, you guys, it never crossed
your mind. Okay. Let's hop to another...
Tatum, do have anything else to add to
that?
- No.
- What is your evidence that cold moves
slower? Because he was just saying heat
was rising, do you have any evidence that
cold would move slower? Let's see, Alex,
what do you think?
- Well, because when we did that
investigation and stuff on molecules,
they move faster when they're hot.
- The coke can.
- Yeah, the coke can investigation.
- Okay, so I'm going to ask them for
specific evidence. So what was your
specific evidence in the coke can, the hot
molec- that they were moving faster?
- Well, there was steam coming out of it,
and then in the solid, everything's...
Molecules in solids are super slow. And
then as they move on to liquid then gas,
they move faster.
- Okay.
- And then you need heat to make liquid
into gas.
- How many of you think that this whole
molecules moving faster in a gaseous state
proves that heat moves faster than cold?
How many of you are kind of stuck on this
idea of cold? So let me ask you a
question, and I want you to think about it
for 10 seconds, then we might move on,
let's see. What is cold? Not looking for
examples of things that are cold but what
is cold? What is the idea of cold or
coldness? Okay, think about it for a
second. Ellie, what is cold?
- Well, it's like... It could be water
that's frozen in... I was thinking that
heat moves faster than, than cold because
if something was frozen, the molecules
wouldn't be moving that fast because if
they were they could try to push out on
that.
- Oh, then it might be [inaudible].
- Okay, so she gave me an example of what
is cold. But is coldness? So what, what
does that even mean? What does that even
mean? Anna.
- Shivering.
- What's that?
- Okay, shivering is because you are cold.
What is coldness? Okay... [inaudible]
- I think it's when the temperature is
really low and everything's kind of darkness, when
you think of the sun warm, it's really
warm, when you have the sun. But it's
when you think of something cold, it's... sometimes.
- Okay, I want... You guys are giving me
some really good examples of what cold is.
Here's what I want to think about... Okay,
how to phrase this... Is there a such
thing as cold? And if so, how would you
define it?
- It's a hard question!
- Oh!
- You got to answer! Get ready to answer!
Get ready, and do one quick response and
then we're going to put it aside for now,
and we're going to move on. Come on,
Hunter.
- No, because it's just heat that's a...
That's just water that can be heated or
[Background Chatter].
- Heat, heat is cold. Heat is that.
- Yeah, it's like...
- Heat, that's cold.
- Yeah.
- Oh.
- So it's all just kind of a scale? Like
you got hot over here and cold over here,
and you're talking about there's less heat
over here than there is here?
- Heat has cold molecules.
- Heat has colder?
- All right. So here's what we're going to
do, we're going to talk more about this
later. We're going to move on to the next
question for now. Here we go.