- [Stephen] From the top.
- [Paul] This way?
- [Stephen] Starting from the top.
Woo hoo!
- [Paul] That went better.
(Background Chatter)
- [Paul] Can we have a ruler?
- [Girl] Yeah.
- [Stephen] 75.
- [Teacher] Okay, make sure you record it. 75 what?
- [Paul] 75 cm
- [Teacher] C-M. What's C-M stand for?
- [Paul] Centimeters!
- Centimeters.
- [Student] Okay, now we've got to get the average.
- [Student] I'm gonna do the average.
- [Teacher] Go ahead, go to your next one.
I'm gonna check on the next group.
- [Student A] Okay, no you don't
put 75 for all of them.
- [Paul] I'm not.
- [Stephen] Just on that one. We knew
it wouldn't go any farther.
Just put 75 for the first one.
- [Paul] Second part.
- [Stephen] Trial two.
Now, what do we do?
- [Teacher] Okay, go ahead. Tell
me what you found out?
What did you discover about bubble wrap,
sand paper, wax paper
and just the plain ramp?
- [Brunette Girl] On the bubble wrap, it didn't go.
Because it was a bumpy surface.
Because all the bumps,
because it was too bumpy
and had to much friction.
- [Teacher] Too much friction, okay.
And so, what did you discover, Sean?
- [Sean] I discovered that on the sand paper
it got higher and lower
- [Teacher] What do you mean by that,
higher and lower, and higher?
Can you explain that
a different way to me?
- [Sean] well-- (Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] So what does that say about the surface?
- [Sean] (Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Increase and decrease.
Spencer, what did you discover?
- [Spencer] So--(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] So it went farther on plain
wrap versus the wax paper?
- [Spencer] Yeah.
- [Teacher] Okay, so, right now
you're going to find
the average, right?
How are you gonna find the average?
- [Spencer] Like 32 plus, plus 30,
plus 41, divided by three.
- [Teacher] Okay, you guys go ahead and do that.
Who's going to be the calculator?
- [Sean] I am.
- [Teacher] You are? Okay.
I might suggest someone
else also be the calculator,
so you can compare your numbers,
and then I'm gonna come back
and talk to you about your results. Okay?
- [Teacher] Okay, let's sit down.
Let's see what your doing.
- [Student] It's not going very
good on the sand paper.
- [Paul] Because it's just like the carpet.
- [Teacher] Why won't it go as far on sandpaper?
- [Paul] Because it's like the carpet.
- [Teacher] Okay, what does that
tell you about friction?
- [Paul] That if it's sand paper it
doesn't have a lot of contact--
- [Girl] It rubs against the rug.
- [Stephen] It rubs against the tires--
I think it doesn't--
- [Teacher] One person at a time. Paul?
- [Paul] Because it rubs up against the tires
and it doesn't have a lot of friction.
If it did have a lot of
friction it would go faster.
- [Teacher] Okay, so does sand paper have
friction, or not? Yes or no?
- [Students] No. No.
- [Students] (Reconsider) Yes.
- [Teacher] What is friction?
One person at a time.
- [Paul] It's like...whoosh.
- [Teacher] That's friction? Hm.
Okay, can you explain,
what is your idea, Stephen?
Friction?
- [Stephen] When a car rolls on carpet,
it's friction because it slows it down.
Sand paper slows it down, too.
- [Teacher] So far, what have you
discovered about friction,
and wax paper versus sand paper?
- [Paul] Wax paper--
- [Teacher] Let's let Stephen tell me, okay?
- [Stephen] Wax paper is, kinda like,
it's probably gonna be like the...
- [Teacher] Look at your numbers and what
have you discovered so far?
Because you already recorded them.
- [Girl] It's the highest so far.
- [Teacher] What does that mean,
it's the highest so far?
- [Stephen] It's the one that has the
least amount of friction.
- [Teacher] It has the least
amount of friction, okay?
And how do you know that?
- [Stephen] Because we did the experiment.
- [Teacher] And what happened?
- [Stephen] It didn't go as far...
- [Teacher] It didn't go as far on what?
- [Stephen] (Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Okay, go ahead an
finish your experiment.
Go ahead and finish on the plain ramp,
you have one more to do, I see here.
Okay? And then we'll talk
about what we should do next.
- [Student] Oh, 39.
- [Teacher] That's showing you more
about fourth dimension.
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Let's talk about our results.
Talk about your results
that you've noticed. Sh.
Stephen, Tanner, I need to be
able to hear this group, okay?
- [Sean] We found now, that our total
averaged out to 85cm.
- [Sean] (Background Chatter)
- ...for our total average.
- [Teacher] Okay, what does this tell
you? Look at your averages.
What does this tell you about friction?
- [Brunette Girl] That friction slows you down,
like the salt slows you down on ice.
Like the plain ramp is kinda like the ice.
It makes you go faster.
- [Teacher] Right, and you know what
it's doing outside, right now?
What is it doing outside right now?
- [Brunette Girl] It's sleeting.
- [Teacher] It's sleeting, it's snowing,
and the roads are very, very slick.
So, what do you think's
gonna be a great idea,
because I know my husband's
coming home from work tonight.
The roads are gonna be slippery.
What's gonna happen so
they can create friction
so the roads are safer?
What should the road crews do?
- [Students] Salt.
- [Teacher] They can put salt and ...?
- [Students] Salt and sand.
- [Teacher] Salt and sand. Yes.
- [Spencer](Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Why?
- [Spencer] (Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] So it didn't go at all?
I wonder if it was small,
little bubble wrap,
if it would work better?
What do you think?
- [Sean] I think if they were popped--
- [Teacher] Oh, if they were popped, I
wonder if they would. Maybe so.
Okay, down here you have a graph
that we're gonna talk
about a little bit later.
But this is what I want you to do:
I want you to pretend
like you're a teacher,
and if you were going to
tell someone one thing
that you learned today from
this experiment that we did.
What would you tell them?
I want you to write it
on the back of here.
What's one thing that you've learned today
that you would teach someone
and then we're gonna talk about it, okay?
I want you to talk about
it when you're done writing,
talk about it with each other
and I'll be back in a minute, okay?
- [Spencer] We can share when we're done writing.
- [Sean] Or we can share them as we write them.
So, what would we tell someone?
- (Background Chatter)
- [Spencer] I would say friction on the ramp
would make something go slower.
What would you say?
- [Brunette Girl] I would say the rougher the
surface, the more friction.
- [Sean] I would say something
about the same thing
that you guys were saying,
except a little bit different.
I would say...
it depends on which kind of surface it is.
If it's bumpy,
it won't go.
If there's bumps and air all over on it.
If it's a smooth and soft surface,
it will probably go a lot faster.
- [Teacher] So, tell me what you--
are you still writing?
- [Sean] We all shared it.
- [Teacher] Okay, but I want to see it in writing.
Like I want to see something written down.
- [Brunette Girl] I said the bumpier the surface
the more friction it makes.
- [Teacher] Okay-- (Background Chatter)
Spencer, what are you gonna write?
- [Spencer] Because I'm gonna write kind
of the same thing as Heather.
- [Teacher] Is there anything your
gonna change about it?
Or add to it?
- [Spencer] I'm gonna say the bumpier
the ramp is
the more friction
and the less... and the less
further it goes.
- [Teacher] Okay, I like that.
I think you guys are
learning a lot about this.
Sean, I see your writing
something a little bit different.
What are you writing?
- [Sean] I'm writing the smoother the surface,
the farther the car goes.
- [Teacher] You guys are right. The
farther it goes. Because why?
- [Sean] Because the friction,
because the surface is too bumpy
and it has a lot of friction
so it was causing it to not go.
But on a smoother surface--
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Barely any what?
What word is she looking for?
She said on a smoother surface
there's barely any friction.
And I like what you said.
You said "A smooth surface is like ice."
A smooth surface is like ice, right?
- [Brunette Girl] I said the bumpier the
surface, the more friction.
- [Teacher] Right, but you also said, something,
that if it was a smooth
surface, it's kinda like ice.
There's no friction to keep it from,
like if it's outside today,
if it's ice, your car could go anywhere,
but putting sand down or
the salt, keeps it ...
- [Brunette Girl] Less friction.
- [Teacher] More, it has more friction.
Okay. Okay, go ahead and finish. What?
What do you want?
- [Sean] I wonder what would
happen if you tried snow
and see if it would run on
snow and then we tried ice.
- [Teacher] Oh, so how would be do that?
I like that. How would we do it?
- [Sean] When it's like an icy day or something
and there's a little bit of ice somewhere,
we could bring the car out or something,
not like a real car--
- [Teacher] Oh, okay. (Chuckles)
- [Sean] Just like a play car--
- [Teacher] And try it out.
- [Sean] Try it out on ice
and then they would put a little snow
and then we would try
and see if it would go faster
on the snow or on the ice.
- [Teacher] How could we change this experiment?
What could we do next time
if we wanted to change it
to find something different out?
- [Brunette Girl] I think you could use a plain surface
and you could probably
use popped bubble wrap.
- [Teacher] We talked about that.
Popped bubble wrap,
and what else did you say?
The bubble wrap could be what?
Talk about that, the
bubble wrap could be what?
Guys, I need you to not come in here.
- [Brunette Girl] You can use
un-popped bubble wrap
and you can use the tile,
and you probably use, like
a grid with the marbles.
Instead you can, like, use a car.
- [Teacher] Okay, talk about that.
- [Brunette Girl] To see if it would fall off.
- [Teacher] Now, what would be the purpose
to see if it would fall off?
With force and motion,
how does that tie in?
- [Brunette Girl] Well, what I mean is,
will it like go far...
- [Sean] If you make a ramp
and you try to get it on
and wanted to see if it
would fall off or not...
- [Brunette Girl] Like if it was on the--
- [Sean] It depends how fast it would go,
if it went faster would it fall off?
- [Teacher] But if we're talking about friction,
does this have anything
to do with friction?
- [Spencer](Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Oh, I love that. So,
wood, carpet, and ice.
And we could freeze ice, because
we have big containers...