[chatter]
- All right, so we're going to need
someone from all the groups to kind of
summarize for us.
- Grace?
- Guys, raise your hands.
[chatter]
- So I figured... okay, you guys
should
[inaudible].
All right, I need everybody on the floor,
and you two groups sit right here, okay?
Everybody's on the floor, criss-cross
applesauce, in five. Five, four, three
two... and one.
Okay. I need you to stay where you are and
just turn around, and I'll just have the
people come talk to me, and they'll talk
to you, all right? We're going to start
with... let's see. We're going to start
with group one, all right? People from
group one, raise your hand. Okay.
Will you girls come up and tell me what
you guys talked about? And I'm going to
listen.
- Our question was, select three
characteristics that you think is most
important for school and tell why. So we
had our score card, and it said stuff. So
then the first one we did was my manners,
because if you're nice, that means that
you're polite, and then you get more
friends.
- All right. Next?
- Following directions, because you won't
have good behavior and you won't do good
on a test if you don't follow directions
and you don't do, like, your study guide,
or study, then you won't do good on a
test. And our last one is behavior in
class, is because behavior is sort of like
not listening, because then you probably
won't listen if you're just
doing, like...
- All right. Thank you. Now tell us,
everybody, we're doing this, and everybody
can answer. So how do you think that
relates to a job? Behavior? Yes.
- If you have good behavior, then you'll
get somebody to hire you, because you can
work good.
- If you have good behavior, most likely
you'll get hired, because you
[inaudible].
Anybody else? Nobody else? Yes, ma'am.
- Um... it's sort of like what they
said, but if you have good behavior when
you're working your job, you won't get
fired.
- Okay. You won't get fired. And, you
know, good behavior is one of those things
such as coming to work on time, okay? If
there's nobody there to work your
position, then your teammates have to pick
up the work, or the work doesn't get done.
Okay, group two, let's see. Lauren, go
ahead, come up and read your question and
answer, please.
- What is a non-traditional career for a
male and a female? And, um...
- Go ahead.
- We wrote for a male, a fashion and a
nail designer.
- That's right.
- And then for a female, a pilot and a car
designer.
- Good, good. Can someone... thank you.
Can someone give me some more ideas about
some things...let's see. I'm going to
call...I'm looking at colors. I'm
going to pick somebody with this color on.
And you can take your jacket off, and I'm
still going to call your color, if it's
your color, red. Give me a job that you
think might be a non-traditional career.
One for a woman. What did you... I
mean, you can use the video as an example.
You want to think about it?
- Construction worker.
- A construction worker as a woman. My
color's red. Yes, sir.
- For a woman or a male?
- It could be for a male or female. Or you
can, it doesn't even matter. Skyler.
- For a girl, maybe a football coach.
- For a female, definitely a football
coach. If you guys watch Glee,  you see
the football coach is a male, a female.
And so, yeah. But now, Sakwan, we're going
to go with you last, and then I'm going to
go to group three.
- Um... for a male, probably a teacher?
- A male as a teacher. Exactly. So let's
have Grace... not Grace.
- Alex.
- Mallory. Mallory, do you have a V under
your name?
- Yes.
- You're from group three? So let's, let
me read yours, and you guys answer. You
can stay there. Let me read it, and you
guys answer. So group three was, using
what you have learned about
non-traditional careers, what would you
say to someone when they say that a boy
can't do a job, or a girl can't? And I
will just let you guys read.
- I would say that it doesn't matter if
you're a male or a female, as long as you
like your job and you can do your job
well. Nobody can tell you that you can't
do something just because you're a boy or
a girl.
- Good. Does anybody disagree with that
one? No? Does anybody agree with that
statement? Okay. All right. Sakwan, come
up, do, you guys are going to do number
four, and we're going to move to the next
activity.
- Our question is, what plans do we have
for being successful in schoolwork? We
wrote, do your homework, follow
directions, paying attention, being
respectful, good grades and not shouting
loud. And the
[inaudible]
oh yeah. And don't have some, like,
yelling or, like, stealing things, like...
- Report cards.
- Yeah, but, no.
- [inaudible]
- Yes.
- Well, we did a couple, like,
[inaudible].
Writing is a little challenging. Reading,
easy, some books.
- Okay. So they went with the idea of, you
know, not too easy, not too hard. Good.
Thank you. Now what we're going to do now
is we're going to do some research on
non-traditional careers. Now, some of you
will be where the purple papers are. Some
of you will be where the white ones are.
And it's just so that you guys will be
able to talk about this later and say,
okay, this is what I experienced on a
policy job, and this is what I experienced
on the other one. So everybody point your
attention to the front, and I'm going to
go through one of the worksheets with you.
I'm going to go through the harder
worksheet with you, okay? Just point your
attention to the front.
And I'm going to go through this one with
you, because this one is the hardest one,
and then all the other ones are the easier
ones. Okay, the worksheet that we're going
to do today is going to tie in what you
guys talked about with careers, subjects.
When do you all get report cards?
- We got it yesterday.
- You got them yesterday. What I want you
to do is I want you to think about your
report card, your favorite subject,
whether it be English, math, science,
social studies, whether it be PE, art,
whatever it is, and I want you to pick
from this site. You see this site? It says
www.bls.gov/k12/, okay? I want you to pick
from that site your, what subject you did
the best in, or what your best interest
is. There are some of you, I know somebody
here likes nature. They will pick nature,
and in that job, if it's a boy, he's going
to pick a job that he thinks mostly
females have.
Who thinks they can give me an idea of
what job mostly females have? Molly?
- Maybe a veterinarian.
- A veterinarian. Most veterinarians I've
seen have been female. So I would go
there. And if I was a boy, I would read
through this sheet. On this sheet, it has
some questions. It says how to get ready.
You'll find that tab, and you'll give me a
summary of how they get ready for this
job. It says what is this job like. You
read that, and you'll give me a one or two
sentence summary of what the job is like.
And it says, are there other jobs like
this? That's to the bottom. And you can
write those jobs down. Another one says,
what about the future? And you'll write a
one or two minute summary of that section.
Also, we have some reflection questions at
the bottom of this worksheet, and the
reflection question is, one is, what did I
learn about careers? The other one is
what's a non-traditional career, and the
last one is what did I learn about myself?
So make sure you answer all those
questions in the worksheet. Now, if I was
a girl and I went to nature, what job do
you think I would pick Alea?
What job do you think most boys have
that's over here for nature?
- Zookeeper?
- Maybe a zookeeper. So the object of this
is to do research in the area that you
find most interesting. Is this what I have
to be when I grow up, Mr. Nealy? No. You
just have to do research in that area. So
the big important part is to have research
done in that area, just so that you can
explore different jobs.
And I think, was it group three that had
that question?
- Yeah.
- Group four that had the question about
what would you tell somebody? Who had that
question?
- Us.
- Group three had that question, and I
think you guys gave a pretty convincing
argument. Okay, I'm going to tell you
who's going to sit at the purple stations.
If you're sitting at a purple station,
you're going to click yes, you want sound.
And your worksheet is already there. And I
want us to compare and contrast the
different information you get from the two
worksheets. Okay, purple station. Skyler,
go to a purple station. Mr. Y-...