(Students passing around yarn)
- [Female Student] Well I can start.
I just kind of wanted
to follow with Lina's
going back to the very
beginning of the book,
and sort of I guess a
response to Mariana's comment.
I think that a big focus of the book
is sort of that beginning
story with the starfish,
like at the very very
beginning when she talks about
how one girl tosses back a
starfish and then she brings
all the other people
that toss back starfish,
so it's not about making this
huge change in one moment,
cause that's never going to happen.
It's about that one step where you inspire
somebody else to take the next step.
And since we are young adults, you know
if we take that step now and we continue
taking those little steps
throughout our entire lives,
before you know it
things are gonna change.
So even though it seems discouraging
like "oh it's really hard and upsetting",
and speaking from personal
experience it can be upsetting,
it's about continuing on and
taking those little steps.
- [Male Student] Yeah you know, at the same time I think
there's something hard about it,
but it's not something
that is beyond our control.
It's just--we don't want
to appear confrontational.
Because I thought we were
having this discussion on Friday,
I was listening in my
science and physiology class
to what people were
saying, and was listening
if there were any instances,
although it doesn't count
as racism, you count it as
prejudice by definition,
I was listening for instances and actually
something does kind of fit.
Because there was this one girl who was
talking about how her stepfather was
or her mom's boyfriend was really mean
and was always cheating on her mom
and yelling at her, and he said
"Oh I wish you were white, he wouldn't
do that stuff if you were white."
This was a black girl.
There was this other,
in my physiology class--
- [Female Student] Isn't that not racism?
- [Teacher] Well, that's not--
- [Teacher] Do you think she was
serious or don't you?
- [Male Student] I don't know, but you
know even if it's joking,
it's still a pretty serious thing to say.
And besides, there was a Mexican boy
in my third block class who was
making fun of one of his friends,
some relative saying
get a bean or a shnean (sic).
But you know, even as jokes
these still have effects
and these are instances
where I could have said
"Well no, that's not an
appropriate thing to say.
"That could be offensive to people."
But you know I didn't, just because
I didn't want to be confrontational.
So obviously that's some fault of my own
for not getting involved there.
- [Male Student] Going off of what Tomas said
about the ethnic jokes or whatever,
I'm wondering if you're considered
actively racist if those
jokes don't bother you.
Like I hear that all the time in my
third block class, and
it doesn't bother me.
It's kind of funny sometimes.
Because a lot of the
time it's not interracial,
it's the same race.
You know what I'm trying to say?
There's no Armenians, but
I can't roast another Armenian.
Should I throw this?
This is not gonna work.
- [Student] Laser it, bro.
- [Student] Maybe you
should just call on somebody
and then throw it.
(Class laughing)
- [Male Student] I think while racist
jokes can show racism
they can also show an amount of...
show how comfortable we
all are with other races
and I make fun of my parents, I make fun
of my teachers because
I'm comfortable with them.
(Class laughing)
- [Teacher] Maybe we
should talk about that.
- [Male Student] And I mean, I can
do it because we love each other
and (class laughs) it's okay,
it's unconditional.
So even if they may get annoyed at me
we become stronger from
making fun of each other.
I'm scared.
- [Male Student] So going back to
what Lina was saying
at the beginning and what Tomas was saying
a little later is with
the escalator thing,
I felt that was a good
metaphor for the system
but it also struck me as
a bit of a false dilemma.
She makes it out that
racism is the biggest
problem facing us today,
and not to say that
it's not a giant problem
but I feel like one can be
passively anti-racist
whilst working actively
towards anti-poverty,
anti-hunger, anti-war,
and making a difference in the world
whether it's in the
field of racism or not.
And then going back to what
Tomas said about the...
and I lost my point, what was it?
It'll come back to me. Who wants to go?
- [Teacher] I think Tatum would agree with you
and she would even I think say that
while you're actively
combating say poverty,
you are having a positive impact for,
say poor African American families.
And she points out the correlation,
statistically speaking
between ethnicity and class.
But one thing I want to say in relation
to some comments from over there is that
I think that one thing that it means to
become an adult, and I'm
thinking what Holly said,
is to suddenly be forced to think of
global concerns and think beyond
our own individual needs and wants.
And I think it's really as simple as that
what Tatum is asking of people.
That she's asking them now you consider
your duties to the people around you.
I want to hear from other people.
- [Student] I got my point
for Tomas, it's coming back.
It came back to me.
I had two points when I asked for the yarn
then I forgot one of them,
and I just remembered it.
- [Teacher] I want to encourage other
people to speak up too.
And we've got 10 minutes left.
There's a lot of voices that
haven't been heard yet today.
What I'm gonna do is something that
I'm gonna encourage
other people to do too.
I'm gonna toss it to somebody
who's not wanting to speak
and make them make their voice heard.
- [Student] I'll keep it short and then
I'll throw it to someone.
- [Teacher] Okay. Toss it to somebody who
doesn't have their hand raised though.
- [Student] So back to what Tomas said about
the confrontational
thing, is it's really hard
to strike that medium between either
being confrontational
or being patronizing.
And it's the fear of the
reaction of either one of those
that I think stops most
people from speaking up.
Like either confrontation
or you're appearing
patronizing and therefore destroying
racial relations even more.
So, Samuel?
- [Student] Yeah, sure.
Well I was gonna say out
of what Chris was saying
sometimes racial humor can actually--
I think while sometimes
it contributes to racism,
and I have a problem with telling too many
off-color jokes and gender-related jokes.
But I think sometimes that kind of humor
can start to eliminate prejudices
and bring that into
the broader dialogue and stuff.
So if you look at people like comedians
say like Dave Chappelle,
how many can say that he's
a racist person because he makes
lots of race-based jokes in his comedy?
On the contrary, I think he actually
helps bat those issues by
bringing that humor out.
- [Female Student] When Tatum mentions the fact that
she thinks there's no such thing as
being passively anti-racist,
I think what she means by that is like
it's sort of hard. I
actually got to mention
you know, our society we
have a lot of comic jokes
and all of these other things here present
in the system of housing and stuff is...
unweighted or whatever.
It's kinda difficult to...
how should I say it?
I don't know what I was trying to say.
I can't put it out into words but
anyways, I kinda agree
and disagree with her.
It's like you can do
little things to change,
however what I was trying to say is that
it's a lot out there
and it may be difficult.
That was all I was trying to say.
I don't even know. Here you go.
- [Female Student] What I would say about
jokes and stuff at times it shows that
you know we're addressing
it sorta kinda in a way,
but at the same time it just shows
how much we see it played
out in our society.
And then for some people that say it
that aren't actually
trying to make a difference
it's like, I mean it's gonna
be hard to make a change
and be like "Hey, let me correct that."
Because to them it's just
like all fun and games.
But to us it's like, okay. Yeah. (laughs)
- [Male Student] It stopped.
It died.
I agree completely with
what Laticia is saying.
Although for instance how Sam was saying
about Dave Chappelle,
although people make jokes
as they do address that in that manner,
it's not like people make
jokes so people understand
that "Oh, we need to
break these stereotypes."
I've come to realize that
every joke has a little
bit of truth in it.
Obviously yes, by making
these stereotypical jokes
yes we're addressing it, but my point
I guess is just it doesn't necessarily
prove that people are anti-racist.
- [Male Student] Alright, I just wanted to say
the question, the prompt is why is there
no such thing as being
passively anti-racist?
And it's because racism is so ingrained
in our system and our being.
From when we're born we're exposed
to racism consistently.
And because of that we can't
be passively anti-racist.
Our default setting for the
most part is being racist.
Not overly racist, but we are.
So it's not possibe just to
not be racist by being alive.
Once you come to being in
this world, you are racist.
You can't change that,
so that's why there's
no such thing as being
passively anti-racist.
You have to work at being anti-racist.
It just doesn't happen.
- [Female Student] So I completely agree
with what Wyatt's saying.
The way I look at racism
is it's like a poison
and once you've been injected or
you know, whatever to it,
it stays in your system forever.
And there's always gonna
be a little part of it
no matter how much you try
to get it out of your system
there's always gonna be a
little bit of it in you.
So before you can fix the
people who have been exposed
you have to get to the source
of the poison and stop it.
Which would be parents or teachers.
I don't know.
- [Teacher] I'm a source of it?
(Class laughing)
- [Female Student] You know like crazy teachers
who say the wrong thing
and then students go home and like,
"Oh yeah my teacher said this" and then
they go and tell their
other friends and stuff
and they kind of get passed around.
I don't know, it's not
you. I'm just saying.
(Class laughing)
- [Teacher] I don't believe you.
- [Male Student] Yeah, I agree with Wyatt and Brooks
because I think that
we were talking about how Disney movies
may have these subliminal
racist undertones
but at the same time,
there are racial undertones
to everything that anyone
says, basically, right?
There are always implicit messages which
aren't necessarily said overtly
which may come through to
the way people word things.
There are subtle subtle messages
and the attributes come
through peoples' speaking.
So everyone's totally surrounded by
all sorts of prejudices from
all sorts of different sources
from the time they can understand words.
So, yeah.
(class laughing)
If someone's gonna hit you in the face,
it might as well be this.
- [Male Student] I want to go back to
what Brooke just said about
parent kin thinking about racism.
I mean, how many times have you ever
hear your parents saying teach
you a lesson about racists?
They don't even try. (class laughing)
They might just give you some parental
info on your surrounding.
Or just say those joke
you were talking about.
- [Teacher] So you're
saying that you think
parents should have
conversations with kids?
- [Male Student] I'm saying that parents
should know how to
combat racism, and they don't even try.
- [Male Student] Going back to what Ryan
said earlier,
I agree because if they keep using
racist jokes as jokes then
it will become overused
and kind of a cliché so people
won't want to use it anymore.