- [Instructor] Present your position to the
other side. Make sure that you include the
SFI that backs up your position. Okay?
After that three minutes, we'll swap
sides. All right. So, three minutes, pros
go right ahead.
[Background Chatter]
- We're talking about how minorities have made
a lot of progress since Reconstruction,
and political things. Originally, there was
no black senators or congressman, but after
Reconstruction, around 1865, there was two black senators
and fourteen congressmen, and now there's four black senators
and I'm sure more black congressmen.
- It's like quadruple the representatives.
- And other minorities are representative-- represented
in the House and Senate, so they've made a lot of
progress becoming a representative government.
[Background Chatter]
- They didn't have the knowledge of earlier.
So that's one way Reconstruction positively affected
education in the South... in America...
[Background Chatter]
Also these statistics show that even though...
even though certain states are slightly low
on the circulation per capita statistics
Virginia is number fifteen, which is relatively high for
a Southern state.
Except Florida is number thirty-four.
And not all Northern states were held higher than--
education held higher than Southern states.
Like Pennsylvania, West Virginia, and Delaware,
which are all Northern states,
are in relatively low positions on the scale.
[Background Chatter]
- And former slaves were able to kind of give back
more to the culture, and they influenced technology,
and science, and advances in those. And kind of
started influencing culture in the South and
kind of in all the United States.
[Background Chatter]
So... and it really basically spread freedom
through the South and finally gave the former
former slaves a voice and a place in the country.
And finally brought them together.
[Background Chatter]
Y'all have anything else?
- [Boy]: I found...
- [Girl]: The ones... they could like
progress forward and they could [inaudible]...
because they have so many African-American positions
and authors for that... for that.
I think, overall, it finally gave blacks a place
and gave the South a place in the country again,
where they had been separated for so long.
Kind of started bringing everybody together again.
- Because after the Civil War, the South still thought
that 'We don't have to cooperate with the North...'
[Timer Beeps]
- All right, guys. That was pro. All
right. Three minutes, let's here the anti.
Three minutes and then we'll after...
Listen real quick, guys. After this three
minutes, we'll give it another minute,
okay, and one more minute after that for a
rebuttal, okay. For the final statement of
the pros, okay? Go ahead, antis.
- 1865 [inaudible] time of Reconstruction and
during... nothing really got done.
If you look at the statistics, the infant mortality
in Mississippi is number one and if you go on to the
lifestyle statistics, Mississippi is the very... has the
least number of museums, concert halls, and observatories
in city centers, showing the link between Reconstruction
and just how it affected the South and how nothing got done
after the Civil War.
- [Instructor]: Let me, I'm sorry to interrupt,
let me ask you this...
What caused... I mean, there had to have been something
I mean... during Reconstruction, everything was progressing.
Something happened to cause that overwhelming
shift in numbers that you just pointed out
That, you know, the Southern states - the old
Confederate states - dominated the bottom of that poll.
Why do you think that is?
Why would that happen?
- Because the North is trying to punish the South.
after the Civil War.
- They're more focused on helping themselves
and not helping the South
- Because they're more focused on slavery than
actually trying the help the South because they
were trying to punish them. So they didn't...
They were trying the free the slaves
they weren't trying to help the South because
they didn't want them to become stronger, also.
- [Instructor]: Was there a particular event that really
solidified this, that really made that come to fruition?
[Background Chatter]
What is it the time frame of your question?
- 1865 to 1877
- Okay, so...
- During Reconstruction.
- Right.
So what happened at the end of Reconstruction?
Why 1877?
[Background Chatter]
What happened in 1877?
- They took the military out of the South.
- Exactly
[Background Chatter]
So, if the military was pulled out, what do you
think caused this result?
[Background Chatter]
- ...economic constraints imposed by Northern owners
and eventual overseas competition hampered development
and Birmingham never developed into the world-class
steel-making center that it was supposed to be.
So yeah, it did sort of improve, but it just
never reached its potential because, and it even says
hampered by Northern constraints. So the North basically
said you can't produce more steel because we say so.
So you can't... so Birmingham just couldn't really get
any better at that point.
[Background Chatter]
- So the South has more industry now, like everything in
the South is [timer beeps] in the lower twenty-eight percent.
- Okay, guys, listen. We're going to give
you one more minute. You have a one minute
period, the pros, if you want to add a
little rebuttal to what you just heard,
okay. After this minute we're going to
take two minutes to compile our final
position, okay, like our final little
thesis, all right, that we're going to
present then to the class. Okay. So one
minute for a rebuttal from the pros. Go
ahead.
[Background Chatter]
- Because, since the military left, everybody revolted, so...
- They had no motivation.
- Everything that had been implemented for those years
went out the window and... [laughter]
- But I think it's still, a positive way, was that it at
least it still left kind of some ideas of how to keep order
and the South still kind of had gotten a taste from the
military on how the Americans wanted things run and how
they needed to do to function as America and...
so I think that mostly the military Reconstruction
like that was good, because it kind of came in and
helped them that way.
[Background Chatter]
- [Instructor]: What is the number of African-American
senators and representatives?
What does it show? What is the difference between
Reconstructive-Era... [timer beeps]... huge difference.
- All right, guys, listen up. You get two
minutes. I need each side to compile your
final argument, okay, your final
statement. This is what you're going to
present to the rest of the class. Remember
you need SFI to back up your position,
okay. That SFI can be census data. More
importantly, it can be book data. Okay.
Just normal, normal information from your
text. So two minutes, go ahead and write
it out if you want. Go.
[Background Chatter]
Each side comes up with their final points.
- We could go into more detail on the three-fifths compromise
and we could mention the Ku Klux Klan intimidated... even though
they got the vote, they were still controlled by the white people.
- Yeah, the social system still was there.
OK, I'll write that down.
[Background Chatter]
- Could this be applied too?
- [Instructor]: Absolutely
Remember, you have to explain to the class in
a way that they can understand it, okay?
They don't have that particular census data in
front of them. So make sure that you're clear
when you present that as SFI in front of the class.
[Background Chatter]
- Tell them how many libraries and [Background Chatter]
- Virginia is the only one that's in the top fifty percent.
- Completed out of fifty, and so... [Background Chatter]
All the Southern states are in the bottom... [Background Chatter]
And then, this is trying to say, what? Twenty-five right here?
Oh, so the bottom twenty-five, half... [Background Chatter]
Existing at the time, which was... [Background Chatter]
Should we tell them that these states aren't... [Background Chatter]
or should we just not tell them? [Background Chatter]
- No, I would just... [Background Chatter]
[Background Chatter]
- Most African-Americans that were unskilled at the time,
worked through this program to become more independent workers
and to learn to read and write, and so...
I'll go back to my statistics here, Virginia and Florida
[timer beeps]
All right, guys, we're going to go in this
order. Listen up. We're going to go in
this order. We're going to go economic,
then social, political, then educational.
Okay. The pros are going to give their
positions first to the class. All right?
Now, the chart that you have in front of
you, what I want you guys to do is while
the rest of the groups are presenting
their findings, their positions, I want
you to take down three different pieces of
information that you hear, specific pieces
of information that you guys hear from the
presenter. All right. Because you're going
to use this when you formulate your own
response at the end of class to how you
feel about, you know, the efficacy of
Reconstruction, based on what you've heard.
Okay. You're going to make your decision,
so you need to make sure that you have
information down to support that, okay, to
support your idea. And make sure you're
getting that from their presentations. All
right? So we're going to go with economic
first. Economic pro, you have two minutes.
Camille, you it?
- [Camille] Yeah.
- All right. Everybody listen to Camille.
- Okay. So we came up with a thesis and it
was, "Reconstruction positively affected
America economically by bringing a broader
selection of products to the South and
North. And the North was trying to find
ways to help the South with the 13th and
14th Amendments." And so, Birmingham, and
Alabama, and Mississippi, and everyone,
they started mining for coal, and iron,
and everything, and so that helped their
economies because they were able to make
more money with that instead of just
cotton.
And the North put a few restrictions on
that, but that still helped their economy
for more products. And the North
manufactured more, like, grain. And we
talked about other things that weren't
really economic. That was about it,
that we could come up with.
- Okay. Thank you. All right.
Anti? Who is our speaker today? Okay,
Grant, go ahead.
- [Grant] All right. So you mentioned the
steel, and iron, and coal industries, and
yes, those did help. But at the same time,
the North industries, the North's economy
was growing, and it was growing faster
than the South. And there was the whole
economic deals with inflation, where... So
the South basically was making more, like
a higher number of dollars, but it
essentially was the same work as before
the war.