- What are some other
indicators that tell us,
"I'm in my target heart rate range?"
Yes.
- [female student] By the
categories on your RPE chart.
- Okay, your RPE Chart,
you could use that.
That's exactly right.
How about within your body?
What's something that
your body can tell you
that you're in that target heart rate range?
Yes young lady.
- [female student] Um, the way you breath
and how you're feeling.
- Okay good, your breathing, your feeling,
some of you want to come
in here and work out
and then talk about how that
your legs startin' to hurt
and your thighs are startin' to be sore.
All those things are physical ways
that your body's sayin',
"Hey, I'm doin' a good job
"in this workout, I'm within
my target heart rate range."
When we do this today,
I want you to kind of
take a mental picture.
Let, take a mental picture
of, "This is how my body feels
"when I'm in my target heart rate range."
Whether your lower end or higher end,
take a mental picture
so that when you're out
walking or, not walking,
but when you're out running
or playing soccer or playing
basketball or things like that,
you can kind of have an idea
how you're feelin' with those,
with those things,
and you can know whether you're close
to being in your target heart rate range.
Now, one of the last things is,
is we filled out that
family health history
that each of you has there
and some of you had some different things
on that health history,
from heart disease,
to high blood pressure,
those types of things.
The cardio workout that we're doin' today,
what areas is that gonna positively impact
on that family health history for you?
Who knows that?
What are some of those areas?
Okay, Let's get you there Amy.
- [Amy] It'll help prevent heart disease,
high blood pressure and diabetes.
- Okay, the heart disease,
that's exactly right.
Good cardio, high blood pressure,
it's gonna bring the blood pressure down.
Also, diabetes.
Along with high blood pressure,
you got high cholesterol.
All of those areas,
cardio, is going to
positively impact those areas.
Okay?
The, yes?
- [female student] What
do I need to lose weight?
- Okay, to lose weight.
That's a question I get a lot of time.
If you want to lose weight,
ideally, you want to be in the upper end
of your target heart rate range,
or about 80%, however,
you do actually at about
60%, at your lower end,
you do burn more cal, fat
calories at about 60%,
but you're gonna burn more calories at 80%
because it's a more intense workout, okay?
So really, ideally,
you'd want to be within
your target heart rate range.
Typically, up towards the higher
end will be a little better
because, if you're gonna be able
to burn a few more calories
than at the lower end.
Okay?
Any other questions on anything?
All right, we're gonna get started here.
You've already got your
target heart rates, there.
I want you to look here,
and I want you to send that
text to this poll everywhere
to where your target heart rate zone is.
What is your zone?
And we'll notice this,
most of you, you know,
we've all figured it out.
You'll notice percentage wise
where most of you are gonna stand,
or where most of you are
gonna be in the chart.
We start all the way down at 100,
go all the way up to above 176.
You'll start to see, that,
that most likely that 151
to 175, that's gonna be
our biggest area here that
we're gonna fall into.
You can see right there, we're at 75%,
83%, within that area,
17% at 176 or higher.
So most of you in here, where's
our target heart rate range?
In between?
- [female student] Between 151 and 175.
- There you go, between 151 and 175.
That is right on the money
for young adults your age.
If you're at that 176 or
higher, that's not a problem,
but that is an area where, you know,
anything over about 185 or so,
then it just means that
you've got to bring your
heart rate up a little bit
higher compared to most people.
So most people though, again,
are gonna be in that 151 to 175.
That's a good job.
Okay, go ahead and go
to your machines here.
Lay your clip boards off to the side.
If you want to listen to
your ipod or to your music,
you can, only one ear phone though,
only one ear piece.
Make sure you put your cell phones up
in the cubby there, we'll do something
with those a little bit later.
And where we're gonna start with here
is we're gonna start together.
We're gonna start with
a two minute workout.
On this workout, two minute warm-up.
All we're gonna do is get warmed up.
You need to be out on the bike,
somewhere around 40 rpms.
Ellipticals, about the
same thing, 35 to 40 rpms.
On the treadmills, around
three speed will be a good,
good place to start with.
Is everybody good, we ready to go?
- (several students in unison) Yes.
Are we good back there?
You all set?
Okay, all right, here we go.
Startin' on two minutes.
And start.
All right so make sure that
we got those magnets on there.
Bump that up to about three or so.
Just to get warmed up.
(talking too low to be
heard over treadmills)
This is just gonna get your
heart rate up a little bit.
Now at the end of this warm up,
we're gonna check where
your heart rate is,
we're gonna check that
and you'll notice it will
be a little bit elevated
compared to, compared to, you know,
what it was for a resting heart rate.
You most likely will not be though,
in your target heart rate zone,
right here after this warm up.
(exercise equipment humming)
About halfway through.
Good job.
Anytime you work folks,
you should always do a warm up.
Now we've already stretched
and done some, a little bit of jogging
down there in the gym
before we came up here.
So you've got some warm up
but anytime you go to a fitness room,
you want to make sure that you
do a little bit of warm up.
Don't jump right in to it.
You're gonna have a tendency
to pull some muscles
and have a lot more soreness
and injury risk, for you.
Good job, everybody doin' good?
- (several students in unison) Yes.
- As we do this, I'm gonna come along
and ask you where you are on
your RPE chart periodically,
'Cause I want to know
how your body's feeling.
Just kind of look at that
and gauge where ever you are.
Okay?
Let's go ahead and get a
heart rate check, here.
Real quick, put your hands on the sensors,
let's get that heart rate checked.
As soon as you get that heart rate check,
go ahead and stop your machine, hop off
and we're gonna record
that under heart rate one,
real quick, under the warm up.
Okay, stop your machine there.
Record that heart rate.
[teacher] As soon as we get this,
go ahead lay those back off to the side,
we're gonna hop back over here
and we're gonna start
goin' through the workout.
Now the workout's gonna be 10 minutes.
Again, bikes, you outta be
pumpin' out about 80 to 85,
of your RPMs there.
Ellipticals, probably
somewhere between 70 and 75.
We really want to try to push this
so at the five minute mark
you're within that target heart rate zone.
Anybody right now in their
target heart rate zone?
- (several students in unison) No.
- No?
A little bit elevated
from the resting though?
- (several students in unison) Yes.
- Okay, all right.
Let's go ahead and start.
(exercise machines beeping and humming)
At the five minute mark,
we will check it again
and we will check that heart rate,
what your heart rate is.
We won't get off the machines again
until the work out's over.
[teacher] Caroline?
- [teacher] Now again, on your own,
once we get into this a couple minutes,
on your own, if you want to kind of gauge
where you are and check those sensors,
you're more than welcome to do that.
You just don't want to
do it the whole time
you're working out,
and that'll kind of give you
an idea where you're standing.
If you need, if you're
below your lower end
of that target heart rate,
go ahead and bump up the
resistance a little bit,
if that's the case, as we
continue on through this.
- [teacher] Are you all doin' good?
Where are we on the chart?
At 3?
That's good.
(talking below sound
of exercise equipment)
You all could do this for an hour, huh?
There you go.
(machines humming)
How you doin' over there?
Where are you on your chart?
- Two.
- That's good.
- Three.
- Two.
- I'd say around two.
Ladies, how we doin' over here?
How you feelin' on your chart?
- (several students in unison) Three.
- Three?
- Yeah.
- You good, Russell?
- Okay.
Andy, how you feelin?
Where are you, on your chart?
About four?
How do you feel, good?
Where are you on your chart?
Doin' good.
Most of you, you're all about a
two, three, four range right now.
Now we're just getting to
the start of the work out,
but here in a few minutes,
that's probably gonna change.
Might be changing right now.
Probably startin' to feel
a little bit of fatigue,
breathing's becoming a
little bit more difficult.
We're gonna do a heart
rate check in two minutes.
Again, remember, I want
you, mental picture
in your mind, "How is my
body feeling when I'm in
"that target heart rate range?"
Doing a good job, good job.
(speaking below level of equipment)
Okay we got one more minute
and we're gonna get a
heart rate check, here.
- [teacher] If you're feelin'
like your in that 4 to 6 range,
you might be able to
go ahead and up your,
up your intensity just a little bit there,
up your speed maybe, up your
resistance a little bit.
Russell, did you forget to
put your phone on vibrate?
- Yeah.
- That's all right, buddy.
Just don't mess with it
while you're on the bike, okay?
I mean while you're on the treadmill.
- Okay.
- Okay, hard to do, hard
to do anything with a phone
while you're running.
All right, let's go ahead and
get a heart rate check here.
Get a quick check.
Remember what this number is.
This is gonna be heart rate
number two on your chart.
We want to be within that range now.
If you're not, we need
to up your resistance.
If you're at the lower end,
I want to try to get on up towards the higher end,
about that 80% mark.
So if that's the case, bump
your speed a little bit,
up your resistance if you need to.
We're gonna get one more check here
in about four and a half minutes.
(speaking below level of machines)
- About 65, I'm in my range.
- Nice, nice.
(machines drowning out voices)
Where are you on your RPE chart?
- Uh, about four.
- About four?
Four or five?
(machines drowning out voices)
Hey, anytime, you know if you're saying,
"God, I just can't get
my heart rate up there,"
if you're on the treadmill,
increase that elevation a little bit.
Elliptical, if you
increase the resistance,
then you'll start to feel it.
How's Callie back here?
She's startin' to get
it right now, aren't ya?
(machines drowning out voices)
How are you all on your chart?
Five or six?
Where are you all on your chart?
- [female student] Five.
- [teacher] Five?
- [female student] Six.
- [teacher] Where are
you guys on your chart?
- [male student] probably around four.
- Ladies how we doin'?
Where are you on your chart?
- [female student] About six.
- [teacher] Six?
- [female student] Yes.
- [teacher] How are you, Russell?
- [Russell] Six, seven.
- How about you?
- [female student] Six.
- [teacher] Six?
- [teacher] Dale, where are you?
- [Dale] Three, four.
- [teacher] Three, four?
You need to increase your resistance,
I mean your elevation a little bit.
How about you?
- [male student] Four?
- Four.
- Most of you are comin' up on that chart.
Comin' up!
Okay, we're gettin' ready
to do another check here.
Good.
A couple more minutes here.
Everybody doing okay?
- (several students in unison) Yup.
- Are you startin' to feel
some of the signs we talked about,
fatigue in the legs?
- (several students in unison) Yes.
- I know it's hard to talk right now.
A little more difficult breathing.
- (teacher) Startin'
to feel it a little bit
more now, aren't you?
- (male student) yeah, a little bit.
(machines drowning out teacher talking)
- [teacher] How's it going back here?
My legs are like rubber (laughs).
So now you know, you just
got increase that resistance
a little bit and keep
it at the same RPMs.
- One mile, Kyle.
- [teacher] Okay, in thirty seconds here,
we're gonna get a heart rate check.
Then we're going into the cool down.
You really push it right here.
You're about to jump off
the elliptical, aren't you?
Good.
Okay, let's get a heart rate check here.
Heart rate check.
Grab those sensors.
Remember this number.
When you get this number,
when you've got this,
go ahead and bring your speed on down.
[teacher] We're goin'
into the cool down phase.
Make sure you remember
what that number was.
- [male student] What was your heart rate?
- [male student] Uh, 170.
- [male student] I'm about 169.
(background chatter)
- [teacher] In your cool down phase now.
There you go, good good.
Did we get in there, in
your range, in your range?
Everybody in your range?
65 over your target heart rate?
Great, good job.
Did you stay in heart rate range?
Good.
Now did anybody on that RPE chart
ever feel like you got up
to about an eight or a nine?
- [several students in unison] Yes.
- [teacher] You did?
Up there? All right.
Did ya'll get in your range?
- [two male students] Yup.
- [teacher] Did you get within your range?
Was ya'll on your upper end
or towards the lower end?
- [male student] Upper end.
- Tried to go up.
How about you guys?
Did you get in your range there?
- [male student] Yeah.
- [teacher] Yeah.
Now, here in
about 45 more seconds,
we're gonna get our last check here,
on the cool down.
You'll notice how quickly as you do this,
you'll be able to tell a major difference
from the last check that you did
during the workout, and even after this
two minute cool down here,
the difference
between where that heart rate drops to.
Are ya'll okay?
Okay, let's go ahead and get
that last heart rate check.