- Exactly. Right. So, what do you all
think about the fact that this is written
almost sort of journalistically? I know
you're the big newspaper man and
everything. What do you think about that?
- That's what I'm talking about. I'm
talking about the growth of the poem
overall. The first passage, it's almost
not objective, but it kind of states
what's happening. It doesn't actually say
what the author is thinking. As the poem
grows and goes on and goes to the next
passages, it becomes more poetic and more
descriptive and it's more of the author's
point of view and the author's stance on
what's happening.
- Nora, what do you think about the poem
so far?
- I thought it was a good, like,
utilization of the message. I'm taking
African American history this year.
- Okay.
- We've been talking about the slave trade
the last few weeks. So, that first part,
we were talking about how they were like
[inaudible],
the sickness.
- What are the specific lines that you
think best describe the sickness and the
death and everything?
- "We have jettisoned the blind to no
avail. It spread. The terrifying sickness
spreads. It's claws have scratched the
sight from the captain's eyes." The
slaves were all tied together in their own
[inaudible]
so the sickness and disease could spread
through them. But also, the slavers, like
the white people on the ship were also
susceptible to disease.
- That's where they got the idea of whites
becoming more like the blacks because
they're in such close quarters that it's
inevitable almost and the fact that they
are holding themselves above them,
superior as civilized, but they're still
acting acts of barbarism is very much a
historical principle.
- So, you really think that there's a
moment of transformation in this poem
where the whites, who are theoretically
the real barbaric people become like the
blacks, who they think are savages.
- I don't think it's even a point of
transformation. I believe that the author,
Robert Hayden, is talking about this as it
has been. So, this kind of opens in maybe
a stress when they're sailing on the slave
ship and they talk about this and it's
like there's all sorts of imagery
throughout this that implies that these
blacks are, er, these whites are becoming
like the blacks.
- What's your favorite line that shows
this, Nick?
- "Standing to America, bringing home
black gold, black ivory, black seed."
Now, I especially liked the middle part of
that, black ivory. Because ivory is
usually white.
- Of course. Yes.
- Yeah.
- So, you have the juxtaposition of black
and white.
- Yes.
- I think the lines after that, "Deep in
the festering hold thy father lies, of his
bones, New England pews are made, those
are altar lights that were his eyes."
Jordan, what do you think the about this
religious connotation?
- Well, seeing that I'm not too familiar
with the Bible-- Judaism and Christianity
are similar-- but in these two paragraphs
that you were just reading, I saw a big
contrast between the glory of taking back
these animals, these slaves and making the
best of them in the new world. Between
that and the evil that they're really
bestowing upon the slaves-- "Standing to
America, bringing home black gold, black
ivory, black seed," is kind of glory and
that contrast between evil, "Deep in the
festering hold thy father lies, of his
bones, New England pews are made, those
are altar lights that were his eyes."
- They also kind of need a religious
figure throughout this voyage because
throughout this we see that they're going
through a time of spiritual crisis.
"What port awaits us, Davy Jones or home?
I've heard of slavers drifting, drifting,
play things of wind and storm and chance,
their crews gone blind, the jungle hatred
crawling up on deck." It's like they
understand that they're becoming
uncivilized and they're trying to find a
way to change this.
- To justify their actions.
- Yeah.
- That's what they need, a justification
for their actions. So, they say God is
with them and everything is okay.
- And you have that sort of anaphora of
the hymn, that "Jesus our Savior pilot,"
throughout this entire thing that sort of
brings and invokes the God into all of
this so that it's almost as if to me,
they're looking for their justification.
They're looking to justify the horrific
actions that they're putting out.
- Which is ironic because these are often,
these spirituals are often sung by slaves
to get through all of the times of
turmoil. So, it's ironic that they're
claiming that God is on their side as a
justification for the enslaving of blacks.
- I think it's also ironic, though, that
the blacks are the ones who receive the
justification from a lot of the whites in
the new world. At the end talking about
John Quincy Adams, he says it was
completely justified what the blacks did
when they revolted and attacked the white
slavers. The suffering that they had been
enduring...
- And that's like the moment of irony.
- Yeah.
- The slavers are saying, "How paradoxical
indeed that you whose wealth, whose tree
of liberty are rooted in the labor of your
slaves should suffer the august John
Quincy Adams to speak with so much passion
of the right of chattel slaves to kill
their lawful masters..."
- "...And with his Roman rhetoric,
weave a hero's garland for Cinquez." This
is what I want you all to think about.
Think about the historical connections
here. John Quincy Adams, one of our
founding fathers, fourth president of the
United States
was ultimately the man who got freedom or
found freedom in court for Cinquez and the
other slaves that were on the Amistad,
which is a ship that, of course, being
discussed in here. Think about these
historical connections. I shall return.
All right, group. What's going on?
- We're talking about a poem.
- You're talking about a poem? I'm going
to talk about a poem, too.
- What a coincidence.
- I know. Isn't it coincidental? What's
going on? What are you all discussing so
far?
- We're looking for the marrow part.
- You're looking for the marrow part?
- Yeah.
- I'm glad you all have your "Beloveds"
out and everything. What really interests
me is the fact-- I think we have a real
instance here where the 60 million or more
to whom the book was dedicated. This is
their story, is it not? What do you all
think? How can we connect our reading of
this poem to our reading of "Beloved?"
- In the second part, in the last
paragraph, it says, "The fever is melting
down my bones."
- Yes.
- Right now we're connecting that to Stamp
Paid, who at some point had said that he
was tired in his marrow, as in his bone
marrow. We're looking for the page right
now.
- Okay. Found it.
- Okay.
- And it's on this.
- Whoa. What is that? Read the passage to
us.
- "'My marrow is tired', he thought. 'I've
been tired all my days, bone tired but now
it's in the marrow. It must be what Baby
Suggs felt when she lay down and thought
about color for the rest of her life.'"
- Okay. So, let's connect what you say in
this stanza, you have, "I'd be trading
still but for the fevers melting down my
bones." What is it about that stanza that
you want to connect to this allusion?
- We thought that her fever is melting
down-- we thought that it was, it's pretty
much the exact same connection because
it's bones going into the marrow, so the
outside going into the inside. "The fever
is melting down to my bones," it's just
taking a different way.
- And to get more than a physiological
point of view here, the marrow is where?
Where is the marrow?
- In your bones.
- It's like the core. So, Raphael, when
we're suggesting that the marrow is being
corrupted in some way, what does it mean
for us?
- It basically means that the entirety of
the whole of the being is being corrupted.
- Okay. So, in essence, then, from a
symbolic point of view, just like in
"Beloved," we can relate this to the
poem. What kind of corruption do you see
here?
- For me, it was mainly corruption of
hypocrisy.
- Okay. Hypocrisy in what context?
- Mainly that the enslavers honestly
believed that they were in the right, that
they were different, like this passage,
this short passage here. "It sickens me to
think of what I saw, of how these apes
throw overboard the butchered bodies of
our men, true Christians all, like so much
jetsam."
- Yes.
- And then at the very beginning, they're
talking about how they're throwing slaves
overboard.
- Or even when the slaves decide to, "Lost
three this morning leaped with crazy
laughter to the wading sharks, sang as
they went under."
- Yeah.
- So, there's this sort of weird
juxtaposition of the whites being thrown
over by the savages or the apes at the end
versus the slaves who choose to jump over
at the beginning. Laura, what do you think
is going on in this particular context?
- With all of the jumping off board, it's
a true escape to eternal freedom, I guess
if you believe in Heaven. The thing that
confuses me is I understand why the savage
blacks would throw the whites over,
obviously death and more of a pain, but it
also ends their misery in a way of staying
on the ship with the slaves getting the
sickness, the blindness and having to
wait, I think it's like another three
weeks before they come to port. So, it's
really contrasting and interesting how it
goes back and forth.
This poem focuses, I think, on both sides,
on black and white.
- Yes. It really does illustrate both.
Which do you think is best illustrated,
Laura, the black side or the white side?
- The black side is really, I don't want
to say common, but it's similar to
everything you hear about slave ships--
- And the slave trade.
- ...and the slave trade. So, I think
it's interesting that Hayden decided to
also put in the white side of it because
you don't really focus on what came of
slavery. Even though it was a horrible
thing, on the last page here it says,
"That you whose wealth, whose tree of
liberty are rooted in the labor of your
slaves," I thought it was interesting
because I often fail to make the
connection that through the slavery, we
actually were able to grow as a country
and through our liberty first, we were
able to bring the slaves out eventually
through the Civil War.
- Jordan, continue.
- I was looking at more of the religious
side of it as with what you were just
talking about. Here it says, "Their
moaning is a prayer for death."
- Yes.
- "Some try to starve themselves." And
then you go down one, two, three, four
stanzas later, it says, "Jesus Savior
pilot me over life's tempestuous sea. We
pray that thou will grant, O Lord, safe
passage to our vessels bringing heathen
souls..." It's not so much praying for
death, it's praying and knowing that Jesus
can lead them to freedom forever and allow
them out of...
- Who is praying for Jesus here, Jordan?
- The slaves.
- Really?
- That's how I took it.
- Okay. Did anybody here take it a
different way?
- I took it as the sailors.
- Exactly. Good. Not that that's-- I think
you're on to something in the sense that
the religion of the slavers was eventually
forced upon the slaves themselves. So, I
think that they could be. So, I think
there's a real sort of duality there.
- For this point in history they
evangelized--
- Evangelized.
- They had already--
- Evangelized. Yes. It's a hard word to
say.
- Africa. I know the Dutch, for example,
had already been there.
- So, historically speaking then, Raphael,
when you say it's the slavers that are the
ones that are praying, what's ironic about
all of this?
- That they're so much in the wrong and
they don't see it all and that kind of
hypocrisy.
- And they're looking for justification
for their actions. Speaking of
justification, what I want you to think
about now for a few minutes-- I'm going to
talk to the other group up front here-- why
is it that the white side of things is all
reported to us literally through almost a
journalistic style? It's all quotes. It's
all basically kind of like it's from a
ship's log. So, think about this and I'm
going to be back to talk to you about it.
All right, group, what's going on?
- It's all going on.
- It's all going on? Okay. Tell me. What
have we discussed?
- Everything.
- Everything? Tell me more.
- Well, we've discussed about how in this
stanza, "That there was hardly room 'tween
decks for half the sweltering cattle
stowed spoon-fashion there; that some went
mad of thirst and tore their flesh and
sucked the blood. " That was talking about
the capture of the Africans.
- Yes.
- Who wouldn't be so thirsty that they
wouldn't tear open their own skin and
drink their own blood.
- Which is just crazy in terms of the
suffering.
- Yeah. And how that shows that in some
way they were driven into some sorts of
savagery. And yet in the next stanza, it
talks about how the crew would lay with
the--
- The Guinea Rose?
- Yeah.
- "The crew and cabin lusted with the
comeliest of the savage girls kept naked
in the cabins..." Okay. Well, let's
talk about it for just a second. We have a
real juxtaposition of pleasure and
suffering. What do you think?
- Yeah. It's a real contrast between
describing these people as sweltering
cattle ripping their flesh open and then
it goes right into how the crew, like,
would sleep with these women.
- Exactly. They're fully taking advantage
of them. Imagine being kept naked in a
cabin for the whole journey.
- Yeah. It's a very big contrast because
they are calling them animals.
- So, what happens after their lust? In
the stanzas right before we begin section
two of the poem, what details are we given
about what happens to this specific crew?
- They abandon the ship.
- It goes up in flames.
- Exactly. So, it's basically set on fire
and then what happens?