(background chatter)
- [Teacher] Okay, so,
write your conjectures down.
Denominators are repeating.
Actually, let's put
this one on number four.
Put it on number four.
(background chatter)
- We got any even number
that had any odd number.
(background chatter)
- [Teacher] Okay, so if it's an odd number
in the denominator, it's repeating.
If it's got an even
number in the denominator?
(background chatter)
Oh, okay, so you want to add to it
not just say it's even.
If it's odd over even --
- It's terminating,
- [Teacher] It's terminating.
and what if it's even over even?
- Even over even?
Two over six.
It would one be one over three
You'd have to simplify it.
- [Teacher] Okay, you'd
have to simplify it,
and so what would happen
when you simplified
2/6 to 1/3?
- It would be repeating.
- [Teacher] It would be repeating,
so maybe you're on to something.
Might want to record that.
Let's check.
That's good.
I haven't heard that one before, guys.
All right, let me here
some of your conjectures.
This group, we're going
with their conjecture.
What's your conjecture guys?
- [Group] That all odd
denominator fractions will repeat.
- All right, here's the conjecture.
All odd numbers in the denominator
will be repeating decimals.
Anybody want to add to it?
Take away from it?
Change it?
All right, what we got here, over here?
- That's false because point two five
goes into 100
4 times.
- [Teacher] Okay, hold on.
- [Teacher] I'm confused.
Point two five.
What is point two five
represented as a fraction?
- [Students] 1/4.
- 1/4,
and they said all odd
numbers are repeating.
(background chatter)
So far it works.
- [Student in Camo] Well then 1/5.
- All right, let's try 1/5.
Well hold on then.
Let's get all the conjectures
before we start trying them out.
I do love the action
that you want to make up
your own fractions and try it
'cause I don't think it's safe just to
take it at a glance.
All right, Dylan, what did y'all's group.
George, share for your group.
What did y'all say?
(background chatter)
Listen guys.
- We had two.
- [Teacher] You had two, okay.
- Even over odd equals terminating.
- [Teacher] Even over
odd is terminating, okay.
- [George] And even
over even is repeating.
- [Teacher] Even over even is repeating.
- He meant two by that.
- Okay, so basically,
and then I would assume that
odd over odd would go here?
Okay, my only question is I see
even over odd, odd over odd,
even over even, what's the other option?
- [Students] Odd over even.
- Odd over even, where do
you think that would go?
Do you think it would go terminating?
-Yes.
- Well, let's pick something really quick.
3/4.
That's odd over even.
That would be terminating.
Okay, so opposites, even
and odd, odd and even,
you're thinking opposites --
- Attract?
- There you go.
Opposites attract to be terminating,
and when they're the same
even and even and odd and odd.
(background chatter)
- They repel.
- Okay, and they repeat.
Pretty good.
Here's what I want you to do now.
Based on what you just told me,
look at number six.
I've given you fractions.
I want you, let's look at them as a group.
I want to come to a consensus as a class.
Do we all agree with this groups thinking?
(various agreement and
disagreement from class)
- We didn't get to share ours
because 8/9 repeat.
- Okay, 8/9 is even over odd,
and that repeats,
so maybe we want to cancel this one out,
and it's just odd over even?
(background chatter)
- There might be something else.
It might be that that
doesn't go, necessarily,
doing anything like
the rules for divisibility
like seven and eight,
they don't have a rule
because it just doesn't work,
but it's right.
It might be that that doesn't work.
- Maybe if it's even a law,
you just gotta work it out.
- So do we want to make our rule this?
If it's odd over eating.
Eating?
Is it time for lunch?
If it's odd over even, it's terminating,
everything else is repeating?
(disagreement from students)
- We should test it out before.
- 3/4 is terminating,
but 7/8 isn't terminating
'cause eight...
- [Teacher] 7/8?
Try it on your paper real quick.
7/8.
- [Students] It terminates.
- [Teacher] So do we want to use this?
(agreement and disagreement from students)
No and yes, okay, let's --
- Let's do more though.
- [Teacher] Let's do a
democracy here, okay?
If you're liking the, well hold on.
Who says no?
Who doesn't want to use this?
Why?
- Those rules may not work all
the time for every fraction.
- [Teacher] Okay, so do you have
a better rule or conjecture?
(background chatter)
So far is it working?
(agreement from class)
Based on what we know
and the numbers we've generated so far,
let's use that rule to categorize
the following fractions,
and I think we could do this as a group.
So here I've got, our rule
we said we wanted to try
was odd over even.
Everything else is going in repeating.
Odd over even.
We've already done these,
so here's our new fractions, okay?
What is this fraction here?
- [Class] 11/24
- It's odd over even,
so where do we want to put it?
- [Class] Terminating.
- Terminating.
15/14.
- [Class] Terminating
- Odd over even, would
make it terminating.
Six what?
- [Class] Sevenths.
- 6/7?
- [Class] Repeating.
- Even over odd terminates.
(background chatter)
- But that didn't work.
That didn't work.
- We tried it, and we saw
that it didn't work, remember?
Yeah, odd over even is the
only one we're going with,
so I've got an odd over even.
I got odd over odd.
- Repeating.
- And I've got an odd over even.
- [Students] Terminating.
- Okay, so here's what I want you to do.
Check it.
Use your calculators as a group, check it.
Circle, go ahead and write 'em down.
Categorize them just
like I did on the board.
Write 'em in your chart and
circle any that don't belong.
(background chatter)
- [Teacher] Use your calculator.
- It doesn't work.
Odd over even.
- [Teacher] It doesn't work?
Oh, no!
Which one doesn't work?
(background chatter)
- Seven over six doesn't work.
- All right, let's do this then.
The 6/7, were we correct there?
(agreement and disagreement from students)
All right, this one's right.
17 over 125.
- No.
- This one was repeating or terminating?
- [Students] Terminating.
- All right, so this one,
we need to move over here.
All right, 5/13?
- I haven't checked --
- Haven't check that one.
- Five divided by 13.
- We don't know.
Too many decimals.
- [Teacher] Okay, if it's too many,
what do you think it's going to be?
- [Students] Repeating.
- Probably going to be repeating,
so that one looks good.
Let's do this.
(background chatter)
Hold on, I want you guys to try 11/24.
I want you to do 15/14.
I want you to check 199 over 200,
and I want you all to check nine over 80.
(background chatter)
- These
rules already tested out.
- That's terminating.
(background chatter)
- The rules weren't tested
enough to be proven.
- [Boy in Camo] I think my rule is solid
even though it's kind of condensed.
(background chatter)
- [Teacher] Five, four, three, two, one.
Thank you.
All right, 11/24?
It stays?
All right, it repeats,
so it goes over here.
All right, 15/14.
- [Students] Repeating.
- [Teacher] All right,
let me change this though.
Let's change this one to 15/24.
Check that one.
15/24.
And while they're checking --
- Point 625.
- [Teacher] Point 625,
so it's actually going to terminate, okay?
199 over 200?
Repeating or terminating?
- Terminating.
- [Teacher] It terminated?
And nine over 80?
- [Group] Terminating.
- [Teacher] Terminating, okay,
so it didn't work.
- So odd over even doesn't work?
- Right, it didn't work,
so let's think about it then.
We got a --
- Do you know a rule?
- I don't know,
so I'm kind of doing this with you.
Let's look at this.
What is important?
Do you think the numerator is important?
Well, if the numerator's what's important?
- I think they're evenly important.
- They're evenly important?
- Without one,
the other wouldn't be the same fraction.
- Do you agree?
He said, "Without one,
"the other wouldn't be the same fraction."
What do you mean by that?
- You said,
"Which one's important?"
If you say the numerator's important,
then if you change the denominator
it might not work,
so they're not the same fraction
without one another.
- Okay.
- If the numerator is one less
than the denominator,
then it will be repeating.
- If the numerator is one
less than the denominator?
What about 5/13?
- That's just one rule,
there's multiple --
- Right, well, I want to come up
with just one rule that
works for them all.
So let's look at this.
If the numerator is what's important,
can we not look at these
two fractions here?
What do they both have in common?
They both have a common denominator,
and they have different numerators,
and it's actually put 'em
in two, separate categories,
but they're both odd.
- Prime number.
- [Teacher] Oh, you're seeing
something about prime number?
(background chatter)
- If it's prime over even
it'll be repeating,
but a prime over an even would be...
- Okay, so we're gonna do
prime over even is which one?
- Repeating.
- Prime over even is repeating.
- Okay, because even number
has what factor in it?
Automatically?
- Two.
- A two, and will a prime number
have two as a factor?
(background chatter)
A prime number will have two as a factor?
What are the factors of prime numbers?
- [Students] One and itself.
- The only problem with that
is the number what?
- [Students] Two.
- Two, okay, so I think
you're on to something.
- If it's prime over even,
then it'll be repeating.
- [Teacher] Prime over
even, then it's repeating?
- I found a problem with that.
- Here's what I want you to do.
- I did 11
over eight.
- [Teacher] 11 over eight.
- It's prime over even.
- Okay, it is a mix number.
It's not a mixed number, I'm sorry.
It's a?
- [Students] Improper fraction.
- What would it need to be a mixed number?
(background chatter)
- A whole number.
- [Teacher] And a fractional part.
Good job.
All right, so here's my question then.
Here's what I want you to do.
Look up here,
and I think with fractions
we always seem to stress
when we're doing equivalent fractions.
To put a fraction in its what?
- Simplest form.
Anytime there's a prime number
it's already going to be in
its simplest form, right?
'Cause you can't reduce it anymore,
so these are already in
their simplest forms.
What about 15/24?
Is there a factor that
they both have in common?
- Three.
- Three, okay,
so if I factor out three out of fifteen?
- [Students] Five.
- I got a five.
- [Students] Eight.
- So that's an equivalent fraction,
so I'm going to get rid of that.
Odd over even.
So maybe we could say
in a fraction's, what?
- Simplest form.
- [Teacher] Simplest form.
In a fraction's simplest form
if it's odd
over even,
then it, what?
- Terminates.
- [Teacher] Terminates.
- So are we doing a rule
that applies to every number?
- [Teacher] Every single number.
So if we were to make a conjecture,
do we just base it off of six numbers?
- [Students] No.
- [Teacher] What I want you to do is
I want you as a group
to come up with your own example
that can either prove this
or disprove this conjecture.
The conjecture is that a fraction
in its simplest form,
if it's odd over even,
will terminate.
I want every group to make up their own,
as a group make up your own example.
- Let's do 7/6.
(background chatter)
- [Teacher] You make up your own, Buck.
You make up your own.
You got notebook paper if you want it.
- I made it up, so can we do it again?
- [Teacher] No, I want a
new one they haven't seen.
(background chatter)
- So 5/6?
- [Teacher] 5/6, okay.
Try 5/6.
Is it in simplest form?
- Yes
- [Teacher] Okay.
(background chatter)
And, so, it actually repeats.
- It disproves the theory.
- [Teacher] So it
disproves it, doesn't it?