- Okay, guys.
I see we'll be looking at investigating
fraction multiplication.
Okay, so can you read the
objective with me please?
So, I ...
- I will be able to
do fraction multiplication.
- Okay. I've also put it in Spanish
just in case that helps you.
Okay, so the first thing I
want to discuss with you today,
is, what do you think about that?
Do you agree or disagree?
And then, why?
So, one-half, does
one-half equal one-half?
Why or why not?
And then, give me some examples.
Okay, Raul.
- It's becuase it is one-half.
They're the same.
- Okay.  Abraham.
- It's like you cut a pear in half,
it's gonna be in equal parts.
- Okay, so you guys are
saying it's equal?
- Yes. [Background Chatter]
- Okay.
What do you think?
Eddie believes he thinks
the same thing.
Taleah, what do you think?
- I think it's the same.
- You think it's the same?
Does everyone think it's the same?
- I do.
- Until you think,
why wouldn't it be the same.
- Okay, so Jose is saying
why wouldn't they be the same.
Okay, so one thing Jose says is
he's trying to think of
are there any examples
why it wouldn't be the same.
Joe.
- It's not the same because
[Background Chatter]
- No, that's just the board point.
- Is there a times?
- Nope, it's just one over two
equals one over two.
- I was thinking it
was a half times a half.
- Okay, so sounds to me like you guys
all agree that it's the same.
Right?
- Yeah.
- So now, how do you explain to me
why you think it's the same?
Why you think it's the same?
Joe?
- Because they have equal parts.
- Okay. Equal parts.
What do you mean by equal parts?
- They have the same fraction.
- Okay. Jose.
- They're both practically the same thing.
- What do you mean by
practically the same thing?
- That once you cut a square in half,
you have equal parts, and
they're gonna be the same thing.
- Okay.
Who is someone we haven't heard from?
Madeline, what do you think?
So I heard you say they
are the same, right?
- Yeah.
- So why do you think
they are the same?
- 'Cause they're
both equal parts and
the same 'cause half equals a half.
- Okay. Antonio,
what do you think?
Think it's the same?
So, sounds like we're all thinking
it's the same, okay.
Abraham, what do you think?
- I think they
equal the same thing.
- Equals the same thing.
Okay, so now let's take a look at ...
maybe, 'cause it sounds
like we're all on the same
path here.
So let's take a look at something else.
Are they really the same?
Is that half of a ...
- Cookie.
- Cookie. Half of a cookie.
Half a ...
- Pizza.
- Are they the same?
- No.
- Yes.
- One at a time, 'cause I'm hearing
a lot of good stuff, but you guys are all
saying it at the same time.
Okay. Miguel.
- They're the same,
'cause if they weren't,
[Background Chatter] the same is just half.
- So I'm hearing, they're the same,
but one's bigger than the other one,
'cause one's a pizza and one's a cookie.
- Yeah.
- Tina, you're kind of
shaking your head.
What do you think about that?
- I think they're both the same,
'cause they're still one-half
they are just different size.
- Victoria, what do you think?
Same or not the same?
- Same 'cause it's still half.
- Okay, so let me ask you this:
I'm hearing a couple things,
and it's kind of contradicting itself.
Meaning you're saying one thing,
but you're also saying the opposite.
Like I heard it's the same
because it's one-half,
but it's different because it's ..
- Different sizes?
- different sizes.
You just told me it's the same,
but now you're telling
me it's different sizes.
[Background Chatter]
- They are both fattening!
- Oh, cookies and pizza
are both fattening? Okay.
Felice.
- Why I think they're
still the same is because
a half is a half no matter
whether it's big or small
because it's still chopped in half.
- Okay. So if a half of a half,
so would you rather have half of $10,
or half of $100?
- Half of a $100!
- Why?
- Because it's bigger!
- Because it's bigger.
But I thought it was the same?
- No.
- No, 'cause it's the same thing.
- It's still half,
but you're commenting,
half of a hundred ...
- It has to be the same thing.
Like the pizza, a whole
pizza, and you cut it in half.
- Okay, you say
it has to be the same thing
for what to happen?
- For it to be half.
But here, it's not the same thing.
You're saying to me that it is equal.
So which is it?
[Background Chatter]
- So now you're saying
you don't think they're the same.
- No. You get more
pieces than a cookie.
- They're still the same.
- They're still half.
- Okay, so who still agrees that
the one-half equals one-half?
Raise your hand. Okay.
Alright now, who says that one-half
maybe, sometimes doesn't equal one-half?
Okay. So we got a couple.
Alright. So, Delphina,
what's your thinking?
I haven't heard from you.
What's your thinking?
- I think it depends on
what you are looking at.
- So, in case you didn't hear her,
Delphina said it depends, okay.
Hear what she said?
It depends on what you're looking at.
'Cause she said with the money example,
that you guys, well
all of you unanimously,
chose half of a hundred, that's $50,
as opposed to $5, half of $10.
So it does matter.
So now we just go back to the question,
does one-half equal one-half?
Okay, Raul?
- I think one-half equals one-half.
I think it's still the same.
It's not talking about how big it is,
it's just talking about a half.
- But it didn't say
in the question what it was.
I think the question is
supposed to say what it was
[inaudible] to say if
it's the same or not.
- Okay, so
what Dallas is saying,
that it needs to tell you
what one-half is.
'Cause she's saying here,
the previous question
just had the number,
one over two, one over two. Equal.
Alright, here, she's
saying well all of a sudden
yeah, the numbers are gone, but you have
half of a pizza and a half of a cookie.
So now it's not the same.
- But it's the same question.
What Dallas is saying,
in the question it should tell you
what is it.
- It's actually like 10 fives ...
five-tenths and and one-half.
- So what do you think?
What's your final thought
as far as one-half
equals one-half?
What's your final thought?
- They're still
the same, it's a half.
- It's still the same ...
- because it's half.
- Okay.
- It's the same and different.
Miguel.
- [inaudible] and
they tell you it's different.
- Okay, so, good question.
Good question.
I like the look of that.
Yes.
- If they are, are they the same?
They're the same, it's
one-half or something.
One is bigger than the other one.
- Okay. Rodrigo.
What about you, bud?
What's your thoughts on this?
- I'm still thinking.
- You're still thinking?
Or are you still, will you compete?
- I'm still basically undecided.
- Okay.  You think they're
basically the same?
So, you added that 'basically'.
Why don't you just put they're the same?
Why did you put 'basically'?
- Because one's bigger than the other.
- It will obviously still be different.
Where we're going with this is,
you have to understand that
it depends on what your unit is.
Your whole unit.
Okay? Alright?
So that's why sometimes
you have to be careful,
what it's asking you to do. Okay?
Let's go on to the next one.
Okay, so what does
one-half look like to you?
So just think right now in your head,
when you think of one-half, okay?
What do you see?
- Half a dollar.
- Half of a dollar.
- Half a fifty.
- Half a gallon of juice.
- Half a body.
- Half of a body.
Half of a cake.
- Half of a cake.
Okay, Guadalupe, what do you see?
- Half a paper.
- Half a paper, okay.
So let me take it to the next step.
So what if we said the half a paper
times
half of a juice.
Does it make sense?
- No.
- Does it make sense?
- No!
- It doesn't make sense.
So we have to make sure that we know what?
- You have to make sense.
- Well, it makes sense,
but how is it gonna make sense?
It's what?
- If they're the same.
But what's the same?
- The object!
- The object, or the whole unit, right?
Like, what is it we're talking about?
We talking about pizza?
We talking about cookies?
- Paper.
- Paper. Juice.
- People.
- Eggs.
- Alright, so the other thing
I wanna talk to you about is,
does multiplication
always make things larger?
Bigger?
- Yes!
- No!
- So I heard yes, yes, yes
and then ...
- No.
- So now then, what?
- 'Cause sometimes it makes it smaller.
If you do nine times
one, it's gonna be nine
and if you do nine times
zero, it makes it zero.
- Jessie.
Did you hear her example?
- No.
- Okay, so what she said was,
'cause it's important.
I want you to make sure you understood.
She said that no, because
nine times one is nine.
Then when you go nine
times zero, it's zero.
So it actually made it less, right?
What do you think though?
When you multiply in general,
when you multiply,
does it make things larger?
When you multiply two things together?
- Yes.
- Okay. Abraham
- It gets bigger, because like
six times two,
it's 12, and it gets bigger.
- Okay.  Raul, what do you think?
Raul V.
When you multiply, does
it always get bigger?
- It depends on the number.
- What?
- It depends on the number
so give me an example.
- Zero times 8100,
is gonna be zero.
- Okay. So can we ...
so I'm hearing kind of like,
a lot of you are saying
yes, it makes it larger.
But there's still like
some of you who are like saying
maybe not always.
Like if we go back to,
if we go back to that one-half,
if we go back to that
one-half and that dollar.
Gino, what's 100 times one-half?
- Times one-half is ...
a hundred and a half?
- A hundred and a half?
- 50?
- 50.
I got 150.
- 150?
Taylor, do you agree?
One hundred times one-half is 150?
Raul B.
- 500?
- Five hundred?
How'd you get five hundred?
- I thought it was half of a thousand.
- A hundred though.
No more thousand, one hundred.
One hundred times one-half.
- Is it 110?
Half of 10 is five.
[Background Chatter]
- So what is your answer?
The one hundred times one-half?
- Five hundred.
- Five hundred?
Okay, so one hundred times
one-half is five hundred?
Tina?
- We don't know
because we don't know
what one-half equals.
- Okay, so Tina's saying now,
you don't know what the one-half is.
What if we're just talking about numbers?
One hundred times one-half,
what would that be?
One hundred times one-half.
[Background Chatter]
Let's say it's money.
A hundred dollars times one-half.
[Background Chatter]
- It could be five or 50.
If we're talking about $100,
then it's gonna be one-half of $100
is 35.
- Okay, so,
- 45.
there was a lot of people talking,
so you couldn't hear, but Louis is saying
it depends, but if you're
talking about money,
if it was hundred dollars times one-half,
it'd be half of $100, which is $50.
Let's take that example.
One hundred times one-half
is 50.
So then when we multiply that,
did it get larger?
- No.
- Yeah.
- It got smaller.
Didn't it?
You start with a hundred,
and you multiply and you got 50,
which is less.
So what do you think now?
Do you think it always
makes things bigger?
- No.
- Sometimes it makes it smaller.
- So, let's ...
can you give me another example then?
That's just ... make sure we prove it.
Is there another example you can give me
that makes it smaller then?
- Like five times four?
- Five times four?
We start with five times four,
you get what?
- 20. It's a bigger number.
- Okay, so that's if you multiply it
times a half, right?
- Ten times one-half?
- Ten times one-half would be?
- Five.
- Raise your hand if you think
it doesn't always make it bigger.
It depends on what you multiply it by.
Alright. Very good.
So, we're gonna use the area model
to show one-half times one-half.
- That's a whole.
- One-half times one-half
Abraham says it's a whole,
but let's go ahead and ...
let's take a look.
I'm gonna go ahead and
shade in one-half, okay.
And then we'll take a look to see
what it actually equals.
Here's a half.
There's a half.
How many squares are
shaded both colors?
- One.
- Two.
- One out of how many total?
- Four.
- One-fourth.
So, one-half times one-half is one-fourth.
Is one fourth smaller than one-half?
- Yes.
- That's another proof
that when you multiply,
it doesn't always get bigger.
- You could make it into money.
Like one-fourth is 25 cents.
- Alright, very good.
- A hundred divided by...
- So, let's take a look
at another example.
If we're to use an area models for this,
what would that look like?
- Three-fourth.
It'd be one-half, right?
We'd see one-half times one-fourth.
So what do you think?
- Half of a fourth? One-eighth?
- Half of a fourth,
which is one eighth, he said.
One-half of one-fourth is
one-eighth, do you agree?
- Yeah.
- Okay.