- Like the chocolate one with the
strawberries that we looked at, that is
going to serve approximately 24 people. So
if you multiple that by two that's
approximately $48 that you should charge
if you're going to charge for your cakes.
Now it's going to depend on did you really
put that much time, energy and effort into
it and do you feel like you really need to
charge that? That's going to have a little
bit of basis to how much you are going to
charge, but that will kind of give you an
idea what to charge for your cakes. Think
about it too, serving sizes for cakes are
typically two inches square. They're
small, so when you are thinking, "But
that's a little cake" well, serving size
is tiny. It's not that you are going to
serve them a whole meal out of cake. It's
just for them to get a taste. Sculpted
cakes like the catfish cake that we looked
at, $100 plus. When I looked these up
specifically for something as big as that
catfish cake because it was a pretty good
size catfish cake. We tried to make it, as
realistic as possible and it was about
this tall. So probably somewhere at $150,
$200 level had we bought that at a bakery.
The wedding cake, like Jessie's wedding
cake that we've seen, somewhere in the
neighborhood of $600 because it was a
seven tiered masterpiece as well.
Who has a question? Come on somebody has
got a question.
- I wanna make a 3D cake.
- Okay, when do you wanna make one?
- I don't know.
- They're fun! So if you were going to
make a 3D cake, what would you make?
- Catfish!
- Okay! Britney's making a catfish! Okay,
Erica's making a dinosaur. Oh, my
favorite. Piggies, butterflies, what else?
What would you like to try?
Penguin, duck, basketball, panda bear
would be cute.
- A tire.
- Brandi, I wanna see your tire cake when
you get that done. A monkey would be fun.
[Background Chatter]
- That would be really cute.
- So you guys are starting to think 3D. We
need to be thinking about your roses, too.
Because we gotta work on those roses and
get that technique down. Let's go over to
our table, and I'll show you about making
those roses.
Okay, so when we get our snow day tomorrow
I expect you to go home and practice,
practice, practice, practice, practice. If
it's snow we probably will get out. Watch
Facebook, Brandi. Or listen to the news.
That's how we'll find out.
I always post it to my Facebook whenever
they tell us. You guys already know about
fixing your pastry bags, and this one is
already fixed and it's all ready to go.
You know me, I like wrapping it up. One of
my just little tricks I like to use for
this, if it starts getting sticky on the
outside-- Which actually I know you have
struggled with this-- these are not my
friends. These are my friends. That's my
first tip. My second tip is if you're
going to use a plastic bag, take a paper
towel and just turn it into your handle.
And the other thing is, don't fill your
bag so full. It really only needs to be
filled to about halfway, maybe a little
bit more than halfway, okay? Then what
you'll do is you'll start rolling it down.
As you're rolling it down, typically what
I do first is I fold it in kind of at a
triangle. Then I start rolling it down.
The reason for that is so when I start
putting pressure on it's got both those
folds and then another fold to keep it
from escaping. Other people like to do the
toothpaste thing and twist. It's totally
up to you how you want to do that.
Either one is totally acceptable. Just
feel what works best for you, okay? Then I
make my little handle out of my paper
towel. Remember on the tips. You will
notice on the tips, especially the Wilton
tips, has a number. That number is
representative of how big the hole is. The
larger the number the larger the hole.
That works on the writing tips. Someone
tell me what number is on that one. Okay,
tell me what number is on that one, Erica.
It's on the outside. Okay, yours is a
number 12.
- Five.
- You've got a number five.
- It says a 230.
- Okay a 230.
- One.
- Okay, and why. A one what? A one M, that
means one monster. No, I don't know what
the M stands for. What is the difference
though between this tip and this tip?
They're pretty much the same thing.
[Background Chatter]
- What would you use this one for?
- For big cakes.
- Or for?
- Wait, don't! I got this!
- You've got it, okay come on, Ashley.
What would you use it for?
- [together] Borders? Borders!
- Yes, great answer! Absolutely. I'm
telling you by the time you have finished
your masterpiece and you're ready to do
the borders, get the big ones cause you're
ready to be done with it. If you pick one
of these little teeny tiny ones, by that
time you're sick of working with frosting
and you're ready to do something else. But
this one's just a number 16. See how tiny
that is? Okay, rose tips. The bigger the
number the bigger the holes. Also on your
rose tip, make sure that the large opening
end is going down. If this is awkward for
you, all you have to do to adjust your
tip, loosen it and then twist it around,
and then tighten your tip. You don't want
to tighten it so much that it's gonna take
a pair of pliers to get it loose, okay?
Let's see if I can get this back in
business. Okay, you've got your rose
nails.
You're just going to put a little squirt
of frosting, and it doesn't have to be
very big... and I'm making a big mess
now. Hold it down. Lay it straight down on
your waxed paper and now you've got your
basis for your rose. This is what we're
gonna build the roses on. We have to make
a pyramid of frosting to start out with.
Remember that on the Power Point? The
first one I'm gonna do, is I'm gonna
rotate this counter-clockwise and make my
little pyramid. See that little circle in
the middle? That's going to be the very
inside of the rosebud. Actually you could
pull these off after you let them set up.
Stick them on a plate or on a cookie
sheet, stick them in the freezer, and you
could have lots of little rosebuds to set
on your cake. Just add your little leaves
add your little vines and make you a
really pretty little rosebush out of that.
If you want it a little bit bigger, you
just squeeze and rotate all at the same
time. It's about pressure and release. So,
if you wanted a little rose you would pull
it off right about now. If you want a
little bit bigger, we're
gonna build it up. My frosting is getting
warm, but that's okay. There's a little
bit bigger one. It's starting to flop over
on me because it's getting really warm in
here. The more petals you add to the
outside, the bigger your rose is going to
be. Did you see that? It just about flew
onto the floor.
- Could you tell me what this would be
used for?
- Yes! That one is actually to decorate
cupcakes. So if we had a whole bunch of
cupcakes this is so you can do some really
delicate work inside the very delicate
areas. Like if you have them all lined up
and you're trying to do them really fast,
you can just do that. Usually what they
will do that for is you know the little
curly things that look like a little snake
on the top? Have you seen them? They just
go "shhhhh." That's what they use that
for.
It kind of is fun. One other way that you
can do your frosting pyramid is just go
straight down and squeeze and just bring
it straight up. So now we've got our cute
little middle of our cute little rose
going. Yeah, it sticks straight up and
we're just gonna wrap our little petals
around it. There we go. See how cute that
is? It looks just like one that you just
picked right off my little rosebush. Some
of my white roses at home look like that.
That one is cute that one's a good one.
Let's see if I can finish this off. We'll
do this one tiny. The smaller you want to
make them, you just add a smidge of
pressure instead of a lot of pressure. If
you add a lot of pressure you're gonna
make a big rose. It is, it's getting
really warm. Who has a question about
making these cute little roses? Okay, and
I know you guys are masters at using your
little star tips for shell borders. All
right, so lets see what you can do. I
think you got your tables set. Who would
like to use this tip. Simone? Do you need
a rose tip? Okay. I'll come around and
check on you and see how you're doing. I
want to see your masterpieces. I wanna see
a couple of good roses from each of you.
Kimberly, do you all need a rose tip over
here? Do you need that? Okay. Sorry, let
me get out of your way.
- Do we just do one or two?
- I want you to practice your borders and
I want you to practice your rose tips. So
if you have a rose tip at your table
you'll probably have to share. I'll come
around and check on you and see how it's
going and if you have any problems or
questions let me know.
- I have a question.
[Background Chatter]
- That is a good question.
It should be but it's not. Don't use this
one. This works best if you take your bag
and just snip it and just drop it straight
back in the bag. Because this coupler is
not designed to fit on this particular
one.
I'll get you a different one you can try.
Brandi, have you used the super star one
that makes-- have you used the leaf tip
yet?
- No.
- Let's try leaves. The big giant one?
This will not fit on here with your
coupler. You'll have to use a different
frosting bag. Most everything else that's
out you can use. This one-- actually you
might have fun with this one. This one
makes swirlies. Cool, it just makes lines
you just zigzag it.
[Background Chatter]
- All the star tips are right here.
- Err, not the star but the rose.
- No, I think all of them are out. You
guys will have to wait and trade out with
each other. Yep, they're all out.
- I just suck at this.
- No you don't! Let me see. Start with
this, Christina. Hold your handle. Handles
are our friends.
- Ooh, it looks like a square rose!
- It does look like a square rose, that's
cool. Okay, Britney make sure the big end
goes to the bottom. The small end goes to
the top. Remember your angles, too. 45 and
90. Sierra that looks good. Let me hand
these to Brandi and I'll be right back.
Brandi? Here.
- How do I make this one work?
- Oh, this one is kind of fun. This one
quite literally is something you'd finish
off, like if you're making grass you just
kind of swirl it around.
You can do it like this. Yeah, there are
two lines. Like if you wanted to do ziggy
zags. You can do circles. You know like
that. It's all about your pressure. Oh!
What happened? What happened?
- They're laughing at my rose.
- What's wrong with it? That's a good
start. Keep building on it. Now remember
Leticia, this big part right here on this
side-- that goes down. There you go. If
it's not in the right location You may
want to unscrew this and realign this. Try
that, see if that works better for ya.
Then remember you're twisting all at the
same time. You're making like upside down
U's, remember? Oh, you did miss that part
of the lesson, too, didn't you. All right,
let me show you and then I'll let you do
one, okay? What you're gonna do, this big
one always goes down. You're making like
an upside down U. Just like that. You're
gonna U and turn it all at the same time
so that it's a slow turn and this motion
all at the same time, okay? Then when
you're done you just set that aside and do
another one. Show me what you're doing.
There you go. Hold it just like that.
That's good.
Hey, you're getting there. You're making a
pyramid of frosting and you can do it one
of two ways. You can either do it this way
or straight up and down. Just make a big
glob of frosting, and turn this all at the
same time. There you go, just like that.
Pull your frosting off, there you go. Okay
now that's a good start, and now you're
gonna start making your upside down U's.
Usually you have three on your bottom
layer. There you go.
You're turning it all at the same time.
It's all about the hand motion there you
go, just like that. Just make little tiny
ones all around. There ya go that looks
good. There ya go. See, you can do this,
Leticia. There, oh look how beautiful that
is! It is! Oh my gosh. That's a perfect
rosebud.
- Thank you.
- That's it. That's all you have to do.
The bigger you wanna make your rose, the
more levels you put around the outside
edge, okay? If that's all you want then
pull it off, set it aside, and do some
more. That's it.
All right, you've got the techniques and
you know what to do. I'll come back and
check on you. Yes. Yes, yes, yes. Oh come
on show me. Show me, show me.
- At least it's better than theirs.
- Hey, you're getting there. I think
you're doing the same thing that Leticia
was doing. See this big piece. You've got
it back. It needs to go down. If this is
awkward for you and you need to twist this
part of it. Just unscrew and re-navigate.
Britney, that looks good.
- Wait, it is on bottom now.
- It is now because I just turned it. When
you were doing it it wasn't. See how these
are heavy on top? That's the reason. It'll
be okay. Do you need some more?
- Is there anymore cut-out things?
- No, but there's stuff to do it. All
right, I'll come back and check on you.
Sierra, I'm gonna leave you in charge over
here. If they need some help, let me know
okay?
- Okay.
- Good job. Where are you over here? Yes!
Yes, yes, yes! Star borders deluxe. Okay,
so how are you doing? You're doing really
good on those leaf tips. Have you tried
any standing up? So you know how to do
that? Literally you start here and you
pull straight up on it at a 90 degree
angle.
- What?
- Just like that.
- Like that, sometimes they roll over. The
stiffer your frosting is the stiffer they
are. See how you can get them to stand up?
Just like that, or if you want them to lay
on the side.
- If you go slow they stay up faster.
- Yeah, and it has to do with the
consistency of your frosting, too.
Remember what you put in it to make it a
little bit thicker?
- Powdered sugar?
- Or you can do what?
[Background Chatter]
- There you go. Sarah! Sarah, I have never
seen-- Don't look. A big no-no. Oh man
that's good frosting. Okay, all right yell
at me. I stuck my thumb in it. I had to
lick it off.
- It's really good by the way. It is.
Don't do as I do, do as I say. That's kind
of like momma's say. Ya know, I'm your
school momma.
- It's not monkey see, monkey do. It's
monkey do what monkey say.
- I'm telling ya, today it's Ms. Morris is
doing something silly. All right, so Sarah
show me another one. Show me some shell
borders, cause I know you've practiced
those. She will, she'll be-- I'll be back.
That's cute. That's very stylish. Now, the
tip that Ashley has the one that looks
like the little grass that's got the two
holes at the same time. If you're gonna do
something real fancy if you'll do this one
white and then put a colored one in there
and do it back and forth it will kinda
look like this. Holly, try it again. Try
again.
- Where's the leaf?
- Leddy's got one of them.
- Do you guys have one? Okay show her what
to do. It's pressure and release. Pressure
and release. That one actually turned out
really good. That one is a very good leaf.
When you're working on your leaves for
your cake this is what you want it to look
like. If they start breaking off like
this, you'll probably want to scrape them
off. It's just a matter of the pressure
and release thing. But those are looking
really, really good. I know I'm gonna
sneeze, too. Okay, maybe I'm not. Bless
you. Hey Mariah. Show me what you can do.
[Background Chatter]
- Oh, come on. Those are good ones. Those
are cute. That's a cute border. Samantha,
you're doing a really good job on that,
too.
[Background Chatter]
Kailyn, that is awesome. So, have you
practiced at home yet?
- No.
- Why not? I figured you would be-- I
figured you would be practicing every
chance you got.
- No, I don't have time.
- What do you mean you don't have time.
Yeah, Drew told me you're working on your
scrapbook. Good job, Brandi. All right,
show me something that you can do. I wanna
see somebody make a rose. I showed you how
now I wanna see them. Yes, I wanna see you
make a rose. Make another one. Oh, Let
me-- You can use my frosting. I'll bring
you some.
Look, you did it! So what is the rule...