- [Child on screen] Look, I can be a serk (sic).
♫ Now, my whole house, is great
♫ I can do anything good
♫ I like my school, I like anything
♫ I like my dad, I like my cousins
♫ I like my aunts, I like my Allisons
♫ I like my mom, I like my sister
♫ I like my dad
♫ I like my hair, I like my hair cuts
♫ I like my pajamas, I like my stuff
♫ I like my room
♫ I like my whole house!
♫ My whole house is great
♫ I can do anything good
♫ Yeah, yeah, yeah
♫ Better then anyone ♫
(Laughter from students)
- [Teacher] Okay.
Ok, what'cha learn from the video?
- [Female Student] She can do anything.
- [Teacher] Ok, what else?
- [Boy] She likes to sing.
- [Girl] Be positive.
- [Teacher] She likes
to sing, be positive.
What else?
What else did you learn about the video?
- [Female student] Believe in yourself.
- [Teacher] Believe in yourself.
Okay now how is this going to be
related to our yearbook class?
- [Female student] Stay positive about it.
People get a... what's gonna--
what the outcome's gonna be.
- [Teacher] Okay, and the outcome
is something that we wanna
be able to serve the entire school.
Okay, what else? How is this
also related to yearbook
and what we're trying to accomplish?
- [Girl in turtleneck] We shouldn't blame ourselves?
- [Teacher] I'm sorry?
- [Girl in turgleneck] We shouldn't blame ourselves?
- [Teacher] Okay, good, good.
Okay, so what we're
going to do after this
this is a good start, I
think, for the work that
we're gonna be having
to do this afternoon.
We're gonna have to work on our ladder.
And I know that we've
spent some time on it,
we've had to make some
considerable changes.
But I think that the compromise..
the agreement that we all
talked about yesterday,
I think it can be implemented today.
So what we're gonna try
to do, is based on...
These are the signatures,
that we have allocated.
One signature for elementary school.
One signature for middle school.
And five signatures for the high school.
I think let's try to fit it in.
Let's try to stay within
the seven signatures.
Don't forget, we have ads also.
Okay, so I think Tanisha, and...
Dustin, and...
Jazz, will be on team one.
And Sammy, Emily, and
Colleen, will be on team two.
Let's work together.
What are the rules of
getting the teamwork going?
When we're trying to discuss,
What are the things that
I want you to think about?
- [Girl in gray] Everyone has a voice.
- [Teacher] Okay, everyone has a voice.
What else?
- [Female student] We all have to agree
to a middle ground.
- [Teacher] Okay.
- [Female student] And it's not just for
the high school seniors.
- [Teacher] Okay, so it's for the entire school.
The elementary school, middle
school and high school.
So let's be fair, and try
to get everybody involved.
What else?
Discussion-wise, among yourselves.
What would I like you to be working on?
Collaborative work?
Compromise?
(Students agreeing)
- [Teacher] Okay, let's go ahead and start.
You have the books there,
you have copies of the previous ladder.
Let's get it good.
(Students discuss among themselves)
-[Teacher] Yeah?
- [Female student] I understand, elementary school,
middle school, high school.
In what order--
- [Teacher] It's up to you honey.
If you want to start
with the middle school,
elementary school, high school.
- [Girl in gray shirt] I don't know, maybe
just 'cause I'm a senior,
I kinda like that plan.
- [Girl in turtleneck] It just seems weird
starting at the elementary school.
I think it's just that, they're
not as important, just that--
- [Girl in gray shirt] 'Cause it's always
started at high school.
It starts with the seniors and it's like
this is what, for--
- [Teacher] Okay now, remember, just
because it's always done before--
- [Girl in gray shirt] I know but--
- [Girl in turtleneck] If we started with
the elementary school,
We'd be starting with the fourth grade.
And that's really our--
- [Girl in gray shirt] Kind of an
awkward place to start.
- [Teacher] Okay, now remember with your signature,
you were gonna start with Student Life, correct?
With the High School?
So you could start with that.
I mean look at it and you can see.
(Students continue discussion)
- [Girl in blue] And then we're
gonna start it with,
like the introduction...
Um, like, um...
- [Boy in red] Pictures.
- [Girl in blue] Student life, candid shots.
- [Teacher] Right.
- [Girl in blue] And then we're going to the
seniors and all the senior
stuff, and our classes.
And then the sports and night clubs?
- [Girl in pink] Yes.
- [Girl in gray shirt] We're
not gonna have a class...
class division page, anymore.
'Cause all of the classes are scrambled.
Are we still thinking,
like, doing division pages?
Like how it was worded originally?
Except, not for the classes.
Because all the classes were split up.
- [Teacher] Yeah, now it makes it easier
to do your "me", right?
Don't forget, what's our theme?
- [Students] "Me".
- [Teacher] Okay, so keep that it mind
when you're creating your signatures.
And I think, now that solicited more...
allocated, the sections are allocated.
Your division pages--
maybe more adaptable.
- [Male student] They'll fit in there more.
- [Teacher] Yeah. They'll fit in there more.
Don't ya think?
- [Girl in gray shirt] I guess.
(Teacher laughs)
- [Girl in turtleneck] So should we
just do one, like
just high school division
page, then middle school--
- [Teacher] Yes, try it and see.
See.
Now you might still need a
division page for sports,
you might still need a division page.
But you don't need as many.
I think--
- [Girl in gray shirt] We definitely won't
have one for the classes.
'Cause they're all split up.
- [Teacher] They're already split up.
And I think this is
what helped save us pages.
Remember, you're getting eight signatures.
- [Girl in gray shirt] Um, Question.
- [Teacher] Yeah.
- [Girl in gray shirt] The yearbook,
two pages and ads
is under the high school?
- [Teacher] Only because, I just put that as
just to remind you that we need
to have ads at the very end.
- [Girl in gray shirt] Okay.
- [Teacher] So whatever, is your last section,
you have to have ads.
We have to start selling ads.
And again, if you have any
questions on the photographs,
Sammy is here she can help you
with what ever photograph you want.
(student's continue to discuss)
- [Boy in red](whispering question)
(Teacher giggles)
- [Girl in blue] Show the blood drive scales.
And then...
(Continued debate)
- [Girl in turtleneck] But their only
sport is the seventh grade basketball.
Everything else is going into high school.
- [Teacher] Does it make sense?
- [Boy in red] Yeah, yeah.
- [Girl in turtleneck] They all happened
right there, together.
- [Boy in red] Are we still gonna do straight lines,
and single lines like they did?
- [Female Student] I think we might
just do a big column.
- [Girl in blue] Yeah.
- [Girl in pink] We can still do that,
and then after our seniors,
we can explore all the classes in line.
- [Teacher] And it makes sense?
If you have that quote.
- [Students] Yeah.
- [Girl in blue] We are gonna do...
"Student Life", seniors,
all the senior stuff,
And then classes?
- [Teacher] Make sure that you
have your page counts.
- [Girl in gray] Are doing
school division pages or are we
doing section division pages?
- [Girl in turtleneck] I guess we could
do school, and then--
We would have to have the
division pages that we thought of--
the spread division page
with all the things.
It could just be different
little division pages.
- [Girl in gray] Yeah, okay, so...
- [Girl in turtleneck] Or like, have
the title at the top of the page.
(Students listing divisions to each other quietly)
- [Teacher] Don't forget,
she has control of the photographs.
So you need to consult with her, okay?
You can ask her.
- [Girl in gray shirt] Okay, um.
- [Girl in turtleneck](whispered question)
- [Girl in gray] So are we going
to do a senior opening page?
- [Girl in turtleneck] I think we could just
have... an opening page, on the division page.
- [Girl in blue] I thought we were going
to do the top.
(Both groups debate to themselves)
- [Girl in blue] Instead
of doing a collage,
how they put in their, like, the song
and all that on the second page.
Around all the photos, we should put--
'Cause, in our theme or
whatever, it's just a strip.
Of pictures.
Blended in the big picture.
So we're have written
around it, to add in these.
So I think that we should put these,
on the first, opening page.
- [Teacher] Now remember, we did
this only because...
we had no choice.
- [Girl in blue] I like, well I like,
the happenings
that we decided not to do,
for the opening page for the seniors.
Because, it's new life.
Since our theme, it's just one strip.
We could arrange it like this.
I think that we should put, on that page,
we should put these.
- [Teacher] Oh, definitely.
Yeah, good idea.
Well, what happened, is the reason
why I placed it and you placed it here
because when you sort it all originally,
it was so empty, and it
didn't mean anything,
so, we went ahead and did that.
- [Boy in red] I think it would have
been better to do that
from the beginning.
- [Teacher] And then we can have
Alex start doing
the onward for two others.
- [Girl in pink] Do we...
want to put favorites before the formal?
- [Girl in blue] I think we should put favorites.
- [Teacher] So, we're talking this one, right?
These are the formals you
want before the favorites.
- [Girl in blue] No, we want our
favorites before our formals.
- [Teacher] Oh, Okay.
- [Girl in blue] And then we're combining formal
and baby pictures in quotes right?
- [Teacher] Yeah.
Well, you know, what do you think?
- [Girl in blue] Well
I like, combining it.
- [Girl in gray] Can you pull up the other ladder?
Do you still have that one?
[Boy in red] If we have that picture,
and then another picture, and then another--
- [Teacher] This one?
Is this the ladder you want to see?
Which section do you want to pull?
- [Girl in gray] "Student life".
I think it's on that.
- [Teacher] Right here?
- [Girl in gray] Yeah.
- [Teacher] Let me know.
Because then I can go
back and let her know.
- [Girl in gray] So, you want to start off with that?
- [Girl in blue] So it'll be like...
The formal, then the
baby, and then the quote.
- [Teacher] Can you tell Emily what
she missed yesterday?
About the quotes.
No, were you present?
When you said that a lot of seniors
who didn't have quotes last year.
- [Girl in gray shirt] They would rather
have a big list of them
and just have them pick and cross it off.
If they can come up with their own.
- [Teacher] And I have a quote book.
Somewhere, and we can start deciding.
We can go from very
funny, to very serious.
So the kids can have a good choice.
(Students continue discussing quietly)
- [Teacher] Did you want me to go
back to the other one?
(Both groups engage in discussion)
- [Teacher] How are you deciding the order?
Is it, just from serious to funny or...
- [Girl in blue] Well it's more, funner
stuff, the memories
into the more serious stuff.
- [Teacher] And you're ending it
with the grauduation?
- [Boy in red] Yeah.
- [Teacher] You rather repeat our homecoming?
- [Girl in gray shirt] But that's spirit week.
- [Teacher] There's another one--
- [Girl in gray shirt] That's what
homecoming fills.
This is the problem.
On the other ladder that we had,
the only high school "Student Life" we had
was "Holten Hemming" and "Spirit Week".
- [Teacher] That's the same thing.
- [Girl in gray shirt] Yeah, Hemming
and Spirit Week.
Like, one spread and
then the awards honors.
Well that doesn't make up
for all the signatures.
- [Girl in turtleneck] Oh, then we had prom.
- [Teacher] You had the prom, and then you had...
how about the senior, the um...
"Sports Banquet".
Sports Banquet should award everybody.
Not just seniors.
- [Girl in gray shirt] Yeah, it's got uh--
- [Teacher] Do you want to put that under student--
- [Girl in gray shirt] I don't...
- [Girl in turtleneck] What if we--
You cut the prom down to one page,
but maybe we could, put
it back to two pages,
we could show, like the planning
of prom and setting it up.
- [Teacher] Okay, but--
- [Girl in turtleneck] 'Cause I'm
on the prom committee.
- [Teacher] Okay, so, and you have
your committee meeting,
start taking pictures.
Guys, remember, we have seven cameras.
So take cameras with you when
you're having little meetings.
Just make sure you're flexible enough,
just in case we don't
have enough pictures,
you can flip back to one
page instead of the signature.
I mean, instead of a spread.
- [Girl in gray shirt] Well,
I don't know how we're
gonna fill up the signature then.
- [Teacher] Well you don't have to have--
we can move everything up.
- [Girl in gray shirt] And then
we move seniors up
into another half of the signature,
and that half would have to be colored.
Because it's the senior signature.
- [Teacher] Um...
Do you have a section for committee?
- [Girl in gray shirt] We had those
in with the clubs.
With like, all of their--
what they do in the community.
- [Teacher] Okay, if you want, you can
bring it up a little more.
Just the overall community
that doesn't have a club.
And use up that space.
Like the blood drive.
The blood drive is not part of the school.
- [Girl in gray shirt] Rotary does that.
- [Teacher] Rotary, yes, but that's the...
interact is with Rotary, yes?
- [Girl in gray shirt] Yeah, we help with that.
We help Rotary.
- [Teacher] But you also do the "Victorian Classic"?
- [Girl in gray shirt] Yes.
- [Teacher] You don't have enough space.
You need to put the blood drive up.
I mean, how much space breaks--
- [Girl in gray shirt] A spread.
- [Teacher] Oh, Interact has a spread?
- [Girl in gray shirt] Yeah, we've
covered this three times now.
- [Teacher] Okay, sorry.
Yes, but we've changed it three times.
So...
Find other community things.
Well, if you want, do you want
to talk about the tax bill?
- [Girl in gray shirt] Well, that's not
really student life.
- [Teacher] It's going to affect your life.
- [Girl in gray shirt] Yeah, but...