- [Insructor] Gina.
- I wanted to test the amount of acid in
different brands of antacids, example
Alka-Seltzer, Maalox and Tums, can
effectively neutralize.
- Okay, so far we've been listening to
this, are we talking mostly the same
equipment, same supplies?
- Yeah.
- Right? Maybe some beakers, maybe some
pipettes and some base? Right? Okay, is
this similar to, Juan's? This one is,
right? So maybe we can start grouping
these two together. Christina.
- The goal of my investigation is to
determine which laundry detergent is most
effective, Tide, Clorox, or OxyClean by
determining which is most basic.
- Any concerns? Yeah? Adrian?
- How do you know that the most effective
detergents are gonna be the most basic?
Maybe there's some other factors that go
into that and they're, it's just,
basic-ness.
- Juan?
- That some of them have really strong
bases and maybe the vapors, I mean, Some
of them have safety warnings that say
like, don't get too close to the vapors
that come out.
- Okay, so there could be some toxic
chemicals that are associated with these
which is why we shouldn't use them? Is
that what you mean?
- Yeah.
- Okay, okay, we use them in our homes,
but don't bring them to school, right?
- Yeah, I'm a little concerned too,
about your idea that it's about which one
is most basic. Okay? 'Cause the active
ingredient in Clorox, I think, is bleach,
and bleach--
- Sodium hypochlorite.
- Is sodium hypochlorite.
- Which has a pretty interesting smell.
- I'd stay away from that.
And then we have Tide, right? Tide is
not bleach, all right? I'm not sure what
the actual detergent, active ingredient
is, but I'm pretty sure it's not bleach.
So, this is probably going to require some
cleaning up and making sure that we test
something that we can test, and that it
makes sense why we're testing it. Okay?
All right, we'll come back to this.
- And OxyClean is powered by Billy Mays,
so it doesn't matter, it wins anyway.
- I think he died, didn't he?
- Yeah he did, it's too bad.
- You know, that guy must have made so
much money, I better not complain.
- Adrian! Go ahead.
- I will find the molarity of one of the
magnesium sulfate bottles in the lab
inventory. To do this I'll mix 50
milliliters of magnesium sulfate with 50
milliliters of one molar calcium chloride
in a beaker. I'll mix it to form a
precipitate of calcium sulfate. After as
much precipitate as possible has formed
I'll weigh the precipitate and calculate
the molarity of the magnesium sulfate
solution with the data collected.
- Any ideas? Jimmy?
- I'm kinda wondering why it's important
to you, like you said, to make the lab
meaningful.
- Yeah, it should be. So Adrian, do you
have a response?
- It's just 'cause bottles that don't have
molarity kind of annoy me, and I feel like
I should, there should be like a label
that says the molarity, I just kinda...
- You know my room is open fifth period
every day, you can come on in and do these
experiments and get them so that you know
their concentrations.
- I don't have a free fifth period.
- After school's fine too.
- That's cool, that's cool.
- What concerns me is, I thought the
theme was titration, right? Is the theme
titration? Okay, where is the titration
aspect to this? Do you know what I'm
asking here?
- Yeah, I know, I just didn't realize.
- Because you're mixing, you're doing a
precipitate reaction, everybody see it
that way. I think you're doing a
precipitate reaction and, so I just feel
like, you know, this, you had the wrong
theme going on here. Anyway, we'll move
on. Nicholas, Artel, Artel. Sirhan Sirhan,
although he was a bad man, though I think,
right? He was accused of being a bad man.
Go ahead!
- The goal of my investigation is to see
which of two pills have more Vitamin C per
100 milligrams. I will take two different
pills and weigh them to 100 milligrams and
cut away mass as appropriate, crush them,
dissolve in water and use a base to
titrate it. I would also use a pH sensor
to see what the solution, to see when the
solution is at seven, to see when it's
neutralized. Doing this will let me know
which company I should buy from for my
Vitamin C pills.
- What do you guys think? Vitamin C is
ascorbic acid, I don't know if you wrote
that. Did you? No, okay, so if it's an
acid, you can titrate it, right? Is
anybody concerned about, like, anything
here? Jimmy?
- Don't the pills tell you how much
Vitamin C is in them? Like, the bottle?
- Wait, let me make sure, if you buy a
Vitamin C that says 100 milligrams of
Vitamin C, my assumption is when you pull
out one of them tablets, and you crush it
and you do this experiment, it's gonna be
close to that 100 milligrams. So are you
testing because you think they're not
accurate?
- Yeah.
- Oh! Okay, so you're testing for accuracy
on their part, just to keep them honest.
- Because, I mean, 100 milligrams, it's
kind of a, non-specific number.
- All right, Ian?
- Actually, another way you could look at
it is that, just because it says 100
milligrams, that's how much of the Vitamin
C is in it, that's not how big the tablet
is. Being that sometime, I mean you could
have, and say, just arbitrary numbers, you
could have a 500 milligram tablet that has
that 100 milligrams of vitamin C, or you
could have a 200 milligram tablet with
that same 100 milligrams of vitamin C, so
you might wanna know which one actually
had more stuff in it, actually had more
stuff in it per, density.
- Okay but, is that what you want him to
do, I thought, are you doing it because you
wanna make sure that when they write 100,
you don't care how big this tablet is,
unless, unless, what's the danger here?
Some of that other that tablet contains,
acids or bases in them, then that would
affect your results, right?
- One of them I have is pretty pure, it's
pretty much just ascorbic acid, the other
company I have does have some other stuff
in it, so I was wondering if anybody else
had like one that was mostly Vitamin C.
- Have you ever been to like, the CVS and
looked in the section--
- I mean, I could find one I just
haven't--
- There's a bunch, you could even--
- What'd you guys figure out?
- It's turning yellow.
- Why do you think it's doing that?
- Maybe the bicarbonate when it dissolves,
gets out some CO2 and turns it acidic. I
didn't think it would be that big of a
deal because--
- Wait! Hang on, so you mean, so far what
you've done is you've crushed these things
you tried to dissolve them and you added
some bromothymol blue?
- Yeah.
- And, that bromothymol blue is not quite
the color that you want?
- That's right.
- That's what you're saying?
- Yeah.
- What color should it be?
- Blue, I guess. It's kind of, green. It
just looks as if this coloring is just,
green dye.
- Have you thought about using like
phenolphthalein? That has a distinctly
pink color, otherwise it's clear.
- No, we did not think of that.
- You wanna try that?
- Yeah.
- Yeah, that'd be better.
[Background Chatter]
- So, the phenolphthalein is gonna be,
it's probably going to be behind... -
If it's pink it's acidic right?
- No, if it's basic.
[Background Chatter]
- Do the bubbles matter?
- All right, could I just stop and ask you
guys, did you guys get your color change
you were looking for?
- Yeah.
- So the titration is working out?
- [together] Yep.
- Very clean.
- What? So, tell me what you got here?
- This is a disinfecting Clorox, we're
just starting out, we're just trying to
measure out 10 milliliters. That one we're
done with, we got it to the brown, like,
it didn't stir anymore, that was it.
- That's as far as it went?
- We put in 61 and that was it. Now we're
going to start this one. And that worked
with the one molar.
- So is this, oh, so this is a different
concentration? Or how is this one
different, this is just a different--
- This is a different type, and it's a
different percentage of the hypochlorate.
- That's disinfecting spray and that's
bleach.
- With a different type of Clorox cleaning
product.
- All right. Did you make sure that mixing
some of these would not produce anything
poisonous?
- No, we did not make sure. But they're--
- I just wanna, you know, we don't wanna
create any of these strange gases coming
out of here.
- When we looked at the reaction this is
the reaction that they showed on the
thing. And this was fine, like it said it
should be done in basic and everything.
- Okay.
- God bless you.
- Excuse me.
[Background Chatter]
- How's everything going?
- Not good with this one.
- What's in there?
- It's red wine vinegar.
- But it hasn't changed color.
- The treatment's too powerful.
- Yeah, we're thinking it's too...
- So, we're gonna do the white--
- What's the solution to that, then? Why
don't you just use less?
- Less of the vinegar?
- Right. All right?
- So we use five milliliters instead of
10.
- Well, I mean, right? If you use less,
then don't you think you'll be able to
titrate it--
- Easier.
- Well, you'd need less base to get there.
- Right.
- Okay.
- Let's go over here, see what happens over here.
[Background Chatter]
- So, squeeze that out.
- What are you guys, so you've got Vitamin
C, crushed in there, you used, is this
bromothymol blue, what did you use?
- Yeah, we used BTB, and now we're gonna
see how much base we used.
- Just out of curiosity, why did you use a
graduat--, what is this about, 50? You
didn't want to use like... 'Cause
that is, are you gonna--
- All the other ones were like dirty.
- Yeah, they were kinda...
- And I think this is accurate to two sig
figs which is our experiment's limit.
[Background Chatter]
- All right, coming along okay it looks
like.
- [together] 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9,
10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19,
20.
- Hi!
- You're adding 20 drops of bromothymol
blue?
- Yeah. Is that too much?
- Well, has it occurred to you, and it
probably hasn't, it's okay, bromothymol
blue itself is either a weak, my guess is
it's a weak acid, it could be a weak base,
but all indicators are going to be weak
acids and bases. So, we always want to use
a bare minimum amount. Therefore, how
about if you use something that has a
distinct color change, roughly at the,
neutral point, like phenolphthalein.
'Cause then it'll go from pink,
your...
- This is acid.
- These are acids, so they'll go from
clear to a pinkish color.
- Okay, okay, but do you think the pink
will be able to be seen?
- Well--
- Like the blue one?
- You know, the blue you need to use a lot
more to get there, although, I don't know,
I suppose since you already did this one--
- I mean, we could remeasure, out--
- You may wanna, well, we don't want to
run out of time here, so, right? Stay
consistent and then consider it, how you
can make improvements later.
- Okay.
- All right?
[Background Chatter] [clapping and laughter]
- Now that's very nice.
- You guys have questions?
- What was your results in comparing what
the company says and what you--
- There was a little bit less, since we
used 500 milligrams and the company
labeled it as pretty much pure, pure
ascorbic acid. As in the first trials it
was around 480 per kil to, which is, it's
pretty close and the other one was around
410, 400.so I mean it's a little bit less
than what you're probably paying for.
But--
- But that's, then again, it could've
been, because--
- Because not all the powder dissolved,
some of it was still settled on the
bottom.
- So they could be really accurate?
- Yeah they could be, you know, dead on.
- For the trials, did you guys use
different amounts of stuff, for the two
trials?
- For the first two trials we used 500
milligrams of powder for each pill, and
then, for the third trial we used 100,
right? A hundred.
- And then for those trials, like the
third one you said you used a different
concentration of NaOH?
- Yeah.
- Why did you use a different
concentration?
- First of all there wasn't much left of
the .567, and also, you know, who's to--,
you know, maybe that could've been
contaminated, it might not have been .567,
so it's also good to use some different
stuff sometimes.
- Right.
- You can't always base it, you can't have
it all on one thing.
- Yeah, that's smart.
- How did yo actually figure out the
amounts? What was the math?
- [together] Oh!
- We did the stoichiometry.
- Yeah, but we assumed that it was a
one-to-one ratio, one hydrogen ion
dissolved from the ascorbic acid from one
OH from the base. And so we just
calculated moles and changed moles to
grams using the formula mass of Vitamin C.
- Do you know with certainty that ascorbic
acid is one H plus?
- No we just assumed that, for the
experiment.
- Maybe you should look that up.
- Yeah.
- The other thing, anybody else? So the
other thing is, and I just wanna make
sure, when you said 500 milligrams, that's
.5 grams, right?
- We did it accurate with--
- Yeah, 'cause that thing, the scales here
give you two sig figs, right? Okay, I mean
to the hundredths, hundredths of a gram,
right? So you crush this thing and you
weighed out .50?
- [together] Yeah.
- That's what you did it? How much was
left in the... ; I mean, of one tablet,
when you, you know what I mean? When you
crush it?
- Yeah--
- How much--
- We had excess, I mean, one of the pills
I had was 1000 milligrams, so we, you
know, we had about, we had a, like, about,
500--
- It is my fault for--
- Oh, you were using 1000 milligram
tablets.
- And then my pill was 500 milligrams and
then we weighed them and it was actually
six five seven, like milligrams.
- That's how we removed--
- So we had to-- we removed mass.
- Oh, well how 'bout this, if it, if they
say 500, but the thing weighs six...
What'd you say, six or seven hundred?
- Oh yeah.
- Then, aren't there other ingredients
already in there?
- Not that were listed, like--
- Yeah, they weren't listed--
- It just said, it just said Vitamin C--
- Because they might just list the active
ingredient, right?
- Yeah.
- In other words, if the pill itself
weighs more than the 500 that they claim,
my guess would be there's more of
something else.
- Okay.
- Because here's another thing. Don't you
need possibly a binding agent to keep all
the Vitamin C in a clump? Do you see what
I'm saying?
- [together] Yeah , yeah.
- And they'll typically use, some, there's
gonna be some certain chemicals they're
gonna use that's in there. So I have a
feeling before you write the company, be
careful, they're--
- [together] Yeah, yeah.
- They probably added other ingredients.
- Yeah.
- Because what I think might've been even
better is if they claim 500, then why
don't you just crush the whole thing,
regardless of how much it weighs? And then
titrate that. You see what I'm saying?
- [together] Yes.
- 'Cause then, they're claiming there's
500 in this thing, let's see, based on
the... You see what I'm saying?
- So that would be taking further just
simply--
- Yeah, that would be--
- The experiment.
- Wouldn't that be like the next--
- Yeah.
- Thing that you could try? Same thing
with 1000, right? I mean if they
claim 1000.
- Yeah.
- Go crush the whole thing and see what--