[Background chatter]
- [Boy in Blue] Isn't it nuclear
fission when, like, fusion?
No, fusion is when they combine.
Nuclear fission is like when
they split apart, right?
- Yes, so it's a fission process.
- [Boy in Blue] See? Ah!
- So that's a (mumbles), I see that,
that efficient.
- [Boy in Blue] Efficient.
- It increases the safety though, right?
- [Boy in Blue] It's
impossible to explain.
- No, I'm just saying, does it?
- [Boy in Blue] No, I don't understand.
Am I the only one here?
- Apparently to you, though. (chuckles)
- So, why is it that when
the atom is unstable
it's radioactive?
- It could be it's removing
protons and neutrons?
- I think you guys can discuss this.
- [Boy in Blue] Isn't it
when like it starts releasing
the neutrons to a different
atom, or something,
and then it gains the neutron,
and that's when it starts becoming, like--
- More vulnerable--
- [Boy in Blue] More vulnerable,
and it starts, like, a chain reaction.
- [Boy in Blue] You guys agree?
- I agree.
- [Multiple] I agree.
- [Boy in Red] I agree with everybody.
- That's right.
(chuckles)
- [Boy in Blue] So, how
can radiation help them?
Like Amy said--
- It could also help in the electricity
and helps us get our resources.
- Like you said.
(students chuckle)
- [Boy in Red] What else though?
- Like cancer.
- [Voiceover] Cancer?
- [Boy in Blue] Cancer.
- I mean, I had an aunt
that suffered from cancer
and it kind of helped her
even though she passed away.
It kept her longer than it would have been
without her having medication.
- Any last thoughts?
Okay, that's fine, thank you.
I have only one major, I guess comment,
about that one.
I noticed Steve used a
lot of vocabulary words.
He did remember a lot of the words,
and I think he planned for that.
And then I liked the way that David
actually redirected the group.
He asked the group, "How
can radiation help us?"
right at the end,
and then people responded to that.
So, he kind of helped redirect the questions
for the discussion group.
So, and then people were able to respond.
So, that was a nice way
to create a discussion.
Okay, question number two.
- [Student] Three.
- [Multiple] Three.
- I'm sorry.
Okay, I mean...
- How about number four next?
- [Teacher] Okay, I'm
going to do number four next.
- No!
- Do number three.
The one with three.
- No, I'm going to do four.
- No, I want to do three.
Okay, number four is going to go next.
You have two minutes to prepare.
(students chatter)
Number four.
Just ignore it.
- What is that?
- [Teacher] A microphone.
- Oh, it works?
So, they can hear me right now?
Oh. (laughs)
- It's recording?
- [Voiceover] Well, why do
you think President Obama
might support building
nuclear power plants
in the USA and what are some arguments
for nuclear energy?
- [Teacher] David, put that away.
(chuckles)
- [Teacher] Okay, Jane,
who's going to go next?
- [Jane] Me.
- Jane.
- [Teacher] Okay, so which
vocabulary and evidence
are you going to focus on?
- [Jane] Nuclear power plant,
nuclear power plant--
- [Teacher] Well, pick several.
- [Jane] The nuclear, yeah.
The nuclear power plant can
help us create more energy.
I mean, well it's--
- Nuclear radiation,
for my argument.
- [Teacher] You know what Dano was saying?
- No.
- [Teacher] He was just
going to put power plants.
- Do you know what it is?
- Yeah, it's where they
(drowned out by chatter).
Yeah.
- [Teacher] Okay, what does it do?
- Creates energy.
- [Teacher] Okay.
- [Teacher] Okay, what
other evidence are you
going to use, though?
- The fact that we are running out of,
well, we're not running out of, but,
in the future we might not be
able to find enough energy
(drowned out by chatter).
So, we need to start.
We need to start thinking
about the future, like--
- Jobs and stuff.
- No, future things that are like,
the future and what's going to happen
and energy and how are we going to have
a good supply.
Like what if we were running out
and start thinking about that?
- Okay, so the next person.
(students chatter)
Okay, so the people on the outside,
if you were recording
the vocabulary last time,
I want the people on the outside to switch
so that you're recording
something different.
So if you did evidence
first, switch to vocabulary.
If you did vocabulary, switch to evidence.
- Oh, Sindi, sit like right here.
(students chatter)
- Okay, this question is why
do you think President Obama
might support building nuclear
power plants in the U.S.,
and based on the video we watched,
what are some arguments to
be made for nuclear energy?
- I think President Obama
might support building
nuclear power plants in the U.S.
because it doesn't release chemicals,
therefore it's eco-friendly,
making the U.S. more green.
Environmentally, green.
- I agree with her, because
another reason I think
the president might support
it is because, like,
like right now we're
in an economic crisis,
what you call the thing? And then like
making new plants may
create more jobs for people.
It'll create jobs for building them,
and then it'll also benefit
everybody for clean power.
- [Multiple] I agree.
(students chuckle)
- I agree because it builds
economic stabilization,
and it'll create jobs for the future,
like, for more years,
because in order to run
a nuclear power plant
you need, you know, like, to build it.
And once it's built, you
still need to work with it
so I think the job's
going to last for a while.
- I agree.
- [Boy in Glasses] But if
we're in an economic crisis,
like if we're in an economic crisis
how are you going to pay for it?
Like, where's the money going to come from?
- Well, we're already in debt, so we'll
get even more debt.
- [Boy in Glasses] Yeah,
it costs a lot to build
a nuclear reactor.
- We'd get funding.
- [Multiple] Yeah.
- And we have to, like,
think about the future
and how it's going to benefit, you know,
for the economy and
making more power plants
would just provide, like, a stable future
for the upcoming people and the jobs
because it supplies more jobs and stuff.
- [Boy in Gray] And more, you know,
we'll get more electricity.
You know, if we build
more nuclear power plants.
- Yeah, and not just 20%, but
more like the other countries
who have 30 and stuff like that--
- (mumbles) needs luxuries,
rising electricity demands.
It won't leave the U.S. behind
and all the new tech stuff?
(student murmurs)
- [Boy in Black Hoodie]
And the more factories,
and the more power plants
we produce, we make,
the more electricity
and the more factories,
it will get more stuff.
It will build the more jobs,
and that will raise up
the economic problems.
- Yeah, because more stuff
will be done that way.
- So, now you guys have
given a lot of arguments
supporting nuclear energy.
What do you think is the biggest
problem with nuclear energy
that we should be aware of?
- The thing that causes cancer.
- Probably be the radioactive waste
that the nuclear power plants give off.
Well, they don't give it
off, the water, the coolant
or whatever.
And then, like, they don't
have nowhere to store it.
I think it was some cave thingy
that they were trying to
build, but they didn't build.
- [Boy in Black Hoodie]
They're going to run out of space
to put the waste in.
(students talk over each other)
- [Boy in Black Hoodie]
Also, it's going to cause cancer
to everyone.
- But doesn't it cure cancer and stuff?
- It has benefits, but more
like some freak accident
can happen, like what
happened in Fukushima.
- Or the third mile.
- At the Three Mile?
- Yeah.
(students speak over each other)
- So, say you never know what can happen,
that's the downside.
Because if it does happen,
then it's like downhill from there
because people start getting sick,
then their kids start
dying, and I don't know.
- Yeah, and like Giovanni said, if
we are in an economic crisis,
like where are we going to
get the rest of the money?
We're just going to get it from debt
and stuff like that.
We're going to help raise it up,
but we'll also fall more in debt.
- Yeah.
- Going back to the nuclear waste,
can someone elaborate on
why is the nuclear waste
such a problem?
- Because it's just there--
- Kevin?
- [Kevin] I think nuclear
waste will cause more
wars and pollution.
That's what I think.
- [Teacher] Cause more what?
- [Kevin] It causes
more war and pollution.
- [Multiple] War?
- [Kevin] Well, I mean.
(students chuckle)
This isn't on camera, right?
(students laugh)
- Okay, someone else?
- Wait, what was the question again?
- Elaborate on what is nuclear waste?
- Nuclear waste?
- Why is that such a problem for us?
- Well, it's a problem
because there's nowhere
where you could actually safely put it.
Other than like, I think they have this,
I read something about they have an island
where all the waste of nuclear waste goes.
That's the only place that
you can, like, get rid of it.
Don't throw it in the ocean
because it'll contaminate everything.
You can't just, like,
leave it in the ground
because then it'll probably like leak.
- And also, doesn't it, if it rains,
if water gets in it, it's dangerous?
So, that's why they have to find a place
where it's not like--
- Why is it dangerous
if water gets into it?
(students speak over each other)
- Soil, I guess?
- [Boy in Black Hoodie]
The waste and the water mix
and then, like, it runs down into the soil
and it might go into
the ocean or the sewers
and it'll mess up the
ocean, or, like, water--
- And we end up drinking it.
- [Boy in Black Hoodie]
And scientists are trying
to find ways to get rid of the waste,
like they're thinking of
shooting it out into space
or anything.
(students chatter)
- One thing nobody talked
about was half-life.
What does the half-life have
to do with nuclear waste?
- I think a bunch of years.
- [Boy in Black Hoodie] What
does it have to do with Obama?
(students murmur)
- Say it louder.
- What?
- We're talking about that noise.
(students chuckle)
- Wait, what was your question?
- What does half-life have
to do with nuclear waste?
- Half-life, nuclear waste.
- So, energy?
- So, why is nuclear waste bad exactly?
- Oh, because they haven't
determined the amount of years
of when the half-life is.
I think they determined like
10,000 years or something.
So they, so it was an estimate.
It wasn't actually a fact,
they just estimated that,
so it could be before,
so they wouldn't be able
to prevent, to prevent it
from affecting society.
- Oh, good.
So, let's just get this done.
Let's try the next group, okay?
Thank you.
(students chattering)
- I know, Bryan.
- I don't need to look it up.
I know this already.
- Okay.
Do you guys want to
break before you go up?
Okay, you guys get one or two minutes
to prep yourself.  So it's not a shock
(chattering)
Okay, question number
three, let's come up.
People seem anxious, let's do this.
(students chattering)
Okay, no phone Diana.
- We're missing people.
- Yeah, we are.
Okay, so people on the outside,
you guys should switch.
So, if you did evidence, you know.
So, what you did one time
evidence, looking for evidence,
and one time you're
looking for vocabulary.
Okay?
So, people on the outside
make sure you're checking different parts.
Okay, so what, I might change
the question, you guys.
- What?
- It happens.
Okay, number three.
What recommendations would
you make to President Obama
regarding clean energy and climate change?
So, for example, they're trying to build
two nuclear power plants in Georgia.
So, what recommendations
will you make to him
about building in Georgia?
- Building in jorj-ee-uh?
- Georgia, the state.
- Um, I think he should
make sure that employees
aren't making careless mistakes
such as the human error in the
Three Mile Island.
- [Girl in Black] I think that
he should promote programs
on alternative energy, but
not just nuclear energy.
But he could also use nuclear
energy because it could,
because the field cost
and operating cost is low
and 20% of our energy already
comes from nuclear energy.
So, we could just get more
energy through nuclear power.
- [Boy in Stripes] I think we
shouldn't use it because of,
it causes harm to people
and you never know
when an accident happens,
and it might hurt the environment
and it leads to cancer.
- Okay, nuclear energy
affects public safety
and it creates,
nuclear power plants create toxic waste.
- [Boy in Stripes] I would
still try to build a nuclear
power plant because it
could also boost our economy
when it's most struggling.
- [Boy in White]
Recommendations I would make
to Obama regarding nuclear energy is that,
to stop because it's
too dangerous to handle,
and that if it gets in
the hands of terrorists,
they can use it to murder,
to murder me or destroy countries.
We can't prevent natural disasters
from destroying nuclear power plants,
then the nuclear radiation,
which is unstable,
can harm by radioactivity,
and a nuclear spill has
happened in the past
with human error that hit Fukushima.
And this means that it can
happen to anyone, even us.
That's what I wrote.
- I think it could be a good idea,
but I think they should focus more on
how it could harm people,
to try and control the harmfulness
so it won't harm people.
Yeah, I think it's a good idea.
- I think my recommendation
for Obama is that it
is not good to (mumbles) nuclear
because it's going to affect us,
it's going to affect our pollution.
And he's going to spend
like more energy on that
and he can save more money
if he didn't do that.
- Yeah, I agree with Charlie, too.
We don't know what nuclear energy
could also, like, harm us, which ways.
Or, I mean we do, but I mean, it's better.
Like we could just focus
on studying more, like,
having more thoughts.
Like, ask him what's better?
It's like to choose nuclear plants or
to keep using what we're using now.
- So, I have to change one question.
Based on all the videos and the articles
you guys saw and read,
what argument has influenced you the most?
- [Boy in White] The Fukushima argument.
- So, go ahead and explain
it to the group, though.
- Because, um,
things happen and they just prove to us
that they can also happen to us,
like human error.
And I think they made
people evacuate the cities
and the damage, the area which is,
nobody can go because it's radioactive,
and they have to wait
for the atoms to decay
which is like, I don't know,
thousands of years just for the half-life,
and we won't be able to
use that space anymore.
It kills everything.
People got cancer.