- [Instructor] Inner circle number two.
Again, this was a question that was asked
in a multitude of ways and this is where
we're going with this: Why did the accident
happen? The accident of May 10th, 1996.
Why did it happen? Any questions?
- [Background Chatter]
- Yes, the May 10th, 1996,
thank you for clarifying, where everybody
died, well not everybody, but a lot of
people died. Why did it happen?
- [male student] Because... [Background Chatter]
- Okay, so, I think the reason the accident
happened was maybe those people just
weren't prepared for for the climb.
They thought it was going to be they're just
going to go up with a guide and some other people
they were just going to go to the top and
come back down and it was gonna be an easy thing
and they didn't expect the challenges that
they were going to face.
- [male student] I agree. They probably
thought it was gonna be a walk in the
park. Turns out that they weren't ready
and it was no cake walk and it turned out
that some of them it was their last
day on the mountain.
- [female student] You were talking
about they
weren't prepared and all that. But they
also said that the guide had never been
through a storm like that and that that wasn't normal.
And I was kind of taken aback by that, because I was like,
if there's a guide who's going
to be guiding me on a life-threatening
thing I would want them to be, seasoned trainer you know...
- [male student] Exactly, I would think
the same thing. That the guide should be
prepared for that kind of storm unlike how
he was and it turned out fatally
for the rest of the crew.
- [female student] I agree with all of you,
but during reading the article, Krakauer
also mentioned that he said that it
wasn't really anyone's fault...
because people were so... not in their
right minds. They were tired and injuries
and how thin the air was, they couldn't
breath very well
So when they looked at the sky and saw the storm coming,
they didn't expect it to be as bas as it was, so nobody could
really prevent it. Anything to add to that? [Background Chatter]
- I agree, and I think that they were just having so much fun
that they weren't really paying attention.
- [male student] I think that they would've all been prepared
if they had been watching the clouds...
[Background noises]
- [female student] I know you mentioned the
clouds but why weren't they watching them?
Why do you think they weren't watching them?
- [male student][inaudible]
...they didn't think that they were actually serious enough
to actually [inaudible]
- [male student] I agree with Matt, that
they were so... they wanted to get
to the top so much they weren't too
worried about looking at the
clouds, 'Oh okay, we can make it back up and
make it back down, maybe before.' Not expecting
trouble along the way.
- [female student] Yeah I agree. I think
that they weren't really prepared. They
were too wrapped up in what was going on to think
about the downfall and what was happening.
They're tired and probably weak, they didn't have
safe... they weren't really all there to think
about what are the consequences of this and what
would happen. Like the guide, if it were me,
I would have made sure they had this... that you're
gonna help me out more than not really being able to.
- [male student] Anything you wanna say, Krystin?
- [Krystin] Well, I said that this quote at the top
it says that, "Ambition has a steep price." And I think
part of like how you guys were talking about how like the
guides weren't too prepared and weren't qualified
but, I think that, well and the author mentions this too,
that climbing this mountian is... it's taking a risk and
your ambition for going up this mountain already when
you're putting your life on the line, there's nothing
really anybody can do to tell you the qualifications that
you have to have to survive, it's just basically putting
your life to chance, and so... that's what I really got
out of it... what do you think?
- [male student] I agree, I think that [inaudible], then
not as many people would've died. They should just listen
to what they're told and and not risk their lives
to do something that [inaudible].
- [female student] I agree with that
No, but I think that what Krystin said makes a lot of sense
that people were just too tired and [inaudible]
- [male student] I agree but I think it's understandable because
just the thought of climbing the biggest mountain in the world is
extremely... cool. and I would definitely want to go up there
soon as possible, and not worry about the weather,
like go all in or don't go at all
- [female student] I agree with [inaudible]
lost or injured I mean but I'm like half
way there [inaudible] go ahead and accomplish
what I set out to do and I think that
would've caused anybody to not really notice the weather
and the risks involved in what we're doing.
- [male student] I agree with what Ellie
said a little while ago heard they should
have turned around, but they probably
thought that this was going to be
probably what could have been a once
in a lifetime chance to be at Mount Everest
I mean it says that they caught about [inaudible]
safely
but they should have have taken it more serious and
not kept going risking their life... [inaudible]
- [female student] One thing I noticed is that they relied
a lot on each other but they didn't go
back and check themselves and I didn't
understand why they didn't go back and
and like, when the one guy says, "there's no oxygen
here, there's no full tanks." Why didn't
they go back and check that themselves? I mean
I would trust that person but yet again,
if my life on the line. I would be
checking it.
Does anyone else think the same way?
[Background Chatter]
- [male student] If my life were at risk, I
wouldn't be relying too much on other
people. I'd be a little weary about
something like that.
- [female student] I don't so much
disagree but I came up with something a
little bit different. I didn't really think that
people relied on each other that
much at all. Who knows if all the deaths that happened
could have been prevented but people were too
tired or too injured or, there was always
something and everybody was more
concerned about getting themselves down the
mountain. In a way I would say that it was
selfish mission but in another way... I
mean if it was my own life, I would be out
for myself rather than trying to help somebody else and I think
we saw that, at least I saw that a lot happen throughout
the story. It's a choice between am I
going to help that person and risk my life
and they might not really pull through this, does it matter?
Or am I going to get down this mountain and survive?
- [male student] Some people were relying on others, like
at the end, someone was trying to
help [inaudible] was trying to help [inaudible],
he tried to help her down,
she grabbed his arm, and he tried to pull her down. But
she just let go and died.
- [male student] I agree with Erin too. I mean
I think that right now
wouldn't be able to. You would think about
yourself more. Whenever you're out there and
and you're with the same people for that long of
a time, and you're doing the same thing, that you become
sort of closer...
They would mean more to you then than they do
right now. You'd be more willing to
sacrifice something, to survive, to help them
give them another chance to get out alive too.
- That's definitely shown at the end of the article when he's
talking about how he can't live a day without thinking about the
lives of those people that he was so close to that were lost
and how he couldn't even come to grips with their deaths
for a very long time.
- [female student] I agree with Erin, I think there was a lot of,
at the end, I think he was talking about the [inaudible] there
was a lot of blame involved and
why couldn't we prevent this, and it brings me back to what
you guys said, I think they really wanted
to help each other and I think that they
wanted to do something but there was
nothing that could be done in some cases. I thought it
was kind of sad actually
dealing with that kind of grief where you couldn't prevent
someone's terrible death.
- [female student] Tyler, what do you think about this? Like
did he grieve, or even just the fact that... who they were
relying on.
- [male student] Well, what strikes me [inaudible]
[Bell Rings] [Background Chatter]
- [Instructor] All right, outer circle,
what'd you notice?
What'd you notice?
- [female student] I noticed that people were [inaudible]
and books and just kind of [inaudible]in inner circle and I felt
that that really helped
them to get the instructions.
- [Instructor] Okay. Blake, what did
you notice?
- I just thought that it was more and more, like Erin really led
the conversation and Krystin really led the conversation and
I think that those were like the two main ones, but like Levi and
Elliot and Alex, they all also communicated a lot but there wasn't
just one person who was talking.
- [Instructor] Okay, so there were definitely two leaders, but
there were other people that were
contributing as they went along. Okay, good. Anthony.
- [Anthony] There were some well-developed
conversations.
- [Instructor] Well-developed
conversations, what do you mean by that?
- Like Erin would say something and someone would build on it,
then someone else would and then another topic and new questions
and another topic.
- [Instructor] Yeah, did you notice- what was the question
they started with?
- [male student] Yeah, we got a little off-topic.
- [Instructor] No you didn't. What, what was the question
you started with?
What caused the disaster? And then you went into
something totally different but, did you
have good conversation about that?
Absolutely! You guys really started
focusing in on that life and death and
relying on somebody else for your own
life. Okay, I really like how-- I mean it
wasn't like you were talking about cookies
and then all of a sudden you were talking
about climbing Mount Everest. It was
definitely very connected to what you were
saying. Dorothy, what'd you notice?
- I noticed the conversation just kept
going and it didn't stop or anything
it just kept going from one
thing to another.
- [Instructor] Right it kept bouncing from
one thing to another. You could see, like
steam coming out of your ears, they were
all impulsive. Blake?
- I thought that also, remember Erin said, "you're relying on
someone," and Krystin's like, "well I don't agree."
backed up Erin and other people backed up Krystin and there
was people who didn't [inaudible]
- [Instructor] Yeah. Is it okay to
disagree with the people that are sitting
around you? Absolutely! But you need to do
it respectfully. Like Krystin did.
Krystin said, "I don't exactly agree with
you Erin.""
then she proceeded to say, 'Why?'  And Levi was over here, he was
nodding his head and shaking, 'yeah.' All right, great.
- [male student] I thought they did a good job of not having any
dramatic pauses, they always had something, someone would pass
on to someone else [inaudible]
- [Instructor] They paused occasionally but it was not pregnated
pauses. You guys ever heard that before?
It wasn't a pregnant pause, it wasn't a
big spacey gap, okay, Anthony?
- [Anthony] Pretty much everyone talked
- [Instructor] Pretty much everyone talked. Yeah, pretty much.
- [inaudible]
- [Instructor] Yeah, did you notice that?
They built on to what other people were
saying, okay? They agreed, I still heard
I agree a lot; but then they
told us why they agree with what they
said. All right? Anything else you guys
noticed? Yes?
- I think that we looked at our [inaudible] more, because they
had wider subject that they talked
about. Eventually it became narrowed
down that is was kind of like you have to look for
specific details. It wasn't the whole
story, it was more like a paragraph or two
and so you need specifics to
deal with that.
- [Instructor] All right. Anything else?