- [Teacher] Okay let's get busy.
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] So before we change the
car we have two more times.
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Okay let's look Jacob, let's help.
- [Student] It's 9-3.
- [Teacher] What is 9, three?
- [Student] 93.
- [Teacher] 93.
Is there a way, that we can
maybe change to other things
here, to make it go further?
Like the car?
- [Students] Yeah.
- [Teacher] How?
Maybe the height?
How about you guys discuss.
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Oh, try it.
Put that way back like that.
It might need help, for
you holding the ramp,
how bout you, do you
think that's a good idea?
- [Student] I'm gonna roll it back.
- [Teacher] Alright.
- [Student] Oh.
(clicks)
- [Teacher] Is it gonna stay you think?
- [Student] Yeah, I bet.
- [Teacher] Awesome.
Let's see how far it went.
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Watch your foot.
- [Student] 105.
- [Teacher] What is 105?
- [Teacher] I love the way
that you're making sure
that that goes nice and
smooth on the way in.
So let's take a look Jacob,
let's look over here.
Let's look at our data,
we have the roll one,
with just the normal
way, we had 101 inches.
And then the roll two which was again
the same way at 93 inches.
And roll three at 105 inches.
Which way went the furthest?
- [Student] 103, roll three.
- [Teacher] Roll three.
Why do you think that is?
- [Student] Because it's 101, that one is 101,
and that ones 105.
- [Teacher] Well why do you think roll one
is different from roll three?
- [Student] Because ones higher then the other.
- [Other Student] (mumbles)...higher then the other.
- [Teacher] Because ones higher then the other.
Okay, so do you want to try to add in
or take away something from this vehicle?
- [Student] I think we should--
- [Teacher] What do you think we should pick?
(Background Chatter)
- [Student] Take away the girl.
- [Teacher] Take away the girl?
- [Student] Nothing. (Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] What do you guys think
about Hailey's idea?
What did she say?
- [Student] Jacob S.
- [Teacher] Hold on, what did Hailey say?
Say it again.
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] We shouldn't even try?
- [Student] Okay, (mumbles)
- [Teacher] Okay so how about Jacob, since Jacob
was trying to make the other car, how 'bout
Jacob tries to put on bigger wheels?
We should see what happens then.
(clicks)
- [Teacher] Here Jacob.
Well look at this, look at which one
would we need bigger wheels on?
- [Student] That one
- [Student] That one.
- [Teacher] Okay.
- [Student] So (Background Chatter) that car.
Go farther, that one will go farther.
- [Teacher] Probably will go farther
you think, with bigger wheels?
- (Background Chatter)
- [Student] Yeah.
- [Student] 'Cause the bigger the wheel,
the easier it has balance.
-  [Teacher] Did you hear what he said?
- [Student] Bigger wheels have balance.
- [Teacher] The bigger the wheels
the more balanced it is.
- [Student] I'm saying like, let's say
you're (Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Is that gonna work?
Is there anything else you
guys want to do to this car?
Or do you just want to change one thing?
- [Student] I just change one thing.
- [Teacher] Okay, it's your car.
So what about your ramp?
Ashley, what about your ramp,
how do you want your ramp to be?
- [Student] Maybe we can take this off
and do it in the normal way.
- [Teacher] Okay.
- [Student] (clickety-clack) 76.
- [Teacher] You want to try that way? Alright.
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] That's true.
- [Student] Whoa.
- [Student] That wasn't go far.
- [Teacher] Alright, let's measure.
- [Student] It goes a little bit.
She needs a little bit of help.
(Background Chatter)
- [Student] 72.
- [Teacher] 72.
- [Student] We're gonna put this vehicle--
- [Teacher] Alright, so we're not
going to change the car,
but what could we do?
- [Student] 32.
- [Student] Whoa look.
- {Student] Guys this is going
to be affecting weight okay?
- [Student] That box could stay here
instead of-- (Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Alright, you guys try
it. You guys got it now?
- [Student] 91 times 2.
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Well that's up to your group.
- [Student] Can I make my car now?
- [Teacher] No, not yet. That's not weight three yet.
- [Student] Split weight right now
so--(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] How you guys doing?
(clickety-clack)
- [Teacher] Did you guys try to move the
weight in different ways?
- [Student] Ok.
- [Student] Alright, back.
- [Student] Let's do it together
(Background Chatter)
- [Student] 56.
- [Teacher] (gasp) Look at
that, let's see what happened.
- [Student] No it's 67.
- [Teacher] Where's your data at?
Put the data over here so
we're all in the same place.
- [Student] 83.
- [Teacher] Okay let's take a look.
What do you have here?
- [Student] 67.
(Background Chatter)
- [Student] This will be so much fun.
- [Student] Okay, you roll it.
- [Student] Ashley, can I work on it, can I have it?
- [Student] Should we take something away first?
- [Student] No.
- [Student] 42!
- [Student] I think we should put a little one.
Gimme that.
- [Student] You think we should--
(Background Chatter)
- [Student] I'm not sure.
- Cause the blue one (background chatter)
- [Student] Wow.
- [Student] Cool!
- [Student] Oh.
Oh my gosh.
- [Student] Here I'll--(Background Chatter)
- [Student] (Background Chatter)
- [Student] Yeah.
- [Student] And without these wheels.
Now?
Are you ready?
- [Student] Go!
- [Student] Here, here we go.
Ouchie.
(Background Chatter) hold the end.
- [Student] I'll hold it.
77.
- [Student] 77?
- [Student] No, it's 67.
- [Student] Jacob (Background Chatter)
- [Student] 67.
- [Student] Might be 77.
- [Student] What is 77?
- (Background Chatter)
[Student] We did it for two ways so
they can do it last way.
- [Student] That was way more.
- [Student] Yeah but (Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] How many inches was that second roll?
- [Student] Look--
- [Student] Three feet so 3 F.
- [Teacher] So what, three feet equals
12 times three, 36 inches.
- [Student] 36 inches.
- [Teacher] We're going to be focused on the inches
so we don't get confused.
- [Student] (Laughs)
- [Teacher] So hold on, wait a second.
When we had that ramp
the first way, what did you do with it,
the same way as the first way?
- [Student] No we did...
this way.
- [Teacher] Just that?
- [Student] Yeah.
- [Student] We haven't done it like that.
- [Teacher] I know just re-adjust this.
- [Student] Yeah.
- [Teacher] So when did it go,
when you did just that?
(Background Chatter)
- [Student] 30 seconds, no it went that.
- [Teacher] What is that?
- [Student] 73.
- [Teacher] 73.
So then we moved it, to make it, which way
did we do it the second way?
- [Student] Higher.
- [Teacher] We did it this way, what
happened to the numbers?
- [Student] It went lower.
- [Teacher] It went lower?
- [Student] So if we go it lower, it goes higher.
- [Teacher] I don't know, let's try.
So what's another ramp that we can make?
Have you tried that way before?
- [Student] Nope.
- [Teacher] Alright, let's see.
Hold on a second David,
we have to measure.
- [David] (Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Nope, your group can help you measure.
Let's see.
- [David] 35.
Ooh, that's seven.
- [Teacher] Okay, let's take a
look again, let's make sure.
What's that?
- [David] (Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] There we go.
So roll three, let's try.
Now let's take a look
at our data, hold on.
- [David] That's not gonna work.
- [Teacher] You don't think so?
Well let's first take a look here and then
we can see if that will work.
- [David] It's probably gonna fall.
- [Teacher] What happened with roll
three, where's the data?
Look at roll three, what is it?
- [Student] 35.
- [Teacher] And what's roll two?
- [Student] I don't know.
- [Teacher] 36.
So what do you think happened,
whenever we made the ramp a little bit higher?
I mean a little bit lower I'm sorry.
- [Student] It changed?
- [Teacher] It changed.
What happened when it changed?
- [Student] The number.
- [Teacher] I see, let's focus.
- [Student] It goes more...faster.
- [Teacher] It might go more faster.
There's not another roll four but you made
a very interesting ramp,
and you guys wanna try that?
- [Student] Yeah.
- [Teacher] Okay let's see, let's
see what happens Taylor.
(gasp) What happened?
- [Students] (gasp)
- [Student] It fell.
- [David] I knew it would.
- [Student] (Background Chatter)--my box.
- [Teacher] Well how about you hold
that, so we can try it again.
Try it again.
Oh no!
Fix em and let's see if
it does that every time,
do you think it'll do it every time?
- [David] Yes.
- [Students] Yes.
-  [Teacher] Let's try again.
- [Student] I'll measure this time.
- [Teacher] You'll measure?
- [Student] Yeah.
- [Teacher] Oh.
- [Student] Oh.
- [Student] We have to do it again.
- [David] Taylor, you can go on the carpet.
- [Student] This time I made it lower.
(Collective gasp)
- [Student] Oh
- [Teacher] So he just said
something, what did he say?
- [Student] He made it lower.
- [David] He made it lower.
- [Teacher] So what's happening, every time
he makes it a little bit lower?
- [Student] It falls off.
- [David] When it falls off, it still can roll.
I mean just keep it
rolling when it falls off.
- [Teacher] Uh oh (laughs).
- [Student] I'll measure it.
- [Student] Okay.
- [Teacher] We don't have enough
space to measure that one,
how about we change the car and try again.
But what did you guys notice
every time the ramp changed?
What happened when it was super high?
- [Taylor] It fell apart.
- [Teacher] It didn't work so well, can you imagine
if you were in a real
car, and you were going
down something that steep?
- [Student] Yeah.
- [Student] No.
- [Teacher] That would be kinda scary wouldn't it?
But, as it kept going down, what happened?
- [Student] It didn't go off.
- [Teacher] It didn't fall apart,
you're right. Alright go back
and try to make a different car.
Okay go back and try
to make it, be careful
your gonna make me nervous.
(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Alright let's
see Jacob, what do you have?
Come on over.
Nope, Jacob come on over.
What in the world did you make?
That looks like a Mack Truck.
Girls do you see this?
- [Students] Yeah.
- [Student] Tractors, throwing in something.
- [Teacher] Now take a look roll
it and see if that one
feels good to you.
- [Student] Big.
- [Teacher] Girls are you watching?
Look at how that rolled.
Girls, you next.
- (Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] Okay.
- [Student] This was all my idea.
- [Teacher] That was your idea? I love it.
- [Student] Could we try it this way?
- [Teacher] We could, keep a hold of
that you might want to try it.
Let's see....
Well we should be working on--
Correctamundo.
- [Student] See? I got a good review.
- [Teacher] What do we got Jacob?
- [Student] 93.
- [Teacher] 93.
So what can we do to change it?
- [Student] I guess we could maybe...
- [Student] We're learning something.
- [Teacher] We are learning something,
what did we learning?
- [Student] We learned the car, the littler it is,
the harder for it to fall.
- [Teacher] That is true?
- [Student] It's your turn.
- [Teacher] Is that what you're finding
out, the smaller the car?
- [Student] Yeah.
- [Student] The smaller the car,
the more it picks up.
- [Teacher] Picks up?
- [Student] Cars go over.
- [Teacher] Oh were we going over?
- [Student] No I--(Background Chatter)
- [Student] It's your turn Preston.
- [Teacher] Oh, did you guys hear him?
Let's take a second and listen.
He was talking about
yesterday's experiment,
what did we do yesterday?
- [Student] We tried rolling little
cars on the carpet.
- [Teacher] Why didn't it work out so well Jacob?
Little cars on the carpet.
- [Student] Because the wheels stopped them.
- [Teacher] Why did they stop, you think?
- [Student] Because the carpets too rough.
- [Teacher] Because the carpet's too rough.
Did you guys find that too?
So what are you finding about today?
- [Student] That the bigger the
wheels, the (Background Chatter)
--on hard surfaces.
- [Teacher] It's faster on smoother and
hard surfaces, it goes further
So what are you finding
out about the ramp?
- [Student] That--(Background Chatter)
- [Teacher] You guys are finding
that? How about you decide
that for this last one, you
tried one way with the ramp.
And now we're going to try,
two more ways with this ramp,
and I want to see if guys can figure out,
how this works better with a ramp.