- [Teacher] Okay, you guys based
on the answer tickets
that we took yesterday,
what we realized, or what I realized,
is that there's still confusion
on going from the general to factor.
General to vertex, or
vice versa on any of those
three particular forms.
Also, another objective we're gonna do is
we're gonna figure out- determine why each
form is important. So, the first
thing I want you guys to do
is, I want you guys to look at number one
on that task card. Can
someone read it out loud?
- [Drew] I will.
- [Teacher] Yeah, Drew.
- [Drew] The Angry
Bird was blasted through a
slingshot at the initial
height of 45 meters.
The bird's initial velocity
was 14.7 meters per second.
Write an equation that gives
the height of the Angry Bird
as a function of time.
- [Teacher] Okay, so what
I need you guys to do is
I need you guys to write that
equation on the white board.
- (background chatter)
- [Teacher] Okay, so now I want people
to put it up on the board.
Okay.
Okay, so can you guys look
around to each other too,
I know you guys are gonna want to,
like, show everybody what people are getting.
- [Students] Yay...Cool...
- [Teacher] Okay, guys,
these are the four things,
or the three things that I saw.
Okay, so right here.
So, if you notice a lot of you guys,
you guys had the first one.
Negative four point nine
'x' squared plus 14.7 'x'
plus 49. Can someone tell
me in words how you were
able to figure that out?
- You just did it.
- What was the question?
- [Teacher] So, can someone tell me how, like,
relate this general formula to the story.
Since you've read already, I
wants someone else to speak.
So who? Okay, Jamilah,
can you explain how you were
able to get this equation?
- So, the height is c, and
the original equation is a 'x'
squared, plus b 'x', plus c.
And so the initial height is
b, which is the y intercept.
And then b is the initial velocity?
And then negative four point
nine is just the random number
that they chose.
- [Teacher] So, you guys, is it random?
- No.
- It's the scale factor.
- [Teacher] Is there any
other terminology for that?
- It's the starting point.
- [Teacher] Hey guys, do you think it's
the starting point? Is
it the starting point?
Or, what else...?
- It's gravity.
- [Teacher] So wait, what does this
negative four point nine mean?
- That's the constant. Remember, it's gravity.
- [Teacher] So, I heard...
- Scale factor?
- [Teacher] Okay, scale factor,
but relatively to your
projectile motion, what is it?
- Acceleration?
- [Teacher] Acceleration. So you guys...(inaudible).
- [Teacher] It's acceleration.
So, right now, what I want you guys to do...
Oh, actually once again, right here-
here are different forms
of an equation that I saw.
So, right here what do you think?
Can someone tell me what's
wrong with this particular one?
- They don't
have a squared and they don't
have an 'x' after the
4.2
- Okay, so, Ravelle, what's
the problem with this one?
- There's no 'y' intercept or... (inaudible).
- [Teacher] So, once
again, I still notice,
now I want to go back to
the original equation.
Okay, someone tell me in words. Ah, Jamilah,
she did a fantastic job
explaining relatively to the
a 'x' squared, plus b
'x', plus c, but according
to the story, can someone
refer to the story
back to the general equation?
- Can you rephrase the question?
- [Teacher] Yes. How are
we able to get 14.7 here?
How did we get 49 here? How
do you know what stuff to use?
- The 49 is the initial height in meters,
so that one's gonna be your 'y' intercept,
And 14.7 is the initial velocity,
and the initial velocity is
always 'b' so... (inaudible)
- [Teacher] Awesome.
So, now what I want you guys to do is,
I want you to go to number two.
So, I want you to put
that on the white board.
- Can I read it again?
- [Teacher] Well,
actually, no. Let's have,
Fatima, can you read number two?
- [Fatima] What does the 'x' axis
represent in this story?
What does the 'y' axis represent in our story?
- [Teacher] Okay, let's do that quickly.
- I have a question.
- [Teacher] Yes.
- Did 'x', never mind,
I'll wait until after this.
- [Teacher] So, let's look
around. So, a lot of people
are getting what?
- 'X' equals time. 'Y' equals height.
- [Teacher] So Markeisha,
what was your question?
- I was gonna say, could
'x' be distance as well?
- [Teacher] Can 'x' be distance, people?
- No.
- No. If it wanted to.
- [Teacher] Why not?
- Because, it's meters
per second, not meters per
(inaudible)
- [Teacher] So, does that make sense?
- (inaudible)
- [Teacher] All right. So, now
what I want you guys to do...
So, so far, let's recap what we've done so far.
Can everyone generalize
what we've just done
in the first couple of questions?
- We set up the equation
and we figured out our 'x'
and y axes, in the general form.
- [Teacher] Okay, right now,
what I want you guys to do is,
I want you guys to work on number four.
Okay, someone read that out loud
that hasn't read out loud yet.
- I haven't.
- [Teacher] So, Leslie, you
want to read? Number four?
- [Leslie] From the equation that you
got from question number one,
show the steps on how you
translate the general form
into the factor form.
- [Teacher] Now what
I want you guys to do,
I want you to turn and talk
about the strategies
you're planning to use
to work out this problem.
- (students discussing the problem)
- [Teacher] Okay, you
guys, I'm gonna stop class
real quick. You guys, I'm
gonna stop class real quick.
- (inaudible)
Okay, so Mary, can you just
ask the question that you
just asked me?
- She asked me.
- [Teacher] Okay, so one
of you guys ask the question
that we just talked about.
So Markeisha, Jamilah?
- Can we use the box to figure it out?
- Yeah, you can.
- [Teacher] Why? How?
Hang on.
Put that back away. So, you guys.
So the question is...
Okay, so Autumn just asked,
can she use the diamond
and rectangle method
as opposed to (inaudible) and why?
- (background chatter)
- [Teacher] You guys...
You guys, let's listen,
please. Mary. Sorry.
- You figure it out by dividing
negative four point nine
by all the numbers. So, if
you divide negative four
point nine 'x' squared, by
negative four point nine,
you'll get 'x' squared. 14.7 divided by
negative four point
nine is negative three.
And then 49 divided by
negative four point nine is
negative ten?
- [Teacher] Okay, I'll
stop you right there.
So, back to what I said. Okay,
so the diamond-rectangle
method, people. So, when you are doing this,
what are you finding?
- We're finding the box.
- [Teacher] You're finding the box.
So, what are those things
outside of the box here?
What are they called.
- The factors.
- [Teacher] The factors.
Okay.
Okay, when you're using, it seems like
a lot of you guys are using
the quadratic formula.
What are you trying to find then?
- (inaudible)
- [Teacher] All right. So, right now...
So, Autumn. So, you have
questions on that right?
So, later on... So, do you mind just moving
over there real quick?
Because Leslie said that
you got it down.
So, you guys, so take two more minutes.
We're gonna see both methods.
- (students discussing the problem)
- So, are you done yet?
- No.
- (background chatter)
- [Teacher] Okay, you guys stop.
Okay, right now,
I'm gonna put this up right here.
We're gonna put up the
most common mistakes
that people tend to do.
Okay, so right now, so how many people got
negative five and two?
- [Students] No...no...no.
- [Teacher] So, what was it?
- Negative two (inaudible).
- Oh, okay, I got negative
two and five. My bad.
- [Teacher] Okay, so right
now. What do you think
was the mistake that she did?
- She didn't square it.
- [Teacher] She didn't what?
- She didn't square.
And then she re-fixed it.
- [Teacher] She fixed it?
- Yeah, she copied mine.
- It's supposed to be negative 14.7.
- [Teacher] Is that
what its supposed to be?
- Yeah.
- [Teacher] And is
that what she's missing?
- Yeah.
- [Teacher] Okay, guys, so
that's one mistake that happens
quite a bit.
Also, let's look at...
Hey, you guys, what form is this right here?
What method did they use?
- Box and diamond method.
- [Teacher] Box and
diamond method, right?
- Okay, so, you guys, what
do you call these two
items right here?
What is it missing?
- The number at the
beginning. The negative four.
- [Teacher] And what is that again?
What is the name of the
four point nine again?
Scale factor or what?
- Acceleration!
- [Teacher] Acceleration.
So, you guys, if you notice,
this is something that
tends to be missing also.
So, now we will look at...ah...
- We have the same thing.
- We all have the same thing.
[Teacher] So, same thing, same thing. All right.
Okay. So, right now I
think we looked at all
the common mistakes that people tend...
Oh actually, (inaudible)
So, now what I want is... so, how
many methods do people use?
- Two?
- Okay, so tell me one
what was one method?
What was the method that you used?
- Quadratic formula?
- Okay, Caleb? What was another
method that people used?
- The box and diamond.
- [Teacher] The box and diamond, right?
So, right now, I want people
to explain their thinking.
So, what I want you to do is, okay,
since... Tiffany, since you said
you did the quadratic
formula, you're gonna go up
and talk about it. Just
talk about the process
of what you did.
- (students cheering for Tiffany)
- [Teacher] How are you gonna
explain the process?
- [Tiffany] All right. So, the
(background chatter)
- Can we do it on this hard board?
- [Teacher] Yeah. Okay. Let's
do it on this hard board.
- [Student] Make sure you talk to us, okay?
- [Teacher] Okay, while you're writing things down,
talk about how you're going through the process.
- So, I used the quadratic formula?
- [Teacher] So, what
are you doing right now?
- I'm writing it.
- [Teacher] Writing what?
- The quadratic formula.
- [Teacher] Okay. So you
see, instead of me asking,
I just want you to explain all
the things that you're doing.
- Okay.
- So, you guys need some visuals...
This will be your a, your b, and your c.
So, you plug all this into this.
- [Teacher] Okay, so let's (inaudible) do it.
- [Student] I have a question.
- [Teacher] Yes.
- [Student] What if the b is already negative?
- [Tiffany] That's a good question.
- (background chatter)
- [Teacher] So, you guys,
while Tiffany is doing
the quadratic formula, think
about what common mistakes
that we just talked about earlier,
and what mistakes that
she may or may not have.
- (background chatter)