- [Teacher] Can someone
come up and put number one
on the graph?
And then we're going to debate about it.
Anassia, can you come up
and show us where you think
one should be?
(background chatter)
- [Anassia] Alright so, what I think is,
I don't know if I'm right
or wrong or whatever,
but I thought kinda one is there.
Do you guys see it?
- [male student] No
(giggling)
- [teacher] OK back, can
you give us a reason why?
- [Anassia] OK, well it
says David had drived back
to pick up his credit card that he forgot
at the restaurant, so I
kinda think that from home,
the restaurant must be close,
that's why he took the chance
to go back to get his credit card.
We don't know if he has
money on him, ya know?
It could depend on
circumstances, but I think that
the restaurant was hella close,
that's why he went back
and went back home.
- [teacher] OK, wait, wait, wait.
Wait, wait, wait. wait. OK.
So, honestly who has that opinion?
So you think one is at the very beginning
- [Beth] Mmmhmmm.
- [teacher] of his trip?
OK, can we have someone
else draw another number one
that is in a different place?
Anassia, can you pick someone?
- [Anassia] Overwhelming. You.
(laughter)
- [Male Student] I put it right here.
Right there.
(background chatter)
- [Teacher] OK, can you give us a reason?
- [Male Student] He's driving and then he
goes to the restaurant,
and then he's driving away.
No! This is the restaurant right here,
and then he's leaving
and he's like, "Oh snap,
I left my credit card." Then he goes back
and then he's driving away.
That's it.
- [teacher] OK wait, so
whose idea do we agree with?
Sidius or Anassia?
- [class] Sidius
- [Teacher] - OK, but we
still have to convince Anassia
because she still thinks
it's at the beginning, right?
- [Male Student] I thought
it was at the beginning too.
- [Teacher] You did? Who convinced you?
- [Male Student] Myself.
- [Teacher] Yourself?
(laughter)
- [Teacher] OK, so if
David is driving back
to the restaurant, then should his slope
be what? What should his slope be?
- [Class] Negative.
- [Teacher] If he's going
back to the restaurant?
Right, because if I'm travelling this way,
my slope's getting bigger, my
distance is getting farther,
But wait, I turn back
so my slope has to be?
- Negative.
- Negative. So do you think one
is when the slope gets negative?
- [Male Student] Yeah.
- So are you convinced now Anasstia?
That it has to be negative
for him to go back?
- [Anasstia] Yeah.
- So are we OK with
erasing that first one?
[Anastassia] Well I have
to erase all of it anyway.
(teacher laughs)
- Oh OK, sorry. OK.
So one should be where
he's going back, right,
where he's going negative, OK? Alright.
[Anasstia] Is there a real end to it?
- Well we're going to see
once we get through them.
[Anasstia] Alright.
- So, Sidi, can you pick the next person
to show us where number two should be?
- [Sidius] No hands?
- [Female Student] I would put two here.
- [teacher] Can you explain why, Candy?
Wait, just give us an explanation.
- [Candy] Yeah, because he said
that his car breaks down so he goes back
so the slope is negative.
He went back.
- [Class] Close to his house.
- Yeah, near his house, but
then it's near the beginning
so the bilaterals have to be near zero.
Because the line there
represents the distance
from his home, right?
- [Female Student] I've got a question.
- OK
- You know how it says he is told a way
to a repair shop near his house?
We're looking at his car,
not looking at the tow away car, aren't we?
So wouldn't it be considered constant
since his car is moving?
[Teacher] - So I guess the car
is on the tow truck, right?
So now, wherever the tow truck goes,
the car has to go, right?
- [Classroom] Yeah
- [Teacher] Does anyone
have a different place
for number two?
- [Classroom] No
- [Teacher] So we all agree that two,
no, do you want to put
two in a different place?
Put it in a different place.
Let's see what you think.
Put it in a different place,
let's see what you think. Go.
- [Male Student] I was thinking
of putting it right here.
That's what I was thinking.
- [Female Student] That's
what I thought too.
- [Teacher] Can you explain why? Why?
- [Male Student] Because he
says that his car broke down
and was towed back to his house.
So I was thinking that the first sentence,
so his car broke down.
So if he was not going anywhere,
then the time was going then constant,
so if, as you see the time,
his speed never changes
while the time is just going down.
That's what I think.
- [Male Student Sitting] That's wrong.
(laughter)
- [Teacher] We don't say that's wrong,
we say, "Well, I disagree. Well."
So convince him otherwise.
- [Male Student Sitting]
Because the car is still moving,
and if you look really,
really closer at the graph,
the last point isn't directly on the girl
so we can assume that since it says the
the repair shop is near his house
that the ending point would have to be
somewhere near zero.
Also, if it was constant,
that means he would just
be in one spot, but
it's clearly saying that
he's being towed back
towards the repair shop,
so he's in motion, like the
slope is showing distance
and not speed.
Well the graph is showing that
the slope is going somewhere.
- [Teacher] So can I say two things?
One thing, so it's a
different interpretation
of this problem, right?
So if he was broken down and
the car was just staying there,
then would this be a good place for two?
- [Class] Yes.
- If the car was just staying there
because distance is not
changing or is changing?
It's not changing, right?
Because time is going on, but
distance is staying the same.
However, number two says
he's going to the repair shop
close to his house.
So is he just staying
in one place? No, right?
So he's gonna go back home,
so if he's going back home
so this slope would be
negative or positive?
- [Class] Negative.
- Negative.
And it's going, here's home, right?
So where does he go back
home? Or very close to home?
Here, right? Are you convinced Danny?
- [Danny] Yes.
- OK, let's erase the other number two.
But Danny, thank you for being brave
because I could understand
that interpretation.
Alright, Danny, can you pick
someone to put number three
on the graph?
- [Female Student] OK, number three
is over here.
- [Female Student Sitting] I disagree.
- [Teacher] Wait, wait.
(laughter)
We haven't even heard her explanation.
Wendy, what's your explanation why?
- [Wendy] Because it's stopped for gas and
got a quick bite to eat
it's kinda constant here
so it can be stopped.
- [Girl Student Sitting]
So why not the long one?
- [Wendy] Because he's in
the restaurant, I suppose.
- But then
- So if one is here, if one is here,
it has to be in the
restaurant then, right?
- Well then one is over
there, so then why would
three be all the way over there?
- One is here, right?
- No, no, no. One is all
the way at the beginning.
- No.
- Sorry, that's "Y."
(laughter)
But then it says that he got a three.
- Yes, but it's here.
- Yeah, he ate there, so
wouldn't that be the one?
Like wouldn't that be
where he gets his gas?
[Girl Student Sitting Number
Two] Number three said
that he went to eat,
but it doesn't say where
did he eat. Maybe he just
eat at that restaurant
that he mention about.
- [Girl Student Sitting] Yeah,
maybe he went a bit farther,
and said, "OK, let me go
somewhere else," so that's why.
- [Wendy] So what did he do here?
- [Class] Eat and gas.
(laughter)
- It doesn't take that long to eat.
(background chatter)
- [Girl Student Sitting] One hour?
People take a bit to
longer to fill up on gas
and then they can't just eat
while they're getting gas.
Oh let me eat while I'm getting gas.
- [Teacher] OK, so are we
going to take a longer time
at the restaurant or a longer
time at the gas station?
- [Class] The restaurant.
- The restaurant.
So do we want the slope to be
zero for a long period of time
or just for a short period of time?
- Short
- Shorter than wherever you pick
where the restaurant is, right?
So we haven't gotten to the
restaurant yet, have we?
- No.
- No, OK.
So could three be the place
where he stops and gets gas?
Could it be?
- [Class] Possibly. We
don't know if quick bite
meant one hour or meant half an hour.
- Or maybe it meant (snaps fingers)
five minutes?
- Yeah you know, you never know.
So if we interpreted five minutes, gas
and quick bite, quick sandwich.
Could we put three at that place?
- Yes.
- Why?
- [Wendy] Because the
slope is almost constant
for a short period of time.
- [Girl Sitting in Class
Number Two] I think that at
three, he went back to the restaurant
to get his credit card.
- [Wendy] Maybe the gas
station is near the restaurant.
(laughter)
- [Male Student] Why you
make this so difficult?
- [Teacher] That's possible, though, right?
I'm like thinking of
putting at the beginning?
- Here?
- Here is four.
- [Girl Student Sitting] Wait, wait, wait.
Don't go on four yet.
- [Girl Student Sitting Number
Two] But I think the three
should be before one.
Because you can't just
eat in the restaurant
and then you eat a quick sandwich,
(background chatter)
- [Teacher] OK, we're going to do this
because I like the debate you're having,
but I want groups to think
about it individually,
and then we're going to come back.
but I want to put one thing
for sure on the board.
OK, so
If, if, if, if. If,
If this is definitely
Let's say this is definitely
where David stopped to eat.
OK, so this is where David is eating.
[Girl Student Sitting] Eating
as in, in the restaurant?
- Eating at the restaurant, yes.
So here David is eating for a long time
at the restaurant, OK?
A long, long time. So that's the longest,
is this the longest time
where the slope is flat?
Yeah. So we're all gonna agree right now
that this is where David is
eating at the restaurant.
So this is where David is
eating at the restaurant,
can you put all the other
numbers in a logical place?
Because I hear you guys
talking about logic.
Like he can't go to the gas
station before he does what?
- Goes to the restaurant
and gets his credit card.
- OK, so, I see that's
one logical statement so,
in your groups, I'm gonna give
you five minutes for this.
Can you put one, two, three,
and four in a logical place
and have a good argument for it? OK.