- Hello, guys.
After all the hard work you've put in
on doing your presentations,
and your tri-board,
and all the really cool stuff you've done,
now we need to put it all together
and see what you think
about these energy sources
that you've done all
this research for. Okay?
So, first off, doing a little poll.
Which energy source do you like the best
and think it would be the best one to use?
- Solar energy.
- Why?
- It looks pretty cool, and, I don't know,
it seems like the most efficient way
because the sun's always there
and the sun won't run out--
- That's the word, whenever
you're done using it--
- You can sell it.
- You can keep the energy from the sun
from the morning and
afternoon during the night.
- You can sell it.
- Okay, so he thinks solar. Who else?
- Okay.
- Go ahead.
- I like the wind.
- (chair squeeks) Oh,
so you can talk to him.
Because you want to be able
to talk to each other, right?
I liked the wind one
because it stored up the battery.
And the battery, whenever it wasn't windy,
and so it kind of was always there.
It didn't matter about the wind.
- Yeah, you can answer the question.
- [Female student] I also
think that wind's the best one
because not only can you store it
and have energy for
whenever there is no wind,
you can also make money off of that.
So, maybe if you get it in enough homes,
you won't even have to have a job.
You can make money off that.
- [Teacher] That's a very good point.
That's a very good point,
making money off of that energy source.
Which other ones did we
say could make money?
- Um, the solar. Solar can
make money (students interject).
- Well, I like the wind.
Because, it's like, the sun
is going to burn up one day,
but the wind is always going to be there.
And the only bad thing about it is
that the birds are going to die,
but that's okay. (laughter around the room)
- [Teacher] Okay, well, what
are some pros and cons then?
So, you just said birds would
die if we use wind power, okay?
Does that outweigh the benefit
that you get from using wind power?
(students answer over one
another, mostly disagreeing)
- I think birds dying isn't that bad,
because, you know, we eat birds,
so I don't think it would
be that bad if birds do die.
I mean, I don't think a
lot of birds die because of
the wind solar energy.
Not as much as oil, or
any of that other stuff.
- Yeah, or like we eat birds.
- The other one I like is the hydro one
that James did, because--
(students agreeing and disagreeing)
- [Male student in grey] His
was ridiculous. That was nice.
- [Teacher] So, what part of it
were you most impressed with?
Like, not like the demonstration,
but it was a great demonstration,
but hydroelectric power in general,
what part of that--
- [Female Student] Like how if
you have a pond or something,
you can put it in there,
and then it will power up your whole house.
- [Teacher] Do we need moving water?
- Oh yeah, you need
moving water to have that.
You'd have to have a stream, but you could
basically do it anywhere
you have moving water.
And if you really wanted
to spend some money,
there's also the pump storage plant
from a high reservoir to a low reservoir.
- [Teacher] So, that one
actually sounds pretty good.
So, somebody want to defend theirs, Rakif?
- I don't really like mine, because--
- [Teacher] Which one did you do?
- [Rakif] I did oil.
- [Other Student] Natural Gas.
- [Teacher] Oil and
natural gas, okay. Why not?
- Because mine isn't as abundant
as the wind or as the solar energy,
so it's probably going
to run out pretty soon.
Like oil, natural gas,
and coal do run out.
They're not going to be as,
here as much as the wind,
or hydro or something like that.
- Well, there's a lot of
dangers involved with using oil, right?
Oil rigs, pipelines, lots
of dangers involved, right?
- Oil prices can cause high gas prices.
- [Teacher] That's true too.
Remember in your presentation,
you talk about some of the dangers.
What were those dangers,
and are those dangers any better or worse
than some of the other dangers
for the other energy sources?
- For oil?
- Yeah.
- The pipelines can burst,
and they can kill marine life
in the water if the oil gets out.
- They could cause another oil spill.
- Explosions.
- But coal, I know you're supposed to like
stick up for your natural resource,
but I kind of think coal can be good,
but it's mostly bad,
because a lot of people's
lives are getting killed
because of all the gasses, smells,
and being down there for so long.
And I think that's also very bad.
- And the land, it hurts the land
and the environment.
- Coal is a very dirty resource
if you think about it.
All the coal dust, it can
cause a lot of lung problems.
So, the miners that go down there,
they're risking their lives right?
- Yeah.
- Any of the other resources as
dangerous as mining coal?
- No.
- [Student] Nuclear energy.
- [Teacher] What?
- Nuclear energy is the worst.
- [Teacher] Okay, what
about nuclear energy?
How dangerous was that
when you looked it up?
- It's a six out of ten chance.
- [Teacher] Of what happening?
- It depends. It costs way
too much, first of all,
to build it.
- [Teacher] It is very
expensive. That's true.
- It's got a lot of risks, like
if it gets into your water,
or if you breathe in
the radiation. (mumbles)
- [Rakif] I imagine it could--
- [Student] It smells bad.
(chair crashing against the floor).
(mumbles)
- [Male Student] Okay, does
collecting oil use more energy
than it provides?
- [Teacher] Good question!
- What do you mean by collecting oil?
- [Male Student] Like, if you have to have
the process of going underground
and drilling the oil,
does it use more energy than it provides?
- No, I don't think so.
Because in my presentation,
it said it produces
like a widespread, like a
very large amount of energy.
And also that, your wave and tidal power
powers our system,
as you said in your presentation.
[Teacher] Oh, good point.
Those two actually work together.
When you talk about the
wave and tidal power,
that energy could be harnessed
to run your offshore drilling.
So, that's a very good thing as well.
- It's a benefit of drilling.
- Absolutely. Are there different energies
that do benefit each other?
- Yes, the solar energy and wind.
Because the wind energy is based off the sun,
because of how the sun
waves come onto the Earth
and then it turns this sun mill,
so it produces the turning of the mill,
so the sun and solar
energy and wind energy--
(loud bell tone sounds)
- The solar energy and the wind,
they actually work together,
because I've seen some wind turbines
that have solar energy panels on the top.
One, then the other can go. That's okay.
- I think solar energy
is a really good thing,
because for a lot of power plants,
like for times, the condition
of natural resources like wind,
even hydroelectric if there's
a drought or something,
or not enough water flow,
you could always have the solar panels
stuck on top of the plant, or anywhere.
- Right, because we've found that solar
is pretty cost-feasible right?
- Yeah, it's not that expensive.
And actually, you won't have
to pay an electrical bill
if you get that.
- If you were going to use solar panels
to power a wind turbine or something,
you're better off just using the solar panel.
It would just cost more money
to have to get the solar
panels and the wind turbine,
or to have the solar
panels power the turbine.
- It doesn't power it.
It's just, like, another way to get energy
at the same time that
you're getting the wind.
When there's no wind,
there's not much of a wind--
- [Student on far left]
That's what the battery's for.
Hmm, interesting.
- I have a question for solar power, too.
For solar power, how can I make aluminum
more efficient in the future?
- Well, it doesn't use a lot of the gas,
so it doesn't affect the environment.
So, it doesn't affect your breathing.
And you don't need solar panels,
like you don't need to turn
stuff on during the day,
because the sun, through the windows,
can give you light, and then
can store up for the night.
- Okay.
- I have a question.
What natural resource do you think
will be the most used in the future?
Like, 50 or so years from now?
(students talking over each other)
- Wind. It was used like 3,000 years ago,
so if it was used 3,000 years ago,
I think it would be used
3,000 years in the future.
- That's not necessarily
true, because it could get
more worn out by the time 3000 years
in the future comes.
- The problem with the
wind thing is (coughing)
it can be used in
country, like rural areas,
because in other areas,
you can't put a wind turbine
in a normal neighborhood.
Because you can't, can you put one?
(students overlap, disagreeing)
- You mean I could put one
outside the school here?
(students argue)
- [Student 1] Well, it would
give energy to the school
and the rest of the houses
that are near the school.
- [Student 2] Well, I'd put
it on top of the school,
because then there would
be more wind higher up.
- Right, and we have
to worry about spacing, right?
Because we were saying wind
power is built usually where?
On wind farms, where you
have a lot of flat land.
Because if you build in
a mountainous region,
are you going to get a lot of the wind?
(students answering all at once)
[Student on left side of
room] If it's high enough it'll
probably be enough.
- Then if you build your wind
turbine high up on a mountain,
what is the chance of that wind turbine
maybe getting struck by lightning,
or being damaged that way?
- [Student on Left] Yeah,
that could be a real problem
because of the wind and the
way it could be struck down.
- Right, that's very possible.
So, when you think about one
(bell tones)
energy source,
is there really one
energy source to go with?
Or do you have to take into consideration
a lot of factors of where
you live, what's available?
Because, again, talking about
building a hydroelectric plant
we established you need running water.
Is there running water everywhere
around the United States?
[Several students] No.
- No. And what's the problem
if you flood an area,
even if there is a running water,
what happens if you flood the area?
- Well, they have to decide.
Usually if it's going to be a major problem,
they will actually dig
a separate reservoir
for the river to flood
instead of it coming up on the banks
of the river and destroying
homes and things.
That's mostly our United States rule.
But, in China, they really don't care.
So they flood three or four
cities, multiple towns,
fill up three gorges of water.
- Wow. That's just insane.
Because once you disrupt water flow,
you have a problem.
So again, there are some
pros and cons to these.
Okay, we're going to take a second,
and we're going to try
to rank the resources
in terms of which one you guys think
is the best one to possibly use.
So, if you had to pick one
that you wanted to go with,
whether there was running water,
think you have those things beside you,
don't limit yourself there,
but turn to your neighbor for a minute,
and discuss which one you
think would be like 1 and 2.
Because each one of you might
have a different opinion.
Give each other a
little bit of a reason why,
and we'll get back
together in just a second.
(students discussing in pairs)
- [Teacher] Alright
guys, another 30 seconds.
Then we'll get back together.
(students continue discussing)
[Teacher] Alright, three, two, one.
Let's wrap up our
conversations. Alright.
How many people, by show of hands,
went with one of the
non-renewable resources,
like coal, oil, or natural gas?
Cool!
So, everybody picked a renewable resource
as the way to go.
Alright, Ryan?
- I think it's either wind or solar power.
- [Teacher] How many people agree?
- Oh, so wind or solar
is the clear choice.
Jonah, why?
- The thing is, I think
solar would be first.
Because solar energy, you can use
almost anywhere, pretty much.
But the wind, if you live here,
you can't get it as easily,
because there's not as much wind.
So, it would be a lot
easier to have solar,
because you can use solar anywhere,
because the sun is shining
pretty much everywhere.
- We think solar too,
because the sun is always there,
even if it is winter,
or it's a little cloudy,
the sun is still there.
- [Student] Yeah, but
what about at night time?
- [Teacher] So, Maddy, what
did we find out about solar?
- At night time, like a
lot of people go to work
during the day, so no one's at their house
using their lights and stuff.
So, there's a battery that
stores all the energy and
then you can come home at night
and you can still power your house.
(students talking over each other)
- You still get some light at night,
bouncing off the moon.
[Teacher] Dustin, what do you think?
- I was thinking that
solar energy would be great
because I was comparing it to
if you want to charge your phone,
and you have it plugged in,
and while it's plugged
in it's fully charged
and you can still use it,
and it won't un-charge
because it's still plugged into the wall.
But, if the power goes out at your house,
then it will stop charging,
and you'll have that much battery left.
So, it's kind of like if
you're out in the day,
and your house is charging
while there's still sun.
So, you're still getting energy,
and at night time when the sun is gone,
you'll have that energy saved
in the battery of the solar thing.
- [Female student] Well,
it's the same thing
with wind power.
You'd still have that battery there.
- Yeah. Wind power would be--
- Would solar power still
work during a storm?
- It depends how severe the storm is.
- So, you mean this is,
like, built to last.
- Yeah, if it gets struck by lightning,
I don't think it would still work.
- [Teacher] But, you know,
when there are clouds
outside during the day on a cloudy day,
you know the solar radiation is still
getting through the clouds,
right? (students agree)
So, that solar panel would
still be getting energy
from the sun on a cloudy
day, just at night
you would still have to use
the battery that's been stored.
Just like with wind power.
There is wind power all
day long, all night long,
but sometimes it does die
down at certain times,
so there's a battery too,
there as well. Exactly.
- I agree with solar power, but
I agree that it would be great
for being on your houses and things,
but I don't see the
purpose of a solar farm.
It takes up a lot of land.
Just the point to collect the sun,
I think it would be better
putting it on a house
or combining it with another power plant,
like wind power or something
like that, because--
- [Female student] And
cost-wise it would be probably
expensive, because it was 900
for just one of those panels.
And Miss Shonda said it would take
about 12 just for one house.
- That's basically about 10,800.
- For one house.
- But we also think that
solar panels blend in more
than winter lines.
Just imagine random winter
lines in your front yard.
- Yeah, but we saw pictures, or a video,
of a solar-powered house, and most people
don't like solar panels because it
looks unattractive on
the top of your house.
Same with the wind power, wind turbines
would look unattractive.
But you can still
decorate them if you want.
You can't really do that
with the wind power,
I mean solar power thing, because it's mostly black.
- [Teacher] That's a good thought.
So, going forward, thinking
of an energy solution,
because as you guys get older,
energy is going to be something
you have to worry about.
We've seen the gas prices.
The gasoline prices
for regular cars go up.
You've seen the ethanol being developed.
Is it good to keep
developing new technologies?
How many of you guys,
once you start driving,
think if you could do it
or your parents could do it
for you, would drive a hybrid car?
- I would.
[Teacher] Okay, would
you drive a hybrid car?
- Yeah, I would drive
one, because it's more in
miles per gallon, and
with rechargeable cars,
you can charge your car
instead of using gas
and spending more money.
- [Teacher] That's good.
Also the emissions from your gas.