♪ [music] ♪
Great job, thank you for playing along.
It's so much nicer to play with live
accompaniment than it is recorded. Your
assignment, two weeks, be able to play an
improvised solo in this key, in F concert
utilizing the Dorian and Mixolydian
scales. We'll leave in just a moment, just
relax. Utilizing the Dorian and Mixolydian
scales. I'll ask you to play live, on this
Bosaladera. I also, want you to, outside
of class, find a Latin piece of music, it
doesn't have to be bossa nova,
that you can play along with
identifying the Dorian and the
Mixolydian scale that fits that key.
Pick a song that you can identify the key,
and that you feel comfortable playing in
that key, to bring back and play for us. I
want a recording here so, you're going
have to find a mp3, CD, DVD, something
along that you can get to class. So you
can share this information with each
other, Questions?
Time frame is two weeks. If you went
through this quickly,
tell your buddy how long you got and
what you have to do, go.
That's a great question,
thank you. Yes, yes, do it in vibes, it
will be wonderful. You can do this, it's
in F scale, it's in F scale, is what it
is. And I saw your results and they were
outstanding. Very good, let's all grab an
encore, thank you, and I will
see you tomorrow.