- What are his tools?
- [Background Chatter]
- Is that your hose? Awesome. Now, what needs to
come out of the hose to put out the fire?
-Water.
- Yeah! What color is it? Miley is helping
you out. Look there. Good water. What do
you do with that thing, Marissa? What's
the doctor going to do with that? I can't
hear you. What? You're right. Listen to
your heart. Very good. Do you remember
what we call that? Not a telescope, a
stethoscope. There you go. All right,
Miley, what does your teacher need? What
tools?
- A smart board.
- A smart board? Are you going to draw the
smart board? All right. Are you finished
with your fireman? Did you hear Miley? Do
you need to draw anything else for your
fireman or is he all good? I don't know
where the fire is. You're the artist,
where's his fire? It's your fire. Marissa,
what is that bag for?
- The doctor bag.
- The doctor bag, I love it. What did you
draw? What is that? Very good. And what do
you do with the stethoscope? Check your
heart. A whole bunch of fire? Well, I'm
glad you're the fireman and you're going
to put it out. I love it. There you go.
Good job.
That is one colorful nurse. I see it.
It's great.
You're almost finished? What is that
orange thing? It goes your mouth and what
does it do? Do you remember? It takes your
temperature. It's a thermometer. Good job.
What are you going to teach your kids
right there? Good job.
- What about the kids?
- She's on the smart board right now. Very
good.
All right just a few more minutes.
We have to finish up so you all can stickers
[Background Chatter]
A, B, C, D, E, F, G, H...
- I.
- You did draw the shot. You're done? All
right. You may go. Give me five. Great
job. I love your fireman.
A, B, C, D, E, F, G...
- H... J
- J. [Background Chatter]
I love how nice you folded that,
Anthony. Good job! Good job, are you all
finished?I love it!
[Background Chatter]
I love it! Good job, I love your teacher.
She's very happy. [Background Chatter]
What are you going to do
in art? Make me a picture? Can't wait.
What is this? A stair bridge? Wow. Who's
going to use it?
I love it. Who has an airplane? What's the
person? I'm a teacher. I teach
kids. Who flies the airplane? Ask Aaron,
see if he can help you out. Do you
remember? Aaron, can you help him out? Who
flies the plane? What's his name?
- The pilot.
- Yeah. The pilot. Good job. Mary! What
are you? You're not the firefighter. What
are you? Who's uniform do you have on?
- The cop.
- The cop's. Very good. You're going to
arrest people? Why? They're speeding?
Watch out, Aaron, Mary's going to catch
some speeders.
- He's arrested.
- He's arrested? What was he doing?
- Speeding.
- Speeding? Oh no! Look what happens when
you speed. You crash. And who's going to
come rescue you? Who will come help you if
you crash? The policeman and who's going
to help you get better? Who did you see
yesterday? Who came to visit us yesterday?
Do you remember? We went out and got to
sit inside of it. Ambulance. Good job.
What's going on over here? You're what?
Tacos? How many? Two? Thank you. Are they
for me?
- This is my cake.
- Your cake? Okay. What are you going to
do with your cake after you mix it up? A
chocolate cake? Oh no.
- It just came out of the oven.
- It just came out of the oven? It looks
great. Is there a special occasion for
your cake?
- [Background Chatter]
- All right. That would be great. I'll
make sure nobody touches your cake. It's
fine. It'll stay right there. What are you
going to make? Cookie dough? What kind?
You don't know? Put your hands up, she
said. You put it in the oven?
How long do you cook it? Five minutes or
five hours? Five minutes? Good job. Oh no,
it fell. I think... you're doing a good
job, but I think you have it crooked. Hang
on. That's an awesome cookie. Thank you.
Great job. What do you tell her? What do
you say?
- Thank you.
[Background Chatter]
You're working hard. You almost have it.
Cross it. Good job. Great job helping.
Awesome. I don't know where the lid is for
this. Did you ask Dylan if he's the one
that had it out? Dylan, do you know where
the lid is for the
[Background Chatter]?
Well then you need to help her. Show her
where it's at. She wasn't sure. Thank you.
[Background Chatter]
Oh, hang on a second. N, O...
Is that an R?
- No.
- No. Let's fix it. R, S. Help him out,
Dylan, what's after S? All right. There
you go. What's next? There's your P, Q, R,
S... V. Then what?
What's going on over here? You're giving
him a shot? Why are you giving him a shot?
What happened to him? What happened to him
that he needs a shot? He's sick? Did it
hurt? What was in that shot? What was in
the shot?
- The needle.
- The needle, but what came out of it? It
was just in his hand. So, what did you
give him? Yeah, medicine. What are you
listening to?
- Your heart.
- My heart? Am I okay?
- Now I'm about to give you a haircut.
- A haircut? All right. Julius, don't run.
All right. So, how do you like your job,
nurse? Good? I see why you made your
picture all different colors. Your nurse
uniform is all different colors. Good job!
I think your next appointment is here.
Have a seat, she can check you out. Leave
the chair right there. That's a shot, too.
There's a different shot. Yes, I'm scared.
Ow! Shots hurt. Ow! I think you only need
one. What did you just give me?
- Medicine.
- Medicine? Is that my Band-Aid?