- A prediction on the
weather temperatures.
- Okay so maybe they can
predict something
that's going to happen.
- Yes.
- [Teacher] Okay.
So, based on the information
that you collected
is there any information,
let's say you could go
out the next day.
What do you think,
based on what you saw,
what do you think might
happen the next day?
- It might go back down
into the 30s or the 20s.
- [Teacher] Okay, and
what makes you say that?
- Because there's more 30s and 20s
then there are 50s and 40s.
And,
then
there was a large spike so.
- [Teacher] Okay, so it got warmer.
But you're saying because
most of them were cooler,
it might get cooler again?
- Yes.
- Okay, so you're making
a conclusion.
You're using your data
to support that.
Shaun, what are you thinking?
- I was thinking that maybe
they might want to track it,
because maybe weather can,
not evolve over time,
but how much it's changing
and predict what's gonna happen.
- Okay, so you're thinking
like a meteorologist
or a scientist might
make a forecast,
make a prediction, so you're
thinking sort of like Hava.
And were your temperatures
similar to her,
or were they very different?
because you might have been
at two different stations.
What do you think might
happen on the next day?
- I think it will drop
down to the 30s,
because I see that it's
dropping down, it's going up,
and then it's dropping down.
I think it's gonna go up
and then drop down again.
- Okay, and it does look like
you had kind of a trend here.
So, what do you think if you
had a day that went down,
do you think it might go up again?
- Mhm.
- Might peak up again?
Okay.
Is there anybody else
who's looking at their
data thinking of
what else might happen with
that temperature change?
Madison, are you
looking at something?
Yeah, what do you think?
- Well, with the wind
speed and it would be like
8.5 for quite a few times a day.
Sort of shot up into
20s or something.
- So what do you think
that was indicating?
- That it was a very windy day.
- A very windy day, okay.
So you guys, some of you look
at your charts if you were,
Madison was in Group A, and
can you make a connection,
or H.
Madison, can you make a connection
to your wind speed really spiked.
On that same day did
you have any difference,
or did you have something
happen in your temperature?
- Well, the temperature
was about 20 degrees
and because of the wind
was making it cooler.
- Okay, so you're saying
that you think that the wind
also has an effect on
the temperature?
- Mhm.
- Okay, so
was there anybody else in Group H
that recorded that sort of thing?
You had a big windy gust,
you had a very windy day,
your temperatures went down?
Did you have a similar
thing happen to you Hava?
- Yes.
- Yes, okay.
So you guys, why would we
want to track something like
not only temperature,
but also the wind speed?
Jada?
- So that they can know what
tomorrow's gonna be like,
or what another day's gonna be like.
Or for them to know if
it's gonna rain or,
- [Teacher] Okay.
- What the temperature
is gonna do.
- So they want to think maybe more,
you guys now your thinking, Jada,
you're even putting
together precipitation?
So maybe there's a
consequence of precipitation?
- No, with low temperature and
maybe heat can
evaporate some water
and then the next day
it can get dropped
down and get colder.
- Okay, so maybe a connection
with the precipitation,
temperature, those sorts of things.
Okay, Katie O. What are you thinking?
- I would think that they wouldn't
just want to track the temperature,
but they'd also do the wind speed
because wind speed can change how,
what the temperature is,
and how it changes.
- So why do you think wind speed
makes a difference with temperature?
What are you making the connection with?
What's your evidence?
- Well wind speed I think would change
like it wouldn't make it warmer,
it would make the
temperature feel colder.
- Okay.  So why do you think that?
- Because the wind...
- Well you go out to the
playground a lot, right?
- Yeah.
- And when you guys
are on the playground
and it's really windy,
is it warm?
- No.
- Okay, so maybe are
you thinking like
when you go out there
and it's really windy
and you don't have a coat,
does it feel cooler to you?
- Yes.
- Does it on sometimes?
- Yeah.
- [Teacher] Alright,
so maybe they're maybe a prediction.
And so you were saying they,
so are you thinking
scientists and meteorologists
are trying to put those two
together, those phenomenons?
- Yeah.
- Okay, so Katie O, let me ask you,
if this was a hypothesis
that you were saying,
if it's windier,
then it may be cooler.
You guys agree as a class?
Okay thumps up, thumbs down,
what do you guys think?
Yes, no, maybe, a little bit there?
Alright, Josh, what are you thinking?
- I was saying that if
people are always looking
at the temperature
so we know what's gonna happen,
when it's gonna happen,
what we can expect,
what we need to do.
- Okay.  So we're taking that
forecast even further maybe?
So let me kind of pose
another question real quick
before I keep going you guys.
Let me ask you, you guys remember
when you went on the computer
and you watched the hurricanes?
And you tracked the hurricanes?
So was that data indicating the speed
or the movement of the hurricane?
- Yes.
- Yes?
So, does a meteorologist even
track something like that
to be able to maybe help people?
- Yes.
Okay.  So do you guys remember
when the meteorologist
came to visit us?
You guys remember that?
And he really talked to us a
lot about tornadoes, didn't he?
But, he was also giving us situations
of how we know a tornado
might be forming, right?
So, yeah, does that make sense,
that that might be another
reason that they start tracking?
So think and talk to
your shoulder partner.
Besides a hurricane, what
else might they track to,
like Josh was saying, to
prepare us for, to let us know.
So talk to your shoulder partner.
[Background Chatter]
- The weather because some people
can know what to like my hands.
- Yeah, or like tornadoes.
- Yeah, or maybe even thunderstorms.
- Or the normal weather.
Very intense temperatures,
we can already know.
- Maybe even like snow,
because that can be
a really heavy and
or kind of get everywhere
like snowbound us.
- Or it could like be rain, snow, hail.
[Background Chatter]
- [Teacher] So what do you think Emily,
what else can we determine?
[Background Chatter]
- Snow storm.
Or a tornado.
- Or a earthquake.
- So what were you
thinking first Alexis,
and then we'll come back to Nick?
- I was thinking either a
tornado or blizzard snowstorm.
- Okay.  So what kind of weather
do you think they're tracking
in order for us to be
prepared about weather.
What do we?
- Wind.
- Wind, maybe.
- And temperature.
- Snow.
- [Teacher] Okay, so if we're
looking for just a tornado,
maybe temperature, maybe the wind.
- Yeah, what kind of wind is
it, is it cold or hot, yeah.
- Okay, hot and cold fronts.
And then we were thinking
about, what else Nick?
- I would say a flood because maybe
maybe the clouds are coming
and there's going to
be a bunch of rain.
Like you said, that we
could get a flash flood.
- Okay.  So and are you
making that connection
to maybe our area that had a fire,
and so we have to think
about would there be,
because it can't absorb the moisture.
Okay, so that's another idea.
So how would meteorologist
or scientists,
how would they Austin,
how would they predict
maybe a flood happening?
What do you think they'd use?
What kind of information
would they be looking at?
- Well if a rainstorm was coming,
because that rain would cause a flood.
- [Teacher] Okay, so a
large amount of rain,
that would make sense yes.
- Or snow.
- Or even if we had a lot of snow.
So if we had large amounts of snow,
what could we possibly
be warning people of,
if that was the case?
Alexis, what do you think?
- Stay inside or wear warm
clothes if you go somewhere
or something so they
don't get so cold.
- [Teacher] Okay, so would
you guys say,
would one of you formulate
some sort of a hypothesis
about snow coming if there was?
- If there was enough cold air.
And some times when it's
raining it starts to hail,
and then it starts to,
sometimes it starts to snow.
- So, if there's cold
weather and clouds,
then we might have consequences.
- Snow, or rain, or yeah.
- [Teacher] of hail,
or heavy snow?
- Yeah.
- [Teacher] Okay, so we'd
wanna keep that in mind.
And does that seem to
happen in our areas?
- Sometimes.
- [Teacher] Sometimes.
And sometimes when we
make that forecast,
and then maybe it doesn't come.
- That happened on Saturday.
- [Teacher] Okay, so if it does come,
what happened on Saturday, Austin?
- I think
it was really humid out at first,
- [Teacher] Mhm.
- And then,
it started to rain,
and then a lot of times
usually rain starts out
as ice and then it melts.
And it started to get colder
and then it started to hail.
- [Teacher] So then we have the
consequences of a hailstorm.
Didn't last Saturday, did it
start out really nice first?
- Yeah.
- Yeah, and then
also happened yesterday too,
because
when I got picked up it was
nice and warm and everything.
And then when I got to my
house it was all windy,
and then it started raining.
So I was like,
I thought it was supposed
to be hot today.
- Right.
So is it possible to use
forecasting information
and still be wrong?
- Yes.
[Background Chatter]
- Well in the weather book,
it explains the rating of tornadoes.
So I'm thinking tornadoes,
or something to track
like the wind speed
if it's gets too crazy,
it get like
wind miles per hour, and
how bad it is.
Like if the wind
speed's really high,
then it can cause a tornado.
Like the scale.
[Background Chatter]
- So they use that information.
We were just talking
and showing the things
that they might be using for
information that they're
collecting to do what now?
To give to the what?
- They're doing it to give us warnings.
They can't tell us that a
tornado's happening prior to it,
- [Teacher] Right.
- So they
have to warn us about them.
And so I think they collect
the data from that to do that.
- Okay, and then Reagan, what
were you connecting that with?
- I was connecting it with
a blizzard or snow storm,
because if there's a delay
and you need to go somewhere,
you can know that there
might be delays.
And if you're gonna go outside
you need to wear a coat,
a heavy coat.
- Okay, so how do we respond,
how do we react to it, good.
Okay, you guys I was going around,
and I heard some
excellent conversations.
And so I think you guys
made strong connections
with your data.
And probably with your
meteorologist visit,
what they were telling you,
and how you were putting
that information together.
So I want you guys to go ahead
and pick up your pencils.
And write underneath your graphs,
I want you to answer this question.
What does your data tell you?
So write there on
underneath your graph,
or write on your graph,
you could even write right
in the middle of your graph,
I want you to write what is
your graph actually telling you?
So is it telling you that you
had a series of cold days?
Make your prediction.
So go ahead and take a minute or two,
write down what your data tells you
and then what changes
did you observe?
What was the most significant
change that you observed?
If at all possible, while
you're writing that,
you can come up with a hypothesis
about your data.
It could either be your wind speed,
or it could be your temperature.
Write down what it is
that actually took place.
Yeah, you want to
answer the question,
what does your data tell you?
What changes did you observe?
On either graph or you
can even write a sentence
that combines the two
of them together.
- So mine says,
I added a little more.
It says, it is telling me
all about my wind speed,
and how it's going high
or low, or high.
What does your say Austin?
- Mine is, it had cold and hot days.
And it went from 44 degrees Fahrenheit
to 20 degrees Fahrenheit.
- [Teacher] So go ahead,
just like Alexis and Austin shared,
go ahead and share with
your face partner this time,
so that you change who
you're talking to.
So Emily and Madison, you can
also share what you wrote.
- It tells me that some
times it can be hot,
and then go down to
a little bit colder,
and then it goes back into hot.
- Yeah, that's what I was kinda saying
when I told the wind speed,
because it's not always wind speed.
Yeah, it's not always wind speed,
but most of the time when we took it,
it was mostly in the winter
so it would mostly go down.
Like, it was 40, then it
was 25, then it was 20,
and then it was 30, and then
it was 30, and then it was 40,
and then it was 50.
So, that's what.
- [Teacher] So John what did
you figure out from your data?
- I figured out that
it was colder the week
we were doing this.
- [Teacher] Okay.
- And the wind speed
was not very high.
- [Teacher] Okay, oh yeah, yeah.
So you were in an area that maybe
was more protected by
the wind, do you think?
- Yeah, we were behind the building.
- [Teacher] Oh okay, so that
might of had an effect too?
- Yeah.
- [Teacher] Okay, did you draw
any conclusions from that?
- I forgot to do that.
- Okay, great.
Braden, tell us a little bit about
what you observed from your data?
- Well, I observed that
I did not get much wind speed.
- Okay, so where was your station?
Were you at a protected area as well?
- Yes.
- Okay, so that definitely
had an effect, didn't it?
- Yes.
- So as a meteorologist,
would you want to be able
to put your anemometers
somewhere where you know
you're gonna catch the wind?
- Yep.
- [Teacher] Okay,
so that was a really important
lesson right there, too.
So what about your
thermometer readings,
since those weren't
dependent necessarily on
being protected from the wind.
What can you observe from
your thermometer reading?
- Well, that it was
40 degrees on Monday,
and then on Tuesday and
Wednesday it got colder.
- Okay, so it got colder
on Tuesday and Wednesday.
So if you were making a prediction,
what do you think would
happen on this day,
based on your data?
Do you think it's gonna
change, stay the same,
what do you think?
- Stay the same.
- Seems like it's
gonna stay the same,
because you have
that pretty consistently?
- Yeah.
- [Teacher] Okay, alright.
Tariq, what do you find
from your data?
What did you discover observing?
- I noticed that for
my temperature I had
up and down weather.
- [Teacher] So your temperature was,
would you say it was fluctuating?
- Yeah.
- [Teacher] Okay, why do you
think that was happening?
- Because, well it was cold
on the days we went out,
but where we were the sun was
kind of coming towards us,
at the times we went out.
- [Teacher] So do you
think that had an effect
on your thermometer as well?
- Yeah.
- [Teacher] Hm, okay so
then that's another thing
as a meteorologist, you
might want to think about
where your thermometer is, right?
Are you just getting straight sun?
Okay, was there something else
you were gonna say about
your wind speed?
- Well, my wind speed.
On Monday we got a lot.
And on Thursday we got a lot.
On the other two days
we didn't get any wind.
- [Teacher] Not too much, okay.
- Then.
- Then I also had,
- [Teacher] Go ahead.
- All three of us were
in the same group.
- [Teacher] You were in
the same group, alright.
So there you go.
- And,
I also had to say
that my wind speed
was never below 20 degrees.
- [Teacher] You to pull out
your sheet, right there that you have
about your temperature on the moon.
I want to ask you
one more question.
And I want you to think about
your temperature on the moon.
Now did you actually go to
the moon to get your data?
- No.
- No, but let's look
at the scientists
who recorded that data.
Why was it important
for them to find out
the temperature on the moon?
And as you look at it,
did it change very much?
So why was it important and
Okay, Jaime.
- I thought that
on
one of the missions
that it was different temperatures.
Like it would be
213,
and then it dropped
down to about 200.
- Okay, and so you're specifically
talking about the day?
- Yeah.
- [Teacher] Okay.
And so you're saying
is it pretty similar?
Is that you're saying?
- Pretty similar, but not very.
- Okay, so.
- The main thing is that
it didn't stay the same.
- Okay, it didn't seem
to stay the same.
- No.
- [Teacher] Okay.
And then we had,
not only day temperature,
but was the other temperature
that we looked at on the moon?
- Night.
- Nighttime, okay.
So what were you thinking
about that Shaun?
- I kind of had the
same data as Jamie did.
- [Teacher] Okay.
- Because
it switched every single mission.
So on mission 11 it was
210 degrees,
well 200 and about 13 degrees.
- [Teacher] Okay.
- And it just kept on going
down and up each mission.
So it changed significantly
each mission.