- Emotions.
- Is emotions, that's so right.
Kippa, were you going
to say something else?
- In this picture, he uses lots of texture
to create, like when he's
doing the sunflowers,
he uses texture to show
the light going on.
- Right, and how did he
show that texture, did he,
how did he apply his paint?
- Sometimes he would squirt
it straight from the tube
onto the canvas because
he wanted to do it fast.
- Sometimes he would squirt
straight from the tube
and he would paint so
thick, Vincent would,
that you could almost
feel it, feel the texture.
And emotion, like Ozea said.
Emotion was huge for Vincent.
If he was happy, he painted bright.
If he was sad, he painted sort of dark.
How about our man Pablo Picasso?
What movement, Logan, is he?
- Do you know the move--
- Cubism.
- [Teacher] Cubism. And why,
do you guys know what the
characteristics are of cubism?
Anybody besides Mr.
Logan, anybody else know?
But thanks Logan for raising--
What are you thinking, what...
- Using geometric shapes to make things.
- Using geometric shapes, that's right.
He was very involved in geometric shapes
and you can even see,
and flattening the shapes
and flattening his color.
Where Van Gogh used his color
to really be part of his painting
and it could be bright or it could be dull
or a mixture of the two.
Picasso used very flat shapes of color
and you can even see that
in his self-portrait.
I wanna put up the work.
Let's start with our man Vincent again.
Let's take a look at--
See where my hand...
Oooh!
You can see all the wrinkles in my hand.
- [Student] No way!
- Isn't that cool?
Okay! Sorry, don't mean
to keep fooling around.
So let's talk about this.
Let's talk about these
two paintings, guys.
What do you guys, and
let's see if someone else
maybe can answer or talk about something.
What do you see, do you
guys see a difference
between these two paintings right here?
Anybody, somebody besides Kippa, Carina?
- That it kinda has to
deal with his emotion,
like where the boats are, I feel like,
what I'm feeling is that
he was kinda depressed
and very sad because the skies
were kinda dark and stuff.
And then at the sunflowers
he's really happy and bright and...
- That was good, Carina.
Okay, Elijah, did you wanna?
Was that about what you were gonna say?
You were gonna talk about the sadness.
What colors, like do you think that if...
Go ahead, Elijah.
- He could've been in the boat
because on the computer the
boats were really bright colors
but the sky was darkened more
but the boats were all
light yellow and dark,
light red and all these
other bright colors.
- Right, and I remember you saying that
when you showed me with the
picture from the computer,
that's why I looked at you
because you were talking about
he must have been conflicted
with his emotions,
wasn't that what you were saying?
- Yeah, he was feeling both happy and sad
'cause the sky was darkened
and then the boats were really bright
and the sea was darkened too.
- Right, that's good. Okay,
Jose, what did you wanna say?
- He's sort of like there too, but
the boats might be out to sea.
Like one's out to sea
but one's not, but torn.
I don't know how many are already but...
Three are out, in. I
don't know how many are out.
- There's four that are here
and then there look
like four that are out.
- I think that's the other--
(student coughing)
- Okay but what were you going to say...
Oh you're right, three.
Well what were you gonna say about them?
- I'm guessing three,
two or three were the
family of six kids and
the mom and a dad.
But they could only take three
because there's only enough for...
There's enough room for only three boats
or three people.
But they only wanted their own boat,
two or three of them
were, but three didn't go
because they didn't know
what to do or anything
but the other three did.
- Interesting, that was sort of your story
behind the picture that you saw?
- Kind of.
- Yeah, I like that, I like that.
Trevor, what're you gonna say?
- It's kinda like medium of a position
between sad and happy
because the sunflowers, they're mostly up
but looks like they're starting to droop.
They're starting to die.
- [Teacher] That is good, I like that.
- He might be like, "Oh,
I'm happy for a while but
"I'm starting to feel back down."
- [Teacher] Nice. Did
you wanna say something?
- I would like to say one has
different types of (mumbles)
One looks more real.
Those ships on the top
look a little bit more real than the...
- Than the bottom, more
realistic than this picture?
He really pushed his color lips
in the sunflowers, I think.
Does anybody know, what
were you gonna say, Elijah?
- You can see in the sunflower one
like at the very top there's bright yellow
but when you go down a
little bit it's orange
and then at the very
bottom it's dark green.
Like right there.
- Yes that is very
true. That is very good.
- The storms and the
sunflowers is trying to say
that nothing is never everlasting.
- [Teacher] Wow, Kyle...
(student mumbles)
Happiness is never lasting and
what was the last one?
I'm moved by that opinion.
Go ahead, and what was the...?
- So in the flowers, the flowers are happy
but then they start to droop and die.
- Because happiness can be fleeting.
And we know--
Oh, does anybody know,
what was the political,
was there any political things going on?
The political mood or the setting.
Where was Vincent from,
did you guys find that in your research?
He stayed in France, is
that where he studied?
Is that what you guys are telling me?
- [Students] Yeah
- That was sorta the hub
of his movement, we'll say.
Any other facts that you guys know
about the artwork that's up?
You can look on your
research papers to see.
Or anything-- Go ahead, Emily.
- I think that the actual
emotions of these paintings
don't really connect at
all with the political mood
because when he painted the
bright sunflower one so awesome
it was kind of a dark time in France.
So really I don't think
they were much of a...
- Really affected him? What were you...
- Going along with Emily,
maybe he was just so dull that,
or maybe it was coming to
an end when he painted them.
Because if there was a war
or some sort of bad time
and it was coming to an end
he was probably starting
to feel better about it
because it was ending.
So it depends, maybe he
was going through things
like maybe a very happy thing
happened in his life then.
Because he didn't have the
happiest of all lives so...
- He didn't. We've even talked about that.
Do you guys remember when we talked about
how Vincent Van Gogh suffered
a little bit mentally?
He was a little...
- Crazy.
- Crazy and in and out
of mental institutions.
- Yeah so maybe something good happened.
'Cause his life was not very happy.
So most of his pictures are...
No, not most of them
but quite a few of them
are actually quite dull.
But you can tell when
he's going through joy
because he has those
bright colors coming in.
Like the boats, you can see
a little bit of happiness in them
but the majority of it
is dark and sort of sad.
And then if you look at the sunflowers
they're all bright and dreamy.
I mean yes, this is a few dark bits
but I think that's
probably a time when he was
going through something
that was better in his life.
- Guys, this is really great.
I love all your comments.
Logan, I'm gonna take one more
and then I'm gonna tell you something.
What, go ahead Logan.
- I thought maybe that he was painting it
and then something happened.
Like maybe he heard that war
was breaking out or something.
And then he started painting it sad.
- I have a question.
- [Teacher] I think that--
You've got something
really important, hon?
- Yeah, so he never really
stopped a painting in the middle.
When he started he
finished. He never stopped.
Because if the light changed
it would totally change the picture.
- [Teacher] That's so
true. That is very true.
And you guys know that--
Jose, is it okay if I speak real quick
and then we'll go back
because we wanna talk about
Picasso too for a minute.
You guys know that Vincent
used to live with a painter.
This is my fun fact.
Not really fun I guess.
But a fact about Vincent.
He lived with a painter, Paul Gauguin.
This was when he was in and
out of mental institutions.
And they had a fight
and he became so upset,
you guys know he cut off his ear.
And I showed you that one picture of him
is a self-portrait of
him with his ear cut off.
You guys remember that?
And the other important
thing I wanted to tell you
was that he didn't sell any of his works
during his lifetime
but he did sell one of
his paintings after...
After he died they sold
one of his paintings
for $8,000,000,000.
Remember that?
It was the most expensive painting
ever sold at the time.
Okay, now let's talk about...
And Van Gogh people,
if you guys wanna talk
about Picasso you can,
but let's give the Picasso
teams some time here.
This is... And I'm sorry the
lighting is not the best.
But who knows what the name
of this painting is? Marie.
- [Marie] Is it Three Musicians?
- Three Musicians. And it was done by who?
- [Students] Pablo
- Pablo Picasso.
Does anybody know where
Pablo Picasso was from?
Let's see someone other
than Mr. Logan. Travis.
- [Travis] Barcelona.
- [Teacher] Barcelona.
Where's Barcelona, you guys?
- Spain.
- [Teacher] Spain.
- [Student] I got my Barcelona jersey.
- Alright and who knows,
Rudy, do you happen to know...
And he's like, "Uh-oh,
I'm on the spot! Ooo!"
Do you happen to know
what movement or style he
painted in, Pablo Picasso?
- In Cubism?
- Cubism, that's correct.
And we did go over,
what were the characteristics
of cubism real fast?
Anybody? Mr Logan.
- [Logan] Geometric shapes.
- [Teacher] Geometric
shapes and what else?
- They were flat.
- [Teacher] What was flat?
- His pictures.
- [Teacher] But what element--
- His painting the colors.
- [Teacher] The colors
were flat. Thank you.
Okay, let's have some opinion
about what you see up here.
The Three Musicians, does anybody have...
Randy, do you have any, how
do you feel about it, honey?
What do you think about it?
- I don't know. It doesn't seem
like it's in a down mood
'cause music is usually
a happy sort of thing.
So it seems like a happy kinda picture.
- [Teacher] Kind of a happy fun picture.
Pablo, he wasn't so concerned
about emotions when he painted.
He maybe was influenced
by the political setting of his time.
Does anybody know what was happening
in Spain at the time?
What are you thinking?
- [Student] Civil war.
- There was a civil war.
So maybe he was a little
bit affected by that.
He also traveled.
Does anybody know where
he traveled to, Rudy?
To go and study the art forms of...
- Paris? He went to Paris
because it was of all
the artwork and stuff.
- So he went to study
there and then where else?
- [Student] He went to Africa.
- [Teacher] He went to Africa
and he really became
obsessed with African masks.
And so he did start using that
as an influence in his painting.
Carina, what were you gonna say, darling?
- Oh, I was thinking it's
kind of like a mix of emotions
'cause it has so many colors.
There's bright orange and yellow
and then if you look deeper,
there's a blue and a black
and it kind of just grabs your attention.
- [Teacher] It's
attention-grabbing, isn't it?
'Cause of all the contrasting.
I think more in his is
the contrasting colors.
You can see the blue and orange
right next to each other.
Those are colors that
lie opposite each other
on the color wheel and
they make for very bright,
they totally stand off each other.
Right, the blue and the orange.
I can't remember what-- Oh,
they're complementary colors.
I couldn't remember what that
was. Right, so that's why.
And I think his color contrast says a lot.
His flat colors and they're bright
and he puts them right next to each other.
What do you think about
this picture, Robert?
Do you like it?
- Yeah.
- [Teacher] Do you know
why you might like it
or you don't like it?
- I like the picture, like... yeah.
- [Teacher] Well you and
Maria are talking about doing,
remember you were talking
about making your own picture?
You wanna tell us about
that, what you guys wanna do?
For your own picture?
And you're doing the style
of Pablo, aren't you?
- Yeah.
- [Teacher] So what do you
think you guys are gonna do?
- Have a picture of me and my brother
and a picture of the Three
Musicians on a porch.
- [Teacher] You wanna
have the Three Musicians
be in a picture with you and your brother?
And Maria, are you gonna--
- Not on a porch. On a deck.
- That's what I was gonna say.
- [Teacher] And you guys are gonna,
are you guys gonna reduce
it down to geometric shapes?
The picture?
- Yeah.
- Try to.
- [Teacher] Good, good.
Do you guys have anybody--
Oh, what were you gonna say, Elijah?
- It makes me think about it,
because there's so many twists and turns
and curves and things.
Kinda like if you look
hard enough you can see 'em
but when you just look at
it you're like, "Whoa."
- Right, when you first
look at it, you're like,
"Whoa, what is that? Are those
people? Are those shapes?
"There's lots of curves and turns."
- [Student] At first
it's a little confusing.
- At first it is a little
confusing, isn't it?
- [Student] When you actually pick a name
and you actually try to look for 'em
you can actually see what it is.
- Right, if we didn't tell
you it was the Three Musicians
you might not know at first.
- You can kinda tell because
of that one right there.
That thing, yeah.
- The instrument here.
And the guitar.
- And then the paper with the two...
- The sheet music.
- The sheet music,
you could kinda tell it
was about the musicians.
- What were you gonna say?
- When you first look at the painting,
your eyes are immediately drawn
to the first guy in blue's clarinet.
Whereas if you peeked
a minute and look at it
you can actually kinda see instruments
like they were saying.
At first, when you just...
but instead you just see
a whole bunch of colors
and then you look at it and
it kinda starts to form.
- It does start to form. What
were you gonna say, Emily?
- I think that in my