[Background chatter]
- [Voiceover] Well frogs do sink, they do.
It's sinking.
- What do you think caused that to happen,
what made it sink that time?
- [Voiceover] I put it like that and...
- And then it was sinking.
Alright, but now we saw some pictures
where the real frogs got on
lily pads and didn't sink.
So, what do you think is different?
- It's like stuck to the ground and...
- The lily pad is stuck to the ground?
- Yeah, I think there's something inside.
I think there's something
in like dirt, you know,
like that causes the lily pad to grow.
But with something in the lily pad seed.
- [Voiceover] We were looking
at this the other day.
Do you girls remember about that?
Okay, what were you all thinking about that.
- [Voiceover] They don't...
- [Voiceover] But what
were you thinking Andrea?
(mumbles)
- You know these eyes right here,
we don't have eyes like this,
but frogs...
But frogs jump really high.
If they don't jump really the same,
they probably
just almost jump
if the momma and daddy frogs turn into,
get some eggs
and the tadpole comes out.
- That tadpole right there,
he was following it and then he stopped.
What if they took the
flashlight, they might move.
- [Voiceover] Yeah.
- Like this, watch.
When you take it off...
I did this in my momma's.
When you take it off
and you turn it this
way he looks back at it,
like this.
That's what he does.
- [Voiceover] How come?
- Because when tadpoles like eat things
that glow, then when you take it off,
you put it back on.
- [Voiceover] How come, why?
- I know, they just don't.
- [Voiceover] But that's not fair.
- [Voiceover] What else
did you notice (mumbles)?
We did the spots.
What else did you notice?
Jamal, look at it again.
- Frog.
- [Voiceover] What body parts do you see?
- [Voiceover] Gray, polka dots.
- You said the spots.
- [Voiceover] The feet.
- [Voiceover] The feet,
what about it (mumbles)?
- [Voiceover] Lines on it.
- [Voiceover] Some lines on it.
And what are you saying, Nikera?
You said it had some things on it.
- [Voiceover] That white stuff.
- What is that?
What is that white stuff on it's feet?
See if I can get a closer look.
What is that?
Jamia, do you see that?
The white things on its feet.
- [Voiceover] It's his foots.
- It's his feet?
Do you have that on your feet?
- [Voiceover] No.
(class chatting)
- [Voiceover] They need peace and quiet.
- If they don't have a calm river...
Look, they live in ponds.
Dude, listen, listen.
- There are trees right here.
There's flowers.
- Listen.
Latan, be quiet.
I'm thinking that this is very calm rivers
and this is what you call
that ooey, gooey stuff
that Ms. Robbie called it.
That's the lake and that's the pond
and there I am (mumbles) frogs.
- They need grass, they need flowers,
they need little trees, they need...
- I was thinking Aleha,
thinking about us living in houses.
We live in houses because
can't breathe water.
This is my house
(mumbles)
and like there's dirt under there.
And there's dirt under there.
Then under that runs the water,
the blue water.
- Let's add something to it.
- So what made it work this time?
- [Voiceover] It stands upside down.
The frog floats.
It doesn't jump on any kind of one,
it only jumps on the ones that are round.
Because it needs something facing up
to make the walls.
- [Voiceover] Because this is facing up,
so you think maybe the lily pad faces up.
- Right, if it does this
it needs like a shield
so the water won't get in
because if the water touches it,
it will tear and it will sink.
- [Voiceover] Did you listen?
- Because they need
something on it like rain.
- [Voiceover] So you're
saying if water touches it,
what happens if water gets on top of it?
- It'll sink because it'll tear
the lily pad up and it'll sink,
but with the flower on
it, it does not sink.
- [Voiceover] So if it has the flower,
you think the flower
keeps it from sinking.
- Because it's stuck.
It's stuck and it's so hard,
it makes it so hard and rainy
and it dries up.
- [Voiceover] So, when
you dried the frog off
did that make a difference?
- [Voiceover] Well, it
doesn't make a difference.
Frogs like to be wet.
- [Voiceover] Frogs are usually wet.
- [Voiceover] That frog is
an African swimming frog
because look at it's feet.
- [Voiceover] It does look
like an African dwarf frog.
- It jumps on the water.
It can run and hop on water.
- [Voiceover] Andrea, what
did you notice about this?
What did you notice?
- [Voiceover] I know
that we have (mumbles).
- [Voiceover] It doesn't float.
(class chatting)
- [Voiceover] Let me show you which one.
- [Voiceover] Which one?
- [Voiceover] What about this one?
- [Voiceover] He was growing legs.
- [Voiceover] No, this one's growing legs.
(class chatting)
- [Voiceover] (mumbles)
but that's what tadpoles
swim in.
Okay, you see them?
- Shine it on it.
- [Voiceover] No.
You see they're moving because
they're growing legs.
(class chatting)
- [Voiceover] If you yell really loud
the glass will break and
then the tadpoles (mumbles).
(class chatting)
- [Voiceover] Frogs.
The frog's body.
(class chatting)
- [Voiceover] There's a water snake.
There's a water snake.
A water snake.
(class chatting)
- What are you talking about over here?
- This thing has a frog in it.
- And he just swam.
- [Voiceover] Okay, so
we're talking over here.
- Ms. Robbie, look.
- So, you're comparing
the pond to your house.
- Yeah.
(class chatting)
- [Voiceover] Alright, did you
see this that she found out?
It says the frog is pulling off its skin.
I wonder why it's doing that.
- Because, so it can have different skin.
- Why would it make different skin?
- It might need different
skin because of the way it lives.
The way it lives, it has
to take off its own skin,
just like a snake takes
off its whole skin.
Snakes take off their skin.
- Be a new frog.
- The way they take off their
skin is they shred it off.
They don't have any arms.
Snakes shed their skin off
and they don't have no arms.
- Snakes shed their skin?
- [Voiceover] Yeah.
- Do you think frogs shed their skin too?
What do you think Aleha?
You found the picture, tell
me what you're thinking.
Let me hear Aleha.
- When it gets old they
have to take it off.
- He has to take it off.
Why do you think he needs
to take his skin off?
- I was thinking...
- Just a moment, Daniel,
let me hear Aleha,
I can't hear.
- When it gets too rough
on him, he can take if off.
- [Voiceover] Maybe if
his skin feels rough.
Hmm, I'm wondering about that.
That's giving me
something to wonder about.
- Ms. Robbie, there's a water beetle.
- Yes, but we're still looking at this
about this frog coming off.
She feels like maybe
when his skin is rough
he takes it off.
What did the page say?
It uses a word I'm not sure about, molt.
It said frogs molt a few times every year.
- Because it's the way they live.
- [Voiceover] It's the way they live.
- But we don't live that
way, the same way we do.
We get bigger instead of shredding skin.
- You're right.
We get--
What, what'd you say?
Say that again.
- We get bigger.
- [Voiceover] We get bigger.
- And they shred.
- [Voiceover] And they shed their skin.
- That's opposite.
- Hmm, I'm going to write
down that word molt.
We're going to talk
about that a little bit.
We're going to try to explore
that a little bit more.
(class chatting)
- The frogs are underground
and they hatch out of the eggs
and turn into the tadpoles
and they're going to grow up a little
and they're going to lost their tail
and they're going to
turn into an adult frog
and then they are underground
when it's winter.
- [Voiceover] When it's
winter they're undergound.
Okay, what have you all
found out about comparing?
- [Voiceover] The frogs
protect their babies.
- Do the frogs protect their babies?
- No, they don't.
What about your (mumbles)?
- They wait until they hatch.
- [Voiceover] They wait till they hatch.
- Frogs have bigger eyes than us
because they have those eyes
like that on their heads
and we don't.
- And we have eyes that are small.
And when you were born did your mom or dad
take care of you or your grown up?
- [Voiceover] Yes.
- [Voiceover] I went to my
grandma when I'm a baby.
- Okay, did your grownup take care of you
when you were a baby, Andreas?
- [Voiceover] Yes.
- Yeah, well what about the mother frogs?
- No.
- [Voiceover] I got a lot of food I love.
- You got a lot of food.
- [Voiceover] I eat chicken
and rice, everything.
- Andreas just think about our tadpoles.
Is the momma frog in here
taking care of those tadpoles?
- [Class] No.
- [Voiceover] They wait till they hatch.
- Maybe the momma frog missed them.
- [Voiceover] Probably if
they die after wintertime...