- [Teacher] Well, you know what,
especially after Mrs. Bennett
taught you the three things
she wanted you to do in reading
by having you look around the room,
and skip around the room,
and flip on the carpet,
we thought, "Oh boy, that Nathan really
"needs to do something hands-on."
And I know from you
being in Reading Recovery
that when you heard a book
twice you practically knew it.
I mean, you knew the story.
You could go somewhere and tell it, right?
- [Nathan] Yep.
- [Teacher] When you read the book
is it easy for you to retell it?
What is it like to retell
a story that you just read?
- [Nathan] Not so easy for me,
'cause I had to
pick up a book,
look at it for a minute
and then I pop it and then I know it.
- [Teacher] Okay, if I read a
story to you would you
be able to go tell it to someone else?
- [Nathan] Yes.
- [Teacher] Okay.
- [Nathan] But right next to me.
- [Nathan] Okay.
- [Teacher] All right, well these
are the things we're gonna practice.
And because we don't want to leave out
the visual style of
learning because it's also
an important way to get information,
we're gonna focus on the
auditory and the kinestetic,
the hearing and the
hands-on type learning,
and we're also gonna include some visual
so that it will strengthen
that part for you.
But we wanna make sure we're getting you
where your strength is.
Because you are fantastic at listening
and doing hands-on activities.
Oh, you have a plan in your mind about
what kind of castle you're gonna build?
- [Nathan] It's not a castle. It's gonna be
like when I see that in movies.
Like a tower like where
the Egypt, Egyptites.
- [Teacher] The Egyptians?
- [Nathan] Yeah.
- [Teacher] Like a pyramid?
- [Teacher] Okay, cool.
All right.
Would you like some extra things,
like maybe some games or
some extra things you can do
to help you remember in class?
- [Nathan] Yeah because my teacher
she gives us free games,
like learning games, in our math book.
There's math games
and you have to put your thing on it
and you have to guess who much it is.
And if you get it right you stay on there.
- [Teacher] Okay, cool.
Well I want to add some games like that
that you're gonna--
And we're gonna add some
things that you can do
to help you remember directions in class
and remember what Miss
Smithson has asked you to do.
'Cause one of the things
that I've noticed is that
when Miss Smithson gives
you two or three directions,
you'll start one and then you
forget what the other ones are.
And you're like, "Ugh, what do I do now?"
- [Nathan] Yeah because my
brain it has so much stuff
and because if I get more
it kind of breaks the other stuff.
- [Teacher] And you know, I wasn't
gonna talk about this yet
but by you saying that, your
brain has so much stuff,
I wanted to remind you about,
do you know what good
listening looks like?
- [Nathan] Uh, huh.
- [Teacher] What do good listeners look like?
- [Nathan] Their hands are crisscrossed
with their hands in their lap
and wherever the teacher goes
they keep their eyes on 'em.
- [Teacher] Okay, and then if you
have a comment, if I say,
"Would anyone like to ask a question
"or make a comment about
what we're learning?"
Let's say I just taught
you about Clemson Football.
- [Nathan] Or I like hockey.
That's my favorite.
- [Teacher] Okay, let's say we were
learning about hockey.
The equipment used in hockey, okay?
So if I asked you to
either ask me a question
or make a comment about
what we're learning,
would you
tell me the names
of some of the hockey
equipment that you know of?
Or would you ask me a question about
a piece of hockey
equipment that you've seen
but you don't know what it's called?
Or would you tell me a story about
how you really like hockey?
- [Nathan] Hmmm, how I really like hockey.
- [Teacher] I knew you'd say that!
You always do that!
You remember one of things that
Miss McGinnis taught
you in Reading Recovery?
And one of the strengths,
this is what I love about you,
one of the things that a lot of people
have trouble with when they're reading
is that they can't relate
what they're reading
to themselves or to their lives.
You are absolutely fantastic with that.
Fantastic.
- [Nathan] If there's a story of
a dog and I have a dog
and my dog did the same thing.
- [Teacher] Right.
So since you're so good at that, though,
sometimes I think that that
is one of the things that
gets your mind off on... on...
"Hey my dog did that."
Instead of on exactly what your
teacher's wanting you to do.
So one of the things about
being a really good listener
is to remember what
comments, and what statements
and what questions are necessary
for what you're learning.
And which comments and
questions should wait for later,
even though they're zinging
around in your head, okay?
So if I'm doing a whole class lesson about
different colored fur on dogs
and I say, "Can anyone think of a color
"that a dog's fur might be?"
What would be a comment you could make?
- [Nathan] Black and brown 'cause
that's what my dog is made out of.
- [Teacher] Okay, black and brown.
All right, let's say somebody says blonde,
somebody else says white
and then somebody raises
their hand and they say,
"Well, I don't know what
all colors dogs can be
"but my dog Sandy is really pretty."
Is that a comment that is necessary
for what we're talking about?
- [Nathan] No.
- [Teacher] Okay, so that's one of the
things that you can practice.
And I love your stories and I
know Miss Smithson does, too.
And you have a lot of kids
and grownups in this school
that feel really close
to you and we feel like
we have a good relationship with you
because you do share
things about yourself.
- [Nathan] Yeah, but I only do that
at the beginning of the day,
the end of the day and at writing.
'Cause I write down the things in writing.
- [Teacher] Good, well then I'm
glad Miss Smithson is also
working on this with
you because as much as I
want to know about you I
don't want it to distract
you from what it is you're
supposed to be thinking about.
Okay?
- [Nathan] Okay.
- [Teacher] Three more blocks.
Okay, let's talk about some of the things
that we're gonna put
in place for you, okay?
A couple of 'em I'm pretty
excited about, okay?
We're gonna work on your memory
with reading and in general with classwork
so that when someone
tells Nathan what to do,
Nathan's gonna be able to remember it.
Instead of getting distracted
and thinking, "Huh.
"I have no idea what I'm
supposed to do next."
- [Nathan] Yeah because in my
class there's some kids,
Zachary and Brody and the two new kids,
they're talking in the back.
- [Teacher] And that's can be very
distracting, can't it?
Okay, do you know how to focus?
Do you know how to tune people out?
What do you do when you're
distracted in the classroom?
- [Nathan] I just turn around and go like this.
- [Teacher] Okay, do you think you
know how to tune people out
without having to tell them to stop?
What if you knew they were
gonna talk no matter what
but you still needed to listen?
Could you?
- [Nathan] I could do this to block their sound.
- [Teacher] Okay, you could.
That kinda reminds me of the bat
we were talking about for some reason.
It's kinda like you're directing
your hearing at one place.
- [Nathan] And sometimes I push it
to what I'm hearing at.
So then when I do that in my mouth
I can hear it more good without
noises from the construction
site that's near our house.
I can focus on it.
- [Teacher] Okay, I think that's
fantastic what you've just said.
You make a conscious effort to focus
on what you're trying to hear.
That what I want you to do when you notice
that other people are talking behind you.
Instead of worrying
about what they're doing,
I want you to focus on what
you need to be hearing.
I want you to stop and think,
"I'm not gonna listen to them,
"I'm gonna listen to Miss Smithson."
Okay?
And see if that helps.
Just like you strain to hear
the construction noises, okay?
All right, we're gonna do
some fun things with you
that I think you're gonna like.
First of all, I know you love video games.
So one of the things
that we've tried before
that doesn't seem to be
working very well is Odyssey.
And I know that when you get on Odyssey
you like to choose the math
games over the reading games.
Probably just--Why do you
choose math over reading?
- [Nathan] 'Cause I wanna get
more math so then I can just
focus on reading 'cause if
I'm really smart at math
I can just drop it so I know everything.
- [Teacher] I know sweetheart.
It's a lot more fun to do something
that you're really good at.
So we're gonna change up
your computer program.
Instead of having you work
on Odyssey during the day,
instead of Odyssey you're gonna
work on a new program called Earobics.
And it's supposed to be super
helpful with your reading skills.
And Mrs. Price, the speech teacher
whose office is across the hall,
she said it is really fun
and that she knew kids
at Griggs Road that did it
and they loved it, okay?
So we're gonna try Earobics.
So we're gonna keep a
computer game for you
but we're gonna try one that
hopefully is gonna work better
to help your reading skills
come up instead of Odyssey.
Okay? All right.
The next thing we're gonna do is
we're gonna give you a
little tape recorder.
Have you ever had a tape recorder?
- [Nathan] No and I haven't even seen one.
- [Teacher] I know, a lot of people don't
use tape recorders anymore.
Most people can record
things on their phone
and all kinds of gadgets.
- [Nathan] Well I had when I
was little I had this
little thing and it had a recorder.
When I would sing a
song into the microphone
I could record it and then
play it to my friends.
- [Teacher] Okay, well we're gonna
do something like that.
We're gonna have you, if Mrs.
Smithson is giving directions
and then you guys are getting
ready to do an assignment
or group work or whatever
it is she wants you to do,
she's gonna come over and she's gonna
give the directions to you.
You get to press record
on your tape recorder
and say the directions yourself
into the tape recorder.
Then you get to stop it and play it back
and hear yourself saying the directions.
Okay?
Unless you need them, we're
gonna have you put the little
tape recorder away so that
it doesn't bother you.
Like maybe in a pocket behind
your seat or something.
And then only if you
get stuck and you think,
"Hmm, what did Miss
Smithson want me to do?"
can you get out that recorder and listen.
- [Nathan] Yeah or I can have it
recording beside me so I
could record everything
and if I still remember it,
like it's so easy I can remember it,
I can just erase it.
- [Teacher] Okay.
But I think the actual act of
hearing it whole group
with the rest of the kids in your room,
hearing it with just Miss
Smithson telling it you,
saying it again yourself and
then hearing what you said,
that may be all you need.
You may not have to listen to it again.
I think just making sure you're
really concentrating on what
the directions are is gonna
be a really good thing for ya.
Okay, also, oop.
I gotta get something from over here.
Okay.
One of the other things we might do is
maybe Miss Smithson
might tell you something,
like give you a direction,
and she's gonna whisper it in your ear
and then you have to whisper
it to the person beside you.
And they're gonna whisper
it to the person beside them
and it's gonna go around the table
until it gets back to you.
How many of you all sit at one group?
- [Nathan] Five or six.
I think it's gonna be five
'cause we got two more kids.
- [Teacher] Okay, so sometimes
Miss Smithson might say,
"Get out your pencil,
get out your math book
"and turn to page 50."
Okay?
So then you have to whisper that
into the ear of the person beside you.
What would you say?
- [Nathan] "Get out your pencil
and get out your math book
"and turn to page 50."
- Okay and then that person would
have to whisper it to them.
Then it's gonna come all the way around
and then the last person's gonna say,
"Get out your pencil,
get out your math book
"and turn to page 60."
Is that right?
- [Nathan] I'll just turn back to
'em and say, "It's 50."
- [Teacher] It's 50. Okay, okay.
That's another way we
might make sure that we
understand the directions
before we get started.
- [Nathan] Sometimes my teacher
she just writes it on--