- Does everyone agree
on the first question?
- Yeah.
- What did you all agree on?
- That it wasn't really fair for--
- For First and Second Class to go through
without any problems,
and the people from the Steerage
had to go through examinations,
and this whole, long hassle.
- And why was that?
Why did people who were
First and Second Class
just get to come right on in
and not have to go through examinations?
- Cause of the money.
- What about the money?
- Because they thought that they had--
they were perfect.
They had no disease.
They had lots of money,
and thought they would work hard.
- So the stereotype is, what?
- That rich people are
more-- can work harder,
or have less chance of disease
than the people in Steerage.
- Do you think that that
stereotype is still true today?
Or do you think it's not true anymore?
It was just for First and
Second Class passengers
for Steerage passengers before emigrating?
- Well, it's kind of like this.
It's not over-the-top, but
it's just a little bit.
- What do you guys think about
what Eric said?
- I agree with him.
- Why?
- It's not fair because
First and Second Class
usually are kings or royalty,
and so if you're in Steerage,
you're just a normal person.
If you're in Steerage,
it's not going to be fair.
You have to go walk through that and--
- Well, First and Second Class Passengers
they weren't necessarily royalty,
they were just people
who had a lot of money.
People who had enough money to buy
those tickets which they
were really expensive.
What do you guys think
about what Eric said?
That the stereotype today is still here,
but not really?
Just kind of back-and-forth?
- It's back-and-forth.
They don't do the same thing anymore.
- Who's "they"? And
what's the "same thing"?
- The American Embassy.
The people that take
care of the immigrants
and everything, and all about them.
They don't go to Ellis Island anymore.
- They don't go to Ellis Island anymore.
- You have to go on a plane,
or you have to drive here.
- But do you think the
stereotype, in general,
that rich people are better
or they don't have diseases,
and they're just better
than people who don't have a lot of money?
Do you think we still have
those stereotypes today?
[calls on student]
- Sometimes.
- Sometimes? Have you seen it ever?
- No.
- No, but you just think it's still there?
- I haven't really seen it at all.
- Yeah, I agree with (inaudible).
- Okay. You can start the next one.
Hold on. Josh, did you
have something else to add?
- Yeah. On TV shows, sometimes they have
rich people
in huge carriages
with horses sometimes.
- And they're usually pretty snotty.
- And how do you know they're snotty?
- They're always like, "Don't touch that!
"It's going to fall and
you're going to pay for that!"
- Oh, okay. So you do see in TV sometimes?
- Yeah.
- All right.
- Do you think immigrants
were treated fairly
at Ellis Island?
Why or why not?
- I don't think they
were treated very fairly,
because they had to go through (inaudible).
- I agree with Jacob
because sometimes
people just sent them
back at Ellis Island,
but some doctors at least
tried to keep us here
to help us be better until
we got to stay in America.
- Yeah, and that was good
that the doctors are
supposed to check them
and see if they were okay.
- Some of the doctors,
two people could have the same diseases,
but both the doctors--
one doctor could send one person home,
and one person could stay at
Ellis Island which is unfair.
- Possibly because of their religion
or the way-- their language?
- I think they were mostly--
- I think they were mostly, yeah.
- So they were mostly treated
well, but sometimes not?
- Sometimes not.
- Yeah.
- The doctors or the
inspectors might think
that one person can stay
because of their religion
or their language and others
might have to be sent back.
- And remember the book that we read?
It kind of said that--
the cousin, he had to be sent back to--
well, he almost had to be sent back
to his country because--
- To Russia.
- Yeah, to Russia,
because he had a scratch
and they thought it was infected.
His father was trying to tell him,
but they didn't listen.
- Yeah. He didn't.
- [Student] I think they
should have translators
with all of them, so then
it would make it fair.
- That spoke English, and that language.
- That language.
So they can understand things.
- So I would say, mostly.
- Yeah. Mostly.
- So should we check them both off?
- I think we should
check off the first one.
- [Another Student] If they
were sick or something,
or if they needed food,
they had places where they could get food.
Or if they were sick and
had to go to the hospital,
like Sophia said.
So I'm in the middle. Kind of.
Because sometimes, they
were treated badly.
- I agree with Josh
because if they were sick,
they would probably be treated less fairly
because they were sick
and had their diseases.
Like, "Oh! Get away from me,
because you're going to spread
that disease to everybody.
It's going to be an epidemic."
- I want to add,
if they were sick,
they could have been contagious,
and there were a lot of
people at Ellis Island
so they might have--
- Usually if they were at a hospital,
they were curing curable diseases,
because if they couldn't cure it--
they didn't have a medicine
or anything to cure that,
they got sent back.
- Yeah, I agree with Eric and Sophia...
- Go ahead. Were you
going to say something?
- I was going to say, if
we all agree on this...
- So your general feeling here is:
were they treated fairly at Ellis Island?
- They weren't treated not very fairly.
Like they were treated half the fair
that they should have been,
but they weren't treated really good.
- They were fed very well,
and all their needs were there,
but they weren't treated
very good like if you were on
an airplane in First Class.
- It's kind of like--
- I would like to add,
they were treated way better
in Ellis Island because on the ship,
in Steerage, they didn't have good food.
They couldn't really bathe,
and it was all crowded.
They didn't really have
a good place to sleep,
but in Ellis Island, they
actually had okay food.
They weren't treated like (inaudible).
- Do you think that it was fair
that they each had to have
$20 on them in order to stay?
- Yeah.
- Sort of. Sort of.
- What I think is they need
to take care of themselves
and
America is actually bringing
lots of them over here.
America just could say, "Stop.
No more immigrants, at all,"
but they've been letting people in.
A lot of people in,
and they've been very generous
by giving them food,
and letting them live here
in this wonderful country.
So they've provided enough.
- I have something-- I
have two things to say.
I agree with Sophia because--
I sort of agree with Sophia
because if they didn't have $20,
they wouldn't have much to live,
and the government
is not really responsible
for the immigrants.
They're responsible for themselves.
They're on their own,
and I would like to say is that,
going back to Sophia's (inaudible).
It said that--
then they were fed well,
and that they were...
- All wanted to get to America,
and even if some of them had money,
how do you know
that they didn't have
a disease or something?
How do you know if they
didn't have lice or something?
- I kind of agree with you,
because if they paid more,
I think they shouldn't
get a lot, a lot more,
but I think they should
get a little bit more,
but they still should go to Ellis Island.
- Yeah.
- Sometimes they did have doctors
who came on the ships,
and kind of gave the medical exams
to First and Second Class Passengers
to make sure they didn't
have any diseases.
And then if their medical
exams checked out fine,
then they could skip everything else.
So they didn't have to get
asked all those questions,
and they didn't have to wait
in all those long lines,
and things like that.
So what do you think about that?
- I think it's still unfair
that they didn't have
to wait in long lines
just because they were
already examined on the boat.
- I think instead of Ellis Island,
they should have checked them
before they got on the boat, for everyone.
- Yeah. I agree with you.
- I think they got all seasick.
Think that's where they all got sick?
- Yeah.
- Like in the Steerage.
Some of them got sick because
they were in Steerage,
and then when they got to Ellis Island,
they had to get sent back.
- The reason why some of them got sick,
was because they didn't have fresh air,
and so they couldn't breathe that well.
- Stuffy in Steerage.
- I think all doctors should have been
actually fair instead of sending
some immigrants back
just because they don't like them,
for their religion and stuff.
- Could doctors send people back
because they didn't like their religion?
Doctors could send people back, why?
Doctors couldn't send people back,
but they would mark letters on your back.
Why could they mark letters on your back?
- Because they probably thought--
they probably saw something different
when it was actually a scratch.
- So, just if you were hurt,
and then they had to go through
further medical exams to see,
but doctors couldn't just say,
"I don't like you! You have to go back!"
They were just examining you
to make sure you didn't
have a contagious disease
that could get other people sick.
- When we were reading,
they said something about the doctors--
where they didn't have
any diseases or anything,
but they'd still send them back.
- And you read that in the book?
- We were reading one of the things.
- Oh, and why would they send them back?
Why would they get sent back,
by the legal inspectors and other people?
- Sometimes, it was like
there were random reasons
they sent them.
- Just because?
- Yeah.
- That's not fair? That's
what you're saying?
- Yeah.
- I'd also change the
part where they had to--
why did they have to mark
stuff on their own clothes?
- Yeah.
- I mean they should have
given a sheet or something.
- Or something.
Because, what if that's
the only thing they had?
You know?
- I think they should mark on their skin,
or something so then you
could just wash it off.
- Like a marker or something?
- No, I don't think they
should do it on the skin,
because then if there
was a water fountain,
they could just wash it off
and say, "I'm in this line." Right?
- True.
- [Student] They could.
They could do that.
We all agree they should do something
other than your own clothes.
- They should give you
a sheet of paper and--
- You could rip it apart.
[background chatter]
- I think that they way they did it,
for example, that guy in the
book did his jacket inside-out.
They should have been kind of more smart
about what they gave them.
Because someone could just say,
"Take this jacket inside-out,"
and then go into the other line.
- Or he could just put
his jacket on tomorrow.
- Yeah. "Oh, I don't have a jacket."
- Yeah.
- If we didn't have Ellis Island,
not as many immigrants
would be here, probably,
because it'd be a lot harder.
And Ellis Island,
they fed you food.
It was good. I like it.
- I agree with Josh
because
they gave you food and water,
a place to sleep.
They built stuff and made kinder-cares,
and made stuff with the little kids
and stuff for the grown-ups.
The people that were there at Ellis Island
didn't even have to pay for any of that.
That was all for free.
I mean, imagine that happening to us
right now?
That will never happen.
- I definitely agree with Sophia
because if you just come to Ellis Island,
and they just give you
potato soup every meal,
it's kind of like they don't get
a good impression of America.
I think they try to give a good impression
for the immigrants on America,
from giving them good food,
and a good way to start
their time in America.
and then they realize
how complicated it is.
- Yeah.
- According to everyone, I kind of agree.
It was good, I think.