- Okay, so for social needs,
we said that their social
needs are being met
because they...
(inaudible)
- They look like the slave
traders can talk to each other
because they speak the same language,
but the slaves don't,
so their social needs
with each other aren't.
- So you feel
your social needs are being met?
- Yeah.
- And how so?
- Because our person can talk to...
- 'Cause you have people
to talk to, don't you?
- Yeah.
- Anybody agree with that?
- I agree, because our person--
- You. I am. You're that person.
Don't say my person, 'cause that's you.
- I can talk to other people.
- So, you do have some social interaction?
So, there's some disagreement there
as social needs are being met or not.
- No hands, Nita, jump in.
- We cannot
(inaudible)
- So your social needs
are not being met?
- Yes, our social needs
are not being met because we...
- They do not understand each other
meaning, like, deaf?
Or they cannot talk?
- So how does that make you feel?
Go ahead and talk about
your emotional needs now
being met or not being met.
- Our emotional needs
are not being met right now.
- I think I disagree.
I think ours are kind of being met.
- I agree with Lauren's.
Ours are being met
because they're more happy
that they're gonna get a lot of money.
- You're the person.
- But our person is kinda serious...
- like he doesn't really want...[inaudible]
(background chatter)
- So as far as
what Nita's already talked about?
Emotionally?
So are your emotional needs being met?
- He looks angry.
- You feel safe,
you're good to go.
- Yeah, 'cause
we know we're--
- She's like, I don't
really want to go, but...
- They want the money.
- But we want money.
We want all the money.
Well, it's the physical needs anyway.
Ours--
- Ours are not being met.
- Ours are being met
'cause we get weapons and everything,
all good food.
- I agree.
And ours are also being met.
- You don't want to mess with them.
- Yeah.
- I disagree
with both of you guys because
ours are not being met at all.
- Definitely not.
We are, like--
- We're starving.
- Starving.
- My needs are not
being met if I'm Ashley,
because I'm scrunched together,
I'm uncomfortable.
My physical needs aren't being met
because it's crowded
and my muscles ache.
Does anyone agree with that?
That their physical
needs are not being met?
- I agree that Ashley's physical needs
aren't being met
because they are scrunched together
and it looks like they're in chains
and they don't have much--
- [Teacher] Are your
physical needs being met?
- Yes.
- Our physical needs
are being met because--
(multiple children talking)
- I disagree with you
because I think you have space.
- Our physical needs are being met.
We're not, like...
(inaudible)
- You're in good shape?
(background chatter)
- With your physical needs being met
how does that link to
emotional and social needs?
How do those kind of all go together?
Talk about how those
all go together overall
and how does that make you feel,
based on this picture.
You're that person,
so use first-person point of view,
and discuss how those are all intertwined.
And then add to your conversation,
as far as I know,
some of you did the bottom two
as far as not--
These are what are being met
and these are not being met.
So make sure you cover those two, okay?
How they all intertwine
or if they do.
And then you can discuss
these bottom questions, too.
Even if you didn't get to
them with your partner,
jump in now with each other.
I'll be right back.
- Alright, so...
(inaudible)
My emotional needs are being met.
I'm earning the money that I should be
and I feel confident...
(background chatter)
- All of our emotional needs,
all of our needs are being met.
(background chatter)
- Why are
the clothes taken off
and why are the--?
Just in case
- Emotional needs are not
- they do jump overboard?
- being met.
It looks like they're sad because,
because we look depressed.
And you can just tell it by the faces
and what they look like.
Our faces and their--
and our body language.
And there was--
and we're scared because
we see the weapons and
we don't know what they're
gonna do with it to us.
- So think about the cause and
effect of that.
- Our emotional kinda was being met.
- Are the people standing up--
- No.
- But how are they not chained?
- Still all of our emotional
needs are being met.
- They're running away.
- They don't look worried,
they look kind of like they're looking at
the scenery kind of.
- They look calm.
- In their expression
they look calm, yeah.
They don't look worried or anything.
- These people, but the people
that are sitting down...
(inaudible)
- I disagree with Alan,
'cause they look calm and confident.
- I kinda disagree with that
because they look like--
That's why they're all
facing different directions.
They're watching for anything suspicious.
(multiple children talking)
They're all looking in
different directions.
- They aren't smiling like
they're looking at beautiful scenery.
- There's like little sections in between,
so like Grayson said, if
they do jump overboard
they don't all fall over and tip the boat.
- Do you think these people
are all in one group?
No, let me rewind and
say my question again.
Do you feel that these people
all everybody in this boat
was represented by a perspective
from your discussion you just had?
Do you understand my question?
I'm not saying it very well.
Were roles of all these people in the boat
given to at least somebody in this group?
- Yeah.
- You think so?
How were the roles different?
- I think there's bosses
and then there was slaves.
Like slave traders and them.
- Kind of serious, like
they just got their reward,
and these people, they
look kind of like chained--
- I don't think they're running away.
- I think they're running away.
- I think they're going to a bigger boat,
'cause these people look like--
- I think they're like--
- That's not the full canoe.
- And they're just taking
the slaves to the big boat.
- So let me say my question again.
Let me say my question again.
- Why would slaves take slaves?
- They're slave traders.
- They're not slaves.
- How do you know they could be slaves
or they could be slave traders?
- Let me say my question again.
I want you to think about your role
and what was just said.
Do you think that all roles
that I gave this group were,
I'm sorry, are on this picture?
- No.
- Oh, you're changing your mind?
Discuss that.
At first you said yes.
Discuss that, why maybe not all the roles
that I gave you were on this picture.
No, do not say your role yet.
Ladies and gentlemen, we
have about one minute.
- I think that they
are people in the tribe
and they're giving their slaves as slaves.
- You know how we were
doing that worksheet,
the graphic organizer?
It said that most of the time,
they would just trade other villages
for their slaves and take those ones.
- Well, I think--
- 'Cause they could still
have their own slaves.
- I think this is a slave trader...
well, not really like a
slave trader, but like
- 'Cause the slave traders
- a slave boss kind of?
- were from England, so I
think they'd have white skin.
- I think they're with the other people--
- But remember
African-Americans were also slave traders.
- Because they're not
chained and they're standing
and the other people, like slaves,
are all tucked together and depressed.
- I think that...
some European traders tried to
persuade other slave people
to say, like
"go get your crime people,
go get your crime people..."
- Slaves.
- Yeah, "your slaves
"in your own tribe, and
then we'll trade you--"
- Gold.
- A bag of tobacco.
- And those helped capture...
So even though they don't have white skin,
they might be slave traders
and they give, like,
(inaudible)
- So we have two different
maybe perspectives
of slave traders, is that
what I'm hearing you say?
One being?
- They could have also
been threatened to work.
- Europeans.
- Hold that thought, David.
One being?
- Europeans and one being African.
- Well not really African-American...
- 'Cause in the book it said
that the African slaves,
not the European slaves,
but the African slaves,
their slaves were kinda like maids.
- So I want you to think about the role
that you were given.
And I asked you to look at that picture
from that perspective.
Is it possible that that
specific role I gave you
has many different perspectives itself?
- Yes.
- Alright.
I want you to wrap up your conversation
if you have anything else to add,
and then we're gonna continue tomorrow.
- You're not gonna tell?
- Not yet, no.
I changed my mind.
You think you know.
- We still have the cards.
- Aw, rats.
- They did it.