- [Instructor] In my classroom, each
student has their own individual workbench
with a set of hand tools in the drawers,
where they also may store their art and
they've each made a back splash of art
inspirational images. In the corner of the
room, I have a resource area including
images of art, books and magazines, a
computer with an internet connection, and
examples. I have a board where I give
notes and it has a calendar with the semester
at a glance. I have a demo table where we
meet for discussions and group
demonstrations. In the corner of the room,
there's acid etching done safely with
rubber gloves and goggles and a rubber
apron. In front of that there's soldering
with a acetylene tanks chained to the
cabinet and a good ventilation system above, and
also, eye protection and gloves. The sink
area includes an emergency eyewash station
and soaps. In the corner of the room, you
see a fire extinguisher, a buffing
machine, a hammering area done safely with
a stump to limit the percussive nature of
each blow, and ear protection, a drill
press done safely with eye protection and
gloves, an emergency eyewash station and
shower, and first aid kit. In here, we
have an enamelling area above banks of
labeled cabinets with ventilation. And in
the front, we have a bulletin board with
notices and class rules and another fire
extinguisher.
This is another reason why people might
own jewelry or want to have jewelry. Now this isn't
jewelry per se You know what these are?
- Coins?
- Coins. There's such an interesting
iconography of coins. I love the
patterning that happened when he cast
them. I mean, I just think its... You've got the
horse. You've got the man. Some sort of a
symbol. I don't really know what all the
symbols are, but you could really use a
lot of this. And do research symbols like
for the production project that is coming
up. And here people have even made jewelry
out of the coins. And here art is an
example of, in north Africa, a lot of
times women, traditional women, it's
probably changing now, but I don't really
know how much it's changed or not changed.
This picture is from 1988 or something, so
it's in the past. But they would get a lot
of their wealth from their family given to
them as jewelry. And they'd wear it
everyday. And it might seem ridiculous to
us, you can do your farming, you're going
about your business, cooking and you're
wearing all that craziness, but that way
it's on them, they have it, if something
happens to their husband, nobody can take
it away because it's on their body. It's
protected. It's also very obvious. If the
husband were to steal the money, and take
it away, they would know because she's not
wearing it. So he would be shamed. So it's
sort of... it's like the dowry, the money
comes into the family from the woman's
parents, but it's also to help protect the
woman. It's not just... it's not just to go
to the husband. So I think it's amusing
that they're wearing it.
- I thought they weren't allowed to wear
makeup.
- Well, it depends in what part of-- where
you are. I mean, are you thinking who is
they?
- I'm thinking Iran and stuff, and north
Africa.
- Right. Iran, there's different sects of
Islam and what people believe as really
strict is different. In this, north
Africa... Iran's more in the Middle East,
getting closer... I mean, does it
even... even in Asia, it might even be
Asia.
- No, it's not in north Africa.
- It's not in Africa. So this is
like... north Africa, there's a lot of
tribal groups that were nomads in the
desert. It's all intermixed. And people in
southern Africa, like in Sudan are
predominantly Islamic and they have a
different take on it, too. So maybe in
Iran it's frowned upon as vanity, but...
- The Muslim culture requires women to
cover their faces. It's not Muslim
religions that only...
- It's Arabian.
- That's very good, Chloe. Very, very
astute.
- It's there traditions. It's not required by the
religion, it's a cultural thing.
- That's good. That's a good
clarification. I didn't think of it that
way. So also, this redeemable investment
or wealth, people like to and they have
people over for dinner.
- Golden silverware?
- On the right, that was the silverware of
Marie Antoinette.
- I've never heard of gold silverware.
- So gold, I know, they're eating on gold.
And it can't be 24 carat, because it would
be too soft. But it's probably a gold
alloy. And there's also cases of people
when times get tough, melting down their
silverware.
- So they can have the...
- Yeah, and you use that as your... it's
like people nowadays are investing in
gold. They're buying gold bars, because
it's like you own something. You see it.
It's not just a piece of paper that says
you own something.
- Yeah, I think there's commercials
about buying gold.
- And this is a chalice through the
church. The church accumulated a lot of
wealth, specifically, the Catholic church
during the Medieval times. And they would
have it made into these things like the
chalice for the blood. Okay, attraction
and beauty. This is pretty obvious,
because where do people usually wear
jewelry?
- On their necks and faces and...
- Yeah, yeah, to draw attention, I think,
to the face usually is a big deal. And
also, this is an example of a Cartier
necklace that was a gift from a man to a
woman. So a lot of times, it's with the
idea of love, or commitment, romantic
love. Here we have Indians from India, and
these are things that you can buy. This is
just off of that. So this is like the
traditional wedding where you've got kind
of an inexpensive version, perhaps, that
you can buy. There's all sorts... there's
all levels of expense that you can buy.
And here we are again with north Africa.
Just kind of thinking about the different
ideas of what is beautiful and what isn't
beautiful. I don't know. How many of you
have tattoos? Any of you have a tattoo?
- I wish.
- Okay, I mean you're a little bit young.
Right? Do you think you might want a tattoo at
some point?
- Yeah, my friend has a whole entire
paragraph on her back.
- Really? Do you like it?
- Yeah, it's really pretty, but I wouldn't
want something like that. Yeah.
- I don't remember what it says...
Something, it has to do with swimming, I
think.
- It's like swimming.
- In some way. It's a really good quote,
though.
- Yeah, she looks like that girl from
Avatar.
- You know, I haven't seen Avatar, but as
a movie designer, James Cameron, what do
you think he was looking at to get
inspiration for the movie?
- Probably...
[Background Chatter]
- If you, I mean, does anybody like Star
Wars? That was a popular kind of thing. But
you know, I always wanted the hair braids.
"Mom, mom, please." She's like, "Your hair
isn't long enough. That was a movie. They
had... it was a wig." I was like, "Do it.
Do it."
- I braid my hair, put beads in it
sometimes.
- There are cultures that wear their hair
like that. So it's like nothing is sort of
new under the sun. People are reinventing
what's already happened.
- I always wanted it just like Pocahontas
that's the entire story.
[Background Chatter]
- The second time I saw it, I was like,
"Oh, this is really bad." One thing, they
represented it wrong, that's like the reason
they were there because it was very valuable...
- Oh, so you're thinking it could have
been a little more creative? [Background Chatter]
[Background Chatter]
- You know, the first time you see it,
it's so good. And then the second time
you're like, "Hey, now that I've seen this..."
- So it's good to critique pop culture to
determine. If you get a job in the movies,
how would you do it better or differently?
- I'd do a different plot. I'd be more
creative.
[Background Chatter]
- Okay, yeah, we better... I'm gonna keep
moving on. All right? Okay, so here we
have ancient Egypt on the left and we have
Miss South Carolina 2000, I can't
remember, 2004, 2006, recently. Isn't it
interesting how similar the eye, the
eyeliner, the long eyebrow, the hair
coming down, the crown? You know, I
mean...
- I think the eyebrows [inaudible].
- Well, she doesn't have the...
[Background Chatter]
- I'm trying to create a bead kind of
thing.
- Okay.
- Melting the stuff Drew was using for his
corset together.
- Oh, the screen? So you're melting the
screen? Oh, interesting. So how will you
use that in your... ?
- I'm thinking I can use it in attaching,
because I think it would look cool if
there was something kind of like that, not
gold and shell-ish.
- Okay. Okay, well, do you want to go look
at your stuff? Or do you want to... or you
feel like you need to finish that?
- Oh, no, that's fine.
[Background Chatter]
- There appears to be no blue stuff.
- Oh, the pickle? It's new.
- Oh.
- It only gets blue from the copper, so
it, it does have pickle in it. It's just
fresh and new. So you could, you
could... see that little yogurt container?
You can put it in that, and that has holes
in it, and then you can just kind of let
that float. Just kind of put a little in
there. Like tip it. Yeah, that's good.
Okay, yeah, let's go look at your... Oh,
should we look at those? Would you rather
do those, or... Okay, let's go... [Background Chatter]
Sorry, we're going outside
now.
- Okay.
[Background noises and wind]
- Oh, wow. What do you think?
- I like them. I really like them as not a
shell color, because they don't seem...
- Can I touch it? Sorry, I touched it
before I asked you.
- I think once you like...as
I did, just find the shell along the
stream.
- Right, you're transforming it. I really
like the shell of the spray paint too,
because it helps tie it in with the metal.
It makes... well, it's metallic spray
paint, so it seems really metal-y, yeah.
Right. Cool. And it makes it a little bit
more blingy. You know?
- And I like how it reflects the light,
all the cracks, and stuff.
- Yes, it gives it a unifying presence
instead of having all that color
variation. Especially if you think about
having one necklace that has many shells
on it. Then this unifies them. It makes
them probably a little bit more wearable
with people's clothes. Do you think? About
how would you, how will you attach... are
you thinking of using these in one group?
Or are they more pendants?
- I think they're more like pendants, and
I was gonna poke a hole.
- Okay.
- Like two holes in them, and I was gonna
use a bunch of different strings together.
So it's kind of like. . .and they're right
there. And maybe bead it, a bunch of
beaded strings.
- So really, this is like one necklace
that's... or is it many necklaces that
people can layer?
- It's just one necklace.
- Okay, all right. Well let's... can we go
look at your sketch book, too? The other
thing is, next time it would be better, I
think, to drill the hole first before you
paint it.
- Okay.
- Because I'm afraid the paint might
scratch in the process of drilling the
hole.
- I was going to just poke a hole with a
needle.
- Can you do that?
- I think so. I mean, they're really a lot
more soft than metal.
- Oh, okay, well try it, and see if it
works. But I have a diamond drill bit. It
can drill and that's what Drew has been
using to drill his glass and stuff.
- Okay, and also, most of these already
have holes.
- Oh, yeah, because of the creature that
eats the muscle.
- Yeah.
- I love the hole that's already in there,
yeah, okay. All right, let's go look at
that. These probably need to dry a little
more.
- Yes.
- Okay, okay, let's go in.
- There's only five more minutes on here.
- Okay, that's good. We'll get this and
that'll be okay.
[Background workshop noises and chatter]
- Oh, look at that. See, that's amazing to
me, because whenever I find coquinas, I
guess I find the live coquinas. I've never
seen the shells, like just the shells. But
they all have a hole. This is a great
find.
- I got my back so sunburned gathering all
of these on the beach.
- Yes.
- Because they all lay next to each other
in the sand.
- And when you, I mean, now do you have
sketches of how these might be transformed
into jewelry?
- I'm not sure yet, because...
- Here, I'll come over... is this better
like this?
- Yeah.
- I could use like... I could put them
all together on one string, on one
necklace. Sort of like the coral. But I
don't know. I don't think I have enough
for that from reproduction.
- Well, you have a lot. What might be
better, right, because, you're right.
Because then they would nest. Right? If
you just put with cubicle, then they don't
take up much space. What if you made a
bunch jump rings with thin wire, and then
you have a little jump ring that would go
through each one. And that could put... see
how you have sort of charms on your chain?
You could... these could also be sort of
like charms hanging down, and you could
layer them maybe with a jump ring, could
have a little chain. And it could hang
down to vary the length or, or you said
that you like to use... did you make your
necklace that's woven there? That's, okay,
you, but you know how to sew? So could you
sew them on something?
- I could, yeah.
- I mean, I have some leather strip, and
that would be keeping with natural
materials. So that might be interesting. I
don't know. I... well, I think what you
need to do is to experiment, sew some, do
some metal through some, and then maybe
lay some out. And you can see how Chloe
has hers laid out in that box, so that she
can keep it. I think you'd need a box or a
tray, and you could sort of lay it out so
you can start to see the composition of
them.
- Yeah.
- Now what are these?
- Those are...
- Oh, and these are a dove's feathers.
- They're so elegant.
- Yes.
- Now do you have your sketch book? Can we
look at the sketch on how you thought you
might do this?
[Background Chatter]
- Here, I think I got it.
- Here you go. I could do this with the
shell.
- Oh, because that's hanging off. And then
what is this round ring part?
- I'm not sure. It could just be like a
round, golden...
- It could be a soldered ring of metal,
like brass, wire soldered together. Is
this an earring?
- Yes.
- Okay.
- That may be for these.
- Right.
- That was... that's what I was planning to
do with the shell. For that, I could do a
bunch of different strings, or I could
just do one string and put two of these
sort of up the string, or something.
- Right, right, asymmetry. Okay, I
like it. And then this is the feather?
These are jump rings and this is the feather.