- [Voiceover] I can go into
group two because that--
- Except this one is
like, these two are like,
both like pop.
These two are kinda like both pop.
Because water's not bubbly.
This one's bubbly and this one's--
- [Voiceover] Coca Cola.
Or Dr. Pepper.
- [Voiceover] Do you have
a secret rule to use?
- We're gonna get, like,
one of those blue ones
and that could be like the bubbles.
- Because they're kinda the same.
- [Voiceover] Okay.
- [Voiceover] And this one, like--
- [Voiceover] So, I'm gonna make sure
I'm understanding what
your rule is gonna be.
Does it have something to do
with bubbles or does it have
something to do with it sticks
to the side of the container?
- It's the bubble.
- Bubbles and stick to the side.
- Yeah.
- [Voiceover] Okay, so
one group is gonna be
sticking to the side
and one group is not sticking to the side.
Is that right?
- Yeah.
- [Voiceover] Okay, great, alright.
Alright, friends.
In order to be closer together,
to really see how this is going to work,
I'm going to ask Anagelia's group
to very quietly come and sit
in these three chairs here.
Go ahead and bring your liquids with you.
(mumbling)
Thank you very much.
And...
What we're going to do
is we're going to set up our rule
so that
it's up here at the front.
So actually, Anagelia, if you don't mind,
Callie and Natalie,
if you guys could scoot
down just a little bit
and then Anagelia's going to
join you on that side
so we can see this front area right here.
Okay?
Thank you.
So, we can set up one of
our groups on this table
and one on this table.
For your, what's my rule, okay.
So, you're thinking of your property
and you're going to put the ones
that fit the property here
and the ones that don't
fit the property here.
Who would like to go first?
Who would like to start?
Okay, so Ryan's group.
Ryan's group.
Come up and set up one
that fits your rule.
Just a minute, Ryan.
Isabella needs to come with you.
One that fits your rule here,
and one that doesn't fit your rule here.
Just one, just one.
One in each.
Okay, thank you.
You can be seated, okay.
So, we have this one fits their rule,
this one doesn't fit their rule.
I can tell Bryson's already thinking about
what it could possibly be.
- This one can fit their rule.
- Hold on one second.
That's where we're going,
but wait one second, okay.
Let's talk about what we see.
Any ideas so far of what
might be going on here?
Bryson, do you have one
that you could bring up
that you think
goes in either space?
- [Bryson] The bubbles on the top.
- Okay, so you think it has
something to do with bubbles.
Do you have one that fits bubbles?
- [Voiceover] That one.
- He's got a hypothesis.
Now Lena, he's got a hypothesis
about what he thinks it might be.
Do you think this fits the rule?
- Yeah.
- Okay.
So, now we need to check
in with Isabella and Ryan.
Does that fit the rule?
- [Voiceover] Yes.
- It does, okay.
- [Voiceover] It doesn't fit my rule.
- So, your rule should be
the same as your partner's.
Do you remember what that rule was, Ryan?
- [Ryan] Yeah.
- Okay, great.
Alright, so Anagelia, thanks
for raising your hand.
Do you have one that
you think fits the rule
or doesn't fit the rule?
Thank you, Callie.
Callie, will you check
in with Isabella and Ryan
and see if that fits.
- Isabella, does that fit the rule?
- [Isabella] Yes.
- Okay.
Anybody else who's ready to bring one up?
- [Voiceover] Oh, another rule?
- Another one that might
fit or doesn't fit.
Rigo, would you like to try?
Which one do you think
would go with this group?
Which ones from the ones you have
Bryson giving you a hint?
- [Voiceover] No, that one doesn't.
That one here.
- So, you think both of these fit?
- The blue one, just the blue one.
Because look at this one.
It doesn't leave white bubbles.
- Okay, so if that one
doesn't fit the rule,
where would it go, Rigo?
Where would this one go?
- This one--
- Over here, right?
Just hold that thought
for a just a second.
No, this one we said does fit it.
Right?
Isabella and Ryan, are we on track so far?
- [Isabella] Yes.
- Okay.
Anagelia, did your group
have another one to bring up?
Okay.
That one you think fits in
this side, fits the rule?
And Callie, you think this
one doesn't fit the rule?
- [Callie] Look, when it shakes.
Doesn't do anything.
- Okay, okay.
Natalina, do you want to take a stab at
stating the rule for us?
What's going on here?
- [Natalina] I think it's the
bubbles and not the bubbles
because that whole group,
when you shake it, it has lots of bubbles.
That one doesn't.
- Okay, so let's go back a minute though
because you said two different things.
Sit on your botton, Rigo.
First, you said bubbles and not bubbles.
And then you said
bubbles when you shake it
and no bubbles when you shake it.
Is that the same rule
or is that different?
Is the shaking part important,
do you think, to that rule?
Okay, so can you state
it one more time for us?
- [Natalina] When you shake it,
if there's bubbles, it will go that one.
If it doesn't go bubbles,
it goes in that one.
- Okay.
And Isabella and Ryan, is that correct?
- [Isabella] Yup.
- Excellent, so the shaking
was the really important
part of that, great.
- [Bryson] At least for
this one it's weird.
- Right, because right now
this one has no bubbles.
But if I shake it, it gets bubbles later.
Okay.
Excellent.
Can you remember which
ones you had in your group?
- [Voiceover] Yes.
- Can you come and get them?
I'm not sure if I can.
I'm glad you can remember.
Can you remember, Rigo,
which one you put out there?
- This.
- - [Voiceover] No, that one's ours.
- No, this is ours.
Um, yeah.
One, two, three, four, five.
- I think you've got five.
These ones are originally from
Isabella and Ryan I think.
- [Voiceover] Yeah.
- Isabella and Ryan, can
you come back and get yours?
Great.
Alright, which partnership
is ready to tell,
to not tell, but to do
another secret rule?
- I thought I brought a blue.
- Did you think you brought a blue one?
You figured it out.
Okay, Natalina's group.
Can you put one on this side
that is fitting the rule
and one on this side that
is not fitting the rule?
Natalina, you want to
check that one more time,
make sure that's correct?
Okay, this one fits the rule
you guys told me about earlier.
And let's leave this on the table.
Anagelia, can you remind
what the rule is?
(whispering)
- Stick to the sides.
Anagelia, can you remind
Callie what the rule is too?
Go remind Callie.
So, these two do fit, right?
Alright, show us one that doesn't, please.
Okay.
Careful with the liquids, please.
You okay?
Alright.
We actually got a little extra
help here now, didn't we?
We got two in this group that fit the rule
and one that does not.
Isabella, do you have one
in your group over there
that you think does or doesn't fit the rule?
Ryan, can you sit on your
bottom again, please?
Watch what Isabella is doing.
- [Voiceover] Oh, cool.
- See if you agree.
Ryan, watch what Isabella's doing
and see if you agree.
Okay.
- [Voiceover] I agree.
- Natalina, Callie, and Anagelia,
thumbs up?
Is that correct?
Did she put it in the right place?
- [Voiceover] Yeah.
- Okay, good.
Bryson and Rigo, do you guys have one
that you want to put in?
- [Voiceover] Yeah, more than one.
- More than one, okay.
- [Voiceover] Oh, three.
- Oh.
Go ahead if you think that's right.
I think that's right, Rigo.
Rigo, can you tell us why
you put these two here?
- Because it can bubble.
Bubbles in it.
- Because they have bubbles in them?
Does this--
- [Voiceover] Does not--
- Just a second, just a second, Callie.
Does this one have bubbles in it?
Yes, it does.
So, it's not bubbles and no bubbles.
You're on the right track though.
Take a look again.
Ryan, do you have one
that you can bring up
and add to our groups here?
- [Voiceover] Stuff on the side.
And this one, it goes away after awhile.
Maybe this is the rule.
- Thank you, Ryan.
So far so good?
- [Voiceover] Yeah.
- Okay.
Let's bring up all the rest.
Oh Bryson, you can go ahead
and leave those there.
You can go ahead and leave those there.
I think we're okay, actually.
If you have any other
liquids to bring up--
- [Voiceover] This one.
- Bring them on up.
And put them where they belong
and we'll see if we can
figure out what the rule is.
Bring it on up, bring it on up.
Ryan, bring that one on up
and see if we can figure
out where it goes.
(mumbling)
- This one's confusing.
- Ooh, a confusing one.
I love a confusing one, do you know why?
- Because it helps you think.
- It helps you think, exactly.
It makes it more difficult to figure out.
Would you like to consult with someone?
Do you want to consult with Ryan?
Ryan, come here a minute.
Your partner needs your help.
She's trying to figure
out where this one goes.
What do you think?
- I think it goes in no bubbles
because no bubbles is the correct one.
- Now remember, we just found out though
that bubbles and no
bubbles is not the rule.
Because look, this one has bubbles.
This one, if I shake it, has bubbles.
So, bubbles and no bubbles
was our last rule.
Okay.
Thanks for your help, Ryan.
Anybody else give Isabella
some assistance here?
Well, you know the rules already right, Anagelia?
What do you think, Anagelia?
Which one do you think it goes in?
Listen to Anagelia, Rigo.
(mumbling)
What's your opinion, what do you think?
Does it go in this group?
Or this one?
What do you think?
Even though you know what the rule is,
can you help her figure
out how to classify it?
Rigo, are you watching?
What do you think?
- [Anagelie] It goes in--
- [Voiceover] In that one.
- [Anagelie] That one.
- In this group right here?
Okay.
What do you think, Isabella?
You want Bryson's idea?
What does Bryson think?
- I think it goes in that one.
- Because?
- Because most of them kind of move
when you shake them.
But when you shake those, they don't.
- Oh, interesting.
Let's try that out, okay.
Okay, Ryan, come a little
closer to me right now, please.
We're trying out something different.
Bryson just said the ones...
Rigo, you can stay where you
are, you're right close by.
(mumbling)
No.
Bryson just said something
really interesting.
He just said,
stand on your own two feet, please.
Thank you.
He just said that these ones
don't move when you shake them,
and these ones do move
when you shake them,
and that's how they're classified.
So, I want to just double check
that I make sure that I agree
with what you're saying.
Okay, Bryson?
Does this one move when I shake it?
- Not really, I can't really.
- Try it out.
- Okay.
- See what you think.
- It kinda does.
- Does this one move
when you shake it?
- Yes.
- [Voiceover] Yes, okay.
- Oh, it sticks on the walls.
- Ah-ha.
So, are you amending your rule?
Are you saying that the rule
is it sticks on the sides?
- Yes.
- So, this group right here is--
- [Voiceover] Ding ding
ding ding ding ding.
- [Voiceover] This group
right here is the one's
that stick on the sides?
- [Bryson] Yes.
- Ding ding ding ding ding.
Ring the bell, ring the bell.
- [Voiceover] But we
still haven't figured out,
even if we know that that's
what the secret rule is,
where does this one go?
- That one.
- [Voiceover] That one, that one.
- Okay, Natalina.
Let's take your opinion first.
Rigo, we're listening to Natalina.
And then we'll hear from you, okay.
Go ahead, Natalina.
- I don't think it follows our rule.
- [Voiceover] It does.
- [Voiceover] You think
it's totally out here, it's separate?
It's not in either category?
- [Natalina] No, I don't
think it goes in this one.
- [Voiceover] You don't
think it goes in this one?
- No, I do think it goes--
- [Voiceover] Because?
- Because it doesn't
really stick to the walls.
- [Voiceover] It doesn't
Okay, you wanna hold it, make sure?
- [Voiceover] Stick to the--
- [Voiceover] Other opinions?
Other opinions?
Anagelia, I couldn't hear you.
Could you say it louder
so the group can hear you?
Go ahead.
- It should go there
because when you move it,
some parts stick to the
wall and some parts...
- [Voiceover] When you move it?
- It sticks to the part.
- [Voiceover] It does stick to the walls?
- Yeah.
- [Voiceover] Okay.
- [Voiceover] It's dirty.
- [Voiceover] Isabella, what do you think?
- I think it should go in this one because
it kind of...
It sticks to the wall at
first, and then it goes down.
So, and then doesn't stick
to the wall (mumbles).
- Okay, it sticks to the wall
first, and then it doesn't,
so you think it goes in this one?
May I have it just for a minute?
One thing I'm noticing that's
a little confusing for me,
if I look at this one
compared to all the others,
this is the only one that's
not colored in this group.
Does that make it feel like
these ones are stickier
because they're colored somehow?
So, this one's not as sticky
because it's less colored maybe?
I don't know.
So, you're saying it sticks at first,
but then not so much after that.
Can we tell how much this one sticks?
- [Voiceover] No.
- [Voiceover] Yeah.
- It really sticks.
How about this one, can you
tell how much this one sticks?
- [Voiceover] Yeah.
- [Voiceover] It kinda sticks.
- [Voiceover] That does stick (mumbles).
- [Voiceover] Most of it.
- Some of it.
- [Voiceover] That does.
- So it sticks, but it is--
- [Voiceover] Most of it
goes away and some stays.
- Some goes away and some stays--